<?xml version="1.0"?>





<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
	<title>Douris</title>
	<author>Diana Buitron-Oliver</author>
	<sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor><principal>Gregory Crane</principal><respStmt><resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp><name>Lisa Cerrato</name></respStmt>
	&fund.NEA;
      </titleStmt>
	<publicationStmt><publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher><pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace><authority>Perseus Project</authority></publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
	<p>Created in electronic form.
      </p></sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>

    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl>
	<refState unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
	<language ident="en">English
	</language><language ident="greek">Greek
      </language></langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
    
    <revisionDesc><!--
      <change><date>24 September 1999</date>
	<respStmt><name>DAS</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>
	$Log: vp.douris.xml,v $
	Revision 1.1  2009-12-09 18:06:56  rsingh04
	moved more xml files around based on copyright status

	Revision 1.4  2009/05/06 20:10:02  lcerrato
	fixed bad bibls

	Revision 1.3  2009/03/04 21:44:15  lcerrato
	fixing bad bibls

	Revision 1.2  2005/08/18 13:56:33  packel
	fixed item tags

	Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 15:06:10  packel
	Converted to XML
	
Revision 1.5  2003/07/01 22:18:53  yorkc
Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)

Revision 1.4  2000/06/19 21:39:29  dasmith
Make all FIGURES REND="float".

Revision 1.3  2000/03/04 20:35:23  dasmith
Added separate funder entity to TEI header.

Revision 1.2  1999/09/24 22:19:50  dasmith
Converted to TEI2 tagging.


</item></change>
    --> <change when="2014-11-13" who="Stella Dee">edited markup and assigned CTS URN</change></revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
<text><body>
<div type="section" n="1"><head>Introduction</head>
<p>The name of Douris is known from his signatures on more than 50 vases. Most of these are drinking cups, but Douris also decorated vases of other shapes. He signed most often as painter, but on a round aryballos in Athens he signed as potter (<rs key="Perseus:object:Athens 15375" type="vase">Athens 15375</rs>, <bibl>ARV2, 447, 274</bibl>), and on a kantharos in Brussels he signed twice, once as potter and again as painter (<rs key="Perseus:object:Brussels A 718" type="vase">Brussels A 718</rs>, <figure n="1993.01.0408" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1993.01.0407" rend="float"></figure>; <bibl>ARV2, 445, 256</bibl>). The frequency with which Douris signs stands in marked contrast to the practice of his contemporaries. In the tradition of the Pioneers, he enjoyed writing, and was better at it than most of his fellow vase painters in spite of occasional misspellings.</p>

<p>The pattern with which Douris signs, whether often or not at all, helps establish a sequence for the vases. Beazley based his chronology for Douris on the signatures as well as kalos names, collaboration with potters, systems of ornament, and stylistic development. Beazley divided Douris' work into four periods: Early, Early Middle, Middle, and Late. The Early Middle or Transitional Period can be further subdivided into a 'rich' and a 'bare' group.</p>

<p>Signatures appear less frequently toward the end of his Middle Period and cease altogether in the Late Period. Douris' stylistic development is also linked with different kalos names: Chairestratos and Panaitios, which occur early, and Hippodamas, a favorite in the Middle Period. Besides helping establish an internal chronology, two of these names have been connected with historical figures: Panaitios, who took part in the Persian wars (<bibl n="Hdt. 8.82">Hdt. 8.82</bibl>); and Hippodamas, who was strategos in 459/8. A third name, Hermolykos, appears on a cup in the Getty Museum (<rs key="Perseus:object:Malibu 83.AE.217" type="vase">Malibu 83.AE.217</rs>; <figure n="1990.05.0219" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1990.05.0220" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1990.05.0221" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1990.05.0222" rend="float"></figure>) and Herodotus mentions a man of this name who distinguished himself in the Persian wars at the battle of Mykale in 479 B.C. (<bibl n="Hdt. 9.105">Hdt. 9.105</bibl>).<note anchored="true" n="1"><p>Hippodamas: <title>IG</title> I 433, 63; Hermolykos: <bibl>D. Buitron-Oliver, "A Cup for a Hero," <title>Greek Vases in the J. Paul Getty Museum</title> 5 (Malibu, 1991) 70-71</bibl>.</p></note> Finally, Athenodotos is written on a cup in Athens where the name of Douris, perhaps the vase-painter Douris is invoked (<rs key="Perseus:object:Athens 1666" type="vase">Athens 1666</rs>, <bibl>ARV2, 1567, 13</bibl>). Athenodotos is named as kalos on two vases that also praise Leagros (<rs key="Perseus:object:Boston 10.179" type="vase">Boston 10.179</rs>; <bibl>CB no. 74</bibl>; <bibl>ARV2, 327, 110</bibl>; <rs key="Perseus:object:London 97.10-28.1" type="vase">London 97.10-28.1</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 354, 24</bibl>).</p>

<milestone ed="JG" unit="Card"/>

<p>Ernst Langlotz, in his fundamental study on the chronology of archaic vase-painting and sculpture, argued that the Leagros, son of Glaukon, named on vases, provided a fixed chronological point in the development of red-figure painting.<note anchored="true" n="2"><p><bibl>E. Langlotz, <title>Zur Zeitbestimmung der strengrotfigurigen Vasenmalerei und der gleichzeitigen Plastik</title> (Leipzig, 1920) 48-52</bibl>.</p></note> Leagros was a contemporary of Themistokles who was strategos in 465 B.C., so if Themistokles was sixty years old when he was strategos, as Langlotz calculates, his Ephebic years, when he would have been kalos, fall between 510 and 505 B.C. Vases praising his contemporary Leagros would therefore date to this period. E.D. Francis and Michael Vickers drew attention to some of the problems raised by Langlotz' conclusions, not the least of which is the likelihood that Leagros, presumably a youth of exceptional beauty, might have been called kalos for a much longer period than five years.<note anchored="true" n="3"><p><bibl>E. D. Francis and M. Vickers, "Leagros kalos," <title>Proceedings of the Cambridge Philological Society</title> 207 (New Series, No. 27, 1981) 97-136</bibl>.</p></note> Although the traditional dating is therefore less than certain, it does perhaps provide a general indication of the period in which Douris was active. Langlotz' method of dating with the help of kalos names does not contradict what we know of the careers of the named individuals. For example, if Hermolykos was kalos at age 18 or so, between 495-490 B.C., he would have been thirty when he fought at Mykale; and if Hippodamas was kalos between 490-480, he would have been strategos in his mid to late forties. For Hippodamas there is additional evidence in the form of a cup fragment from the Persian debris on the Acropolis on which he is praised (<rs key="Perseus:object:Athens, Acr. 311" type="vase">Athens, Acr. 311</rs>, <bibl>ARV2, 478, 314</bibl>). We can extrapolate that the career of Douris probably began before 500 and his Middle Period style was reached by 490/485.</p>

<milestone ed="JG" unit="Card"/>

<p>Evidence of another kind can be used to place Douris' Late Period in time: the appearance in his repertory of a new shape, the rhyton. Herbert Hoffmann suggested that this shape, which had its origin in Persia, appears in Greece in the wake of the Persian wars, that is, shortly after 480 B.C.<note anchored="true" n="4"><p><bibl>H. Hoffmann, "The Persian Origin of Attic Rhyta," <title>AK</title> 4 (1961) 21-6</bibl>.</p></note> Hoffmann places the rhyta by Douris, along with those by the Brygos Painter, in the early phase of development of the shape, that is, in the 470s. Douris' career might therefore span a thirty- or forty-year period, from shortly before 500 to 470 or slightly later.</p></div> 

<div type="section" n="2"><head>Early Period</head>

<p>In his Early Period, Douris painted cups made by at least three potters, one of whom, Euphronios, was his teacher. The earliest cups by Douris share the kalos name Chairestratos, and a special border, a trapped meander framing the tondo and serving as a ground-line on the exterior. The subject matter of the early vases focuses on komasts in scenes of revel, or on warriors. A cup in Baltimore (<rs key="Perseus:object:Baltimore, Hopkins AIA B8" type="vase">Baltimore, Hopkins AIA B8</rs>; <figure n="1990.06.0273" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1990.06.0274" rend="float"></figure>) shows two running warriors, the one in front wearing Attic armor and carrying a shield (device: lion head); the second figure, an archer, gorytos on his hip, wears an oriental sleeved and trousered combination with a thin chiton over it, and a soft, peaked hat with ear flaps. These warriors with their limber poses may be compared with the Amazons on the body of Euphronios' volute krater in Arezzo (<rs key="Perseus:object:Arezzo 1465" type="vase">Arezzo 1465</rs>; <figure n="1993.01.0360" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1993.01.0361" rend="float"></figure>; <bibl>ARV2, 15, 6</bibl>). The oriental sleeved and trousered combination featured by Douris, a favorite also with his contemporaries, was popularized by Euphronios. Like Euphronios, Douris was interested in the contrasting effects of different strengths of glazes, but he uses them in an original way to help unify and focus his tondo compositions, juxtaposing areas of dilute or full-strength glaze with the patterns created by the lines of drapery folds. On the cup in Baltimore, the dilute glaze lines of the archer's chiton contrast with the eastern style black striped garment worn underneath. In this scene Douris utilizes a standard compositional type which reflects an actual situation in battle when lightly-armed archers shot from the cover of the hoplite's shield. The round shields echoing the circular frame combined with the diagonal lines of limbs and spears make it an attractive tondo composition. Here, Douris extends the repetition of diagonals created by the juxtaposed limbs by giving the archer a spear paralleling that of the hoplite instead of the bow he should normally carry. Douris exhibits skill and individuality in using groups of lines and gradations of glaze to help centralize and enliven the scene.</p>

<milestone ed="JG" unit="Card"/>

<p>Euphronios also influenced Douris' fellow cup painters, especially Onesimos, who, like Douris, painted cups made by Euphronios. Beazley suggested that Douris and Onesimos sat side by side in Euphronios' workshop and the two younger painters shared subject matter, ornamental borders, and unusual techniques in their early periods; yet their artistic personalities were different. Comparison of the fight scene on the exterior of a cup by Douris in Boston (<rs key="Perseus:object:Boston 00.338" type="vase">Boston 00.338</rs>; <bibl>CB no. 125</bibl>; <figure n="1990.24.0446" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1992.11.0294" rend="float"></figure>) with a fight scene by Onesimos also on a cup in Boston (<rs key="Perseus:object:Boston 01.8021" type="vase">Boston 01.8021</rs>; <figure n="1992.11.0159" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1992.11.0160" rend="float"></figure>; <bibl>CB no. 75</bibl>; <bibl>ARV2, 320, 14</bibl>) makes the difference clear. The figures by Douris seem posed, graceful, and beautifully spaced in the composition. In the scene by Onesimos the figures are larger and closer together, the proportions somewhat clumsy, and it is clear that Onesimos' prime concerns are to convey vigorous action, vivid characterization, and effective narrative. Like Euphronios, Onesimos is willing to sacrifice elegance to naturalistic effect. Douris is not; his primary interest is in creating an elegant, graceful picture, but it might have been at least partly due to Onesimos that he developed his own more subtle method of story-telling. Euphronios and Onesimos remained the major influences on Douris throughout the Early Period.</p></div>

<div type="section" n="3"><head>Early Middle or Transitional Period</head>

<p>In the next period, the workshop collaboration with Euphronios appears to have ended. Douris is his own potter in one documented instance in this period, the signed kantharos in Brussels (<rs key="Perseus:object:Brussels A 718" type="vase">Brussels A 718</rs>, <figure n="1993.01.0408" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1993.01.0407" rend="float"></figure>). Douris also collaborated with the potter Kleophrades, and he began his long association with the potter Python. Chairestratos is still the favorite kalos-name but there are others, among them Panaitios, which is found on many cups by Onesimos as well. Douris' figures have now become more naturalistic, they move easily and stand gracefully. His talent as a master of composition and his ability as a subtle story-teller become apparent.</p>

<p>In this period Douris experiments with two different approaches to vase decoration, one a "rich style," characterized by more crowded compositions, elaborately patterned drapery, complex, often unusual, ornamental borders, unusual schemes of decoration such as zoned cups, and full use of linear detail juxtaposed with dilute and regular strength glaze. Douris used the rich style mainly for mythological subjects. In the "bare style" Douris focused on athletic and courting scenes which called for less crowded compositions and simple ornamental schemes. In these cups Douris could experiment with drawing the male body in a variety of poses.</p></div>

<div type="section" n="4"><head>Early Middle or Transitional Period: "Rich" Style</head>

<p>A cup in Vienna is an example of Douris' Transitional "rich" style at its best (<rs key="Perseus:object:Vienna 3695" type="vase">Vienna 3695</rs>; <figure n="1993.01.0320" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1993.01.0322" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1993.01.0321" rend="float"></figure>; <bibl>ARV2, 429, 26</bibl>). The three pictures depict episodes involving the arms of Achilles: on the exterior, the quarrel of Ajax and Odysseus on side A, and the vote with Athena presiding on side B. The identity of the figures in the tondo is not certain, but it must be Odysseus presenting the arms of Achilles to Neoptolemos. The young Neoptolemos has a more compact and unified body than the loose-limbed warriors of the Early Period. His hands and feet are smaller, and his proportions are more natural. The neck is not so long and the head is set more realistically without seeming to strain forward. The faces too show more unity. Douris no longer drew each feature separately and painstakingly; greater ease is apparent. The characteristic Dourian facial type has a turned-down mouth, long nose and heavy chin. Douris now used dilute glaze to suggest differing textures; on Neoptolemos he uses it to suggest the light fuzz of a young man's beard in front of the ears.</p>

<milestone ed="JG" unit="Card"/>

<p>The scenes on the exterior have many figures but the compositions are strongly centralized; the action is clear, the scenes easily read. Some of the eagerness and vitality of the earlier scenes is gone, but it is replaced with a masterly ability to tell a story.</p>

<p>The story of Ajax and the armor of Achilles is told by other late archaic vase painters, notably the Brygos Painter and Makron (Brygos Painter: <rs key="Perseus:object:London E 69" type="vase">London E 69</rs>, <bibl>ARV2, 369, 2</bibl>; <rs key="Perseus:object:Malibu 86.AE.286" type="vase">Malibu 86.AE.286</rs>: <figure n="1990.05.0300" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1990.05.0299" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1990.05.0301" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1990.05.0298" rend="float"></figure>; Makron: <rs key="Perseus:object:Louvre C 11271" type="vase">Louvre C 11271</rs>, <bibl>ARV2, 460, 12</bibl>; <rs key="Perseus:object:Athens, Acr. 315" type="vase">Athens, Acr. 315</rs>, <bibl>ARV2, 459, 11</bibl>).<note anchored="true" n="5"><p><bibl>D. Williams, "Ajax, Odysseus and the Arms of Achilles," <title>AK</title> 23 (1980) 137-145</bibl>.</p></note> Douris' Vienna cup is by far the most subtle in using composition, gesture and pose to convey the terrible story. On the side with the quarrel, Agamemnon, standing behind the disputed armor, forms a strong central vertical, his stance and position conveying the steadfastness of the decision against which Ajax vainly protest (<figure n="1993.01.0320" rend="float"></figure>). The movement of the Achaean warriors, three on each side of Agamemnon, leads the eye toward the center. Douris heightens the dramatic tension by placing the antagonists directly opposite each other, kept apart by the iron will of Agamemnon and the restraining hands of their companions. The arm gestures of the three central figures are used compositionally to suggest the conflict.</p>

<p>On the other side, attention is centered on Athena who stands behind the voting block and gestures to the winner, Odysseus, who raises his hands in covetous glee while Ajax, on the far right, cradles his veiled head in sorrow and shame (<figure n="1993.01.0322" rend="float"></figure>). Their emotions reflect the results of the voting in which the other figures take part, the number of votes clearly higher on Odysseus' side. Odysseus and Ajax thus frame the scene both visually and literally, and the direction of the picture flows outward from Athena toward them.</p>

<milestone ed="BZ" unit="page"/>
<milestone ed="JG" unit="Card"/>

<p>A related composition, only partly preserved, is on the interior of a phiale in Malibu (<rs key="Perseus:object:Malibu 81.AE.213" type="vase">Malibu 81.AE.213</rs>; <figure n="1990.05.0490" rend="float"></figure>) which shows running figures, a combat, and an assembly of deities. The subject is difficult to interpret. Martin Robertson has assessed the evidence and suggests that the scenes represent episodes loosely linked with the Trojan royal house, Ganymede pursued, Ganymede received by the assembled deities, and Achilles fighting Hector, the two stories providing a contrast between a transformation that led to immortality for Ganymede, and the stark death of Hector. The exterior scenes of two episodes from the story of Eurytos carry on the theme of death and survival, contrasting Herakles with Eurytos and his sons.<note anchored="true" n="6"><p><bibl>M. Robertson, "A Fragmentary Phiale by Douris," <title>Greek Vases</title> 5 (Malibu, 1991) 75-98</bibl>.</p></note></p>

<p>A white lekythos in Malibu belongs to this same period (<rs key="Perseus:object:Malibu 84.AE.770" type="vase">Malibu 84.AE.770</rs>; <figure n="1990.05.0263" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1990.05.0264" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1990.05.0265" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1990.05.0266" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1990.05.0267" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1990.05.0268" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1990.05.0269" rend="float"></figure>). Two youths arm, attended by a woman with a shield (device: quatrefoil) and spear, and a boy with a sword and spear. The figures reflect the influence of a major artistic personality of the period, the Kleophrades Painter, whose athletes also have loose-limbed but sturdily constructed bodies, square-shaped heads with strong chins and thick lips (compare for example a calyx-krater in <rs key="Perseus:object:Tarquinia RC 4196" type="vase">Tarquinia RC 4196</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 185, 35</bibl>).</p>

<p>A less common subject occurs on a white lekythos in Cleveland (<rs key="Perseus:object:Cleveland 66.114" type="vase">Cleveland 66.114</rs>; <figure n="1990.18.0054" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1990.18.0055" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1990.18.0056" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1990.18.0057" rend="float"></figure>): Atalante running from Erotes. John Boardman has proposed that Atalante, whose dislike of men is a constant theme in literature from Hesiod on, is fleeing from marriage.<note anchored="true" n="7"><p><bibl>LIMC, II 949 (J. Boardman)</bibl>; see also <bibl>CVA, Cleveland I 22D (Boulter)</bibl>.</p></note> Her running pose probably alludes to the footrace which she and her suitors engaged in and which she always won, thereby allowing her to kill the suitor who had challenged her. The garland held by one Eros would be a symbol of the marriage Atalante flees; the whip held by the other suggests that such a reluctant bride would have to be beaten into submission. Atalante's rejection of men and her desire for chastity is linked with her dedication to Artemis.</p>

<milestone ed="JG" unit="Card"/>

<p>Douris experimented with an unusual decorative scheme during this time. Five cups of the Transitional "rich" period have a figured zone around the tondo; two of them seem to be a pair, both in Berlin (<rs key="Perseus:object:Berlin F 2283" type="vase">Berlin F 2283</rs> and <rs key="Perseus:object:Berlin F 2284" type="vase">Berlin F 2284</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 429, 21-22</bibl>); and three others are in Malibu (<rs key="Perseus:object:Malibu 87.AE.11" type="vase">Malibu 87.AE.11</rs>; <rs key="Perseus:object:Malibu 87.AE.45" type="vase">Malibu 87.AE.45</rs>; <rs key="Perseus:object:Malibu 90.AE.36" type="vase">Malibu 90.AE.36</rs>). Figured zones are known in Attic black-figure but are not common on red-figure cups of the early fifth century. Contemporaries of Douris who also decorated zoned cups are the Triptolemos and Kleophrades Painters, and since Kleophrades the potter signed the foot of one of Douris' Berlin cups, it is possible that the scheme was connected to him.</p></div>

<div type="section" n="5"><head>Early Middle or Transitional Period: "Bare" Style</head>

<p>The predominant subjects of Douris' "bare" cups, athletic and courting scenes, allow Douris to experiment with drawing the male body in a variety of poses and call for less crowded compositions in which he can focus attention on the outlines of the figures and on the balance of light and dark areas. The ornament consists of reserved lines as borders. The finished product has a bare look compared with the "rich" group.</p>

<p>Douris' komasts on a cup in Boston (<rs key="Perseus:object:Boston 98.930" type="vase">Boston 98.930</rs>; <figure n="1990.24.0437" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1990.24.0438" rend="float"></figure>) demonstrate his preoccupation with outline and space. They dance independently of one another, not yet united by a rhythm that leads the eye from one figure to the next. We do not sense a completed composition; rather these are separate studies of figures in different poses that have the appeal of a well-performed exercise.</p>

<milestone ed="JG" unit="Card"/>

<p>The masterpiece of this period is the psykter in London with a chorus of eleven cavorting satyrs (<rs key="Perseus:object:London E 768" type="vase">London E 768</rs>; <figure n="1990.33.0504.sm" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1990.33.0504.lg" rend="float"></figure>; <bibl>ARV2, 446, 262</bibl>). Their leader, with kerykeion, boots, a Thracian cloak, and traveling hat, impersonates Hermes. The spacing of the figures creates an even flow of activity around the entire vase with the satyr dressed as Hermes as an anchor. There are two groups of three satyrs, the two lateral figures focused on the central satyr who performs a trick on the ground; additionally there are two groups of two satyrs engaged in a trick with a cup. Tricks like these occur on the Boston cup (<rs key="Perseus:object:Boston 98.930" type="vase">Boston 98.930</rs>, see above) where the performers are men, not satyrs. Both compositions provided opportunities for Douris' masterly exhibition of the male figure in motion. Anatomy is detailed and precise, dilute glaze used abundantly for the inner markings such as the curly hair of the muscular divisions on the belly of the satyrs. Some of the poses have been seen previously in battle scenes, such as the satyr fallen to one knee drinking both from a wine skin and an oinochoe, the latter shown in a foreshortened front view. Others are new, such as the handstand of the satyr drinking from a cup on the ground. On both the cup and the psykter we see a figure bent sideways at the waist, his torso shown in a three-quarter view; on the psykter, the satyr kicks up his right leg behind him. Douris' signature as painter is directly above this figure, and he may have been especially proud of it; the pose occurs again for satyrs on his later cups (for example <rs key="Perseus:object:Munich 2647" type="vase">Munich 2647</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 438, 132</bibl>; see below).</p>

<p>Beazley noted that these satyrs show the influence of the Berlin Painter.<note anchored="true" n="8"><p><bibl>J.D. Beazley, "The Master of the Berlin Amphora," <title>JHS</title> 31 (1911) 177, 291</bibl>.</p></note> Anatomical details are clearly different, but, as Beazley also remarked, the two painters are similar temperamentally. Both incorporate the revolutionary advances of the Pioneers but employ them for a decorative end; their prime concern is creating an attractive design. The Berlin Painter is a purist, however, in comparison with Douris and tends not to attempt the peculiar perspective views of the body with which we see Douris experimenting.</p>

<milestone ed="JG" unit="Card"/>

<p>The general effect of the psykter is of a virtuoso demonstration of draftsmanship, but upon close examination we see that the figures are not rendered realistically. For example, the two arms of the satyr performing the handstand are of unequal lengths, and the bend of the figure kicking up his leg to the side is not reflected in his chest muscles. Characteristically, Douris' manner of drawing is elegant, graceful and precise, but he decided not to strive for naturalism at the cost of elegance, and his use of perspective views and unusual poses is ultimately done for decorative effect.</p></div>

<div type="section" n="6"><head>Middle Period</head>

<p>The vases of the Middle Period illustrate the consolidation of the two approaches apparent in Douris' earlier work. From the "rich" vases he retains a love for elaborate ornament which is developed into a standard scheme for the decoration of cups: around the tondo a distinctive border consisting of 'Dourian' meanders<note anchored="true" n="9"><p>A meander peculiar to Douris in which the ductus goes into the center of the maze and does not come out again.</p></note> alternating with cross-squares; on the exterior, lavish palmette clusters at the handles. About forty percent of the extant vases by Douris are assigned to the Middle Period, and it is the work of this period that inspired his numerous following. As we turn from the charming and lively products of his formative stages to the balance and grace of his mature work, two distinct changes must be noted. Douris no longer experiments widely with varied and lavish ornamental schemes. His standardization of ornament may follow upon his close association with one potter, Python, who was responsible for almost all the cups of the period. There is also a change in the inscriptions: signatures and kalos names become less frequent, and Hippodamas, the kalos name after which the Middle Period is sometimes called, replaces Chairestratos.</p>

<p>A cup in Berlin (<rs key="Perseus:object:Berlin F 2285" type="vase">Berlin F 2285</rs>; <figure n="1992.07.0220" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1992.07.0225" rend="float"></figure>) was one of the first vases by Douris to provoke extensive scholarly discussion. It illustrates the three main disciplines of Athenian education: athletics, music, and grammar. The scene in the tondo shows a youth preparing for exercise, his discarded clothing on a stool, his walking cane propped against a basin, his athletic equipment ready at hand (<figure n="1992.07.0221" rend="float"></figure>). The exterior scenes preserve one of the earliest representations of a school known in vase-painting; its appearance on vases coincides with the earliest mention of schools in literature.<note anchored="true" n="10"><p><bibl>H. Immerwahr, "Book Rolls on Attic Vases," <title>Classical, Mediaeval and Renaissance Studies in Honor of Berthold Louis Ullman</title> vol. I (Rome, 1964) 17</bibl>; and <bibl>Immerwahr, "More Book Rolls on Attic Vases," <title>AK</title> 16 (1973) 143-7</bibl>.</p></note> The composition is a version of what became the standard courting or conversation scene, one with figures alternately standing or seated, a type that dominated Douris' output during the Middle Period. On the Berlin cup, the details are unusual: the waiting pedagogue to the right of each scene, the writing tablets in use and hung on the wall, and the roll with the beginning of a literary text. The man seated in the center of side A holds a partly open book roll on which can be read: <foreign xml:lang="greek">*M*O*I*S*A *M*O*I</foreign> / <foreign xml:lang="greek">*A*F*I *S*K*A*M*A*N*D*R*O*N</foreign> / <foreign xml:lang="greek">*E*U*R*W*N *A*R*X*O*M*A*I</foreign> / <foreign xml:lang="greek">*A*E*I*N*D*E*N</foreign> "Muse to me... I begin to sing of wide-flowing Scamander." (<figure n="1992.07.0228" rend="float"></figure>)  The line has been associated with Stesichorus.<note anchored="true" n="11"><p><bibl>J.D. Beazley, "Hymn to Hermes," <title>AJA</title> 52 (1948) 338</bibl>.</p></note></p>

<milestone ed="JG" unit="Card"/>

<p>A cup in Malibu (<rs key="Perseus:object:Malibu 86.AE.290" type="vase">Malibu 86.AE.290</rs>; <figure n="1990.05.0303" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1990.05.0304" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1990.05.0305" rend="float"></figure>) illustrates Douris' developed conversation scenes. A man and a youth with a lyre, perhaps engaged in a music lesson, are in the tondo. The figures are beautifully placed within the circle, filling it comfortably without a sense of crowding. The larger figure of the man is slightly closer to the center of the circle; the smaller youth is to the right, balanced by the stool on the left. The quiet poses, sense of space, and general lucidity of the composition suggest an almost classic art. The balance of light and dark achieved in the figured scene is reinforced by the standard Middle Period border of cross-squares and meanders alternating one to one. The quiet poses of the figures in the tondo carry through to the exterior scenes of men courting youths; on each side are two pairs of seated youths and standing men with another man to the right of the scene. The basic poses of each pair are the same, but the gestures vary, and the question arises whether Douris meant to represent the same couple in four stages of courtship, or four different couples.</p>

<p>A small stemless cup in Oxford (formerly at Harvard, Rosenberg Collection, <bibl>ARV2, 445, 252</bibl>) decorated inside only gives an unusual glimpse into a Greek wine shop. A youth wearing soft leather shoes and carrying a purse stands between two large wine jars. Only the upper corner of the one on the right is visible. Its scale is larger than the other, which is set in a stand near the youth's feet. A third vase, a small oinochoe, is suspended behind the youth. The different sizes, and the arrangement of the three vases receding in space, suggest some deliberate attempts at perspective. Other examples of this appear sporadically in Douris' work. The youth holds either a sponge or a stopper in his right hand. If it is a sponge, he may be testing the taste and bouquet of the wine. An inscription on the left reads <foreign xml:lang="greek">*T*R*I*K*O*T*U*L*O*S</foreign> which Immerwahr suggests translating as "holding three kotylai (or measures)" or "costing (an obol) for three kotylai."<note anchored="true" n="12"><p><bibl>H. Immerwahr, "An Athenian Wineshop," <title>Transactions of the American Philological Association</title> 79 (1948) 184-190</bibl>.</p></note></p>

<milestone ed="BZ" unit="page"/>
<milestone ed="JG" unit="Card"/>

<p>Two women preparing wool are featured in the tondo of a cup in Berlin (<rs key="Perseus:object:Berlin F 2289" type="vase">Berlin F 2289</rs>; <figure n="1992.07.0423" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1992.07.0426" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1992.07.0433" rend="float"></figure>). The seated woman is spinning or combing wool without implements, rolling the fibers between hand and shin, a process for which an onos or epinetron might be used, although it is absent in this scene. Douris and his contemporaries often represented women occupied with the crafts for which they were esteemed in antiquity. The scenes on the interior and exterior of this cup might be interpreted as illustrating the different social lives of men and women. The males on the exterior are revelers perhaps returning home from a party. One of them wears a sakkos instead of a wreath, perhaps in imitation of 'Anacreontic' dress, a style of clothing associated with Anacreon's stay in Athens.<note anchored="true" n="13"><p><bibl>Kurtz &amp; Boardman 1986, 50-70</bibl>; for another interpretation see  <bibl>Keuls 1985, 357</bibl>; compare <rs key="Perseus:object:Munich 2647" type="vase">Munich 2647</rs> below.</p></note></p>

<milestone ed="JG" unit="Card"/>

<p>Among the mythological scenes painted in the Middle Period is one of Douris' masterpieces: a cup in Paris with Eos and Memnon in the tondo (<rs key="Perseus:object:Louvre G 115" type="vase">Louvre G 115</rs>; <figure n="1992.06.0575" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1992.06.0576" rend="float"></figure>). The forms of the composition work in harmony with the subject matter to evoke a feeling of noble pathos. Eos forms a strong central vertical, her robes and wings powerful yet graceful. The impression of her strength is reinforced by the ease with which she lifts the stiff, brittle corpse of Memnon. His body forms a diagonal across the tondo, his right leg, arms, and head (but not his hair) drooping, while his torso remains stiff. His body seems almost weightless. Eos' wings are lifted suggesting her imminent flight to carry her son home to Africa. Her face is without emotion, and it is her strength and larger size in relation to Memnon that convey her protective, maternal role and elicit our compassion. This masterly adjustment of the size of the figures in relation to the space of the tondo, the sense of repose and inevitability with which the story is told again bring forth a classic spirit.</p>

<p>The exterior shows fight scenes. On side A, Menelaos chases Paris, whose mouth is open as he gasps for breath; Hera and Artemis are in the wings. On side B, Athena and Apollo flank Ajax, who, armed with shield and spear, has hurled a rock at Hector, a method of combat he resorted to several times according to Homer (<bibl n="Hom. Il. 7.268">Hom. Il. 7.268-272</bibl>; <bibl n="Hom. Il. 14.409">Hom. Il. 14.409-415</bibl>).</p>

<milestone ed="BZ" unit="page"/>
<milestone ed="JG" unit="Card"/>

<p>A cup in Malibu (<rs key="Perseus:object:Malibu 84.AE.569" type="vase">Malibu 84.AE.569</rs>; <figure n="1990.05.0257" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1990.05.0258" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1990.05.0259" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1990.05.0260" rend="float"></figure>) and the cup with Eos and Memnon share the tongue pattern forming the line of the tondo exergue. The figure style shows many similarities as well. In the Malibu tondo, a bearded man, perhaps Zeus, sits on a stool before an elaborate altar with a snake pediment and palmette acroterion. He holds a kylix straight out in front of him, a little too close to the youth, Ganymede, who has had to contract his own arm and holds his oinochoe awkwardly in order to pour into the cup. Zeus displays an eager impetuosity before which Ganymede retreats slightly, a subtlety of emotion effectively conveyed by Douris.</p>

<p>On the exterior, Zeus and Eos, both named, capture respectively, Ganymede and Tithonos (also named), in the presence of five dignified, fully dressed men with sceptres who raise their arms in surprise. The two men on the left of Eos are named: they are Pandion and Kekrops, legendary kings of Athens and eponymous heroes for whom two of Kleisthenes' ten tribes were named. On the analogy of these, one of the men on the other side might be Erechtheus.</p>

<milestone ed="JG" unit="Card"/>

<p>Douris paints fewer satyrs and Dionysiac thiasoi than do his contemporaries, the Brygos Painter and Makron. His satyrs make their earliest appearance on the psykter in London (<rs key="Perseus:object:London E 768" type="vase">London E 768</rs>, see above) where they have become a vehicle for more exuberant and improbable poses than Douris seemed to have thought proper for the ordinary mortal komasts which are their model. A cup in Boston (<rs key="Perseus:object:Boston 00.499" type="vase">Boston 00.499</rs>; <bibl>CB no. 129</bibl>; <figure n="1990.24.0440" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1990.24.0441" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1990.24.0442" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1990.24.0443" rend="float"></figure>) shows Dionysos in the tondo, with satyrs and maenads on the exterior. The satyrs and maenads dance in harmony except for one hairy satyr, his face shown frontally, who leaps exuberantly, one leg kicked up behind at the knees in a pose similar to that of one of the satyrs on the London psykter. Perhaps this fellow has instigated a riot on the other side where the same satyr and his balding companion chase the now infuriated maenads. The maenads have pulled their chitons over their hands to make wing sleeves. This rendering is often seen in maenads by the Brygos and Briseis Painters as well, and may reflect the dance of a maenad chorus.<note anchored="true" n="14"><p>On wing sleeves see <bibl>CB ii p. 40</bibl>; <bibl>M.W. Edwards, "Representation of Maenads on Archaic Red-Figure Vases," <title>JHS</title> 80 (1960) 82-3</bibl>; on the maenad chorus see <bibl>T.B.L. Webster, <title>The Greek Chorus</title> (London, 1970) 17-18</bibl>.</p></note></p>

<p>The large number of cups placed in Douris' Middle Period show the artist moving from the remarkable degree of care and subtlety he bestowed on his Transitional vases, especially those depicting mythological subjects, to a rather freer, less detailed rendering especially evident in the genre scenes, which dominate the Middle Period output. The simplification of Douris' art might have come about because of his success and the consequent greater demand for his work. The Berlin School cup, the Malibu conversation cup and the Eos and Memnon cup show Douris at his best. In these cups, to a greater degree than any of his contemporaries, he reflects something of the early classical spirit of the period.</p></div>

<div type="section" n="7"><head>Late Period</head>

<p>Douris' drawing style does not develop in new directions in the Late Period. He had achieved the height of his style in the Middle Period, the perfect blend of grace and ease, the attainment, on some cups, of a 'classic' spirit. Douris continues to make use of many of the same forms, but his inspiration seems diminished. Nevertheless, he is still capable of charm, and occasional surprises, such as the unusual number of new vase shapes that he decorates at this time: pyxides, rhyta, and an oinochoe.</p>

<p>The transition to the Late Period is gradual. Signatures, which had become less frequent through the Middle Period, now cease altogether. Kalos names become rare, but three are present: Hiketes, Polyphrasmon and Leosthenes. The favorite border, which had already made an appearance in the later Middle Period, consists of cross-squares alternating with meander pairs. Handle palmettes now sprout extra buds, leaves and tendrils, a trend also started in the Middle Period. Douris sometimes adds extra buds, leaves and tendrils to the figured compositions as well. The continuity of style and ornament from the Middle to Late Period is consistent with Douris' steady relationship with the potter Python, who made most of the preserved, complete cups in this groups including a large number decorated on the inside only.</p>

<p>A cup in Munich (<rs key="Perseus:object:Munich 2646" type="vase">Munich 2646</rs>; <figure n="1990.34.0429" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1990.34.0435" rend="float"></figure>) falls early in the sequence. The symposion in the tondo shows a youthful musician with a flute accompanying a singer holding a stemless cup in one hand; the words of a drinking song emanate from his mouth: <foreign xml:lang="greek">*O*Y *D*Y*N*A*M*O*Y</foreign>, "I cannot...," which has been connected with the beginning of a drinking song by Theognis.<note anchored="true" n="15"><p><bibl>Hartwig 1893, 258, note 8</bibl>; for the line from Theognis see Loeb Classical Library, <title>Elegy and Iambus</title> I vv. 939-942.</p></note></p>

<milestone ed="JG" unit="Card"/>

<p>One exterior picture on the Munich cup shows Herakles attacking his music teacher Linos who, according to the mythological tradition, had struck him. Linos stretches out his left arm in supplication and, in a dramatic gesture, throws up his right arm holding his lyre. The sturdy, youthful hero, characterized by his fierce, round eye, recalls earlier versions of Herakles by Douris, but the pose of the figure on the Munich cup seems frozen in comparison. Herakles' weapon is the broken stool he or Linos was sitting on, the rest of which is shown on the ground behind the fleeing youths.</p>

<p>The other exterior picture on the Munich cup shows a courting scene, three pairs of men and youths conversing, the pair in the center raising their hands in a rhetorical gesture.<note anchored="true" n="16"><p>See <bibl>Neumann 1965, 11</bibl>.</p></note> A palaestra setting is suggested by the strigil and athletic equipment carried by the man in the center.</p>

<p>Douris' delight and skill in drawing komasts persists. The tondo of another cup in Munich (<rs key="Perseus:object:Munich 2647" type="vase">Munich 2647</rs>; <figure n="1990.34.0442" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1990.34.0448" rend="float"></figure>) shows two komasts, one in 'Anacreontic' dress, holding drinking cups and a wine amphora as they dance. On the exterior, Dionysos, satyrs and maenads cavort. Dionysos holds a kantharos above the head of the satyr in the center of side A, as if he is about to balance it on his head. The maenads have made wing sleeves like those on the Middle Period cup in Boston (<rs key="Perseus:object:Boston 00.499" type="vase">Boston 00.499</rs>; <bibl>CB no. 129</bibl>; see above), but their dress is less realistic; their breasts are emphasized by short converging lines that interrupt the vertical folds. On both sides of this cup a satyr closes in on a maenad, one leg raised. On side B he has her between his legs but on side A she has eluded him, and though he grasps her arm, his legs do not trap her. This satyr is infibulated, while the others have no visible erection. The ithyphallic satyr in the tondo of a cup in Boston (<rs key="Perseus:object:Boston 00.343" type="vase">Boston 00.343</rs>; <bibl>CB no. 132</bibl>; <figure n="1990.24.0433" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1990.24.0434" rend="float"></figure>) has progressed beyond this preliminary attack and has his leg well hooked around the tall maenad's hips. Two other satyrs, both infibulated, cavort beside the struggling pair. Rather than the usual exergue, Douris draws a wavy line to indicate the wild country where satyrs and maenads live.</p>

<milestone ed="BZ" unit="page"/>
<milestone ed="JG" unit="Card"/>

<p>In the tondo of a cup in Baltimore (<rs key="Perseus:object:Baltimore, Hopkins AIA B9" type="vase">Baltimore, Hopkins AIA B9</rs>; <figure n="1990.06.0371" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1990.06.0378" rend="float"></figure>), Hermes shows a boy how to spin a top, and the poses of the figures reflect the turn of the top. The connection of Hermes with this toy is attested on other vases, as well as in a verse from the Palatine Anthology.<note anchored="true" n="17"><p><bibl>Palatine Anthology VI, 309, third century B.C. Loeb Classical Library I p. 467</bibl>; on tops see <bibl>A.D. Trendall and G. Schneider-Hermann, "Eros with a Whipping-top on an Apulian Pelike," <title>BABesch</title> 50 (1975) 269</bibl>; and <bibl>D.W. Gould, "The Uncertain Fate of a Princely Diversion," <title>Expedition</title> (1980) 43-7</bibl>.</p></note></p>

<p>A scene of love-making appears on a cup in Boston (<rs key="Perseus:object:Boston 1970.233" type="vase">Boston 1970.233</rs>; <figure n="1990.24.0436" rend="float"></figure>). Beazley questioned whether this cup was not a school piece, and though the symplegma portrayed is without parallel in Douris' work, the drawing, especially that of the man's stomach, is quite characteristic of Douris himself.<note anchored="true" n="18"><p>On the subject see <bibl>Johns 1982</bibl>; and <bibl>Keuls 1985</bibl>.</p></note></p>

<p>A lion head rhyton in Paris (<rs key="Perseus:object:Louvre MNB 1294" type="vase">Louvre MNB 1294</rs> or <rs key="Perseus:object:Louvre H 65" type="vase">Louvre H 65</rs>; <figure n="1992.06.1554" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1992.06.1559" rend="float"></figure>) is one of the five rhyta decorated by Douris during his Late Period. Four of these, two with lion heads and two with vulture heads, are placed together by Herbert Hoffmann in a class named after the artist, the 'Dourian' Class. These rhyta are unusual in two respects: the choice of creatures, lions and vultures are rare; and the shape, the painted bowl, dominates the mold-made part. The lion head in Paris and another in London (<rs key="Perseus:object:London E 796" type="vase">London E 796</rs>; <bibl>ARV1, 445, 258</bibl>) were made in the same mold. Hoffmann noted that the mold appears to have been borrowed from a group of black-figure, one-handled kantharoi of the late sixth century on which similar lion heads of approximately the same size decorate the juncture of the handle rim.<note anchored="true" n="19"><p><bibl>Hoffmann 1962, 13-15</bibl>.</p></note> The bowls of the lion head rhyta provide a large field for painted decoration. On the Paris rhyton there is a tongue pattern around the rim and as a base ornament. Ornamental borders also divide the bowl into three distinct sections. Alternating black and white lozenges decorate the main central area opposite the handle and above the animal's forehead. The two sides show komasts making for the center, framed on the handle side by a meander border.</p>

<milestone ed="JG" unit="Card"/>

<p>Most of the subjects represented in the Late Period belong to well-established compositional types. Exceptions are the tondos with Hermes and the top, and the scenes of love-making. Little development in new directions is apparent in the Late Period, except in the production of different shapes such as the rhyta. Douris' drawing style is always competent and neat, but it often seems to have lost the vigor and charm of previous periods.</p>
</div>
</body></text></TEI>
