<?xml version="1.0"?>





<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Three Court Days</title>
				<title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
				<author>Alan Boegehold</author>
				<sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor><principal>Gregory Crane</principal><respStmt><resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp><name>Lisa Cerrato</name></respStmt>
				<funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB Project</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt><publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher><pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace><authority>Perseus Project</authority></publicationStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note anchored="true">Text from MS Word file.</note>
				<note anchored="true">Lowell Bowditch compared w/ printed version.</note>
				<note anchored="true">EM converted it.</note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl>	  <author>Alan Boegehold</author>
					<title>“Three Court Days” in Symposion 1990. Papers on Greek and Hellenistic Legal History</title>
					<editor role="editor">Michael Gagarin</editor>
					<pubPlace>Köln</pubPlace>
					<publisher>Böhlau Verlag,</publisher>
					<date>1991</date>
					<note anchored="true">Copyright Böhlau Verlag, and used by their permission.</note>
				</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		
		<encodingDesc>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit="section"/>
			</refsDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English
				</language><language ident="greek">Greek
				</language></langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		
		<revisionDesc><!--
			<change><date>6/5/93</date>
				<respStmt><name>EM</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
				<item>validated tagging.</item>
			</change>
			<change><date>16 September 1999</date>
				<respStmt><name>DAS</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
				<item>Changes</item>
			</change>
			<change><date>22 July 2005</date>
				<respStmt><name>DM</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
				<item>XML version</item>
			</change>
			<change><date>5/27/09</date><respStmt><name>RS</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt>
				<item>  
					$Log: boegehold.xml,v $
					Revision 1.1  2009-10-08 19:12:56  rsingh04
					began reorganizing texts module by collection.  created separate work directory in texts module to keep hopper files separate from in progress files

					Revision 1.7  2009/06/19 19:03:42  lcerrato
					fixed bad bibls

					Revision 1.6  2009/06/12 20:57:07  lcerrato
					fixed bad bibls

					Revision 1.5  2009/05/27 16:39:07  rsingh04
					added/fixed cvs log keyword

				</item>
			</change>
		--> <change when="2014-11-13" who="Stella Dee">edited markup and assigned CTS URN</change></revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="section" n="1">
				<head>Introduction</head>
				<p>As a way of showing how court procedures changed over the course of a hundred and forty years or so, an account is offered here of the way a trial might have happened on three separate court days, each representing a set of circumstances that are somewhat different from those of the others.  The first is a day sometime between ca. 460 and 410 B.C.  The second represents a time between 410 and ca. 340, the third, a time between ca. 340 and 322.</p>
				<p>The three segments of time which these dates bracket are not to be thought of as eras or as stages in the development of dikastic procedures at Athens.  It happens we know of certain changes in procedure at or around these dates, and these changes are important enough to cite as markers, i.e. reference points that offer a place to stop and take a focused look before continuing on in what is finally a good long history.  But the points of demarcation offered here do not show when <emph>all</emph> the changes of the preceding years were effected.  The change in voting procedure, for instance, from one pebble to two specially designed ballots seems to have been made sometime after 405 but before the middle of the fourth century (<title>IG II(2)</title> 1641, lines 25-33; <title>IG II(2)</title> 1646, line 8; <bibl n="Aeschin. 1.79">Aeschin. 1.79</bibl>).  What might be called the old style of voting, therefore, obtained throughout the first of my arbitrary (in some respects) segments, and during an undetermined part of the second.</p>
				<p>A tripartite division such as this has an obvious affinity with learned arrangements by which certain prehistoric cultures are divided into Early, Middle, and Late.  And in fact when so much is unknown, there is a natural order to this sort of segmenting.  But the divisions are at the same time arbitrary in that judicial procedures existed at Athens before 460, and because the court system shows fluidity throughout the one hundred and forty years this account includes.  Certain constant—we might say characterizing—features, namely large judging bodies, allotments, and secret balloting, remained essential, while Athenians modified ways by which they moved the judging bodies around, allotted courts and dikasts, and guarded the integrity of voting.  But any particular change can have been occasioned by more than one sort of person or event.  That is, perception of malpractice, or general constitutional upheaval or reform, or resentment at the outcome of a trial, or even just one man's notion of how the system could be improved—any of these could be a sufficient factor.</p>
				<p>This account takes 460 (ca.) as a beginning because in 462 an Ephialtes is credited with initiating an important if not satisfactorily documented shift in responsibilities, whereby the <term>dikastêria</term> assumed powers that the Council of the Areopagus had had previously; and not long after that, we find evidence of secret balloting.  The secret ballot is such an important discovery in constitutional and juridical determinations that in the absence of reliable information about the conduct of earlier trials, Athenians' use of a secret ballot seems appropriate as a beginning for the first of these three schematized court days.  Another distinctive Athenian practice, that of paying dikasts, also began in these years and may be connected with the institution of the secret ballot.</p>
				<p>410 is the time of another important change, namely the procedure by which dikasts were assigned to courts and to seats in those courts.  If we do not know exactly how these assignments were made, it is a likely inference that before 410 an Athenian citizen became a dikast or heliast by allotment and then was assigned (perhaps again by lot) to one particular court for a year at a time or more.  Around or shortly after 410, however, dikasts were clearly allotted to courts each day and to seating places in the courts.  They may have been sworn into the eligible body once a year; they were in any case no longer assigned to particular courts.  Chance and the god (Apollo, presumably) would make it impossible for litigants to ascertain beforehand who the dikasts were going to be on their day in court.</p>
				<p>340 (again, roughly) is the time when Athenians organized their court buildings in accordance with the procedure Aristotle describes in <bibl n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 63">Aristot. Ath. Pol. 63-69</bibl>.  Before then on a day when two or more courts functioned, all dikasts allotted to serve on that day were dispersed by panels to judge in separate buildings.  These buildings, however, could be as far apart from each other as the Odeion (at the southeastern foot of the Acropolis) and the Stoa Poikile (on the northern boundary of the Agora).  But once Athens had a single, contained complex of structures, dikasts were in a protected area when they walked to their courts.  As a consequence, litigants and others who hoped to influence judgements beforehand could not easily make contact with dikasts and be sure they would be in the right place at the right time.</p>
				<p>The year 322 is generally agreed to be the end of the Athenian democratic court procedures, at least in approximately the overall conformation they had during the preceding century.  Some features and equipment may have been the same as before, but the authority of the courts, widely recognized in the fifth and fourth centuries as paramount, appears from the time of Demetrios of Phaleron and after to be modified or diluted.</p>
				<p>In the presentation at hand, popular courts, as distinguished from homicide courts, provide the examples.  Testimonia for homicide courts give information concerning sites, furnishings, and procedure at different times but not enough for a linear account in which changes or disruptions can be illustrated by circumstantial detail.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="2">
				<head>
					<dateRange exact="none" from="-460" to="-410">460 to 410 (roughly)</dateRange>
				</head>
				<p>A citizen by a law attributed to Solon can indict anyone he perceives as doing wrong.  In cases where two parties disagree about money, informal arbitration is possible but there is no known formal, state-administered apparatus of arbitration.  To initiate an action as prosecutor, a citizen notifies a defendant formally and with witnesses.  He does this by sending a crier along with friends who will act as witnesses, or, since he knows the notification will be in a public place, he can hope to enroll casual by-standers as witnesses.  This act of formal notification, once executed, requires the defendant to appear before a magistrate.  There he answers his prosecutor's charges.  What magistrate to choose is the prosecutor's responsibility: he identifies a magistracy as appropriate for an initial hearing, and that same magistrate reserves him a place on the court calendar.  A case that involved a foreigner or metic, for instance, would begin with a hearing before the polemarch, who would then himself decide whether or not responsibility for that sort of case fell within his competence.</p>
				<p>Once a magistrate—let us say for the purposes of this reconstruction he is an archon—has acknowledged the case as one he is to administer, he fixes a day for prosecutor (or prosecutors) and defendant to appear and swear charges and denials or counter-charges.  If at his hearing (called <term>anakrisis</term>, because there was questioning to determine when and where a trial should be held) the archon determines his office does not superintend the sort of trial that the charge entails, the prosecutor can withdraw and go find the right magistrate.</p>
				<p>Suppose the archon accepts responsibility.  He has a scribe write charges and denials on a wax tablet.  He authorizes a public notification of the impending trial.  This notice he has printed in charcoal or black paint on a whitened wooden tablet, and its form is as follows:  “So-and-so, son of Q, from deme R in a sworn indictment has charged Such-and-such, son of X, from deme Y with committing the following crime(s).”  One or more crimes are specified.  After the crimes, a penalty, which may be a monetary fine or death or exile, can be written.  It is signalled by the single word “penalty.”  The defendant's sworn denial may be subjoined in some form such as follows: “I, Such-and-such, son of X, from deme Y, did not commit (whatever crime has been specified).”  The tablet (or board if it needs to be large enough to hold notices of other trials scheduled for the same day) will be displayed before the statues of the Eponymous Heroes, which stand near the southwestern corner of the Agora.  A railed fence around the ten statues holds the notices on display.</p>
				<p>Some litigants giving vent to their feelings or hoping to improve their chances used a curse.  This bit of magic was directed against the principal antagonist and any of his friends or relations who might be thought to be coming to his aid.  One form of curse was to scratch into a sheet of lead a formulaic prayer to Hermes or Demeter asking these gods to disarm so-and-so by freezing and stupefying his mind, his tongue, his arms, his legs, etc.  If an average Athenian lacked savoir-faire, he could go to the Agora and find an amanuensis who knew exactly what to do, i.e., write out the proper words, commit them to the proper material, and explain how to post the message efficaciously.  One way was to roll up the lead sheet on which the curse was scratched, drive a nail through it, and drop the package down a well, or into a grave, preferably that of someone who had died before his time.</p>
				<p>A magistracy, we can suppose, is consistently associated with a certain court, the Eleven, for instance, with Parabyston (Harpokration, s.v. Parabysto), the archon with the Odeion (Photios, s.v. Odeion). The archon's court is accordingly a long way around from the Agora, where other, contemporary courts like the Parabyston and Stoa Poikile were situated.  On occasions when a trial seemed to require a larger judging body, two or three panels met in combination to form a heliaia of one thousand or fifteen hundred dikasts.  A total of fifteen hundred dikasts could have met in the large square building (more or less regularly called Heliaia in modern studies) at the southwest corner of the Agora, or indeed in the Odeion or the Theater of Dionysos or the Pnyx, if an extraordinary heliaia of 6,000 heliasts were needed.</p>
				<p>To return to the archon, he has a list of days on which he can schedule trials in the Odeion.  For the case in question—let us say the month is Maimakterion and that the issue is alimony—he chooses the tenth day of Maimakterion.  On that day, he, the prosecutor(s) and the defendant arrive at the Odeion early in the morning.  About five hundred dikasts also arrive singly or in groups.  All of them have gotten up early.  Most reside in the city, which means they spend much of each day in the Agora whether judging or not.  They accordingly have seen the notice posted by the Eponymous Heroes and so know well in advance what the court days will be.  Men from outlying areas, however, could also participate.  For a man with a farm near Sounion or up in Akharnai, Athens is a long trip, but farming in Attica allowed trips to the city.  Grapes and olives require intensive work only at particular seasons, and on many days there needed only someone to feed and water the livestock.</p>
				<p>A dikast (or heliast in the earlier terminology) had to be at least thirty years old and a citizen.  These are what might be called generic qualifications for a dikast.  If he was listed as a state-debtor he was not allowed to judge, for a man in that category was not fully a citizen.  He had lost certain rights of citizenship.  Dikasts as a group may have averaged considerably older than thirty.  Their means are modest enough so that the obol or two or three that they earn for a day's judging is meaningful.  They also enjoy their work.  Every trial has its own drama, and it is exciting to be a participant in such dramas, many of which are literally life and death contests.  It is the pay and the excitement that may have brought countrymen in from comparatively distant places like Sounion and Akharnai.</p>
				<p>Dikasts who arrive late, i.e. after the archon has signalled that the gate is closed, will not judge that day.  The gate in question (<foreign xml:lang="greek">kigkli/s</foreign>) gives entrance through a wooden fence (<foreign xml:lang="greek">dru/faktoi</foreign>) that runs around the whole court building.  It is there to keep the world in general at a distance from the immediate area of the trial.  Interested persons could nonetheless stand by this fence, no matter that it was outside the court proper, and still try to get the attention of approaching dikasts (<bibl n="Aristoph. Wasps 552">Aristoph. Wasps 552-61</bibl>).</p>
				<p>Inasmuch as other magistracies were allotted at Athens starting well before the middle of the fifth century, it would be surprising if dikasts were not also allotted.  At least as early as 422 B.C. dikasts depended on an allotment for work (and pay) in the courts: Aristophanes (<bibl n="Aristoph. Wasps 673">Aristoph. Wasps 673-74</bibl>) cites them as rabble living off the <foreign xml:lang="greek">khqa/rion</foreign>. Whatever the exact form of this allotment, it seems to have entitled a citizen to serve as dikast for one year rather than for just one day.  It is clear in any case that dikasts were not allotted to particular courts on particular days.  If all hopeful candidates assembled at Ardettos Hill once a year and some from this number were chosen by an allotment, <term>kêtharion</term> could be a metaphorical way of referring to this allotment.  On the other hand, citizens could have been assigned to panels by allotment the day they were to judge.  There is no dependable contemporary account.</p>
				<p>The number of dikasts is large enough to give substance to the legal fiction that a dikastic panel is the city of Athens sitting in judgement.  (There can be therefore no higher tribunal to which one can appeal a verdict).  The number five-hundred, however, to take one example, is not in itself absolute: it constitutes one critical mass.  That is, for a certain class of offence, that of Socrates for instance, Athenians fixed the number of dikasts at five hundred rather than one thousand or four hundred or two hundred as the aggregation proper for an authentic verdict.  But the absence of one or two dikasts was not crucial: a panel that did not furnish its full complement of votes could deliver a verdict that would stand.  Dikasts, like citizens at a meeting of the ekklesia, were not accountable to any magistrate or any office for their judgements.  They did not have to face <term>euthynai</term> at the end of their year.  They did swear an oath, possibly on the occasion they were officially recognized as dikasts, possibly again on each court day, whereby they undertook to judge fairly.</p>
				<p>Coming into the Odeion the dikasts sit wherever they like.  The Odeion is big enough to seat easily five hundred and more, even allowing for the numerous columns that hold up its roof.  Friends, cronies, people who have some interest in common, gather in clusters.  Many carry cushions or reed mats for comfort.  They sit together and keep up a running commentary on all developments as the trial goes on.  And when they choose to approve, they make themselves heard.  They likewise make themselves heard when they do not approve.  On such occasions they might even order the speaker of the moment to step down from the <term>bêma</term>, a raised area where a speaker stood while addressing the court.</p>
				<p>When the archon decides that the panel is full he signals that all is ready, and the opposing parties enter.  There may be one prosecutor or several, so long as each has an arguable basis for complaint.  Friends, relations, and witnesses may also be in attendance.  A defendant likewise brings as many supporters as he can find or manage.  There is no apparent official control over number and identity of supporters.  He will try to include some character witnesses.  Litigants who wanted their own relevant memoranda might use wax tablets and a stylus, as in Demosthenes 46.11, or papyrus, and ordinary stew pots (<term>echinos</term>, <term>chytra</term>, or <term>lopas</term>) to transport and safeguard them for the trial.  There may have been separate <term>bêmata</term>, one for prosecution and one for defence.  Now a herald or a priest swears the dikasts.  They undertake by oath to judge without partiality, and they swear by Zeus, Demeter, and Apollo.</p>
				<p>Someone now mans the <term>klepsydra</term>.  This “water-thief” is a timekeeping device.  It consists of a terra-cotta pot with an overflow hole near its rim and a short bronze outlet pipe at its base.  The pot is filled with water, which runs out into a similar pot while litigants are speaking.  Different sorts of trials and speeches are assigned differing but stipulated amounts of time, the units of which are expressed as liquid measures.  Two <term>choes</term>, for instance, are given to the second speech in a trial where 2000-5000 drachmas are at issue.  In our terms, that would be six to eight minutes.  If the <term>klepsydra</term> is the property of a tribe, the operation of any given <term>klepsydra</term> surely remains in the hands of the tribe that owns it.</p>
				<p>A secretary reads the formal charge.  The prosecutor speaks first.  He tries to establish himself as a person whom the defendant's wrongdoing has affected directly and personally.  If he does not, five hundred Athenian dikasts might well judge him a busybody or a sycophant and discount his accusation accordingly.  It does not matter that Solon long ago established the right of “anyone who wants” to initiate a prosecution.  A litigant is expected to speak for himself in his own words.  If a citizen in these circumstances did not have a script, he would be only prudent if he availed himself of expert advice.  Courtroom speeches—those of the orators that we possess, at least—had a recognizable form.  In addition, they contained formulaic turns of speech.  The same ones can be found in orations almost a century apart.  Consider, to take a single instance, the speaker who asks for the dikasts' forbearance.  He declares he is not a trained or practiced speaker, has never in fact been in a courtroom before: the dikasts therefore must take him as he is, rough-hewn but sincere.</p>
				<p>Form and formulae, we can imagine, are elements of presentation that the dikasts expect.  Another consideration that tells against purely extemporaneous speaking in court is the<term> klepsydra</term>.  When a speaker's time is limited this way, he must, if he wants to protect his life and property, reach middle and end of what he wants to say before his water runs out.  And yet a man who had never had any instruction could hardly know what he needed to say or how long it would take him to enunciate it, nor how to ascertain degrees of irrelevance when time was measured and precious.</p>
				<p>The defendant speaks second.  In defending himself he invokes his whole life as testimony.  Military service, liturgies, family friends, children, all could be presented to a dikastic panel as causes to find the defendant not culpable.  Since he, like the plaintiff or prosecutor, is timed by the drip of water from a jar, he likewise wants urgently to reach the end of his plea or defense before all his water runs out.  Defendant and prosecutor also work under another limitation.  If either takes a line of argument that angers the dikasts, he can be made by hostile noise to step down from his <term>bêma</term> before using all of his time.  Citizens—and the general public as well—could watch and listen to trials from outside.  Speakers appeal to them regularly as <foreign xml:lang="greek">periesthko/tes</foreign> and we can visualize them standing just outside whatever area or building has been delimited as the court area for the day.  They too may have influenced the proceedings with their shouts.</p>
				<p>After the two speakers finish, the dikasts vote.  No official stands up to give an objective summation of what has been said; the dikasts' vote for innocent or guilty is an immediate response to speeches they have just heard.  There were apparently two modes of voting, one of which was more general in its applications.  In this mode, two urns are set up, touching each other but standing in such a way that one can be described as nearer and one as further from the dikasts.  The nearer of the two takes the votes to condemn, the other, further away, the votes to acquit.  A dikast drops his single pebble (or seashell) into one of the two urns, and when all the dikasts have done so, officials empty one urn onto a flat stone for counting.  They count the ballots and award a verdict by simple majority.  A tie favors the defendant.  A herald announces the result.  The trial is over, and defendant either exits free, or relevant functionaries under the direction of the Eleven exact the penalty immediately.</p>
				<p>The vote was secret: each dikast could vote without anyone else knowing for whom he had voted.  References to an apparatus or fixture called <foreign xml:lang="greek">khmo/s</foreign> may provide hints as to how secrecy was made possible.  A <term>kêmos</term> (in some uses of the word) was a truncated cone of basket-work, open at both ends, and used as a trap for crabs and lobsters.  A closely woven basketwork fixture of that shape could have kept the voting secret in the following way.  The large, open end rests on the shoulders of two urns that stand side by side.  The <term>kêmos</term> rises to a smaller opening, now at the top, which becomes in effect a single mouth for both urns.  A heliast can approach the two urns, set up, it will be remembered, so that one is nearer, the other further away, put his hand with its pebble inside the mouth of the <term>kêmos</term>, and then drop his pebble into the urn he chooses.  His hand is hidden so that no one can see which urn he has chosen.  If a pebble, by rattling against the wall of an urn into which it had been dropped, could reveal a dikast's choice, a packing of straw could have deadened the noise.  In any case, the method, whatever its shortcomings, was serviceable: it was in use until sometime after 405.</p>
				<p>When a charge carried a penalty already stipulated by law, the penalty (as noted above) was exacted without delay.  There were charges, however, that required a second balloting, because the same dikastic panel that had voted to convict had also to judge what a culprit must pay or suffer.  In such cases, the prosecutor again spoke first, and within a stipulated time proposed a penalty and argued why exactly that penalty was appropriate.  Next the defendant offered his own notion of a sufficient penalty, hoping to find one just severe enough to satisfy judges who had found him guilty less than an hour before, but at the same time milder than that proposed by the prosecutor.</p>
				<p>Here a second mode of voting may have been used.  Dikasts had wooden tablets covered with wax.  A dikast, using a stylus (<foreign xml:lang="greek">e)gkentri/s</foreign>) or his fingernail, scratched a short line if he favored the defendant's proposed penalty, a long line for that proposed by the prosecutor.  A dikast voted for one or the other.  He had no other choice, except perhaps to abstain.  Here as in the first balloting a simple majority ruled, with ties going to the defendant.  (<bibl n="Aristoph. Wasps 106">Aristoph. Wasps 106-8</bibl>, <bibl n="Aristoph. Wasps 166">Aristoph. Wasps 166-67</bibl>, with scholia to 106) seems to allude to such a mode of voting in 422.  Since penalties were acted upon immediately, no need was felt for systematic record-keeping.  What's done is done.  A magistrate might include a notation in his own accounts, against the coming judicial review of his year in office, but publication of a trial's outcome was not a legal requirement .</p>
				<p>A single panel judged as many cases in a day as daylight allowed.  The <term>klepsydra</term> put foreseeable limits on the amount of time any given trial would take.  A dikast was paid for a day's work, two obols at first, then—thanks to Kleon in the 420's—three.  If it was not a grand sum, it was enough to make a difference in the way a man lived, and more than enough to sustain mere existence.  Furthermore, even when in the fourth century other sorts of pay were raised, three obols remained the pay for dikasts.</p>
				<p>To consider the magnitude of sums expended annually for dikasts, if the courts sat, let us say for the sake of example, two hundred days a year, and on each of those days two thousand dikasts judged, the total paid out was in the neighborhood of thirty-three talents.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="3">
				<head>
					<dateRange from="-409" to="-340">409-340</dateRange>
				</head>
				<p>So far as one can tell, Athenians as citizens of a democracy continued to initiate lawsuits as they had in the past.  In the case of a homicide, a member of the decedent's family, as defined in Drakon's law, might initiate a prosecution, but not just any member of the community.  In other kinds of wrongdoing, the injured person (or in the case of a woman, her <term>kyrios</term>) issued the summons (<term>prosklêsis</term>).  But when the best interests of the state were involved, anyone who wanted could be prosecutor.  The prosecutor hailed the defendant before a magistrate.  The magistrate asked enough questions to determine whether the proposed litigation fell within the area of his responsibilities, and if he decided Yes, he had a public notice posted on the railings that ran around the statues of the Eponymous Heroes.</p>
				<p>Notice of a trial started with some such form as the following, which we have preserved in a Demosthenic oration:  “Apollodoros, son of Pasion, from Akharnai [in a sworn indictment charges] Stephanos, son of Menekles, from Akharnai with giving false witness.  Penalty: one talent.  Stephanos testified falsely against me when he attested the written documents in the container.”  “I, Stephanos, son of Menekles, from the deme Akharnai, testified truly when I attested the written documents in the container.”  (<bibl n="Dem. 45.8">Dem. 45.8</bibl>; cf. <bibl n="Dem. 21.103">Dem. 21.103</bibl>). The notice next told litigants when and where to be for their day in court.  And the rest of town, always interested in some new thing, also wanted to know who was being tried, for what, and when.  Spectators, kept outside of critical areas by <term>dryphaktoi</term> but still close enough to see what was happening and to hear arguments and verdicts, and indeed to make themselves heard, continued to participate even if only marginally in the conduct of trials.</p>
				<p>Whether or not earlier in the fifth century the general body of dikasts was divided in any way—other, that is, than the formation of groups of other dikastic panels—is a matter for speculation.  It is natural to suppose that any necessary administrative divisions would have followed affiliations by tribe.  Our single <term>klepsydra</term> is labelled property “of Antiochis.” Other dikastic equipment (assuming that the <term>klepsydra</term> is dikastic) ought likewise to have been maintained and disposed as property of the tribe, and dikasts themselves may have been organized according to tribe as well.  Now, however, perhaps as soon as ca. 410, the eligible men of each tribe were allotted letters (A to K) that identified them as belonging to one of ten dikastic sections.  These sections cut across tribe lines so that each was made up of a roughly equal number of men from each of the ten tribes.  An aim of this division was to prevent men from the same tribe from making combinations by which they could influence the outcome of a trial.</p>
				<p>Assignment of section letters to dikasts could have been a simple procedure such as drawing lettered balls from a container.  It might have gone somewhat as follows: the balls, lettered A to K, are shaken up in a wickerwork vessel called <foreign xml:lang="greek">khqi/s</foreign> or <foreign xml:lang="greek">kh/qion</foreign> or <foreign xml:lang="greek">khqa/rion</foreign> (<bibl n="Aristoph. Wasps 673">Aristoph. Wasps 673-74</bibl>, with scholia). If there are two vessels to a tribe, there were perhaps 300 balls to a vessel.  Each citizen who is eligible to be a dikast draws one letter.  That letter is forthwith his section letter, and it is duly stamped into his <term>pinakion</term>.  These small tags, into which some dikasts pierced holes for string to hang around their necks, had stamped into them the dikast's name, his father's name, his demotic, and a section letter.  The section letters (A to K) label the ten dikastic sections noted above.  Bronze <term>pinakia</term> are attested in mid-fourth century, and about 150 examples are preserved.  <term>Klêrôtêria</term> could have been set up at organization areas for tribes.  These allotment machines were <term>stêlai</term> of wood or stone with columns of slots.  Along one side a tube was affixed vertically.  Suppose that as later there were two <term>klêrôtêria</term> for each tribe.  Each <term>klêrôtêrion</term> in that case would have five columns of slots, making a total of ten columns, each with a letter from A to K at its top.  Would-be dikasts plug their <term>pinakia</term> into appropriate columns.  Balls marked with the names of courts are drawn in a chance order one at a time.  Each ball in our example either assigns five dikasts to a court for the day or disqualifies five, depending on whether or not the ball is marked with the name of a court.</p>
				<p>In the present illustration, i.e. a trial held sometime between 409 and ca. 340, trials continued to be held in buildings and localities widely separated from each other.  On one and the same day, the Odeion and the Stoa Poikile could have been in use.  The building in which the heliaia met can have been the same capacious structure in the southwest corner of the Agora, although by this time Building A, under the Stoa of Attalos, seems a better candidate.  If a judging body of two thousand or more dikasts was needed, that is to say, an assembly larger than could be accommodated in the Heliaia, theoretically archons could convene such a body in the Theater of Dionysos immediately west of the Odeion; or in the Pnyx; or in the Agora, where a fence would serve to mark the venue.</p>
				<p>But to return to days on which two or more widely separated <term>dikastêria</term> were working, suppose the allotment of dikasts to courts took place in the Agora.  It is hard to see how the dikasts, after being allotted, could fail to pass through open areas in the Agora in order to reach that court.  Furthermore, if that court happened to be the Odeion, dikasts had to traverse parts of the town outside the Agora.  Aristotle in his account of later procedure (that of ca. 325) describes the courts as being within an enclosed area.  Athenians, we can infer, had come to acknowledge the possibilities of corruption at this critical point.  There may have been scandals.  Think of Anytos, who Aristotle says in 409 became known as the first man ever to corrupt a whole <term>dikastêrion</term> (<bibl n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 27.5">Aristot. Ath. Pol. 27.5</bibl>).  In the scheme under consideration here, when courts on any given day could be situated at good distances from each other, a staff was no protection.  Colored or not, a staff in the hand of a dikast would make him a target for malefactors.  That litigants could approach dikasts on their way to court and offer bribes or threats was an obvious vulnerability.  This was surely a principal consideration when Athenians later planned an enclosed complex of courts (see below).</p>
				<p>The allotment of dikasts to ten sections of the whole body of dikastai was one innovation of the late fifth century.  Another was the assignment by lot of seats, or rather of sections of the seating.  Dikasts upon entering the court to which they had been allotted drew lettered, bronze tokens.  These tokens (<term>symbola</term>) were coin-like pieces, each with a letter of an alphabet that contained in addition to the canonical letters A through <foreign xml:lang="greek">W</foreign>, an extra imported letter, <foreign xml:lang="greek">T</foreign>, which had been added on to create a twenty-fifth label.  Dikasts on entering draw a token, look at the letter, and sit in a section identified by that letter.</p>
				<p>In allotting dikasts to courts and assigning seating areas by chance Athenians were guarding against two ways by which their aim of an even-handed administration of justice could be spoiled.  First, interested persons could not approach dikasts beforehand, since neither the dikasts nor anyone else knew until the morning of their service where they would judge.  (Unfortunately, however, dikasts could still be approached en route to their courts.)  Secondly, dikasts could not sit where they liked and so form blocs of friends or relations with kindred interests.</p>
				<p>As for the actual trial, it seems to have followed the earlier plan.  A magistrate—let us say this time he is the Basileus—ascertains that the dikastic panel is full.  Early in the fourth century 500 dikasts would make up a full panel, but by the 80's an odd man had been added.  A panel now needed 501 dikasts to be full, ostensibly to make tie-votes impossible (Schol. Dem. 24.9). There was, however, no need for such a measure since the Athenians had long before established a principle that tie votes were in favor of the defendant.  The addition of an odd man may consequently attest some formal consideration or look to tradition.  The fifty-one ephetai, for instance, may have provided a model.</p>
				<p>In any case the basileus gives a signal to the herald, who in turn brings in the prosecutor (with supporters) and the defendant (likewise with supporters).  If the court in question is meeting in the Stoa Poikile, there will be <term>dryphaktoi</term>, that is railings between columns, and prosecutor and defendant will enter through a <term>kinklis</term> in those railings.  The herald announces the charges and denials.  A man is posted at the <term>klepsydra</term>, and the prosecutor begins his address to the judging panel.  He is standing on the <term>bêma</term>, and the herald stands next to him as he speaks (<bibl n="Aeschin. 1.79">Aeschin. 1.79</bibl>).  He has as much time as it takes a stipulated amount of water to run out of the <term>klepsydra</term>.  The man in charge stops the flow whenever a prosecutor is having laws, oaths, or testimonies introduced.  Anyone speaking on behalf of the prosecutor does so while the prosecution's water continues to run.  There is apparently some constraint on all litigants to keep to the point while speaking, but we do not know what the sanctions were, nor can it be clear from preserved orations, which were surely edited and sometimes augmented after having been used in court, that the injunction was consistently effective.</p>
				<p>The defendant follows, speaking under the same rules and with the same time limits.  He tries to show how unlikely the accusation against him is.  He does not cite precedents except as reminders.  A precedent cited in court had no necessary force.</p>
				<p>One new control is now available for plaintiff and defendant.  If the disputants have come to this trial by way of an arbitration that failed, neither party to the action is allowed to use any law, testimony, witness, oath or the like that was not brought forward at the arbitration or <term>anakrisis</term>.  This prohibition was meant to stop litigants from multiplying and changing documents and arguments which had not previously been considered, and thereby changing the actual question to be judged.  This innovation also reflects a time when men had come to desire the fixity and precision of a written text, as compared with the fluidity of speech.  They recognized, therefore, that there was such a thing as a true text.  For if laws, oaths, etc.  used in the trial must be the same as those cited at arbitration or <term>anakrisis</term>, two kinds of sameness are necessary.  First, the documents must be of the same sort.  That is to say, one testimony of X and one oath of Y cannot be replaced by an oath of Z or augmented by citation of a law.  Second, the wording of those documents must also be the same.  As a control, both parties have access to sealed copies of all the documents, for at the close of a failed arbitration, each contestant deposits copies of all documents in <term>echinoi</term>.  These plain, unglazed cooking vessels had lids which could be tied on with string and sealed with wax.  The <term>echinoi</term> were then entrusted to arbitrators of the litigant's own tribe and kept against the trial that was to follow.  If at the trial one party heard cited some law, testimony, or oath that had not figured in the arbitration, he could challenge his opponent.  And a response to that challenge might be for a litigant to demonstrate to the <term>dikastêrion</term> that the seal on his <term>echinos</term> was unbroken.  Once he had done that, he had the <term>echinos </term>opened.  The texts would be taken out, identified and read aloud, and the dikasts in their deliberations would weigh what they had heard.  Such confrontations could establish a basis for a challenge at the end of a trial, an important capability in view of the paramount authority of the <term>dikastêrion</term>.  There was no appeal from its judgement, although a successful challenge could lead to a trial in which false witness was charged, and that in turn could lead to a reversal.  A second control is the whitened tablet (<term>pinakion</term>) on which a witness may write his deposition (at home, if he likes), and a third is a wax tablet, which a witness might use to make (and erase) notes in responding to challenges.  (<bibl n="Dem. 46.11">Dem. 46.11</bibl>)</p>
				<p>When the defendant (and his supporters) has used up his water, i.e. said as much as his stipulated time allows, the panel of dikasts receive ballots and exiguous voting instructions.  There is no charge to the jury.  No time is given for conferring or deliberation.</p>
				<p>The manner of voting is different from that described in the preceding period.  Sometime after 405 but not later than 345, Athenians began to cast votes at trials using two official ballots, one of which signified “vote for the defendant,” the other, “vote against the defendant.”  Both ballots are made of bronze and have the shape of a disk pierced at its center, by a short tube, in one form, and by a short peg in the other.  Tube and peg constitute the essential difference between ballots, which in Greek are called accordingly “pierced” and “full.”  A pierced ballot represents a vote for the party who speaks first, i.e. the prosecutor or plaintiff.  A full ballot is a vote for the defendant.  A dikast receives two ballots, one of each sort, and holds them in either hand, thumb over one end of the axle, a finger over the other.  When he holds his ballots this way, no one can see which ballot is which.</p>
				<p>The herald's instructions amount to no more than a reminder of the unchanging convention that “pierced” is a vote for the prosecutor, “full,” for the defendant.  The dikasts take two ballots each, one of each sort, and walk to one of two amphoras, which stand near the <term>bêma</term> at the front of the court (<bibl n="Dem. 19.311">Dem. 19.311</bibl>). They drop one ballot into that amphora, and this is the ballot that counts.  The other ballot, the one that is not meant to count, goes into the other amphora, which is designated for discards.  When all the dikasts have voted, ballots from the validating amphora are emptied out and counted.  A simple majority rules.  Ties favor the defendant.</p>
				<p>In the case of a second vote, as in Plato's representation of Socrates' trial (<bibl n="Plat. Apol. 36a">Plat. Apol. 36-38b</bibl>), when alternate penalties are proposed and determined, the voting is again by ballot, a change from the special assessing tablets of twenty years or so earlier.  Penalties are exacted immediately after the vote, unless, as in the case of Socrates, special circumstances cause a delay.  The Eleven have responsibility for the execution of verdicts, unless the verdict is of a sort that authorizes a plaintiff to employ self-help.</p>
				<p>The same dikastic panel may hear a second or even third trial on the same day, so long as there is daylight.  In some instances, one whole day was given to a single trial, and a regular formula for the division of such days is fragmentarily preserved by Aristotle (<bibl n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 67">Aristot. Ath. Pol. 67</bibl>).</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="4">
				<head>
					<dateRange exact="to" from="-340" to="-322">340 (roughly) to 322</dateRange>
				</head>
				<p>Sometime around 340 the Athenians consolidated their court buildings.  We may have references to these structures in Agora inscriptions I 1749, lines 12-13, 116-117, and I 5656, lines 12-21, where a First and a Middle “New Court” are named.  To put out of the discussion for a moment the building remains under the Stoa of Attalos, what would be the architectural requirements for such a complex?  The essential organization is one of at least three buildings close enough together to be enclosed by a fence of some sort.  The fence need not be high or strong.  It merely defines an area where unauthorized persons are not supposed to be.  In the fence there are ten entrances, one for each tribe, and just outside every entrance there stand two <term>klêrôtêria</term> and ten boxes, each box labelled with one of the letters of the alphabet from A to K.  At or inside each entrance there stands a <term>hydria</term>, and somewhere nearby (just inside, it would seem) a different set of boxes.  The number of this second set of boxes varies with the number of courts in session on any given day.  Two or three will be a usual number.  The entrance itself is controlled by a gate.  Would-be-dikasts assemble by tribes, each tribe before two <term>klêrôtêria</term>, which stand outside the one gate that is reserved for that tribe.  The dikasts introduce and validate themselves as candidates by producing their <term>pinakia</term>.  These identification tags are now made of boxwood.  The information they carry is nonetheless the same as that on the earlier ones of bronze, viz. section letter, name, father's name, and demotic.  A prospective dikast, on approaching his tribal entrance, threw his <term>pinakion</term> into that one of ten boxes which was labelled with his section letter.  At the magistrate's signal, a slave picked up the boxes, each containing some dozens of <term>pinakia</term>, and shook them well.</p>
				<p>The responsible magistrate now picked a single pinakion at random out of each box and summoned its owner to step forward and act as an <term>empektês</term>, i.e. a dikast who inserts all <term>pinakia</term> bearing the same section letter as his own into appropriate slots in the <term>klêrôtêrion</term>.  These slots are cut into the stele in vertical rows and each vertical row is identified by a section letter, A to K.  Ten <term>empektai</term> consequently are chosen in this simple form of allotment, and they are assured thereby of a place on a dikastic panel for that day.  When all <term>pinakia</term> have been plugged in, the archon shakes up black and white dice in a cup (<term>oxybaphos</term> or <term>kêtharion</term>) and pours them into a tube, which is affixed vertically to one side of the face of the <term>klêrôtêrion</term>.  The end of the tube has been stopped, and so the dice are now held one on top of another in chance order.  The archon releases dice one by one, and matches each as it comes out with a horizontal row of five <term>pinakia</term>.  Each die thus validates or invalidates the applications of five would-be-dikasts at a time.  If a white die comes out, five dikasts, i.e. one from each one of the five section letters on that <term>klêrôtêrion</term>, are allotted as dikasts for the day.  A black die, on the other hand, means that five would-be-dikasts will not have work that day.  No one touches the invalidated <term>pinakia</term>:  they are left in their slots until the whole allotment is over.  The archon takes out the valid <term>pinakia</term> one by one and by calling out the names written on them, summons the dikasts one by one to the next step in their progress toward a court for the day.  This step is another allotment, one that assigns them to specific panels.  The allotment is performed in the following simple way.  Each dikast reaches into a jar (<term>hydria</term>) and withdraws what Aristotle calls an “acorn” (<term>balanos</term>). Whatever this piece might actually be, it bears one letter of the alphabet, beginning with <term>lambda</term>.  Aristotle says from <term>lambda</term> on, but one may rationally doubt whether on any given day there was need for letters beyond <term>nu</term>, for it seems otherwise likely that not more than three courts were normally in use on any one day.</p>
				<p>An allotted dikast shows the letter on his acorn to the archon, and the archon throws the dikast's <term>pinakion</term> (marked, it will be remembered, with his section letter) into a box marked with the same letter as that on the acorn.  This is one of the two or three letters, i.e.  <term>lambda</term>, <term>mu</term>, <term>nu</term>, that identify it as one of the day's courts.  The dikast then shows his acorn again to a functionary, enters the enclosure through the gate, and receives a staff whose color matches that of some easily visible part of the entrance to the court to which he has been assigned.  The staff is an easily recognizable badge that will admit him to his allotted court and deny him entrance to any other court.</p>
				<p>Each of the courts at the beginning of a court day receives a new allotted label, i.e.  letter.  But while letters change every day, the court colors remain constant.  It is according to Aristotle the <foreign xml:lang="greek">sfh/kiskos</foreign> of a court that carries the court's distinctive color, and modern students have more or less agreed to translate the Greek word as “lintel,” but the usage is singular.  Usually the word means “beam.”  A <term>thesmothetês</term>, himself chosen by allotment for this task, has already allotted letters to courts for that day.  The procedure was simple, and Aristotle does not mention <term>klêrôtêria</term> or any other apparatus such as jars or boxes in connection with this allotment.  We may suppose the way it was done was traditional and obvious to any Greek reader, and not worth discussing.  Accordingly by the time an allotted dikast receives his staff, his court building has been suitably identified by an allotment that prevents any sort of foreknowledge of that aspect of the day's proceedings.</p>
				<p>Once arrived in his court for the day, the dikast gives his acorn and staff to a functionary, receiving in turn a token picked at random that tells him where to sit.  There were twenty-five seating areas, and so when a panel was composed of five-hundred dikasts, twenty tokens were needed for each of the twenty-five letters.  The dikast in question proceeds, let us say, to area A.</p>
				<p>An allotment of magistrates to courts is meanwhile being performed by means of two <term>klêrôtêria</term> that are set up in the first of the courts.  Two sets of bronze dice come into play, one with names of offices painted on or incised, the other with colors of courts.  Two <term>thesmothetai</term>, allotted to the task, shake up the dice, pour them into the tubes, release them one by one, and match the name of the office on one ball as it comes out with the color on the other, which comes out at the same time.  As the magistrates in question are matched with colors, a herald announces the results, and they go off to their courts.</p>
				<p>At about this time, the fence that surrounds the court complex is disassembled—or the gates in it are opened so that Athenians who want to watch and listen can approach the courts.  Aischines (<bibl n="Aeschin. 3.55">Aeschin. 3.55-56</bibl>, <bibl n="Aeschin. 3.207">Aeschin. 3.207</bibl>) refers to this audience.  Most were citizens, but there were foreigners in it as well (<bibl n="Dem. 25.98">Dem. 25.98</bibl>).</p>
				<p>Once at their courts, the magistrates allot dikasts to tend to ballots, <term>klepsydra</term>, and pay-out tokens.  To do this they must have the boxes into which dikasts dropped their <term>pinakia</term> just after entering the enclosure.  These are the boxes labelled with letters that correspond to courts working that day.  There are ten of them, one from each tribal entrance.  Each now contains <term>pinakia</term> from all ten dikastic sections, i.e., <term>pinakia</term> stamped with section letters A to K.  Functionaries have brought them to their courts.  The archon has the ten boxes shaken and takes at random one <term>pinakion</term> out of each.  He drops the ten <term>pinakia</term> collected this way into a single empty box, which is shaken in its turn.  From this box the archon draws five <term>pinakia</term>.  The owner of the first will tend the <term>klepsydra</term>, and the next four, distribution, counting, and collection of ballots.  The five <term>pinakia</term> that remain in the box identify the dikasts who will supervise payment of dikasts at the end of the trial.</p>
				<p>The four dikasts allotted to ballots will be responsible for 1002 bronze ballots, five hundred and one pierced and five hundred and one full.  First they set them out—using what Aristotle calls a lampstand—and at the end they collect them.  The man at the <term>klepsydra</term> stops and starts the water as required.  At the end of the trial the men allotted to pay-out tokens organize the dikasts into proper groups and give tokens to those who vote.  No vote, no token, no pay.</p>
				<p>The trial is now ready to begin.  It would be consistent with the seriousness of the undertaking for dikasts to swear their oath at the beginning of the trial, and for there to be an altar and a sacrifice, but these sacramental or ceremonial functions are not attested.  The herald announces the names of the litigants and repeats the sworn charges and denials from the notice posted by the Eponymous Heroes.  The prosecutor or plaintiff stands and gives the details of his accusation.  His friends and relations, if he feels he needs them, also speak, although they do take up part of the time allowed him.  He and they must decide how they can help him most.  When he is through, the defendant must in his turn decide how much of the time given him he can use for his own speech, and how much to apportion to persuasive friends and relations.</p>
				<p>When the defendant (and supporters) have finished speaking, the herald announces that any challenge of the testimony must be presented before voting begins.  Such challenges continue to represent a litigant's best chance at a review of the judgement, for there was no appeal from a <term>dikastêrion</term>'s judgement otherwise.  If a panel of dikasts could be thought of as the city, and if there could be no higher tribunal than the city, then it followed that no appeal to a higher authority was possible.  If, on the other hand, testimony could be shown to be perjured or wrong, then a man who had been judged as culpable had access to a whole new set of legal manoeuvres.  After the announcement concerning challenges, the herald enunciates a convention, venerable by now, that a pierced ballot represents a vote for the prosecutor or plaintiff, a full ballot, a vote for the defendant.  There is no summation by a presiding officer nor is there any officially designated time for dikasts to confer among themselves.  They stand up from their benches and walk to a “lampstand”  (<foreign xml:lang="greek">luxnei=on</foreign> to receive their two ballots, one of each sort, and then proceed to the voting urns.  Note, however, that in the time it takes five-hundred men to do all of the foregoing, there is time for talk.</p>
				<p>In the course of receiving ballots they give up the bronze token that designated their seating area.  They drop a single ballot into an urn that holds valid ballots, and the remaining ballot into an urn that takes discards.  The one urn is bronze, can be disassembled, and has a fitting on the top that allows only one ballot to go through at a time.  The other urn, the one that takes discards, is of wood.  As each dikast votes, he receives a bronze token marked with a gamma or some other sign for three obols.  This is his pay-token.  When all the dikasts have voted, a functionary empties out the bronze urn, and all the ballots are displayed for counting.  An abacus, a board with five-hundred holes in it, receives the ballots, whose axles, hollow or full, fit them to be plugged into the board.  A magistrate counts them through, and a simple majority determines the outcome.  A tie favors the defendant.</p>
				<p>If the defendant was found innocent, he went free.  If he was found guilty, and the charge was of a sort where the <term>dikastêrion</term> had to decide upon a penalty, then each dikast received his staff back again (presumably because the act of voting took him out of the court area and he needed a badge to return) and went back into the court to hear arguments about a penalty.  Prosecutor (first) and defendant (second) propose their notions of a suitable punishment and justify their proposals as far as they can in the time it takes a half-chous of water to run out of the <term>klepsydra</term>.  After hearing these arguments, the dikasts voted again, using the same ballots and amphoras as before.  The pay-token, when a second balloting was in view, would not be handed out until there had been a vote on the penalty.</p>
				<p>Again upon voting they receive pay-tokens, and this time they will be able to turn the token in for their day's pay.  Those five dikasts who at the beginning of the day had been allotted to the task of paying now go to work: each takes charge of two boxes of <term>pinakia</term>.  There were ten of these boxes in all, one from each tribal entrance, and they had been brought to the court at the beginning of the trial.  The dikast in charge reaches in at random, picks out a <term>pinakion</term>, calls the owner's name, and the owner collects both <term>pinakion</term> and pay.  This is in fact the last allotment of the day, for the random selection of <term>pinakia</term> from the boxes constitutes yet another allotment, that which determines the order in which the dikasts were paid.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="5">
				<head>Summary</head>
				<p>The three foregoing sketches of court days show consistency in the principal elements that establish the identity of classical Athenian court procedure.  For as far back as our evidence goes, the judging panels were composed of many citizens.  All the dikasts who sat in judgement could therefore be thought to constitute an assembly that was in some sense the city itself.  In having been chosen by allotment, they had been chosen by chance, possibly thought of as Pythian Apollo.  Litigants were supposed to speak their own minds in their own words, but they had to know how to do so within a certain span of time measured out by the time-keeping device.  A degree of expertise was therefore almost a necessity whether one acquired it by training or had it made accessible by friends or political allies.  The citizens, who acted as judge and jury alike, registered by means of a secret ballot judicial decisions each was considered to have reached essentially by himself.</p>
				<p>The observable changes in procedure were technical refinements, better ways to protect the integrity of the characterizing principles.  The ways by which secrecy in voting was first maintained needed improvement.  Pebbles made a sound as they went into the voting urns, and despite the fact that sounds are hard to locate, some Athenians thought they were hearing which urn the pebble entered.  And so someone designed two distinct bronze “pebbles” and a validating urn with a special cover.  The waxed tablets on which a dikast scratched a line to signal his vote for one penalty or another seem not to have been in service for long.  One reason for this may have been that such records could easily be altered after they had left a dikast's hands.</p>
				<p>Allotment procedures showed need again and again to be refined, and Athenians may have found the study of such problems congenial.  In any case a basic rearrangement of the topography of the courts was at last found practicable.  At first, so far as we can tell, there was only an allotment by which a citizen gained the right to serve as heliast.  In that capacity, he was assigned to a court and was thereby assured of work possibly half the days of the year.  Since, however, his appearance at that court was predictable, litigants could identify him and try to influence him before their trial.  Another thing that made this sort of manipulation easy was the known association between magistrates, the kinds of litigation they supervised, and certain courts.  Furthermore, if assignment to courts was originally effected by tribe, members of the same tribe could arrange themselves in seating blocs of like-minded dikasts.  This sort of abuse at least can be inferred from the nature of a reform, by which the whole body of Athenian dikasts was divided into ten sections.  Dikasts thereafter were allotted to courts by section, and the sections were allotted to courts by the day on the very day they were to judge.</p>
				<p>But not even these precautionary measures turned out to be fully effective.  The Athenians next enclosed their courts within a fenced area and multiplied the number of allotments it took to get magistrate, dikastic panel, and litigants to a resolution of justice in a formal context.  If we do not hear of any further important changes after the time Aristotle describes, it can be because the city had undergone a transformation.  Some of the old forms, to be sure, survived, but Athenians did not use the courts for the same variety of business and with the same unrelenting passion.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="6">
				<head>Bibliographical Note</head>
				<p>The preceding essay is substantially a chapter (without the footnotes) in A. L. Boegehold et. al. <title>Lawcourts at Athens.  Sites, Buildings, Equipment, Procedure and Testimonia </title>(American School of Classical Studies publication, forthcoming 1992).  Principal ancient sources of information include Aristophanes (with scholia), especially <title>Wasps</title>, Attic orators (and later rhetorical lexica), Aristotle's <title>Constitution of the Athenians</title>, and various monuments, structural remains and paraphernalia found in archaeological excavations of the Athenian Agora.  For a larger context with references to ancient literature and thorough surveys of modern studies up to the time of publication, see J. R. Lipsius, <title>Das attische Recht und Rechtsverfahrung</title> (Leipzig 1905-1915); H. Hommel, <title>Heliaia</title>, <title>Philologus</title> Supplementband 19.2 (1927);  R. J. Bonner and G. Smith, <title>The Administration of Justice from Homer to Aristotle</title>, vol. I (Chicago 1928);  A. R. W. Harrison, <title>The Law of Athens.  Procedure </title>(Oxford 1971);  D. M. MacDowell, <title>The Law in Classical Athens </title>(London 1978); P. J. Rhodes, <title>A Commentary on the Aristotelian Athenaion Politeia </title>(Oxford 1981) especially the commentary to chapters 63-69;  M. Ostwald, <title>From Popular Sovereignty to the Sovereignty of Law</title> (Berkeley, Los Angeles, London 1986); and now most recently Mortimer Chambers, <title>Aristoteles. Der Staat der Athener</title> (Berlin 1990).  For the archaeological material, see H. A. Thompson and R. E. Wycherley, <title>The Agora of Athens.  The History, Shape, and Uses of an Ancient City Center</title> (Princeton 1972); and J. McK. Camp II, <title>The Athenian Agora.  Excavations in the Heart of Classical Athens</title> (London 1986).  Some relevant particular studies are: A. L. Boegehold, “Aristotle's <title>Athenaion Politeia</title> 65.2: The ‘Official Token’” <title>Hesperia</title> 29 (1960) 393-401; id. “Toward a Study of Athenian Voting Procedure,” <title>Hesperia</title> 32 (1963) 366-374; id. “Many Letters: Aristophanes <title>Plutus</title> 1166-1167” <title>Studies Presented to Sterling Dow etc.</title>, Greek Roman and Byzantine Monograph 10 (Durham, N.C. 1984) 23-29; id. “A Lid with Dipinto” <title>Studies Presented to Eugene Vanderpool</title>, <title>Hesperia</title> Supplement 19 (1982) 1-6; S. Dow, “Aristotle, the Kleroteria, and the Courts” <title>HSCP</title> 50 (1939) 1-34; M. Gagarin, “The Vote of Athena,” <title>AJP</title> 96 (1975) 121-127; M. H. Hansen, “The Athenian Heliaia from Homer to Aristotle,” <title>Class. et Med. </title>33 (1981-82) 9-47; J. H. Kroll, <title>Athenian Bronze Allotment Plates</title> (Cambridge, Mass. 1972).</p>
			</div>
		</body></text></TEI>
