<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader type="text">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Volsunga Saga</title>
        <editor>William Morris and Eirikr Magnusson</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Prepared under the supervision of: </resp>
          <name>This electronic edition was edited, proofed, and prepared by</name>
          <name>Douglas B. Killings</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <extent>135 K</extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
      </publicationStmt>

      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <title>Volsunga Saga</title>
            <editor>William Morris and Eirikr Magnusson</editor>
            <imprint>
              <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
              <publisher>Walter Scott Press</publisher>
              <date>1888</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>

    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState n="chunk" unit="chapter"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>

    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>

    <revisionDesc>
      <!--
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp> Prepared under the supervision of: </resp><name>DMM</name><name>markup</name></respStmt>
<item>initial TEI markup
</item>
</change>
-->
      <change when="2014-11-13" who="Stella Dee">converted to EpiDoc</change>
    </revisionDesc>

  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <body>
      <div type="translation">

        <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="introduction">
          <p> It would seem fitting for a Northern folk, deriving the greater and better part of
            their speech, laws, and customs from a Northern root, that the North should be to them,
            if not a holy land, yet at least a place more to be regarded than any part of the world
            beside; that howsoever their knowledge widened of other men, the faith and deeds of
            their forefathers would never lack interest for them, but would always be kept in
            remembrance. One cause after another has, however, aided in turning attention to classic
            men and lands at the cost of our own history. Among battles, "every schoolboy" knows the
            story of Marathon or Salamis, while it would be hard indeed to find one who did more
            than recognise the name, if even that, of the great fights of Hafrsfirth or
            Sticklestead. The language and history of Greece and Rome, their laws and religions,
            have been always held part of the learning needful to an educated man, but no trouble
            has been taken to make him familiar with his own people or their tongue. Even that
            Englishman who knew Alfred, Bede, Caedmon, as well as he knew Plato, Caesar, Cicero, or
            Pericles, would be hard bestead were he asked about the great peoples from whom we
            sprang; the warring of Harold Fairhair or Saint Olaf; the Viking <note place="foot"
              >Viking (Ice. "Vikingr"; "vik", a bay or creek, "ingr", beloning to, (or men of)
              freebooters.</note> kingdoms in these (the British) Western Isles; the settlement of
            Iceland, or even of Normandy. The knowledge of all these things would now be even
            smaller than it is among us were it not that there was one land left where the olden
            learning found refuge and was kept in being. In England, Germany, and the rest of
            Europe, what is left of the traditions of pagan times has been altered in a thousand
            ways by foreign influence, even as the peoples and their speech have been by the influx
            of foreign blood; but Iceland held to the old tongue that was once the universal speech
            of northern folk, and held also the great stores of tale and poem that are slowly
            becoming once more the common heritage of their descendants. The truth, care, and
            literary beauty of its records; the varied and strong life shown alike in tale and
            history; and the preservation of the old speech, character, and tradition -- a people
            placed apart as the Icelanders have been -- combine to make valuable what Iceland holds
            for us. Not before 1770, when Bishop Percy translated Mallet's "Northern Antiquities",
            was anything known here of Icelandic, or its literature. Only within the latter part of
            this century has it been studied, and in the brief book-list at the end of this volume
            may be seen the little that has been done as yet. It is, however, becoming ever clearer,
            and to an increasing number, how supremely important is Icelandic as a word-hoard to the
            English- speaking peoples, and that in its legend, song, and story there is a very mine
            of noble and pleasant beauty and high manhood. That which has been done, one may hope,
            is but the beginning of a great new birth, that shall give back to our language and
            literature all that heedlessness and ignorance bid fair for awhile to destroy. </p>
          <p> The Scando-Gothic peoples who poured southward and westward over Europe, to shake
            empires and found kingdoms, to meet Greek and Roman in conflict, and levy tribute
            everywhere, had kept up their constantly-recruited waves of incursion, until they had
            raised a barrier of their own blood. It was their own kin, the sons of earlier invaders,
            who stayed the landward march of the Northmen in the time of Charlemagne. To the
            Southlands their road by land was henceforth closed. Then begins the day of the Vikings,
            who, for two hundred years and more, "held the world at ransom." Under many and brave
            leaders they first of all came round the "Western Isles"<note place="foot">"West over
              the Sea" is the word for the British Isles.</note> toward the end of the eighth
            century; soon after they invaded Normandy, and harried the coasts of France; gradually
            they lengthened their voyages until there was no shore of the then known world upon
            which they were unseen or unfelt. A glance at English history will show the large part
            of it they fill, and how they took tribute from the Anglo-Saxons, who, by the way, were
            far nearer kin to them than is usually thought. In Ireland, where the old civilisation
            was falling to pieces, they founded kingdoms at Limerick and Dublin among other
              places;<note place="foot">See Todd (J. H.). "War of the Gaedhil with the
              Gaill".</note> the last named, of which the first king, Olaf the White, was
            traditionally descended of Sigurd the Volsung,<note place="foot">He was son of Ingiald,
              son of Thora, daughter of Sigurd Snake-I'-th'-eye, son of Ragnar Lodbrok by Aslaug,
              daughter of Sigurd by Brynhild. The genealogy is, doubtless, quite mythical. </note>
            endured even to the English invasion, when it was taken by men of the same Viking blood
            a little altered. What effect they produced upon the natives may be seen from the
            description given by the unknown historian of the "Wars of the Gaedhil with the Gaill":
            "In a word, although there were an hundred hard-steeled iron heads on one neck, and an
            hundred sharp, ready, cool, never-rusting brazen tongues in each head, and an hundred
            garrulous, loud, unceasing voices from each tongue, they could not recount, or narrate,
            or enumerate, or tell what all the Gaedhil suffered in common -- both men and women,
            laity and clergy, old and young, noble and ignoble -- of hardship, and of injury, and of
            oppression, in every house, from these valiant, wrathful, purely pagan people. Even
            though great were this cruelty, oppression, and tyranny, though numerous were the
            oft-victorious clans of the many- familied Erinn; though numerous their kings, and their
            royal chiefs, and their princes; though numerous their heroes and champions, and their
            brave soldiers, their chiefs of valour and renown and deeds of arms; yet not one of them
            was able to give relief, alleviation, or deliverance from that oppression and tyranny,
            from the numbers and multitudes, and the cruelty and the wrath of the brutal, ferocious,
            furious, untamed, implacable hordes by whom that oppression was inflicted, because of
            the excellence of their polished, ample, treble, heavy, trusty, glittering corslets; and
            their hard, strong, valiant swords; and their well-riveted long spears, and their ready,
            brilliant arms of valour besides; and because of the greatness of their achievements and
            of their deeds, their bravery, and their valour, their strength, and their venom, and
            their ferocity, and because of the excess of their thirst and their hunger for the
            brave, fruitful, nobly-inhabited, full of cataracts, rivers, bays, pure, smooth-plained,
            sweet grassy land of Erinn" -- (pp. 52-53). Some part of this, however, must be abated,
            because the chronicler is exalting the terror-striking enemy that he may still further
            exalt his own people, the Dal Cais, who did so much under Brian Boroimhe to check the
            inroads of the Northmen. When a book does <note place="foot">A Collection of Sagas and
              other Historical Documents relating to the Settlements and Descents of the Northmen on
              the British Isles. Ed., G. W. Dasent, D.C.L, and Gudbrand Vigfusson, M.A. "In the
              Press. Longmans, London. 8vo.</note> appear, which has been announced these ten years
            past, we shall have more material for the reconstruction of the life of those times than
            is now anywhere accessible. Viking earldoms also were the Orkneys, Faroes, and
            Shetlands. So late as 1171, in the reign of Henry II., the year after Beckett's murder,
            Earl Sweyn Asleifsson of Orkney, who had long been the terror of the western seas,
            "fared a sea-roving" and scoured the western coast of England, Man, and the east of
            Ireland, but was killed in an attack on his kinsmen of Dublin. He had used to go upon a
            regular plan that may be taken as typical of the homely manner of most of his like in
            their cruising: "Sweyn had in the spring hard work, and made them lay down very much
            seed, and looked much after it himself. But when that toil was ended, he fared away
            every spring on a viking-voyage, and harried about among the southern isles and Ireland,
            and came home after midsummer. That he called spring-viking. Then he was at home until
            the corn- fields were reaped down, and the grain seen to and stored. Then he fared away
            on a viking-voyage, and then he did not come home till the winter was one month off, and
            that he called his autumn- viking."<note place="foot">"Orkneyinga Saga".</note>
          </p>
          <p> Toward the end of the ninth century Harold Fairhair, either spurred by the example of
            Charlemagne, or really prompted, as Snorri Sturluson tells us, resolved to bring all
            Norway under him. As Snorri has it in "Heimskringla": "King Harold sent his men to a
            girl hight Gyda.... The king wanted her for his leman; for she was wondrous beautiful
            but of high mood withal. Now when the messengers came there and gave their message to
            her, she made answer that she would not throw herself away even to take a king for her
            husband, who swayed no greater kingdom than a few districts; `And methinks,' said she,
            `it is a marvel that no king here in Norway will put all the land under him, after the
            fashion that Gorm the Old did in Denmark, or Eric at Upsala.' The messengers deemed this
            a dreadfully proud-spoken answer, and asked her what she thought would come of such an
            one, for Harold was so mighty a man that his asking was good enough for her. But
            although she had replied to their saying otherwise than they would, they saw no
            likelihood, for this while, of bearing her along with them against her will, so they
            made ready to fare back again. When they were ready and the folk followed them out, Gyda
            said to the messengers -- `Now tell to King Harold these my words: -- I will only agree
            to be his lawful wife upon the condition that he shall first, for sake of me, put under
            him the whole of Norway, so that he may bear sway over that kingdom as freely and fully
            as King Eric over the realm of Sweden, or King Gorm over Denmark; for only then,
            methinks, can he be called king of a people.' Now his men came back to King Harold,
            bringing him the words of the girl, and saying she was so bold and heedless that she
            well deserved the king should send a greater troop of people for her, and put her to
            some disgrace. Then answered the king. `This maid has not spoken or done so much amiss
            that she should be punished, but the rather should she be thanked for her words. She has
            reminded me,' said he, `of somewhat that it seems wonderful I did not think of before.
            And now,' added he, `I make the solemn vow, and take who made me and rules over all
            things, to witness that never shall I clip or comb my hair until I have subdued all
            Norway with scatt, and duties, and lordships; or, if not, have died in the seeking.'
            Guttorm gave great thanks to the king for his oath, saying it was "royal work fulfilling
            royal rede." The new and strange government that Harold tried to enforce -- nothing less
            than the feudal system in a rough guise - -- which made those who had hitherto been
            their own men save at special times, the king's men at all times, and laid freemen under
            tax, was withstood as long as might be by the sturdy Norsemen. It was only by dint of
            hard fighting that he slowly won his way, until at Hafrsfirth he finally crushed all
            effective opposition. But the discontented, "and they were a great multitude," fled
            oversea to the outlands, Iceland, the Faroes, the Orkneys, and Ireland. The whole coast
            of Europe, even to Greece and the shores of the Black Sea, the northern shores of
            Africa, and the western part of Asia, felt the effects also. Rolf Pad-th'-hoof, son of
            Harold's dear friend Rognvald, made an outlaw for a cattle-raid within the bounds of the
            kingdom, betook himself to France, and, with his men, founded a new people and a
            dynasty. </p>
          <p> Iceland had been known for a good many years, but its only dwellers had been Irish
            Culdees, who sought that lonely land to pray in peace. Now, however, both from Norway
            and the Western Isles settlers began to come in. Aud, widow of Olaf the White, King of
            Dublin, came, bringing with her many of mixed blood, for the Gaedhil (pronounced "Gael",
            Irish) and the Gaill (pronounced "Gaul", strangers) not only fought furiously, but made
            friends firmly, and often intermarried. Indeed, the Westmen were among the first
            arrivals, and took the best parts of the island -- on its western shore, appropriately
            enough. After a time the Vikings who had settled in the Isles so worried Harold and his
            kingdom, upon which they swooped every other while, that he drew together a mighty
            force, and fell upon them wheresoever he could find them, and followed them up with fire
            and sword; and this he did twice, so that in those lands none could abide but folk who
            were content to be his men, however lightly they might hold their allegiance. Hence it
            was to Iceland that all turned who held to the old ways, and for over sixty years from
            the first comer there was a stream of hardy men pouring in, with their families and
            their belongings, simple yeomen, great and warwise chieftains, rich landowners, who had
            left their land "for the overbearing of King Harold," as the "Landnamabok" <note
              place="foot">Landtaking-book -- "landnam", landtaking, from "at nema land", hence also
              the early settlers were called "landnamsmenn".</note> has it. "There also we shall
            escape the troubling of kings and scoundrels", says the "Vatsdaelasaga". So much of the
            best blood left Norway that the king tried to stay the leak by fines and punishments,
            but in vain. </p>
          <p> As his ship neared the shore, the new-coming chief would leave it to the gods as to
            where he settled. The hallowed pillars of the high seat, which were carried away from
            his old abode, were thrown overboard, with certain rites, and were let drive with wind
            and wave until they came ashore. The piece of land which lay next the beach they were
            flung upon was then viewed from the nearest hill-summit, and place of the homestead
            picked out. Then the land was hallowed by being encircled with fire, parcelled among the
            band, and marked out with boundary-signs; the houses were built, the "town" or
            home-field walled in, a temple put up, and the settlement soon assumed shape. In 1100
            there were 4500 franklins, making a population of about 50,000, fully three- fourths of
            whom had a strong infusion of Celtic blood in them. The mode of life was, and is, rather
            pastoral than aught else. In the 39,200 square miles of the island's area there are now
            about 250 acres of cultivated land, and although there has been much more in times past,
            the Icelanders have always been forced to reckon upon flocks and herds as their chief
            resources, grain of all kinds, even rye, only growing in a few favoured places, and very
            rarely there; the hay, self-sown, being the only certain harvest. On the coast fishing
            and fowling were of help, but nine-tenths of the folk lived by their sheep and cattle.
            Potatoes, carrots, turnips, and several kinds of cabbage have, however, been lately
            grown with success. They produced their own food and clothing, and could export enough
            wool, cloth, horn, dried fish, etc., as enabled them to obtain wood for building, iron
            for tools, honey, wine, grain, etc, to the extent of their simple needs. Life and work
            was lotted by the seasons and their changes; outdoor work -- fishing, herding,
            hay-making, and fuel- getting -- filling the long days of summer, while the long, dark
            winter was used in weaving and a hundred indoor crafts. The climate is not so bad as
            might be expected, seeing that the island touches the polar circle, the mean temperature
            at Reykjavik being 39 degrees. </p>
          <p> The religion which the settlers took with them into Iceland -- the ethnic religion of
            the Norsefolk, which fought its last great fight at Sticklestead, where Olaf Haraldsson
            lost his life and won the name of Saint -- was, like all religions, a compound of myths,
            those which had survived from savage days, and those which expressed the various degrees
            of a growing knowledge of life and better understanding of nature. Some historians and
            commentators are still fond of the unscientific method of taking a later religion, in
            this case christianity, and writing down all apparently coincident parts of belief, as
            having been borrowed from the christian teachings by the Norsefolk, while all that
            remain they lump under some slighting head. Every folk has from the beginning of time
            sought to explain the wonders of nature, and has, after its own fashion, set forth the
            mysteries of life. The lowest savage, no less than his more advanced brother, has a
            philosophy of the universe by which he solves the world-problem to his own satisfaction,
            and seeks to reconcile his conduct with his conception of the nature of things. Now, it
            is not to be thought, save by "a priori" reasoners, that such a folk as the Northmen --
            a mighty folk, far advanced in the arts of life, imaginative, literary -- should have
            had no further creed than the totemistic myths of their primitive state; a state they
            have wholly left ere they enter history. Judging from universal analogy, the religion of
            which record remains to us was just what might be looked for at the particular stage of
            advancement the Northmen had reached. Of course something may have been gained from
            contact with other peoples -- from the Greeks during the long years in which the
            northern races pressed upon their frontier; from the Irish during the existence of the
            western viking-kingdoms; but what I particularly warn young students against is the
            constant effort of a certain order of minds to wrest facts into agreement with their pet
            theories of religion or what not. The whole tendency of the more modern investigation
            shows that the period of myth-transmission is long over ere history begins. The same
            confusion of different stages of myth- making is to be found in the Greek religion, and
            indeed in those of all peoples; similar conditions of mind produce similar practices,
            apart from all borrowing of ideas and manners; in Greece we find snake-dances,
            bear-dances, swimming with sacred pigs, leaping about in imitation of wolves,
            dog-feasts, and offering of dogs' flesh to the gods -- all of them practices dating from
            crude savagery, mingled with ideas of exalted and noble beauty, but none now, save a
            bigot, would think of accusing the Greeks of having stolen all their higher beliefs.
            Even were some part of the matter of their myths taken from others, yet the Norsemen
            have given their gods a noble, upright, great spirit, and placed them upon a high level
            that is all their own.<note place="foot">To all interested in the subject of comparative
              mythology, Andrew Lang's two admirable books, "Custom and Myth" (1884, 8vo) and "Myth,
              Ritual, and Religion" (2 vols., crown 8vo, 1887), both published by Longmans, London,
              may be warmly recommended.</note> From the prose Edda the following all too brief
            statement of the salient points of Norse belief is made up: -- "The first and eldest of
            gods is hight Allfather; he lives from all ages, and rules over all his realm, and sways
            all things great and small; he smithied heaven and earth, and the lift, and all that
            belongs to them; what is most, he made man, and gave him a soul that shall live and
            never perish; and all men that are right-minded shall live and be with himself in
            Vingolf; but wicked men fare to Hell, and thence into Niithell, that is beneath in the
            ninth world. Before the earth `'twas the morning of time, when yet naught was, nor sand
            nor sea was there, nor cooling streams. Earth was not found, nor Heaven above; a
            Yawning-gap there was, but grass nowhere.' Many ages ere the earth was shapen was
            Niflheim made, but first was that land in the southern sphere hight Muspell, that burns
            and blazes, and may not be trodden by those who are outlandish and have no heritage
            there. Surtr sits on the border to guard the land; at the end of the world he will fare
            forth, and harry and overcome all the gods and burn the world with fire. Ere the races
            were yet mingled, or the folk of men grew, Yawning-gap, which looked towards the north
            parts, was filled with thick and heavy ice and rime, and everywhere within were fog and
            gusts; but the south side of Yawning-gap lightened by the sparks and gledes that flew
            out of Muspell-heim; as cold arose out of Niflheim and all things grim, so was that part
            that looked towards Muspell hot and bright; but Yawning-gap was as light as windless
            air, and when the blast of heat met the rime, so that it melted and dropped and
            quickened; from those life- drops there was shaped the likeness of a man, and he was
            named Ymir; he was bad, and all his kind; and so it is said, when he slept he fell into
            a sweat; then waxed under his left hand a man and a woman, and one of his feet got a son
            with the other, and thence cometh the Hrimthursar. The next thing when the rime dropped
            was that the cow hight Audhumla was made of it; but four milk-rivers ran out of her
            teats, and she fed Ymir; she licked rime-stones that were salt, and the first day there
            came at even, out of the stones, a man's hair, the second day a man's head, the third
            day all the man was there. He is named Turi; he was fair of face, great and mighty; he
            gat a son named Bor, who took to him Besla, daughter of Bolthorn, the giant, and they
            had three sons, Odin, Vili, and Ve. Bor's sons slew Ymir the giant, but when he fell
            there ran so much blood out of his wounds that all the kin of the Hrimthursar were
            drowned, save Hvergelmir and his household, who got away in a boat. Then Bor's sons took
            Ymir and bore him into the midst of Yawning-gap, and made of him the earth; of his blood
            seas and waters, of his flesh earth was made; they set the earth fast, and laid the sea
            round about it in a ring without; of his bones were made rocks; stones and pebbles of
            his teeth and jaws and the bones that were broken; they took his skull and made the lift
            thereof, and set it up over the earth with four sides, and under each corner they set
            dwarfs, and they took his brain and cast it aloft, and made clouds. They took the sparks
            and gledes that went loose, and had been cast out of Muspellheim, and set them in the
            lift to give light; they gave resting-places to all fires, and set some in the lift;
            some fared free under it, and they gave them a place and shaped their goings. A wondrous
            great smithying, and deftly done. The earth is fashioned round without, and there
            beyond, round about it lies the deep sea; and on that sea-strand the gods gave land for
            an abode to the giant kind, but within on the earth made they a burg round the world
            against restless giants, and for this burg reared they the brows of Ymir, and called the
            burg Midgard. The gods went along the sea-strand and found two stocks, and shaped out of
            them men; the first gave soul and life, the second wit and will to move, the third face,
            hearing, speech, and eyesight. They gave them clothing and names; the man Ask and the
            woman Embla; thence was mankind begotten, to whom an abode was given under Midgard. Then
            next Bor's sons made them a burg in the midst of the world, that is called Asgard; there
            abode the gods and their kind, and wrought thence many tidings and feats, both on earth
            and in the Sky. Odin, who is hight Allfather, for that he is the father of all men and
            sat there in his high seat, seeing over the whole world and each man's doings, and knew
            all things that he saw. His wife was called Frigg, and their offspring is the Asa-
            stock, who dwell in Asgard and the realms about it, and all that stock are known to be
            gods. The daughter and wife of Odin was Earth, and of her he got Thor, him followed
            strength and sturdiness, thereby quells he all things quick; the strongest of all gods
            and men, he has also three things of great price, the hammer Miolnir, the best of
            strength belts, and when he girds that about him waxes his god strength one-half, and
            his iron gloves that he may not miss for holding his hammer's haft. Balidr is Odin's
            second son, and of him it is good to say, he is fair and: bright in face, and hair, and
            body, and him all praise; he is wise and fair-spoken and mild, and that nature is in him
            none may withstand his doom. Tyr is daring and best of mood; there is a saw that he is
            tyrstrong who is before other men and never yields; he is also so wise that it is said
            he is tyrlearned who is wise. Bragi is famous for wisdom, and best in tongue-wit, and
            cunning speech, and song-craft. `And many other are there, good and great; and one,
            Loki, fair of face, ill in temper and fickle of mood, is called the backbiter of the
            Asa, and speaker of evil redes and shame of all gods and men; he has above all that
            craft called sleight, and cheats all in all things. Among the children of Loki are
            Fenris-wolf and Midgards-worm; the second lies about all the world in the deep sea,
            holding his tail in his teeth, though some say Thor has slain him; but Fenris-wolf is
            bound until the doom of the gods, when gods and men shall come to an end, and earth and
            heaven be burnt, when he shall slay Odin. After this the earth shoots up from the sea,
            and it is green and fair, and the fields bear unsown, and gods and men shall be alive
            again, and sit in fair halls, and talk of old tales and the tidings that happened
            aforetime. The head-seat, or holiest-stead, of the gods is at Yggdrasil's ash, which is
            of all trees best and biggest; its boughs are spread over the whole world and stand
            above heaven; one root of the ash is in heaven, and under the root is the right holy
            spring; there hold the gods doom every day; the second root is with the Hrimthursar,
            where before was Yawning-gap; under that root is Mimir's spring, where knowledge and wit
            lie hidden; thither came Allfather and begged a drink, but got it not before he left his
            eye in pledge; the third root is over Niflheim, and the worm Nidhogg gnaws the root
            beneath. A fair hall stands under the ash by the spring, and out of it come three
            maidens, Norns, named Has-been, Being, Will-be, who shape the lives of men; there are
            beside other Norns, who come to every man that is born to shape his life, and some of
            these are good and some evil. In the boughs of the ash sits an eagle, wise in much, and
            between his eyes sits the hawk Vedrfalnir; the squirrel Ratatoskr runs up and down along
            the ash, bearing words of hate betwixt the eagle and the worm. Those Norns who abide by
            the holy spring draw from it every day water, and take the clay that lies around the
            well, and sprinkle them up over the ash for that its boughs should not wither or rot.
            All those men that have fallen in the fight, and borne wounds and toil unto death, from
            the beginning of the world, are come to Odin in Valhall; a very great throng is there,
            and many more shall yet come; the flesh of the boar Soerfmnir is sodden for them every
            day, and he is whole again at even; and the mead they drink that flows from the teats of
            the she-goat Heidhrun. The meat Odin has on his board he gives to his two wolves, Geri
            and Freki, and he needs no meat, wine is to him both meat and drink; ravens twain sit on
            his shoulders, and say into his ear all tidings that they see and hear; they are called
            Huginn and Muninn (mind and memory); them sends he at dawn to fly over the whole world,
            and they come back at breakfast-tide, thereby becomes he wise in many tidings, and for
            this men call him Raven's-god. Every day, when they have clothed them, the heroes put on
            their arms and go out into the yard and fight and fell each other; that is their play,
            and when it looks toward mealtime, then ride they home to Valhall and sit down to drink.
            For murderers and men forsworn is a great hall, and a bad, and the doors look northward;
            it is altogether wrought of adder-backs like a wattled house, but the worms' heads turn
            into the house, and blow venom, so that rivers of venom run along the hall, and in those
            rivers must such men wade forever." There was no priest-class; every chief was priest
            for his own folk, offered sacrifice, performed ceremonies, and so on. </p>
          <p> In politics the homestead, with its franklin-owner, was the unit; the "thing", or
            hundred-moot, the primal organisation, and the "godord", or chieftainship, its tie. The
            chief who had led a band of kinsmen and followers to the new country, taken possession
            of land, and shared it among them, became their head- ruler and priest at home, speaker
            and president of their Thing, and their representative in any dealings with neighbouring
            chiefs and their clients. He was not a feudal lord, for any franklin could change his
            "godord" as he liked, and the right of "judgment by peers" was in full use. At first
            there was no higher organisation than the local thing. A central thing, and a speaker to
            speak a single "law" for the whole island, was instituted in 929, and afterwards the
            island was divided in four quarters, each with a court, under the Al-thing. Society was
            divided only into two classes of men, the free and unfree, though political power was in
            the hands of the franklins alone; "godi" and thrall ate the same food, spoke the same
            tongue, wore much the same clothes, and were nearly alike in life and habits. Among the
            free men there was equality in all but wealth and the social standing that cannot be
            separated therefrom. The thrall was a serf rather than a slave, and could own a house,
            etc., of his own. In a generation or so the freeman or landless retainer, if he got a
            homestead of his own, was the peer of the highest in the land. During the tenth century
            Greenland was colonised from Iceland, and by end of the same century christianity was
            introduced into Iceland, but made at first little difference in arrangements of society.
            In the thirteenth century disputes over the power and jurisdiction of the clergy led,
            with other matters, to civil war, ending in submission to Norway, and the breaking down
            of all native great houses. Although life under the commonwealth had been rough and
            irregular, it had been free and varied, breeding heroes and men of mark; but the "law
            and order" now brought in left all on a dead level of peasant proprietorship, without
            room for hope or opening for ambition. An alien governor ruled the island, which was
            divided under him into local counties, administered by sheriffs appointed by the king of
            Norway. The Al-thing was replaced by a royal court, the local work of the local things
            was taken by a subordinate of the sheriff, and things, quarter-courts, trial by jury,
            and all the rest, were swept away to make room for these "improvements", which have
            lasted with few changes into this century. In 1380 the island passed under the rule of
            Denmark, and so continues. <note place="foot">Iceland was granted full independence from
              Denmark in 1944. -- DBK.</note> During the fifteenth century the English trade was the
            only link between Iceland and the outer world; the Danish government weakened that link
            as much as it could, and sought to shut in and monopolise everything Icelandic; under
            the deadening effect of such rule it is no marvel that everything found a lower level,
            and many things went out of existence for lack of use. In the sixteenth century there is
            little to record but the Reformation, which did little good, if any, and the ravages of
            English, Gascon, and Algerine pirates who made havoc on the coast; <note place="foot"
              >These pirates are always appearing about the same time in English State papers as
              plundering along the coasts of the British Isles, especially Ireland.</note> they
            appear toward the close of the century and disappear early in the seventeenth. In the
            eighteenth century small-pox, sheep disease, famine, and the terrible eruptions of 1765
            and 1783, follow one another swiftly and with terrible effect. At the beginning of the
            present century Iceland, however, began to shake off the stupor her ill-hap had brought
            upon her, and as European attention had been drawn to her, she was listened to.
            Newspapers, periodicals, and a Useful Knowledge Society were started; then came free
            trade, and the "home-rule" struggle, which met with partial success in 1874, and is
            still being carried on. A colony, Gimli, in far-off Canada, has been formed of Icelandic
            emigrants, and large numbers have left their mother- land; but there are many
            co-operative societies organised now, which it is hoped will be able to so revive the
            old resources of the island as to make provision for the old population and ways of
            life. There is now again a representative central council, but very many of the old
            rights and powers have not been yet restored. The condition of society is peculiar
            absence of towns, social equality, no abject poverty or great wealth, rarity of crime,
            making it easy for the whole country to be administered as a co-operative commonwealth
            without the great and striking changes rendered necessary by more complicated systems. </p>
          <p> Iceland. has always borne a high name for learning and literature; on both sides of
            their descent people inherited special poetic power. Some of older Eddaic fragments
            attest the great reach and deep overpowering strength of imagination possessed by their
            Norse ancestors; and they themselves had been quickened by a new leaven. During the
            first generations of the "land-taking" a great school of poetry which had arisen among
            the Norsemen of the Western Isles was brought by them to Iceland. <note place="foot">For
              all the old Scandinavian poetry extant in Icelandic, see "Corpus Poeticum Borealis" of
              Vigfusson and Powell.</note> The poems then produced are quite beyond parallel with
            those of any Teutonic language for centuries after their date, which lay between the
            beginning of the ninth and the end of the tenth centuries. Through the Greenland colony
            also came two, or perhaps more, great poems of this western school. This school grew out
            of the stress and storm of the viking life, with its wild adventure and varied commerce,
            and the close contact with an artistic and inventive folk, possessed of high culture and
            great learning. The infusion of Celtic blood, however slight it may have been, had also
            something to do with the swift intense feeling and rapidity of passion of the earlier
            Icelandic poets. They are hot-headed and hot-hearted, warm, impulsive, quick to quarrel
            or to love, faithful, brave; ready with sword or song to battle with all comers, or to
            seek adventure wheresoever it might be found. They leave Iceland young, and wander at
            their will to different courts of northern Europe, where they are always held in high
            honour. Gunnlaug Worm-tongue <note place="foot">Snake-tongue -- so called from his
              biting satire.</note> in 1004 carne to England, after being in Norway, as the saga
            says: -- "Now sail Gunnlaug and his fellows into the English main, and come at
            autumntide south to London Bridge, where they hauled ashore their ship. Now, at that
            time King Ethelred, the son of Edgar, ruled over England, and was a good lord; the
            winter he sat in London. But in those days there was the same tongue in England as in
            Norway and Denmark; but the tongues changed when William the Bastard won England, for
            thenceforward French went current there, for he was of French kin. Gunnlaug went
            presently to the king, and greeted him well and worthily. The king asked him from what
            land he came, and Gunnlaug told him all as it was. `But,' said he, `I have come to meet
            thee, lord, for that I have made a song on thee, and I would that it might please thee
            to hearken to that song.' The king said it should be so, and Gunnlaug gave forth the
            song well and proudly, and this is the burden thereof -- <quote>
              <l>"'As God are all folk fearing</l>
              <l>The fire lord King of England,</l>
              <l>Kin of all kings and all folk,</l>
              <l>To Ethelred the head bow.'</l>
            </quote> The king thanked him for the song, and gave him as song-reward a scarlet cloak
            lined with the costliest of furs, and golden- broidered down to the hem; and made him
            his man; and Gunnlaug was with him all the winter, and was well accounted of." </p>
          <p> The poems in this volume are part of the wonderful fragments which are all that remain
            of ancient Scandinavian poetry. Every piece which survives has been garnered by
            Vigfusson and Powell in the volumes of their "Corpus", where those who seek may find. A
            long and illustrious line of poets kept the old traditions, down even to within a couple
            centuries, but the earlier great harvest of song was never again equalled. After
            christianity had entered Iceland, and that, with other causes, had quieted men's lives,
            although the poetry which stood to the folk in lieu of music did not die away, it lost
            the exclusive hold it had upon men's minds. In a time not so stirring, when emotion was
            not so fervent or so swift, when there was less to quicken the blood, the story that had
            before found no fit expression but in verse, could stretch its limbs, as it were, and be
            told in prose. Something of Irish influence is again felt in this new departure and that
            marvellous new growth, the saga, that came from it, but is little more than an
            influence. Every people find some one means of expression which more than all else suits
            their mood or their powers, and this the Icelanders found in the saga. This was the life
            of a hero told in prose, but in set form, after a regular fashion that unconsciously
            complied with all epical requirements but that of verse -- simple plot, events in order
            of time, set phrases for even the shifting emotion or changeful fortune of a fight or
            storm, and careful avoidance of digression, comment, or putting forward by the narrator
            of ought but the theme he has in hand; he himself is never seen. Something in the
            perfection of the saga is to be traced to the long winter's evenings, when the whole
            household, gathered together at their spinning, weaving, and so on, would listen to one
            of their number who told anew some old story of adventure or achievement. In very truth
            the saga is a prose epic, and marked by every quality an epic should possess. Growing up
            while the deeds of dead heroes were fresh in memory, most often recited before the
            sharers in such deeds, the saga, in its pure form, never goes from what is truth to its
            teller. Where the saga, as this one of the Volsungs is founded upon the debris of songs
            and poems, even then very old, tales of mythological heroes, of men quite removed from
            the personal knowledge of the narrator, yet the story is so inwound with the tradition
            of his race, is so much a part of his thought-life, that every actor in it has for him a
            real existence. At the feast or gathering, or by the fireside, as men made nets and
            women spun, these tales were told over; in their frequent repetition by men who believed
            them, though incident or sequence underwent no change, they would become closer knit,
            more coherent, and each an organic whole. Gradually they would take a regular and
            accepted form, which would ease the strain upon the reciter's memory and leave his mind
            free to adorn the story with fair devices, that again gave help in the making it easier
            to remember, and thus aided in its preservation. After a couple of generations had
            rounded and polished the sagas by their telling and retelling, they were written down
            for the most part between 1141 and 1220, and so much was their form impressed upon the
            mind of the folk, that when learned and literary works appeared, they were written in
            the same style; hence we have histories alike of kingdoms, or families, or miracles,
            lives of saints, kings, or bishops in saga-form, as well as subjects that seem at first
            sight even less hopeful. All sagas that have yet appeared in English may be found in the
            book-list at end of this volume, but they are not a tithe of those that remain. </p>
          <p> Of all the stories kept in being by the saga-tellers and left for our delight, there
            is none that so epitomises human experience; has within the same space so much of nature
            and of life; so fully the temper and genius of the Northern folk, as that of the
            Volsungs and Niblungs, which has in varied shapes entered into the literature of many
            lands. In the beginning there is no doubt that the story belonged to the common
            ancestral folk of all the Teutonic of Scando-Gothic peoples in the earliest days of
            their wanderings. Whether they came from the Hindu Kush, or originated in Northern
            Europe, brought it with them from Asia, or evolved it among the mountains and rivers it
            has taken for scenery, none know nor can; but each branch of their descendants has it in
            one form or another, and as the Icelanders were the very crown and flower of the
            northern folk, so also the story which is the peculiar heritage of that folk received in
            their hands its highest expression and most noble form. The oldest shape in which we
            have it is in the Eddaic poems, some of which date from unnumbered generations before
            the time to which most of them are usually ascribed, the time of the viking-kingdoms in
            the Western Isles. In these poems the only historical name is that of Attila, the great
            Hun leader, who filled so large a part of the imagination of the people whose power he
            had broken. There is no doubt that, in the days when the kingdoms of the Scando-Goths
            reached from the North Cape to the Caspian, that some earlier great king performed his
            part; but, after the striking career of Attila, he became the recognised type of a
            powerful foreign potentate. All the other actors are mythic-heroic. Of the Eddaic songs
            only fragments now remain, but ere they perished there arose from them a saga, that now
            given to the readers of this. The so-called Anglo-Saxons brought part of the story to
            England in "Beowulf"; in which also appear some incidents that are again given in the
            Icelandic saga of "Grettir the Strong". Most widely known is the form taken by the story
            in the hands of an unknown medieval German poet, who, from the broken ballads then
            surviving wrote the "Nibelungenlied" or more properly "Nibelungen Not" ("The Need of the
            Niblungs"). In this the characters are all renamed, some being more or less historical
            actors in mid-European history, as Theodoric of the East-Goths, for instance. The whole
            of the earlier part of the story has disappeared, and though Siegfried (Sigurd) has
            slain a dragon, there is nothing to connect it with the fate that follows the treasure;
            Andvari, the Volsungs, Fafnir, and Regin are all forgotten; the mythological features
            have become faint, and the general air of the whole is that of medieval romance. The
            swoard Gram is replaced by Balmung, and the Helm of Awing by the Tarn-cap -- the former
            with no gain, the latter with great loss. The curse of Andvari, which in the saga is
            grimly real, working itself out with slow, sure steps that no power of god or man can
            turn aside, in the medieval poem is but a mere scenic effect, a strain of mystery and
            magic, that runs through the changes of the story with much added picturesqueness, but
            that has no obvious relation to the working-out of the plot, or fulfilment of their
            destiny by the different characters. Brynhild loses a great deal, and is a poor creature
            when compared with herself in the saga; Grimhild and her fateful drink have gone; Gudrun
            (Chriemhild)is much more complex, but not more tragic; one new character, Rudiger,
            appears as the type of chivalry; but Sigurd (Siegfred) the central figure, though he has
            lost by the omission of so much of his life, is, as before, the embodiment of all the
            virtues that were dear to northern hearts. Brave, strong, generous, dignified, and
            utterly truthful, he moves amid a tangle of tragic events, overmastered by a mighty
            fate, and in life or death is still a hero without stain or flaw. It is no wonder that
            he survives to this day in the national songs of the Faroe Islands and in the
            folk-ballads of Denmark; that his legend should have been mingled with northern history
            through Ragnar Lodbrog, or southern through Attila and Theodoric; that it should have
            inspired William Morris in producing the one great English epic of the century; <note
              place="foot">"Sigurd the Volsung", which seems to have become all but forgotten in
              this century. -- DBK.</note> and Richard Wagner in the mightiest among his
            music-dramas. Of the story as told in the saga there is no need here to speak, for to
            read it, as may be done a few pages farther on, is that not better than to read about
            it? But it may be urged upon those that are pleased and moved by the passion and power,
            the strength and deep truth of it, to find out more than they now know of the folk among
            whom it grew, and the land in which they dwelt. In so doing they will come to see how
            needful are a few lessons from the healthy life and speech of those days, to be applied
            in the bettering of our own. </p>
          <p> H. HALLIDAY SPARLING. </p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="preface">
          <p> In offering to the reader this translation of the most complete and dramatic form of
            the great Epic of the North, we lay no claim to special critical insight, nor do we care
            to deal at all with vexed questions, but are content to abide by existing authorities,
            doing our utmost to make our rendering close and accurate, and, if it might be so, at
            the same time, not over prosaic: it is to the lover of poetry and nature, rather than to
            the student, that we appeal to enjoy and wonder at this great work, now for the first
            time, strange to say, translated into English: this must be our excuse for speaking
            here, as briefly as may be, of things that will seem to the student over well known to
            be worth mentioning, but which may give some ease to the general reader who comes across
            our book. </p>
          <p> The prose of the "Volsunga Saga" was composed probably some time in the twelfth
            century, from floating traditions no doubt; from songs which, now lost, were then known,
            at least in fragments, to the Sagaman; and finally from songs, which, written down about
            his time, are still existing: the greater part of these last the reader will find in
            this book, some inserted amongst the prose text by the original story-teller, and some
            by the present translators, and the remainder in the latter part of the book, put
            together as nearly as may be in the order of the story, and forming a metrical version
            of the greater portion of it. </p>
          <p> These Songs from the Elder Edda we will now briefly compare with the prose of the
            Volsung Story, premising that these are the only metrical sources existing of those from
            which the Sagaman told his tale. </p>
          <p> Except for the short snatch on p. 24 (1) of our translation, nothing is now left of
            these till we come to the episode of Helgi Hundings-bane, Sigurd's half-brother; there
            are two songs left relating to this, from which the prose is put together; to a certain
            extent they cover the same ground; but the latter half of the second is, wisely as we
            think, left untouched by the Sagaman, as its interest is of itself too great not to
            encumber the progress of the main story; for the sake of its wonderful beauty, however,
            we could not refrain from rendering it, and it will be found first among the metrical
            translations that form the second part of this book. </p>
          <p> Of the next part of the Saga, the deaths of Sinfjotli and Sigmund, and the journey of
            Queen Hjordis to the court of King Alf, there is no trace left of any metrical origin;
            but we meet the Edda once more where Regin tells the tale of his kin to Sigurd, and
            where Sigurd defeats and slays the sons of Hunding: this lay is known as the "Lay of
            Regin". </p>
          <p> The short chap. xvi. is abbreviated from a long poem called the "Prophecy of Gripir"
            (the Grifir of the Saga), where the whole story to come is told with some detail, and
            which certainly, if drawn out at length into the prose, would have forestalled the
            interest of the tale. </p>
          <p> In the slaying of the Dragon the Saga adheres very closely to the "Lay of Fafnir"; for
            the insertion of the song of the birds to Sigurd the present translators are
            responsible. </p>
          <p> Then comes the waking of Brynhild, and her wise redes to Sigurd, taken from the Lay of
            Sigrdrifa, the greater part of which, in its metrical form, is inserted by the Sagaman
            into his prose; but the stanza relating Brynhild's awaking we have inserted into the
            text; the latter part, omitted in the prose, we have translated for the second part of
            our book. </p>
          <p> Of Sigurd at Hlymdale, of Gudrun's dream, the magic potion of Grimhild, the wedding of
            Sigurd consequent on that potion; of the wooing of Brynhild for Gunnar, her marriage to
            him, of the quarrel of the Queens, the brooding grief and wrath of Brynhild, and the
            interview of Sigurd with her -- of all this, the most dramatic and best-considered parts
            of the tale, there is now no more left that retains its metrical form than the few
            snatches preserved by the Sagaman, though many of the incidents are alluded to in other
            poems. </p>
          <p> Chap. xxx. is met by the poem called the "Short Lay of Sigurd", which, fragmentary
            apparently at the beginning, gives us something of Brynhild's awakening wrath and
            jealousy, the slaying of Sigurd, and the death of Brynhild herself; this poem we have
            translated entire. </p>
          <p> The Fragments of the "Lay of Brynhild" are what is left of a poem partly covering the
            same ground as this last, but giving a different account of Sigurd's slaying; it is very
            incomplete, though the Sagaman has drawn some incidents from it; the reader will find it
            translated in our second part. </p>
          <p> But before the death of the heroine we have inserted entire into the text as chap.
            xxxi. the "First Lay of Gudrun", the most lyrical, the most complete, and the most
            beautiful of all the Eddaic poems; a poem that any age or language might count among its
            most precious possessions. </p>
          <p> From this point to the end of the Saga it keeps closely to the Songs of Edda; in chap.
            xxxii. the Sagaman has rendered into prose the "Ancient Lay of Gudrun", except for the
            beginning, which gives again another account of the death of Sigurd: this lay also we
            have translated. </p>
          <p> The grand poem, called the "Hell-ride of Brynhild", is not represented directly by
            anything in the prose except that the Sagaman has supplied from it a link or two wanting
            in the "Lay of Sigrdrifa"; it will be found translated in our second part. </p>
          <p> The betrayal and slaughter of the Giukings or Niblungs, and the fearful end of Atli
            and his sons, and court, are recounted in two lays, called the "Lays of Atli"; the
            longest of these, the "Greenland Lay of Atli", is followed closely by the Sagaman; the
            Shorter one we have translated. </p>
          <p> The end of Gudrun, of her daughter by Sigurd and of her sons by her last husband
            Jonakr, treated of in the last four chapters of the Saga, are very grandly and
            poetically given in the songs called the "Whetting of Gudrun", and the "Lay of Hamdir",
            which are also among our translations. </p>
          <p> These are all the songs of the Edda which the Sagaman has dealt with; but one other,
            the "Lament of Oddrun", we have translated on account of its intrinsic merit. </p>
          <p> As to the literary quality of this work we in say much, but we think we may well trust
            the reader of poetic insight to break through whatever entanglement of strange manners
            or unused element may at first trouble him, and to meet the nature and beauty with which
            it is filled: we cannot doubt that such a reader will be intensely touched by finding,
            amidst all its wildness and remoteness, such a startling realism, such subtilty, such
            close sympathy with all the passions that may move himself to-day. </p>
          <p> In conclusion, we must again say how strange it seems to us, that this Volsung Tale,
            which is in fact an unversified poem, should never before been translated into English.
            For this is the Great Story of the North, which should be to all our race what the Tale
            of Troy was to the Greeks -- to all our race first, and afterwards, when the change of
            the world has made our race nothing more than a name of what has been -- a story too --
            then should it be to those that come after us no less than the Tale of Troy has been to
            us. </p>
          <p> WILLIAM MORRIS and EIRIKR MAGNUSSON. </p>
        </div>




        <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="1">
          <p> Here begins the tale, and tells of a man who was named Sigi, and called of men the son
            of Odin; another man withal is told of in the tale, hight Skadi, a great man and mighty
            of his hands; yet was Sigi the mightier and the higher of kin, according to the speech
            of men of that time. Now Skadi had a thrall with whom the story must deal somewhat,
            Bredi by name, who was called after that work which he had to do; in prowess and might
            of hand he was equal to men who were held more worthy, yea, and better than some
            thereof. </p>
          <p> Now it is to be told that, on a time, Sigi fared to the hunting of the deer, and the
            thrall with him; and they hunted deer day- long till the evening; and when they gathered
            together their prey in the evening, lo, greater and more by far was that which Bredi had
            slain than Sigi's prey; and this thing he much misliked, and he said that great wonder
            it was that a very thrall should out-do him in the hunting of deer: so he fell on him
            and slew him, and buried the body of him thereafter in a snow-drift. </p>
          <p> Then he went home at evening tide and says that Bredi had ridden away from him into
            the wild-wood. "Soon was he out of my sight," he says, "and naught more I wot of him." </p>
          <p> Skadi misdoubted the tale of Sigi, and deemed that this was a guile of his, and that
            he would have slain Bredi. So he sent men to seek for him, and to such an end came their
            seeking, that they found him in a certain snow-drift; then said Skadi, that men should
            call that snow-drift Bredi's Drift from henceforth; and thereafter have folk followed,
            so that in such wise they call every drift that is right great. </p>
          <p> Thus it is well seen that Sigi has slain the thrall and murdered him; so he is given
            forth to be a wolf in holy places, (1) and may no more abide in the land with his
            father; therewith Odin bare him fellowship from the land, so long a way, that right long
            it was, and made no stay till he brought him to certain war- ships. So Sigi falls to
            lying out a-warring with the strength that his father gave him or ever they parted; and
            happy was he in his warring, and ever prevailed, till he brought it about that he won by
            his wars land and lordship at the last; and thereupon he took to him a noble wife, and
            became a great and mighty king, and ruled over the land of the Huns, and was the
            greatest of warriors. He had a son by his wife, who was called Refit, who grew up in his
            father's house, and soon became great of growth, and shapely. </p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="2">
          <p> Now Sigi grew old, and had many to envy him, so that at last those turned against him
            whom he trusted most; yea, even the brothers of his wife; for these fell on him at his
            unwariest, when there were few with him to withstand them, and brought so many against
            him, that they prevailed against him, and there fell Sigi and all his folk with him. But
            Rerir, his son, was not in this trouble, and he brought together so mighty a strength of
            his friends and the great men of the land, that he got to himself both the lands and
            kingdom of Sigi his father; and so now, when he deems that the feet under him stand firm
            in his rule, then he calls to mind that which he had against his mother's brothers, who
            had slain his father. So the king gathers together a mighty army, and therewith falls on
            his kinsmen, deeming that if he made their kinship of small account, yet none the less
            they had first wrought evil against him. So he wrought his will herein, in that he
            departed not from strife before he had slain all his father's banesmen, though dreadful
            the deed seemed in every wise. So now he gets land, lordship, and fee, and is become a
            mightier man than his father before him. </p>
          <p> Much wealth won in war gat Rerir to himself, and wedded a wife withal, such as he
            deemed meet for him, and long they lived together, but had no child to take the heritage
            after them; and ill-content they both were with that, and prayed the Gods with heart and
            soul that they might get them a child. And so it is said that Odin hears their prayer,
            and Freyia no less hearkens wherewith they prayed unto her: so she, never lacking for
            all good counsel, calls to her her casket-bearing may, (1) the daughter of Hrimnir the
            giant, and sets an apple in her hand, and bids her bring it to the king. She took the
            apple, and did on her the gear of a crow, and went flying till she came whereas the king
            sat on a mound, and there she let the apple fall into the lap of the king; but he took
            the apple and deemed he knew whereto it would avail; so he goes home from the mound to
            his own folk, and came to the queen, and some deal of that apple she ate. </p>
          <p> So, as the tale tells, the queen soon knew that she big with child, but a long time
            wore or ever she might give birth to the child: so it befell that the king must needs go
            to the wars, after the custom of kings, that he may keep his own land in peace: and in
            this journey it came to pass that Rerir fell sick and got his death, being minded to go
            home to Odin, a thing much desired of many folk in those days. </p>
          <p> Now no otherwise it goes with the queen's sickness than heretofore, nor may she be the
            lighter of her child, and six winters wore away with the sickness still heavy on her; so
            that at the last she feels that she may not live long; wherefore now she bade cut the
            child from out of her; and it was done even as she bade; a man-child was it, and great
            of growth from his birth, as might well be; and they say that the youngling kissed his
            mother or ever she died; but to him is a name given, and he is called Volsung; and he
            was king over Hunland in the room of his father. From his early years he was big and
            strong, and full of daring in all manly deeds and trials, and he became the greatest of
            warriors, and of good hap in all the battles of his warfaring. </p>
          <p> Now when he was fully come to man's estate, Hrimnir the giant sends to him Ljod his
            daughter; she of whom the tale told, that she brought the apple to Rerir, Volsung's
            father. So Volsung weds her withal; and long they abode together with good hap and great
            love. They had ten sons and one daughter, and their eldest son was hight Sigmund, and
            their daughter Signy; and these two were twins, and in all wise the foremost and the
            fairest of the children of Volsung the king, and mighty, as all his seed was; even as
            has been long told from ancient days, and in tales of long ago, with the greatest fame
            of all men, how that the Volsungs have been great men and high-minded and far above the
            most of men both in cunning and in prowess and all things high and mighty. </p>
          <p> So says the story that king Volsung let build a noble hall in such a wise, that a big
            oak-tree stood therein, and that the limbs of the tree blossomed fair out over the roof
            of the hall, while below stood the trunk within it, and the said trunk did men call
            Branstock. </p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="3">
          <p> There was a king called Siggeir, who ruled over Gothland, a mighty king and of many
            folk; he went to meet Volsung, the king, and prayed him for Signy his daughter to wife;
            and the king took his talk well, and his sons withal, but she was loth thereto, yet she
            bade her father rule in this as in all other things that concerned her, so the king took
            such rede (1) that he gave her to him, and she was betrothed to King Siggeir; and for
            the fulfilling of the feast and the wedding, was King Siggeir to come to the house of
            King Volsung. The king got ready the feast according to his best might, and when all
            things were ready, came the king's guests and King Siggeir withal at the day appointed,
            and many a man of great account had Siggeir with him. </p>
          <p> The tale tells that great fires were made endlong the hall, and the great tree
            aforesaid stood midmost thereof, withal folk say that, whenas men sat by the fires in
            the evening, a certain man came into the hall unknown of aspect to all men; and suchlike
            array he had, that over him was a spotted cloak, and he was bare- foot, and had
            linen-breeches knit tight even unto the bone, and he had a sword in his hand as he went
            up to the Branstock, and a slouched hat upon his head: huge he was, and seeming-ancient,
            and one-eyed. (2) So he drew his sword and smote it into the tree- trunk so that it sank
            in up to the hilts; and all held back from greeting the man. Then he took up the word,
            and said -- </p>
          <p> "Whoso draweth this sword from this stock, shall have the same as a gift from me, and
            shall find in good sooth that never bare he better sword in hand than is this." </p>
          <p> Therewith out went the old man from the hall, and none knew who he was or whither he
            went. </p>
          <p> Now men stand up, and none would fain be the last to lay hand to the sword, for they
            deemed that he would have the best of it who might first touch it; so all the noblest
            went thereto first, and then the others, one after other; but none who came thereto
            might avail to pull it out, for in nowise would it come away howsoever they tugged at
            it; but now up comes Sigmund, King Volsung's son, and sets hand to the sword, and pulls
            it from the stock, even as if it lay loose before him; so good that weapon seemed to
            all, that none thought he had seen such a sword before, and Siggeir would fain buy it of
            him at thrice its weight of gold, but Sigmund said -- </p>
          <p> "Thou mightest have taken the sword no less than I from there whereas it stood, if it
            had been thy lot to bear it; but now, since it has first of all fallen into my hand,
            never shalt thou have it, though thou biddest therefor all the gold thou hast." </p>
          <p> King Siggeir grew wroth at these words, and deemed Sigmund had answered him
            scornfully, but whereas was a wary man and a double- dealing, he made as if he heeded
            this matter in nowise, yet that same evening he thought how he might reward it, as was
            well seen afterwards. </p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="4">
          <p> Now it is to be told that Siggeir goes to bed by Signy that night, and the next
            morning the weather was fair; then says King Siggeir that he will not bide, lest the
            wind should wax, or the sea grow impassable; nor is it said that Volsung or his sons
            letted him herein, and that the less, because they saw that he was fain to get him gone
            from the feast. But now says Signy to her father -- </p>
          <p> "I have no will to go away with Seggeir, neither does my heart smile upon him, and I
            wot, by my fore-knowledge, and from the fetch (1) of our kin, that from this counsel
            will great evil fall on us if this wedding be not speedily undone." </p>
          <p> "Speak in no such wise, daughter!" said he, "for great shame will it be to him, yea,
            and to us also, to break troth with him, he being sackless; (2) and in naught may we
            trust him, and no friendship shall we have of him, if these matters are broken off; but
            he will pay us back in as evil wise as he may; for that alone is seemly, to hold truly
            to troth given." </p>
          <p> So King Siggeir got ready for home, and before he went from the feast he bade King
            Volsung, his father-in-las, come see him in Gothland, and all his sons with him whenas
            three months should be overpast, and to bring such following with him, as he would have,
            and as he deemed meet for his honour; and thereby will Siggeir the king pay back for the
            shortcomings of the wedding-feast, in that he would abide thereat but one night only, a
            thing not according to the wont of men. So King Volsung gave word to come on the day
            named, and the kinsmen-in-law parted, and Siggeir went home with his wife. </p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="5">
          <p> Now tells the tale of King Volsung and his sons that they go at the time appointed to
            Gothland at the bidding of King Siggeir, and put off from the land in three ships, all
            well manned, and have a fair voyage, and made Gothland late of an evening tide. </p>
          <p> But that same night came Signy and called her father and brothers to a privy talk, and
            told them what she deemed King Siggeir was minded to do, and how that he had drawn
            together an army no man may meet. "And," says she, "he is minded to do guilefully by
            you; wherefore I bid you get ye gone back again to your own land, and gather together
            the mightiest power ye may, and then come back hither and avenge you; neither go ye now
            to your undoing, for ye shall surely fail not to fall by his wiles if ye turn not on him
            even as I bid you." </p>
          <p> Then spake Volsung the king, "All people and nations shall tell of the word I spake,
            yet being unborn, wherein I vowed a vow that I would flee in fear from neither fire nor
            the sword; even so have I done hitherto, and shall I depart therefrom now I am old? Yea
            withal never shall the maidens mock these my sons at the games, and cry out at them that
            they fear death; once alone must all men need die, and from that season shall none
            escape; so my rede is that we flee nowhither, but do the work of our hands in as manly
            wise as we may; a hundred fights have I fought and whiles I had more, and whiles I had
            less, and yet even had I the victory, nor shall it ever be heard tell of me that I fled
            away or prayed for peace." </p>
          <p> Then Signy wept right sore, and prayed that she might not go back to King Siggeir, but
            King Volsung answered -- </p>
          <p> "Thou shalt surely go back to thine husband, and abide with him, howsoever it fares
            with us." </p>
          <p> So Signy went home, and they abode there that night but in the morning, as soon as it
            was day, Volsung bade his men arise and go aland and make them ready for battle; so they
            went aland, all of them all-armed, and had not long to wait before Siggeir fell on them
            with all his army, and the fiercest fight there was betwixt them; and Siggeir cried on
            his men to the onset all he might; and so the tale tells that King Volsung and his sons
            went eight times right through Siggeir's folk that day, smiting and hewing on either
            hand, but when they would do so even once again, King Volsung fell amidst his folk and
            all his men withal, saving his ten sons, for mightier was the power against them than
            they might withstand. </p>
          <p> But now are all his sons taken, and laid in bonds and led away; and Signy was ware
            withal that her father was slain, and her brothers taken and doomed to death, that she
            called King Siggeir apart to talk with her, and said -- </p>
          <p> "This will I pray of thee, that thou let not slay my brothers hastily, but let them be
            set awhile in the stocks, for home to me comes the saw that says, "Sweet to eye while
            seen": but longer life I pray not for them, because I wot well that my prayer will not
            avail me." </p>
          <p> Then answered Siggeir </p>
          <p> "Surely thou art mad and witless, praying thus for more bale for thy brothers than
            their present slaying; yet this will I grant thee, for the better it likes me the more
            they must bear, and the longer their pain is or ever death come to them." </p>
          <p> Now he let it be done even as she prayed, and a mighty beam was brought and set on the
            feet of those ten brethren in a certain place of the wild-wood, and there they sit
            day-long until night; but at midnight, as they sat in the stocks, there came on them a
            she-wolf from out the wood; old she was, and both great and evil of aspect; and the
            first thing she did was to bite one of those brethren till he died, and then she ate him
            up withal, and went on her way. </p>
          <p> But the next morning Signy sent a man to the brethren, even one whom she most trusted,
            to wot of the tidings; and when he came back he told her that one of them was dead, and
            great and grievous she deemed it, if they should all fare in like wise, and yet naught
            might she avail them. </p>
          <p> Soon is the tale told thereof: nine nights together came the she- wolf at midnight,
            and each night slew and ate up one of the brethren, until all were dead, save Sigmund
            only; so now, before the tenth night came, Signy sent that trusty man to Sigmund, her
            brother, and gave honey into his hand, bidding him do it over Sigmund's face, and set a
            little deal of it in his mouth; so he went to Sigmund and did as he was bidden, and then
            came home again; and so the next night came the she-wolf according to her wont, and
            would slay him and eat him even as his brothers; but now she sniffs the breeze from him,
            whereas he was anointed with the honey, and licks his face all over with her tongue, and
            then thrusts her tongue into the mouth of him. No fear he had thereof, but caught the
            she-wolf's tongue betwixt his teeth, and so hard she started back thereat, and pulled
            herself away so mightily, setting her feet against the stock that all was riven asunder;
            but he ever held so fast that the tongue came away by the roots, and thereof she had her
            bane. </p>
          <p> But some men say that this same she-wolf was the mother of King Siggeir, who had
            turned herself into this likeness by troll's lore and witchcraft. </p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="6">
          <p> Now whenas Sigmund is loosed and the stocks are broken, he dwells in the woods and
            holds himself there; but Signy sends yet again to wot of the tidings, whether Sigmund
            were alive or no; but when those who were sent came to him, he told them all as it had
            betid, and how things had gone betwixt him and the wolf; so they went home and tell
            Signy the tidings; but she goes and finds her brother, and they take counsel in such
            wise as to make a house underground in the wild-wood; and so things go on a while, Signy
            hiding him there, and sending him such things as he needed; but King Siggeir deemed that
            all the Volsungs were dead. </p>
          <p> Now Siggeir had two sons by his wife, whereof it is told that when the eldest was ten
            winters old, Signy sends him to Sigmund, so that he might give him help, if he would in
            any wise strive to avenge his father; so the youngling goes to the wood, and comes late
            in evening-tide to Sigmund's earth-house; and Sigmund welcomed him in seemly fashion,
            and said that he should make ready their bread; "But I," said he, "will go seek
            firewood." </p>
          <p> Therewith he gives the meal-bag into his hands while he himself went to fetch firing;
            but when he came back the youngling had done naught at the bread-making. Then asks
            Sigmund if the bread be ready -- </p>
          <p> Says the youngling, "I durst not set hand to the meal sack, because somewhat quick lay
            in the meal." </p>
          <p> Now Sigmund deemed he wotted that the lad was of no such heart as that he would be
            fain to have him for his fellow; and when he met his sister, Sigmund said that he had
            come no nigher to the aid of a man though the youngling were with him. </p>
          <p> Then said Signy, "Take him and kill him then; for why should such an one live longer?"
            and even so he did. </p>
          <p> So this winter wears, and the next winter Signy sent her next son to Sigmund; and
            there is no need to make a long tale thereof, for in like wise went all things, and he
            slew the child by the counsel of Signy. </p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="7">
          <p> So on a tide it befell as Signy sat in her bower, that there came to her a witch-wife
            exceeding cunning, and Signy talked with her in such wise, "Fain am I," says she, "that
            we should change semblances together." </p>
          <p> She says, "Even as thou wilt then." </p>
          <p> And so by her wiles she brought it about that they changed semblances, and now the
            witch-wife sits in Signy's place according to her rede, and goes to bed by the king that
            night, and he knows not that he has other than Signy beside him. </p>
          <p> But the tale tells of Signy, that she fared to the earthhouse of her brother, and
            prayed him give her harbouring for the night; "For I have gone astray abroad in the
            woods, and know not whither I am going." </p>
          <p> So he said she might abide, and that he would not refuse harbour to one lone woman,
            deeming that she would scarce pay back his good cheer by tale-bearing: so. she came into
            the house, and they sat down to meat, and his eyes were often on her, and a goodly and
            fair woman she seemed to him; but when they are full, then he says to her, that he is
            right fain that they should have but one bed that night; she nowise turned away
            therefrom, and so for three nights together he laid her in bed by him. </p>
          <p> Thereafter she fared home, and found the witch-wife and bade her change semblances
            again, and she did so. </p>
          <p> Now as time wears, Signy brings forth a man-child, who was named Sinfjotli, and when
            he grew up he was both big and strong, and fair of face, and much like unto the kin of
            the Volsungs, and he was hardly yet ten winters old when she sent him to Sigmund's
            earth-house; but this trial she had made of her other sons or ever she had sent them to
            Sigmund, that she had sewed gloves on to their hands through flesh and skin, and they
            had borne it ill and cried out thereat; and this she now did to Sinfjotli, and he
            changed countenance in nowise thereat. Then she flayed off the kirtle so that the skin
            came off with the sleeves, and said that this would be torment enough for him; but he
            said -- </p>
          <p> "Full little would Volsung have felt such a smart this." </p>
          <p> So the lad came to Sigmund, and Sigmund bade him knead their meal up, while he goes to
            fetch firing; so he gave him the meal-sack, and then went after the wood, and by then he
            came back had Sinfjotli made an end of his baking. Then asked Sigmund if he had found
            nothing in the meal. </p>
          <p> "I misdoubted me that there was something quick in the meal when I first fell to
            kneading of it, but I have kneaded it all up together, both the meal and that which was
            therein, whatsoever it was." </p>
          <p> Then Sigmund laughed out, he said -- </p>
          <p> "Naught wilt thou eat of this bread to-night, for the most deadly of worms (1) hast
            thou kneaded up therewith." </p>
          <p> Now Sigmund was so mighty a man that he might eat venom and have no hurt therefrom;
            but Sinfjotli might abide whatso venom came on the outside of him, but might neither eat
            nor drink thereof. </p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="8">
          <p> The tale tells that Sigmund thought Sinfjotli over young to help him to his revenge,
            and will first of all harden him with manly deeds; so in summer-tide they fare wide
            through the woods and slay men for their wealth; Sigmund deems him to take much after
            the kin of the Volsungs, though he thinks that he is Siggeir's son, and deems him to
            have the evil heart of his father, with the might and daring of the Volsungs; withal he
            must needs think him in no wise a kinsome man, for full oft would he bring Sigmund's
            wrongs to his memory, and prick him on to slay King Siggeir. </p>
          <p> Now on a time as they fare abroad in the wood for the getting of wealth, they find a
            certain house, and two men with great gold rings asleep therein: now these twain were
            spell-bound skin- changers, (1) and wolf-skins were hanging up over them in the house;
            and every tenth day might they come out of those skins; and they were kings' sons: so
            Sigmund and Sinfjofli do the wolf- skins on them, and then might they nowise come out of
            them, though forsooth the same nature went with them as heretofore; they howled as
            wolves howl but both knew the meaning of that howling; they lay out in the wild-wood,
            and each went his way; and a word they made betwixt them, that they should risk the
            onset of seven men, but no more, and that he who was first to be set on should howl in
            wolfish wise: "Let us not depart from this," says Sigmund, "for thou art young and
            over-bold, and men will deem the quarry good, when they take thee." </p>
          <p> Now each goes his way, and when they were parted, Sigmund meets certain men, and gives
            forth a wolf's howl; and when Sinfjotli heard it, he went straightway thereto, and slew
            them all, and once more they parted. But ere Sinfjotli has fared long through the woods,
            eleven men meet him, and he wrought in such wise that he slew them all, and was awearied
            therewith, and crawls under an oak, and there takes his rest. Then came Sigmund thither,
            and said -- </p>
          <p> "Why didst thou not call on me?" </p>
          <p> Sinfjotli said, "I was loth to call for thy help for the slaying of eleven men." </p>
          <p> Then Sigmund rushed at him so hard that he staggered and fell, and Sigmund bit him in
            the throat. Now that day they might not come out of their wolf-skins: but Sigmund lays
            the other on his back, and bears him home to the house, and cursed the wolf-gears and
            gave them to the trolls. Now on a day he saw where two weasels went and how that one bit
            the other in the throat, and then ran straightway into the thicket, and took up a leaf
            and laid in on the wound, and thereon his fellow sprang up quite and clean whole; so
            Sigmund went out and saw a raven flying with a blade of that same herb to him; so he
            took it and drew it over Sinfjotli's hurt, and he straightway sprang up as whole as
            though he had never been hurt. There after they went home to their earth-house, and
            abode there till the time came for them to put off the wolf-shapes; then they burnt them
            up with fire, and prayed that no more hurt might come to any one from them; but in that
            uncouth guise they wrought many famous deeds in the kingdom and lordship of King
            Siggeir. </p>
          <p> Now when Sinfjotli was come to man's estate, Sigmund deemed he had tried him fully,
            and or ever a long time has gone by he turns his mind to the avenging of his father; if
            so it may be brought about; so on s certain day the twain get them gone from their
            earth-house, and come to the abode of King Siggeir late in the evening, and go into the
            porch before the hall, wherein were tuns of ale, and there they lie hid: now the queen
            is ware of them, where they are, and is fain to meet them; and when they met they took
            counsel and were of one mind that Volsung should be revenged that same night. </p>
          <p> Now Signy and the king had two children of tender age, who played with a golden toy on
            the floor, and bowled it along the pavement of the hall, running along with it; but
            therewith a golden ring from off it trundles away into the place where Sigmund and
            Sinfjotli lay, and off runs the little one to search for the same, and beholds withal
            where two men axe sitting, big and grimly to look on, with overhanging helms and bright
            white byrnies; (2) so he runs up the hall to his father, and tells him of the sight he
            has seen, and thereat the king misdoubts of some guile abiding him; but Signy heard
            their speech, and arose and took both the children, and went out into the porch to them
            and said -- </p>
          <p> "Lo ye! These younglings have bewrayed you; come now therefore and slay them!" </p>
          <p> Sigmund says, "Never will I slay thy children for telling of where I lay hid." </p>
          <p> But Sinfjotli made little enow of it, but drew his sword and slew them both, and cast
            them into the hall at King 8iggeir's feet. </p>
          <p> Then up stood the king and cried on his men to take those who had lain privily in the
            porch through the night. So they ran thither and would lay hands on them, but they stood
            on their defence well and manly, and long he remembered it who was the nighest to them;
            but in the end they were borne down by many men and taken, and bonds were set upon them,
            and they were cast into fetters wherein they sit night long. </p>
          <p> Then the king ponders what longest and worst of deaths he shall mete out to them; and
            when morning came he let make a great barrow of stones and turf; and when it was done,
            let set a great flat stone midmost inside thereof, so that one edge was aloft, the other
            alow; and so great it was that it went from wall to wall, so that none might pass it. </p>
          <p> Now he bids folk take Sigmund and Sinfjotli and set them in the barrow, on either side
            of the stone, for the worse for them he deemed it, that they might hear each the other's
            speech, and yet that neither might pass one to the other. But now, while they were
            covering in the barrow with the turf-slips, thither came Signy, bearing straw with her,
            and cast it down to Sinfjotli, and bade the thralls hide this thing from the king; they
            said yea thereto, and therewithal was the barrow closed in. </p>
          <p> But when night fell, Sinfjotli said to Sigmund, "Belike we shall scarce need meat for
            a while, for here has the queen cast swine's flesh into the barrow, and wrapped it round
            about on the outer side with straw." </p>
          <p> Therewith he handles the flesh and finds that therein was thrust Sigmund's sword; and
            he knew it by the hilts as mirk as it might be in the barrow, and tells Sigmund thereof,
            and of that were they both fain enow. </p>
          <p> Now Sinfjotli drave the point of the sword up into the big stone, and drew it hard
            along, and the sword bit on the stone. With that Sigmund caught the sword by the point,
            and in this wise they sawed the stone between them, and let not or all the sawing was
            done that need be done, even as the song sings: <quote>
              <l>"Sinfjotli sawed</l>
              <l>And Sigmund sawed,</l>
              <l>Atwain with main</l>
              <l>The stone was done."</l>
            </quote> Now are they both together loose in the barrow, and soon they cut both through
            stone and through iron, and bring themselves out thereof. Then they go home to the hall,
            whenas all men slept there, and bear wood to the hall, and lay fire therein; and withal
            the folk therein are waked by the smoke, and by the hall burning over their heads. </p>
          <p> Then the king cries out, "Who kindled this fire, I burn withal?" </p>
          <p> "Here am I," says Sigmund, "with Sinfjotli, my sister's son; and we are minded that
            thou shalt wot well that all the Volsungs are not yet dead." </p>
          <p> Then he bade his sister come out, and take all good things at his hands, and great
            honour, and fair atonement in that wise, for all her griefs. </p>
          <p> But she answered, "Take heed now, and consider, if I have kept King Siggeir in memory,
            and his slaying of Volsung the king! I let slay both my children, whom I deemed
            worthless for the revenging of our father, and I went into the wood to thee in a
            witch-wife's shape; and now behold, Sinfjotli is the son of thee and of me both! And
            therefore has he this so great hardihood and fierceness, in that he is the son both of
            Volsung's son and Volsung's daughter; and for this, and for naught else, have I so
            wrought, that Siggeir might get his bane at last; and all these things have I done that
            vengeance might fall on him, and that I too might not live long; and merrily now will I
            die with King Siggeir, though I was naught merry to wed him." </p>
          <p> Therewith she kissed Sigmund her brother, and Sinfjotli, and went back again into the
            fire, and there she died with King Siggeir and all his good men. </p>
          <p> But the two kinsmen gathered together folk and ships, and Sigmund went back to his
            father's land, and drave away thence the king, who had set himself down there in the
            room of king Volsung. </p>
          <p> So Sigmund became a mighty King and far-famed, wise and high- minded: he had to wife
            one named Borghild, and two sons they had between them, one named Helgi and the other
            Hamund; and when Helgi was born, Norns came to him, (3) and spake over him, and said
            that he should be in time to come the most renowned of all kings. Even therewith was
            Sigmund come home from the wars, and so therewith he gives him the name of Helgi, and
            these matters as tokens thereof, Land of Rings, Sun-litten Hill and Sharp-shearing
            Sword, and withal prayed that he might grow of great fame, and like unto the kin of the
            Volsungs. </p>
          <p> And so it was that he grew up high-minded, and well beloved, and above all other men
            in all prowess; and the story tells that he went to the wars when he was fifteen winters
            old. Helgi was lord and ruler over the army, but Sinfjotli was gotten to be his fellow
            herein; the twain bare sway thereover. </p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="9">
          <p> Now the tale tells that Helgi in his warring met a king hight Hunding, a mighty king,
            and lord of many men and many lands; they fell to battle together, and Helgi went forth
            mightily, and such was the end of that fight that Helgi had the victory, but King
            Hunding fell and many of his men with him; but Helgi is deemed to have grown greatly in
            fame because he had slain so mighty a king. </p>
          <p> Then the sons of Hunding draw together a great army to avenge their father. Hard was
            the fight betwixt them; but Helgi goes through the folk of those brothers unto their
            banner, and there slays these sons of Hunding, Alf and Eyolf, Herward and Hagbard, and
            wins there a great victory. </p>
          <p> Now as Helgi fared from the fight he met a many women right fair and worthy to look
            on, who rode in exceeding noble array; but one far excelled them all; then Helgi asked
            them the name of that their lady and queen, and she named herself Sigrun, and said she
            was daughter of King Hogni. </p>
          <p> Then said Helgi, "Fare home with us: good welcome shall ye have!" </p>
          <p> Then said the king's daughter, "Other work lies before us than to drink with thee." </p>
          <p> "Yea, and what work, king's daughter?" said Helgi. </p>
          <p> She answers, "King Hogni has promised me to Hodbrod, the son of King Granmar, but I
            have vowed a vow that I will have him to my husband no more than if he were a crow's son
            and not a king's; and yet will the thing come to pass, but and if thou standest in the
            way thereof and goest against him with an army, and takest me away withal; for verily
            with no king would I rather bide on bolster than with thee." </p>
          <p> "Be of good cheer, king's daughter," says he, "for certes he and I shall try the
            matter, or ever thou be given to him; yea, we shall behold which may prevail against the
            other; and hereto I pledge my life." </p>
          <p> Thereafter, Helgi sent men with money in their hand to summon his folk to him, and all
            his power is called together to Red-Berg: and there Helgi abode till such time as a
            great company came to him from Hedinsey; and therewithal came mighty power from Norvi
            Sound aboard great and fair ships. Then King Helgi called to him the captain of his
            ships, who was hight Leif, and asked him if he had told over the tale of his army. </p>
          <p> "A thing not easy to tell, lord," says he, "on the ships that came out of Norvi Sound
            are twelve thousand men, and otherwhere are half as many again." </p>
          <p> Then bade King Helgi turn into the firth, called Varin's firth, and they did so: but
            now there fell on them so fierce a storm and so huge a sea, that the beat of the waves
            on board and bow was to hearken to like as the clashing together of high hills broken. </p>
          <p> But Helgi bade men fear naught, nor take in any sail, but rather hoist every rag
            higher than heretofore; but little did they miss of foundering or ever they made land;
            then came Sigrun, daughter of King Hogni, down on to the beach with a great army, and
            turned them away thence to a good haven called Gnipalund; but the landsmen see what has
            befallen and come down to the sea-shore. The brother of King Hodbrod, lord of a land
            called Swarin's Cairn, cried out to them, and asked them who was captain over that
            mighty army. Then up stands Sinfjotli, with a helm on his head, bright shining as glass,
            and a byrny as white as snow; a spear in his hand, and thereon a banner of renown, and a
            gold- rimmed shield hanging before him; and well he knew with what words to speak to
            kings -- </p>
          <p> "Go thou and say, when thou hast made an end of feeding thy swine and thy dogs, and
            when thou beholdest thy wife again, that here are come the Volsungs, and in this company
            may King Helgi be found, if Hodbrod be fain of finding him, for his game and his joy it
            is to fight and win fame, while thou art kissing the handmaids by the fire-side." </p>
          <p> Then answered Granmar, "In nowise knowest thou how to speak seemly things, and to tell
            of matters remembered from of old, whereas thou layest lies on chiefs and lords; most
            like it is that thou must have long been nourished with wolf-meat abroad in the
            wild-woods, and has slain thy brethren; and a marvel it is to behold that thou darest to
            join thyself to the company of good men and true, thou, who hast sucked the blood of
            many a cold corpse." </p>
          <p> Sinfjotli answered, "Dim belike is grown thy memory now, of how thou wert a witch-wife
            on Varinsey, and wouldst fain have a man to thee, and chose me to that same office of
            all the world; and how thereafter thou wert a Valkyria (1) in Asgarth, and it well- nigh
            came to this, that for thy sweet sake should all men fight; and nine wolf whelps I begat
            on thy body in Lowness, and was the father to them all." </p>
          <p> Granmar answers, "Great skill of lying hast thou; yet belike the father of naught at
            all mayst thou be, since thou wert gelded by the giant's daughters of Thrasness; and lo
            thou art the stepson of King Siggeir, and were wont to lie abroad in wilds and woods
            with the kin of wolves; and unlucky was the hand wherewith thou slewest thy brethren
            making for thyself an exceeding evil name." </p>
          <p> Said Sinfjotli, "Mindest thou not then, when thou were stallion Grani's mare, and how
            I rode thee an amble on Bravoli, and that afterwards thou wert giant Golnir's goat
            herd?" </p>
          <p> Granmar says, "Rather would I feed fowls with the flesh of thee than wrangle any
            longer with thee." </p>
          <p> Then spake King Helgi, "Better were it for ye, and a more manly deed, to fight, rather
            than to speak such things as it is a shame even to hearken to; Granmar's sons are no
            friends of me and of mine, yet are they hardy men none the less." </p>
          <p> So Granmar rode away to meet King Hodbrod, at a stead called Sunfells, and the horses
            of the twain were named Sveipud and Sveggjud. The brothers met in the castle-porch, and
            Granmar told Hodbrod of the war-news. King Hodbrod was clad in a byrny, and had his helm
            on his head; he asked -- </p>
          <p> "What men are anigh, why look ye so wrathful?" </p>
          <p> Granmar says, "Here are come the Volsungs, and twelve thousand men of them are afloat
            off the coast, and seven thousand are at the island called Sok, but at the stead called
            Grindur is the greatest company of all, and now I deem withal that Helgi and his
            fellowship have good will to give battle." </p>
          <p> Then said the king, "Let us send a message through all our realm, and go against them,
            neither let any who is fain of fight sit idle at home; let us send word to the sons of
            Ring, and to King Hogni, and to Alf the Old, for they are mighty warriors." </p>
          <p> So the hosts met at Wolfstone, and fierce fight befell there; Helgi rushed forth
            through the host of his foes, and many a man fell there; at last folk saw a great
            company of shield-maidens, like burning flames to look on, and there was come Sigrun,
            the king's daughter. Then King Helgi fell on King Hodbrod, and smote him, and slew him
            even under his very banner; and Sigrun cried out -- </p>
          <p> "Have thou thanks for thy so manly deed! Now shall we share the land between us, and a
            day of great good hap this is to me, and for this deed shalt thou get honour and renown,
            in that thou hast felled to earth so mighty a king." </p>
          <p> So Helgi took to him that realm and dwelt there long, when he had wedded Sigrun, and
            became a king of great honour and renown, though he has naught more to do with this
            story. </p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="10">
          <p> Now the Volsungs fare back home, and have gained great renown by these deeds. But
            Sinfjotli betook himself to warfare anew; and therewith he had sight of an exceeding
            fair woman, and yearned above all things for her, but that same woman was wooed also of
            the brother of Borghild, the king's wife: and this matter they fought out betwixt them,
            and Sinfjotli slew that king; and thereafter he harried far and wide, and had many a
            battle and even gained the day; and he became hereby honoured and renowned above all
            men; but in autumn tide he came home with many ships and abundant wealth. </p>
          <p> Then he told his tidings to the king his father, and he again to the queen, and she
            for her part bids him get him gone from the realm, and made as if she would in nowise
            see him. But Sigmund said he would not drive him away, and offered her atonement of gold
            and great wealth for her brother's life, albeit he said he had never erst given weregild
            (1) to any for the slaying of a man, but no fame it was to uphold wrong against a woman. </p>
          <p> So seeing she might not get her own way herein, she said, "Have thy will in this
            matter, O my lord, for it is seemly so to be." </p>
          <p> And now she holds the funeral feast for her brother by the aid and counsel of the
            king, and makes ready all things there -- or in the best of wise, and bade thither many
            great men. </p>
          <p> At that feast, Borghild the queen bare the drink to folk, and she came over against
            Sinfjofli with a great horn, and said -- </p>
          <p> "Fall to now and drink, fair stepson!" </p>
          <p> Then he took the horn to him, and looked therein, and said -- </p>
          <p> "Nay, for the drink is charmed drink" </p>
          <p> Then said Sigmund, "Give it unto me then;" and therewith he took the horn and drank it
            off. </p>
          <p> But the queen said to Sinfjotli, "Why must other men needs drink thine ale for thee?"
            And she came again the second time with the horn, and said, "Come now and drink!" and
            goaded him with many words. </p>
          <p> And he took the horn, and said -- </p>
          <p> "Guile is in the drink." </p>
          <p> And thereon, Sigmund cried out -- </p>
          <p> "Give it then unto me!" </p>
          <p> Again, the third time, she came to him, and bade him drink off his drink, if he had
            the heart of a Volsung; then he laid hand on the horn, but said -- </p>
          <p> "Venom is therein." </p>
          <p> "Nay, let the lip strain it out then, O son," quoth Sigmund; and by then was he
            exceeding drunk with drink, and therefore spake he in that wise. </p>
          <p> So Sinfjotli drank, and straightway fell down dead to the ground. </p>
          <p> Sigmund rose up, and sorrowed nigh to death over him; then he took the corpse in his
            arms and fared away to the wood, and went till he came to a certain firth; and then he
            saw a man in a little boat; and that man asked if he would be wafted by him over the
            firth, and he said yes thereto; but so little was the boat, that they might not all go
            in it at once, so the corpse was first laid therein, while Sigmund went by the
            firth-side. But therewith the boat and the man therein vanished away from before
            Sigmund's eyes. (2) </p>
          <p> So thereafter Sigmund turned back home, and drave away the queen, and a little after
            she died. But Sigmund the king yet ruled his realm, and is deemed ever the greatest
            champion and king of the old law. </p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="11">
          <p> There was a king called Eylimi, mighty and of great fame, and his daughter was called
            Hjordis, the fairest and wisest of womankind; and Sigmund hears it told of her that she
            was meet to be his wife, yea if none else were. So he goes to the house of King Eylimi,
            who would make a great feast for him, if so be he comes not thither in the guise of a
            foe. So messages were sent from one to the other that this present journey was a
            peaceful one, and not for war; so the feast was held in the best of wise and with many a
            man thereat; fairs were in every place established for King Sigmund, and all things else
            were done to the aid and comfort of his journey: so he came to the feast, and both kings
            hold their state in one hall; thither also was come King Lyngi, son of King Hunding, and
            he also is a-wooing the daughter of King Eylimi. </p>
          <p> Now the king deemed he knew that the twain had come thither but for one errand, and
            thought withal that war and trouble might be looked for from the hands of him who
            brought not his end about; so he spake to his daughter, and said -- </p>
          <p> "Thou art a wise woman, and I have spoken it, that thou alone shalt choose a husband
            for thyself; choose therefore between these two kings, and my rede shall be even as
            thine." </p>
          <p> "A hard and troublous matter," says she; "yet will I choose him who is of greatest
            fame, King Sigmund to wife albeit he is well stricken in years." </p>
          <p> So to him was she betrothed, and King Lyngi gat him gone. Then was Sigmund wedded to
            Hjordis, and now each day was the feast better and more glorious than on the day before
            it. But thereafter Sigmund went back home to Hunland, and King Eylimi, his
            father-in-law, with him, and King Sigmund betakes himself to the due ruling of his
            realm. </p>
          <p> But King Lyngi and his brethren gather an army together to fall on Sigmund, for as in
            all matters they were wont to have the worser lot, so did this bite the sorest of all;
            and they would fain prevail over the might and pride of the Volsungs. So they came to
            Hunland, and sent King Sigmund word how that they would not steal upon him and that they
            deemed he would scarce slink away from them. So Sigmund said he would come and meet them
            in battle, and drew his power together; but Hjordis was borne into the wood with a
            certain bondmaid, and mighty wealth went with them; and there she abode the while they
            fought. </p>
          <p> Now the vikings rushed from their ships in numbers not to be borne up against, but
            Sigmund the King, and Eylimi set up their banners, and the horns blew up to battle; but
            King Sigmund let blow the horn his father erst had had, and cheered on his men to the
            fight, but his army was far the fewest. </p>
          <p> Now was that battle fierce and fell, and though Sigmund were old, yet most hardily he
            fought, and was ever the foremost of his men; no shield or byrny might hold against him,
            and he went ever through the ranks of his foemen on that day, and no man might see how
            things would fare between them; many an arrow and many a spear was aloft in air that
            day, and so his spae-wrights wrought for him that he got no wound, and none can tell
            over the tale of those who fell before him, and both his arms were red with blood, even
            to the shoulders. </p>
          <p> But now whenas the battle had dured a while, there came a man into the fight clad in a
            blue cloak, and with a slouched hat on his head, one-eyed he was, (1) and bare a bill in
            his hand; and he came against Sigmund the King, and have up his bill against him, and as
            Sigmund smote fiercely with the sword it fell upon the bill and burst asunder in the
            midst: thenceforth the slaughter and dismay turned to his side, for the good-hap of King
            Sigmund had departed from him, and his men fell fast about him; naught did the king
            spare himself, but the rather cheered on his men; but even as the saw says, "No might
            'gainst many", so was it now proven; and in this fight fell Sigmund the King, and King
            Eylimi, his father-in-law, in the fore-front of their battle, and therewith the more
            part of their folk. </p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="12">
          <p> Now King Lyngi made for the king's abode, and was minded to take the king's daughter
            there, but failed herein, for there he found neither wife nor wealth; so he fared
            through all the realm, and gave his men rule thereover, and now deemed that he had slain
            all the kin of the Volsungs, and that he need dread them no more from henceforth. </p>
          <p> Now Hjordis went amidst the slain that night of the battle, and came whereas lay King
            Sigmund, and asked if he might be healed; but he answered -- </p>
          <p> "Many a man lives after hope has grown little; but my good-hap has departed from me,
            nor will I suffer myself to be healed, nor wills Odin that I should ever draw sword
            again, since this my sword and his is broken; lo now, I have waged war while it was his
            will." </p>
          <p> "Naught ill would I deem matters," said she, "if thou mightest be healed and avenge my
            father." </p>
          <p> The king said, "That is fated for another man; behold now, thou art great with a
            man-child; nourish him well; and with good heed, and the child shall be the noblest and
            most famed of all our kin: and keep well withal the shards of the sword: thereof shall a
            goodly sword be made, and it shall be called Gram, and our son shall bear it, and shall
            work many a great work therewith, even such as eld shall never minish; for his name
            shall abide and flourish as long as the world shall endure: and let this be enow for
            thee. But now I grow weary with my wounds, and I will go see our kin that have gone
            before me." </p>
          <p> So Hjordis sat over him till he died at the day-dawning; and then she looked, and
            behold, there came many ships sailing to the land: then she spake to the handmaid -- </p>
          <p> "Let us now change raiment, and be thou called by my name, and say that thou art the
            king's daughter." </p>
          <p> And thus they did; but now the vikings behold the great slaughter of men there, and
            see where two women fare away thence into the wood; and they deem that some great
            tidings must have befallen, and they leaped ashore from out their ships. Now the captain
            of these folks was Alf, son of Hjalprek, king of Denmark, who was sailing with his power
            along the land. So they came into the field among the slain, and saw how many men lay
            dead there; then the king bade go seek for the women and bring them thither, and they
            did so. He asked them what women they were; and, little as the thing seems like to be,
            the bondmaid answered for the twain, telling of the fall of King Sigmund and King
            Eylimi, and many another great man, and who they were withal who had wrought the deed.
            Then the king asks if they wotted where the wealth of the king was bestowed; and then
            says the bondmaid -- </p>
          <p> "It may well be deemed that we know full surely thereof." </p>
          <p> And therewith she guides them to the place where the treasure lay: and there they
            found exceeding great wealth; so that men deem they have never seen so many things of
            price heaped up together in one place. All this they bore to the ships of King Alf, and
            Hjordis and bondmaid went them. Therewith these sail away to their own realm, and talk
            how that surely on that field had fallen the most renowned of kings. </p>
          <p> So the king sits by the tiller, but the women abide in the forecastle; but talk he had
            with the women and held their counsels of much account. </p>
          <p> In such wise the king came home to his realm with great wealth, and he himself was a
            man exceeding goodly to look on. But when he had been but a little while at home, the
            queen, his mother, asked him why the fairest of the two women had the fewer rings and
            the less worthy attire. </p>
          <p> "I deem," she said, "that she whom ye have held of least account is the noblest of the
            twain." </p>
          <p> He answered: "I too have misdoubted me, that she is little like a bondwoman, and when
            we first met, in seemly wise she greeted noble men. Lo now, we will make trial of the
            thing." </p>
          <p> So on a time as men sat at the drink, the king sat down to talk with the women, and
            said: -- </p>
          <p> "In what wise do ye note the wearing of the hours, whenas night grows old, if ye may
            not see the lights of heaven?" </p>
          <p> Then says the bondwoman, "This sign have I, that whenas in my youth I was wont to
            drink much in the dawn, so now when I no longer use that manner, I am yet wont to wake
            up at that very same tide, and by that token do I know thereof." </p>
          <p> Then the king laughed and said, "Ill manners for a king's daughter!" And therewith he
            turned to Hjordis, and asked her even the same question; but she answered -- </p>
          <p> "My father erst gave me a little gold ring of such nature, that it groweth cold on my
            finger in the day-dawning; and that is the sign that I have to know thereof." </p>
          <p> The king answered: "Enow of gold there, where a very bondmaid bore it! But come now,
            thou hast been long enow hid from me; yet if thou hadst told me all from the beginning,
            I would have done to thee as though we had both been one king's children: but better
            than thy deeds will I deal with thee, for thou shalt be my wife, and due jointure will I
            pay thee whenas thou hast borne me a child." </p>
          <p> She spake therewith and told out the whole truth about herself: so there was she held
            in great honour, and deemed the worthiest of women. </p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="13">
          <p> The tale tells that Hjordis brought forth a man-child, who was straightly borne before
            King Hjalprek, and then was the king glad thereof, when he saw the keen eyes in the head
            of him, and he said that few men would be equal to him or like unto him in any wise. So
            he was sprinkled with water, and had to name Sigurd, of whom all men speak with one
            speech and say that none was ever his like for growth and goodliness. He was brought up
            in the house of King Hjalprek in great love and honour; and so it is, that whenso all
            the noblest men and greatest kings are named in the olden tales, Sigurd is ever put
            before them all for might and prowess, for high mind and stout heart; wherewith he was
            far more abundantly gifted than any man of the northern parts of the wide world. </p>
          <p> So Sigurd waxed in King Hjalprek's house, and there was no child but loved him;
            through him was Hjordis betrothed to King Alf, and jointure meted to her. </p>
          <p> Now Sigurd's foster-father was hight Regin, the son of Hreidmar; he taught him all
            manner of arts, the chess play, and the lore of runes, and the talking of many tongues,
            even as the wont was with kings' sons in those days. But on a day when they were
            together, Regin asked Sigurd, if he knew how much wealth his father had owned, and who
            had the ward thereof; Sigurd answered, and said that the kings kept the ward thereof. </p>
          <p> Said Regin, "Dost thou trust them all utterly?" </p>
          <p> Sigurd said, "It is seemly that they keep it till I may do somewhat therewith, for
            better they wot how to guard it than I do." </p>
          <p> Another time came Regin to talk to Sigurd, and said -- </p>
          <p> "A marvellous thing truly that thou must needs be a horse-boy to the kings, and go
            about like a running knave." </p>
          <p> "Nay," said Sigurd, "it is not so, for in all things I have my will, and whatso thing
            I desire is granted me with good will." </p>
          <p> "Well, then," said Regin, "ask for a horse of them." </p>
          <p> "Yea," quoth Sigurd, "and that shall I have, whenso I have need thereof." </p>
          <p> Thereafter Sigurd went to the king, and the king said -- </p>
          <p> "What wilt thou have of us?" </p>
          <p> Then said Sigurd, "I would even a horse of thee for my disport." </p>
          <p> Then said the king, "Choose for thyself a horse, and whatso thing else thou desirest
            among my matters." </p>
          <p> So the next day went Sigurd to the wood, and met on the way an old man, long-bearded,
            that he knew not, who asked him whither away. </p>
          <p> Sigurd said, "I am minded to choose me a horse; come thou, and counsel me thereon." </p>
          <p> "Well then," said he, "go we and drive them to the river which is called Busil-tarn." </p>
          <p> They did so, and drave the horses down into the deeps of the river, and all swam back
            to land but one horse; and that horse Sigurd chose for himself; grey he was of hue, and
            young of years, great of growth, and fair to look on, nor had any man yet crossed his
            back. </p>
          <p> Then spake the grey-beard, "From Sleipnir's kin is this horse come, and he must be
            nourished heedfully, for it will be the best of all horses;" and therewithal he vanished
            away. </p>
          <p> So Sigurd called the horse Grani, the best of all the horses of the world; nor was the
            man he met other than Odin himself. </p>
          <p> Now yet again spake Regin to Sigurd, and said -- </p>
          <p> "Not enough is thy wealth, and I grieve right sore, that thou must needs run here and
            there like s churl's son; but I can tell thee where there is much wealth for the
            winning, and great name and honour to be won in getting of it." </p>
          <p> Sigurd asked where that might be, and who had watch and ward over it. </p>
          <p> Regin answered, "Fafnir is his name, and but a little way hence he lies, on the waste
            of Gnita-heath; and when thou comest there thou mayst well say that thou hast never seen
            more gold heaped together in one place, and that none might desire more treasure, though
            he were the most ancient and famed of all kings." </p>
          <p> "Young am I," says Sigurd, "yet know I the fashion of this worm, and how that none
            durst go against him, so huge and evil is he." </p>
          <p> Regin said, "Nay it is not so, the fashion and the growth of him is even as of other
            lingworms, (1) and an over great tale men make of it; and even so would thy forefathers
            have deemed; but thou, though thou be of the kin of the Volsungs, shalt scarce have the
            heart and mind of those, who are told of as the first in all deeds of fame." </p>
          <p> Sigurd said, "Yea, belike I have little of their hardihood and prowess, but thou hast
            naught to do, to lay a coward's name upon me, when I am scarce out of my childish years.
            Why dost thou egg me on hereto so busily?" </p>
          <p> Regin said, "Therein lies a tale which I must needs tell thee." </p>
          <p> "Let me hear the same," said Sigurd. </p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="14">
          <p> "The tale begins," said Regin. "Hreidmar was my father's name, a mighty man and z
            wealthy: and his first son was named Fafnir, his second Otter, and I was the third, and
            the least of them all both for prowess and good conditions, but I was cunning to work in
            iron, and silver, and gold, whereof I could make matters that availed somewhat. Other
            skill my brother Otter followed, and had another nature withal, for he was a great
            fisher, and above other men herein; in that he had the likeness of an otter by day, and
            dwelt ever in the river, and bare fish to bank in his mouth, and his prey would he ever
            bring to our father, and that availed him much: for the most part he kept him in his
            otter-gear, and then he would come home, and eat alone, and slumbering, for on the dry
            land he might see naught. But Fafnir was by far the greatest and grimmest, and would
            have all things about called his. </p>
          <p> "Now," says Regin, "there was a dwarf called Andvari, who ever abode in that force,
            (1) which was called Andvari's force, in the likeness of a pike, and got meat for
            himself, for many fish there were in the force; now Otter, my brother, was ever wont to
            enter into the force, and bring fish aland, and lay them one by one on the bank. And so
            it befell that Odin, Loki, and Hoenir, as they went their ways, came to Andvari's force,
            and Otter had taken a salmon, and ate it slumbering upon the river bank; then Loki took
            a stone and cast it at Otter, so that he gat his death thereby; the gods were well
            content with their prey, and fell to flaying off the otter's skin; and in the evening
            they came to Hreidmar's house, and showed him what they had taken: thereon he laid hands
            on them, and doomed them to such ransom, as that they should fill the otter skin with
            gold, and cover it over without with red gold; so they sent Loki to gather gold together
            for them; he came to Ran, (2) and got her net, and went therewith to Andvari's force,
            and cast the net before the pike, and the pike ran into the net and was taken. Then said
            Loki -- <quote>
              <l>"`What fish of all fishes,</l>
              <l>Swims strong in the flood,</l>
              <l>But hath learnt little wit to beware?</l>
              <l>Thine head must thou buy,</l>
              <l>From abiding in hell,</l>
              <l>And find me the wan waters flame.'</l>
            </quote> "He answered -- <quote>
              <l>"`Andvari folk call me,</l>
              <l>Call Oinn my father,</l>
              <l>Over many a force have I fared;</l>
              <l>For a Norn of ill-luck,</l>
              <l>This life on me lay</l>
              <l>Through wet ways ever to wade.'</l>
            </quote> "So Loki beheld the gold of Andvari, and when he had given up the gold, he had
            but one ring left, and that also Loki took from him; then the dwarf went into a hollow
            of the rocks, and cried out, that that gold-ring, yea and all the gold withal, should be
            the bane of every man who should own it thereafter. </p>
          <p> "Now the gods rode with the treasure to Hreidmar, and fulfilled the otter-skin, and
            set it on its feet, and they must cover it over utterly with gold: but when this was
            done then Hreidmar came forth, and beheld yet one of the muzzle hairs, and bade them
            cover that withal; then Odin drew the ring, Andvari's loom, from his hand, and covered
            up the hair therewith; then sang Loki -- <quote>
              <l>"`Gold enow, gold enow,</l>
              <l>A great weregild, thou hast,</l>
              <l>That my head in good hap I may hold;</l>
              <l>But thou and thy son</l>
              <l>Are naught fated to thrive,</l>
              <l>The bane shall it be of you both.'</l>
            </quote> "Thereafter," says Regin, "Fafnir slew his father and murdered him, nor got I
            aught of the treasure, and so evil he grew, that he fell to lying abroad, and begrudged
            any share in the wealth to any man, and so became the worst of all worms, and ever now
            lies brooding upon that treasure: but for me, I went to the king and became his
            master-smith; and thus is the tale told of how I lost the heritage of my father, and the
            weregild for my brother." </p>
          <p> So spake Regin; but since that time gold is called Ottergild, and for no other cause
            than this. </p>
          <p> But Sigurd answered, "Much hast thou lost, and exceeding evil have thy kinsmen been!
            But now, make a sword by thy craft, such a sword as that none can be made like unto it;
            so that I may do great deeds therewith, if my heart avail thereto, and thou wouldst have
            me slay this mighty dragon." </p>
          <p> Regin says, "Trust me well herein; and with that same sword shalt thou slay Fafnir."
          </p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="15">
          <p> So Regin makes a sword, and gives it into Sigurd's hands. He took the sword, and said
            -- </p>
          <p> "Behold thy smithying, Regin!" and therewith smote it into the anvil, and the sword
            brake; so he cast down the brand, and bade him forge a better. </p>
          <p> Then Regin forged another sword, and brought it to Sigurd, who looked thereon. </p>
          <p> Then said Regin, "Belike thou art well content therewith, hard master though thou be
            in smithying." </p>
          <p> So Sigurd proved the sword, and brake it even as the first; then he said to Regin -- </p>
          <p> "Ah, art thou, mayhappen, a traitor and a liar like to those former kin of thine?" </p>
          <p> Therewith he went to his mother, and she welcomed him in seemly wise, and they talked
            and drank together. </p>
          <p> Then spake Sigurd, "Have I heard aright, that King Sigmund gave thee the good sword
            Gram in two pieces?" </p>
          <p> "True enough," she said. </p>
          <p> So Sigurd said, "Deliver them into my hands, for I would have them." </p>
          <p> She said he looked like to win great fame, and gave him the sword. Therewith went
            Sigurd to Regin, and bade him make a good sword thereof as he best might; Regin grew
            wroth thereat, but went into the smithy with the pieces of the sword, thinking well
            meanwhile that Sigurd pushed his head far enow into the matter of smithying. So he made
            a sword, and as he bore it forth from the forge, it seemed to the smiths as though fire
            burned along the edges thereof. Now he bade Sigurd take the sword, and said he knew not
            how to make a sword if this one failed. Then Sigurd smote it into the anvil, and cleft
            it down to the stock thereof, and neither burst the sword nor brake it. Then he praised
            the sword much, and thereafter went to the river with a lock of wool, and threw it up
            against the stream, and it fell asunder when it met the sword. Then was Sigurd glad, and
            went home. </p>
          <p> But Regin said, "Now whereas I have made the sword for thee, belike thou wilt hold to
            thy troth given, and wilt go meet Fafnir?" </p>
          <p> "Surely will I hold thereto," said Sigurd, "yet first must I avenge my father." </p>
          <p> Now Sigurd the older he grew, the more he grew in the love of all men, so that every
            child loved him well. </p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="16">
          <p> There was a man hight Grifir,(1) who was Sigurd's mother's brother, and a little after
            the forging of the sword Sigurd went to Grifir, because he was a man who knew things to
            come, and what was fated to men: of him Sigurd asked diligently how his life should go;
            but Grifir was long or he spake, yet at the last, by reason of Sigurd's exceeding great
            prayers, he told him all his life and the fate thereof, even as afterwards came to pass.
            So when Grifir had told him all even as he would, he went back home; and a little after
            he and Regin met. </p>
          <p> Then said Regin, "Go thou and slay Fafnir, even as thou hast given thy word." </p>
          <p> Sigurd said, "That work shall be wrought; but another is first to be done, the
            avenging of Sigmund the king and the other of my kinsmen who fell in that their last
            fight." </p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="17">
          <p> Now Sigurd went to the kings, and spake thus -- </p>
          <p> "Here have I abode a space with you, and I owe you thanks and reward, for great love
            and many gifts and all due honour; but now will I away from the land and go meet the
            sons of Hunding, and do them to wit that the Volsungs are not all dead; and your might
            would I have to strengthen me therein." </p>
          <p> So the kings said that they would give him all things soever that he desired, and
            therewith was a great army got ready, and all things wrought in the most heedful wise,
            ships and all war-gear, so that his journey might be of the stateliest: but Sigurd
            himself steered the dragon-keel which was the greatest and noblest; richly wrought were
            their sails, and glorious to look on. </p>
          <p> So they sail and have wind at will; but when a few days were overpast, there arose a
            great storm on the sea, and the waves were to behold even as the foam of men's blood;
            but Sigurd bade take in no sail, howsoever they might be riven, but rather to lay on
            higher than heretofore. But as they sailed past the rocks of a ness, a certain man
            hailed the ships, and asked who was captain over that navy; then was it told him that
            the chief and lord was Sigurd, the son of Sigmund, the most famed of all the young men
            who now are. </p>
          <p> Then said the man, "Naught but one thing, certes do all say of him, that none among
            the sons of kings may be likened unto him; now fain were I that ye would shorten sail on
            some of the ships, and take me aboard." </p>
          <p> Then they asked him of his name, and he sang -- <quote>
              <l>"Hnikar I hight,</l>
              <l>When I gladdened Huginn,</l>
              <l>And went to battle,</l>
              <l>Bright son of Volsung;</l>
              <l>Now may ye call</l>
              <l>The carl on the cliff top,</l>
              <l>Feng or Fjolnir:</l>
              <l>Fain would I with you."</l>
            </quote> They made for land therewith, and took that man aboard. </p>
          <p> Then quoth Sigurd,(1) as the song says -- <quote>
              <l>"Tell me this, O Hnikar,</l>
              <l>Since full well thou knowest</l>
              <l>Fate of Gods, good and ill of mankind,</l>
              <l>What best our hap foresheweth,</l>
              <l>When amid the battle</l>
              <l>About us sweeps the sword edge."</l>
            </quote> Quoth Hnikar -- <quote>
              <lg>
                <l>"Good are many tokens</l>
                <l>If thereof men wotted</l>
                <l>When the swords are sweeping:</l>
                <l>Fair fellow deem I</l>
                <l>The dark-winged raven,</l>
                <l>In war, to weapon-wielder.</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>"The second good thing:</l>
                <l>When abroad thou goest</l>
                <l>For the long road well arrayed,</l>
                <l>Good if thou seest</l>
                <l>Two men standing,</l>
                <l>Fain of fame within the forecourt.</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>"A third thing:</l>
                <l>Good hearing,</l>
                <l>The wolf a howling</l>
                <l>Abroad under ash boughs;</l>
                <l>Good hap shalt thou have</l>
                <l>Dealing with helm-staves,</l>
                <l>If thou seest these fare before thee.</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>"No man in fight</l>
                <l>His face shall turn</l>
                <l>Against the moon's sister</l>
                <l>Low, late-shining,</l>
                <l>For he winneth battle</l>
                <l>Who best beholdeth</l>
                <l>Through the midmost sword-play,</l>
                <l>And the sloping ranks best shapeth.</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>"Great is the trouble</l>
                <l>Of foot ill-tripping,</l>
                <l>When arrayed for fight thou farest,</l>
                <l>For on both sides about</l>
                <l>Are the Disir (2) by thee,</l>
                <l>Guileful, wishful of thy wounding.</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>"Fair-combed, well washen</l>
                <l>Let each warrior be,</l>
                <l>Nor lack meat in the morning,</l>
                <l>For who can rule</l>
                <l>The eve's returning,</l>
                <l>And base to fall before fate grovelling."</l>
              </lg>
            </quote> Then the storm abated, and on they fared till they came aland in the realm of
            Hunding's sons, and then Fjolnir vanished away. </p>
          <p> Then they let loose fire and sword, and slew men and burnt their abodes, and did waste
            all before them: a great company of folk fled before the face of them to Lyngi the King,
            and tell him that men of war are in the land, and are faring with such rage and fury
            that the like has never been heard of; and that the sons of King Hunding had no great
            forecast in that they said they would never fear the Volsungs more, for here was come
            Sigurd, the son of Sigmund, as captain over this army. </p>
          <p> So King Lyngi let send the war-message all throughout his realm, and has no will to
            flee, but summons to him all such as would give him aid. So he came against Sigurd with
            a great army, he and his brothers with him, and an exceeding fierce fight befell; many a
            spear and many an arrow might men see there raised aloft, axes hard driven, shields
            cleft and byrnies torn, helmets were shivered, skulls split atwain, and many a man
            felled to the cold earth. </p>
          <p> And now when the fight has long dured in such wise, Sigurd goes forth before the
            banners, and has the good sword Gram in his hand, and smites down both men and horses,
            and goes through the thickest of the throng with both arms red with blood to the
            shoulder; and folk shrank aback before him wheresoever he went, nor would either helm or
            byrny hold before him, and no man deemed he had ever seen his like. So a long while the
            battle lasted, and many a man was slain, and furious was the onset; till at last it
            befell, even as seldom comes to hand, when a land army falls on, that, do whatso they
            might, naught was brought about; but so many men fell of the sons of Hunding that the
            tale of them may not be told; and now whenas Sigurd was among the foremost, came the
            sons of Hunding against him, and Sigurd smote therewith at Lyngi the king, and clave him
            down, both helm and head, and mail- clad body, and thereafter he smote Hjorward his
            brother atwain, and then slew all the other sons of Hunding who were yet alive, and the
            more part of their folk withal. </p>
          <p> Now home goes Sigurd with fair victory won, and plenteous wealth and great honour,
            which he had gotten to him in this journey, and feasts were made for him against he came
            back to the realm. </p>
          <p> But when Sigurd had been at home but a little, came Regin to talk with him, and said
            -- </p>
          <p> "Belike thou wilt now have good will to bow down Fafnir's crest according to thy word
            plighted, since thou hast thus revenged thy father and the others of thy kin." </p>
          <p> Sigurd answered, "That will we hold to, even as we have promised, nor did it ever fall
            from our memory." </p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="18">
          <p> Now Sigurd and Regin ride up the heath along that same way wherein Fafnir was wont to
            creep when he fared to the water; and folk say that thirty fathoms was the height of
            that cliff along which he lay when he drank of the water below. Then Sigurd spake -- </p>
          <p> "How sayedst thou, Regin, that this drake (1) was no greater than other lingworms;
            methinks the track of him is marvellous great?" </p>
          <p> Then said Regin, "Make thee a hole, and sit down therein, and whenas the worm comes to
            the water, smite him into the heart, and so do him to death, and win thee great fame
            thereby." </p>
          <p> But Sigurd said, "What will betide me if I be before the blood of the worm?" </p>
          <p> Says Regin, "Of what avail to counsel thee if thou art still afeard of everything?
            Little art thou like thy kin in stoutness of heart." </p>
          <p> Then Sigurd rides right over the heath; but Regin gets him gone, sore afeard. </p>
          <p> But Sigurd fell to digging him a pit, and whiles he was at that work, there came to
            him an old man with a long beard, and asked what he wrought there, and he told him. </p>
          <p> Then answered the old man and said, "Thou doest after sorry counsel: rather dig thee
            many pits, and let the blood run therein; but sit thee down in one thereof, and so
            thrust the worm's heart through." </p>
          <p> And therewithal he vanished away; but Sigurd made the pits even as it was shown to
            him. </p>
          <p> Now crept the worm down to his place of watering, and the earth shook all about him,
            and he snorted forth venom on all the way before him as he went; but Sigurd neither
            trembled nor was adrad at the roaring of him. So whenas the worm crept over the pits,
            Sigurd thrust his sword under his left shoulder, so that it sank in up to the hilts;
            then up leapt Sigurd from the pit and drew the sword back again unto him, and therewith
            was his arm all bloody, up to the very shoulder. </p>
          <p> Now when that mighty worm was ware that he had his death-wound, then he lashed out
            head and tail, so that all things soever that were before him were broken to pieces. </p>
          <p> So whenas Fafnir had his death-wound, he asked "Who art thou? And who is thy father?
            And what thy kin, that thou wert so hardy as to bear weapons against me?" </p>
          <p> Sigurd answered, "Unknown to men is my kin. I am called a noble beast: (2) neither
            father have I nor mother, and all alone have I fared hither." </p>
          <p> Said Fafnir, "Whereas thou hast neither father nor mother, of what wonder weft thou
            born then? But now, though thou tellest me not thy name on this my death-day, yet thou
            knowest verily that thou liest unto me." </p>
          <p> He answered, "Sigurd am I called, and my father was Sigmund." </p>
          <p> Says Fafnir, "Who egged thee on to this deed, and why wouldst thou be driven to it?
            Hadst thou never heard how that all folk were adrad of me, and of the awe of my
            countenance? But an eager father thou hadst, O bright eyed swain!" </p>
          <p> Sigurd answered, "A hardy heart urged me on hereto, and a strong hand and this sharp
            sword, which well thou knowest now, stood me in stead in the doing of the deed. `Seldom
            hath hardy eld a faint-heart youth.'" </p>
          <p> Fafnir said, "Well, I wot that hadst thou waxed amid thy kin, thou mightest have good
            skill to slay folk in thine anger; but more of a marvel is it, that thou, a bondsman
            taken in war, shouldst have the heart to set on me, `for few among bondsmen have heart
            for the fight.'" </p>
          <p> Said 8igurd, "Wilt thou then cast it in my teeth that I am far away from my kin?
            Albeit I was a bondsman, yet was I never shackled. God wot thou hast found me free
            enow." </p>
          <p> Fafnir answered, "In angry wise dost thou take my speech; but hearken, for that same
            gold which I have owned shall be thy bane too." </p>
          <p> Quoth Sigurd, "Fain would we keep all our wealth til that day of days; yet shall each
            man die once for all." </p>
          <p> Said Fafnir, "Few things wilt thou do after my counsel, but take heed that thou shalt
            be drowned if thou farest unwarily over the sea; so bide thou rather on the dry land for
            the coming of the calm tide." </p>
          <p> Then said Sigurd, "Speak, Fafnir, and say, if thou art so exceeding wise, who are the
            Norns who rule the lot of all mothers' sons." </p>
          <p> Fafnir answers, "Many there be and wide apart; for some are of the kin of the Aesir,
            and some are of Elfin kin, and some there are who are daughters of Dvalin." </p>
          <p> Said Sigurd, "How namest thou the holm whereon Surt (3) and the Aesir mix and mingle
            the water of the sword?" </p>
          <p> "Unshapen is that holm hight," said Fafnir. </p>
          <p> And yet again he said, "Regin, my brother, has brought about my end, and it gladdens
            my heart that thine too he bringeth about; for thus will things be according to his
            will." </p>
          <p> And once again he spake, "A countenance of terror I bore up before all folk, after
            that I brooded over the heritage of my brother, and on every side did I spout out
            poison, so that none durst come anigh me, and of no weapon was I adrad, nor ever had I
            so many men before me, as that I deemed myself not stronger than all; for all men were
            sore afeard of me." </p>
          <p> Sigurd answered and said, "Few may have victory by means of that same countenance of
            terror, for whoso comes amongst many shall one day find that no one man is by so far the
            mightiest of all." </p>
          <p> Then says Fafnir, "Such counsel I give thee, that thou take thy horse and ride away at
            thy speediest, for ofttimes it fails out so, that he who gets a death-wound avenges
            himself none the less." </p>
          <p> Sigurd answered, "Such as thy redes are I will nowise do after them; nay, I will ride
            now to thy lair and take to me that great treasure of thy kin." </p>
          <p> "Ride there then," said Fafnir, "and thou shalt find gold enow to suffice thee for all
            thy life-days; yet shall that gold be thy bane, and the bane of every one soever who
            owns it." </p>
          <p> Then up stood Sigurd, and said, "Home would I ride and lose all that wealth, if I
            deemed that by the losing thereof I should never die; but every brave and true man will
            fain have his hand on wealth till that last day that thou, Fafnir, wallow in the
            death-pain til Death and Hell have thee." </p>
          <p> And therewithal Fafnir died. </p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="19">
          <p> Thereafter came Regin to Sigurd, and said, "Hail, lord and master, a noble victory
            hast thou won in the slaying of Fafnir, whereas none durst heretofore abide in the path
            of him; and now shall this deed of fame be of renown while the world stands fast." </p>
          <p> Then stood Regin staring on the earth a long while, and presently thereafter spake
            from heavy-mood: "Mine own brother hast thou slain, and scarce may I be called sackless
            of the deed." </p>
          <p> Then Sigurd took his sword Gram and dried it on the earth, and spake to Regin -- </p>
          <p> "Afar thou faredst when I wrought this deed and tried this sharp sword with the hand
            and the might of me; with all the might and main of a dragon must I strive, while thou
            wert laid alow in the heather-bush, wotting not if it were earth or heaven." </p>
          <p> Said Regin, "Long might this worm have lain in his lair, if the sharp sword I forged
            with my hand had not been good at need to thee; had that not been, neither thou nor any
            man would have prevailed against him as at this time." </p>
          <p> Sigurd answers, "Whenas men meet foes in fight, better is stout heart than sharp
            sword." </p>
          <p> Then said Regin, exceeding heavily, "Thou hast slain my brother, and scarce may I be
            sackless of the deed." </p>
          <p> Therewith Sigurd cut out the heart of the worm with the sword called Ridil; but Regin
            drank of Fafnir's blood, and spake, "Grant me a boon, and do a thing little for thee to
            do. Bear the heart to the fire, and roast it, and give me thereof to eat." </p>
          <p> Then Sigurd went his ways and roasted it on a rod; and when the blood bubbled out he
            laid his finger thereon to essay it, if it were fully done; and then he set his finger
            in his mouth, and lo, when the heart-blood of the worm touched his tongue, straightway
            he knew the voice of all fowls, and heard withal how the wood- peckers chattered in the
            brake beside him -- </p>
          <p> "There sittest thou, Sigurd, roasting Fafnir's heart for another, that thou shouldest
            eat thine ownself, and then thou shouldest become the wisest of all men." </p>
          <p> And another spake: "There lies Regin, minded to beguile the man who trusts in him." </p>
          <p> But yet again said the third, "Let him smite the head from off him then, and be only
            lord of all that gold." </p>
          <p> And once more the fourth spake and said, "Ah, the wiser were he if he followed after
            that good counsel, and rode thereafter to Fafnir's lair, and took to him that mighty
            treasure that lieth there, and then rode over Hindfell, whereas sleeps Brynhild; for
            there would he get great wisdom. Ah, wise he were, if he did after your redes, and
            bethought him of his own weal; `for where wolf's ears are, wolf's teeth are near.'" </p>
          <p> Then cried the fifth: "Yea, yea, not so wise is he as I deem him, if he spareth him
            whose brother he hath slain already." </p>
          <p> At last spake the sixth: "Handy and good rede to slay him, and be lord of the
            treasure!" </p>
          <p> Then said Sigurd, "The time is unborn wherein Regin shall be my bane; nay, rather one
            road shall both these brothers fare." </p>
          <p> And therewith he drew his sword Gram and struck off Regin's head. </p>
          <p> Then heard Sigurd the wood-peckers a-singing, even as the song says. (1) </p>
          <p> For the first sang: <quote>
              <l>"Bind thou, Sigurd,</l>
              <l>The bright red rings!</l>
              <l>Not meet it is</l>
              <l>Many things to fear.</l>
              <l>A fair may know I,</l>
              <l>Fair of all the fairest</l>
              <l>Girt about with gold,</l>
              <l>Good for thy getting."</l>
            </quote> And the second: <quote>
              <l>"Green go the ways</l>
              <l>Toward the hall of Giuki</l>
              <l>That the fates show forth</l>
              <l>To those who fare thither;</l>
              <l>There the rich king</l>
              <l>Reareth a daughter;</l>
              <l>Thou shalt deal, Sigurd,</l>
              <l>With gold for thy sweetling."</l>
            </quote> And the third: <quote>
              <l>"A high hall is there</l>
              <l>Reared upon Hindfell,</l>
              <l>Without all around it</l>
              <l>Sweeps the red flame aloft.</l>
              <l>Wise men wrought</l>
              <l>That wonder of halls</l>
              <l>With the unhidden gleam</l>
              <l>Of the glory of gold."</l>
            </quote> Then the fourth sang: <quote>
              <lg>
                <l>"Soft on the fell</l>
                <l>A shield-may sleepeth</l>
                <l>The lime-trees' red plague</l>
                <l>Playing about her:</l>
                <l>The sleep-thorn set Odin</l>
                <l> Into that maiden</l>
                <l>For her choosing in war</l>
                <l>The one he willed not.</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>"Go, son, behold</l>
                <l>That may under helm</l>
                <l>Whom from battle</l>
                <l>Vinskornir bore,</l>
                <l>From her may not turn</l>
                <l>The torment of sleep.</l>
                <l>Dear offspring of kings</l>
                <l>In the dread Norns' despite."</l>
              </lg>
            </quote> Then Sigurd ate some deal of Fafnir's heart, and the remnant he kept. Then he
            leapt on his horse and rode along the trail of the worm Fafnir, and so right unto his
            abiding-place; and he found it open, and beheld all the doors and the gear of them that
            they were wrought of iron: yea, and all the beams of the house; and it was dug down deep
            into the earth: there found Sigurd gold exceeding plenteous, and the sword Rotti; and
            thence he took the Helm of Awe, and the Gold Byrny, and many things fair and good. So
            much gold he found there, that he thought verily that scarce might two horses, or three
            belike, bear it thence. So he took all the gold and laid it in two great chests, and set
            them on the horse Grani, and took the reins of him, but nowise will he stir, neither
            will he abide smiting. Then Sigurd knows the mind of the horse, and leaps on the back of
            him, and smites and spurs into him, and off the horse goes even as if he were unladen.
          </p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="20">
          <p> By long roads rides Sigurd, till he comes at the last up on to Hindfell, and wends his
            way south to the land of the Franks; and he sees before him on the fell a great light,
            as of fire burning, and flaming up even unto the heavens; and when he came thereto, lo,
            a shield hung castle before him, and a banner on the topmost thereof: into the castle
            went Sigurd, and saw one lying there asleep, and all-armed. Therewith he takes the helm
            from off the head of him, and sees that it is no man, but a woman; and she was clad in a
            byrny as closely set on her as though it had gown to her flesh; so he rent it from the
            collar downwards; and then the sleeves thereof, and ever the sword bit on it as if it
            were cloth. Then said Sigurd that over-long had she lain asleep; but she asked -- </p>
          <p> "What thing of great might is it that has prevailed to rend my byrny, and draw me from
            my sleep?" </p>
          <p> Even as sings the song (1) <quote>
              <l>"What bit on the byrny,</l>
              <l>Why breaks my sleep away,</l>
              <l>Who has turned from me</l>
              <l>My wan tormenting?"</l>
            </quote> "Ah, is it so, that here is come Sigurd Sigmundson, bearing Fafnir's helm on
            his head and Fafnir's bane in his hand?" </p>
          <p> Then answered Sigurd -- <quote>
              <l>"Sigmund's son</l>
              <l>With Sigurd's sword</l>
              <l>E'en now rent down</l>
              <l>The raven's wall."</l>
            </quote> "Of the Volsung's kin is he who has done the deed; but now I have heard that
            thou art daughter of a mighty king, and folk have told us that thou wert lovely and full
            of lore, and now I will try the same." </p>
          <p> Then Brynhild sang -- <quote>
              <lg>
                <l>"Long have I slept</l>
                <l>And slumbered long,</l>
                <l>Many and long are the woes of mankind,</l>
                <l>By the might of Odin</l>
                <l>Must I bide helpless</l>
                <l>To shake from off me the spells of slumber.</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>"Hail to the day come back!</l>
                <l>Hail, sons of the daylight!</l>
                <l>Hail to thee, dark night, and thy daughter!</l>
                <l>Look with kind eyes a-down,</l>
                <l>On us sitting here lonely,</l>
                <l>And give unto us the gain that we long for.</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>"Hail to the Aesir,</l>
                <l>And the sweet Asyniur! (2)</l>
                <l>Hail to the fair earth fulfilled of plenty!</l>
                <l>Fair words, wise hearts,</l>
                <l>Would we win from you,</l>
                <l>And healing hands while life we hold."</l>
              </lg>
            </quote> Then Brynhild speaks again and says, "Two kings fought, one hight Helm Gunnar,
            an old man, and the greatest of warriors, and Odin had promised the victory unto him;
            but his foe was Agnar, or Audi's brother, and so I smote down Helm Gunnar in the fight;
            and Odin, in vengeance for that deed, stuck the sleep-thorn into me, and said that I
            should never again have the victory, but should be given away in marriage; but there
            against I vowed a vow, that never would I wed one who knew the name of fear." </p>
          <p> Then said Sigurd, "Teach us the lore of mighty matters!" </p>
          <p> She said, "Belike thou cannest more skill in all than I; yet will I teach thee; yea,
            and with thanks, if there be aught of my cunning that will in anywise pleasure thee,
            either of runes or of other matters that are the root of things; but now let us drink
            together, and may the Gods give to us twain a good day, that thou mayst win good help
            and fame from my wisdom, and that thou mayst hereafter mind thee of that which we twain
            speak together." </p>
          <p> Then Brynhild filled a beaker and bore it to Sigurd, and gave him the drink of love,
            and spake -- <quote>
              <lg>
                <l>"Beer bring I to thee,</l>
                <l>Fair fruit of the byrnies' clash,</l>
                <l>Mixed is it mightily,</l>
                <l>Mingled with fame,</l>
                <l>Brimming with bright lays</l>
                <l>And pitiful runes,</l>
                <l>Wise words, sweet words,</l>
                <l>Speech of great game.</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>"Runes of war know thou,</l>
                <l>If great thou wilt be!</l>
                <l>Cut them on hilt of hardened sword,</l>
                <l>Some on the brand's back,</l>
                <l>Some on its shining side,</l>
                <l>Twice name Tyr therein.</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>"Sea-runes good at need,</l>
                <l>Learnt for ship's saving,</l>
                <l>For the good health of the swimming horse;</l>
                <l>On the stern cut them,</l>
                <l>Cut them on the rudder-blade</l>
                <l>And set flame to shaven oar:</l>
                <l>Howso big be the sea-hills,</l>
                <l>Howso blue beneath,</l>
                <l>Hail from the main then comest thou home.</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>"Word-runes learn well</l>
                <l>If thou wilt that no man</l>
                <l>Pay back grief for the grief thou gavest;</l>
                <l>Wind thou these,</l>
                <l>Weave thou these,</l>
                <l>Cast thou these all about thee,</l>
                <l>At the Thing,</l>
                <l>Where folk throng,</l>
                <l>Unto the full doom faring.</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>"Of ale-runes know the wisdom</l>
                <l>If thou wilt that another's wife</l>
                <l>Should not bewray thine heart that trusteth:</l>
                <l>Cut them on the mead-horn,</l>
                <l>On the back of each hand,</l>
                <l>And nick an N upon thy nail.</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>"Ale have thou heed</l>
                <l>To sign from all harm</l>
                <l>Leek lay thou in the liquor,</l>
                <l>Then I know for sure</l>
                <l>Never cometh to thee,</l>
                <l>Mead with hurtful matters mingled.</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>"Help-runes shalt thou gather</l>
                <l>If skill thou wouldst gain</l>
                <l>To loosen child from low-laid mother;</l>
                <l>Cut be they in hands hollow,</l>
                <l>Wrapped the joints round about;</l>
                <l>Call for the Good-folks' gainsome helping.</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>"Learn the bough-runes wisdom</l>
                <l>If leech-lore thou lovest;</l>
                <l>And wilt wot about wounds' searching</l>
                <l>On the bark be they scored;</l>
                <l>On the buds of trees</l>
                <l>Whose boughs look eastward ever.</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>"Thought-runes shalt thou deal with</l>
                <l>If thou wilt be of all men</l>
                <l>Fairest-souled wight, and wisest,</l>
                <l>These areded</l>
                <l>These first cut</l>
                <l>These first took to heart high Hropt.</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>"On the shield were they scored</l>
                <l>That stands before the shining God,</l>
                <l>On Early-waking's ear,</l>
                <l>On All-knowing's hoof,</l>
                <l>On the wheel which runneth</l>
                <l>Under Rognir's chariot;</l>
                <l>On Sleipnir's jaw-teeth,</l>
                <l>On the sleigh's traces.</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>"On the rough bear's paws,</l>
                <l>And on Bragi's tongue,</l>
                <l>On the wolfs claws,</l>
                <l>And on eagle's bill,</l>
                <l>On bloody wings,</l>
                <l>And bridge's end;</l>
                <l>On loosing palms,</l>
                <l>And pity's path:</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>"On glass, and on gold,</l>
                <l>And on goodly silver,</l>
                <l>In wine and in wort,</l>
                <l>And the seat of the witch-wife;</l>
                <l>On Gungnir's point,</l>
                <l>And Grani's bosom;</l>
                <l>On the Norn's nail,</l>
                <l>And the neb of the night-owl.</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>"All these so cut,</l>
                <l>Were shaven and sheared,</l>
                <l>And mingled in with holy mead,</l>
                <l>And sent upon wide ways enow;</l>
                <l>Some abide with the Elves,</l>
                <l>Some abide with the Aesir,</l>
                <l>Or with the wise Vanir,</l>
                <l>Some still hold the sons of mankind.</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>"These be the book-runes,</l>
                <l>And the runes of good help,</l>
                <l>And all the ale-runes,</l>
                <l>And the runes of much might;</l>
                <l>To whomso they may avail,</l>
                <l>Unbewildered unspoilt;</l>
                <l>They are wholesome to have:</l>
                <l>Thrive thou with these then.</l>
                <l>When thou hast learnt their lore,</l>
                <l>Till the Gods end thy life-days.</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>"Now shalt thou choose thee</l>
                <l>E'en as choice is bidden,</l>
                <l>Sharp steel's root and stem,</l>
                <l>Choose song or silence;</l>
                <l>See to each in thy heart,</l>
                <l>All hurt has been heeded."</l>
              </lg>
            </quote> Then answered Sigurd -- <quote>
              <l>"Ne'er shall I flee,</l>
              <l>Though thou wottest me fey;</l>
              <l>Never was I born for blenching,</l>
              <l>Thy loved rede will I</l>
              <l>Hold aright in my heart</l>
              <l>Even as long as I may live."</l>
            </quote>
          </p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="21">
          <p> Sigurd spake now, "Sure no wiser woman than thou art one may be found in the wide
            world; yea, yea, teach me more yet of thy wisdom!" </p>
          <p> She answers, "Seemly is it that I do according to thy will, and show thee forth more
            redes of great avail, for thy prayer's sake and thy wisdom ;" and she spake withal -- </p>
          <p> "Be kindly to friend and kin, and reward not their trespasses against thee; bear and
            forbear, and win for thee thereby long enduring praise of men. </p>
          <p> "Take good heed of evil things: a may's love, and a man's wife; full oft thereof doth
            ill befall! </p>
          <p> "Let not thy mind be overmuch crossed by unwise men at thronged meetings of folk; for
            oft these speak worse than they wot of; lest thou be called a dastard, and art minded to
            think that thou art even as is said; slay such an one on another day, and so reward his
            ugly talk. </p>
          <p> "If thou farest by the way whereas bide evil things, be well ware of thyself; take not
            harbour near the highway, though thou be benighted, for oft abide there ill wights for
            men's bewilderment. </p>
          <p> "Let not fair women beguile thee, such as thou mayst meet at the feast, so that the
            thought thereof stand thee in stead of sleep, and a quiet mind; yea, draw them not to
            thee with kisses or other sweet things of love. </p>
          <p> "If thou hearest the fool's word of a drunken man, strive not with him being drunk
            with drink and witless; many a grief, yea, and the very death, groweth from out such
            things. </p>
          <p> "Fight thy foes in the field, nor be burnt in thine house. </p>
          <p> 'Never swear thou wrongsome oath; great and grim is the reward for the breaking of
            plighted troth. </p>
          <p> "Give kind heed to dead men, -- sick-dead, Sea-dead, or ~word- dead; deal heedfully
            with their dead corpses. </p>
          <p> "Trow never in him for whom thou hast slain father, brother, or whatso near kin, yea,
            though young he be; `for oft waxes wolf in youngling'. </p>
          <p> "Look thou with good heed to the wiles of thy friends; but little skill is given to
            me, that I should foresee the ways of thy life; yet good it were that hate fell not on
            thee from those of thy wife's house." </p>
          <p> Sigurd spake, "None among the sons of men can be found wiser than thou; and thereby
            swear I, that thee will I have as my own, for near to my heart thou liest." </p>
          <p> She answers, "Thee would I fainest choose, though I had all men's sons to choose
            from." </p>
          <p> And thereto they plighted troth both of them. </p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="22">
          <p> Now Sigurd rides away; many-folded is his shield, an blazing with red gold, and the
            image of a dragon is drawn thereon; and this same was dark brown above, and bright red
            below; and with even such-like image was adorned helm, and saddle, and coat-armour; and
            he was clad in the golden byrny, and all his weapons were gold wrought. </p>
          <p> Now for this cause was the drake drawn on all his weapons, that when he was seen of
            men, all folk might know who went there; yea, all those who had heard of his slaying of
            that great dragon, that the Voerings call Fafnir, and for that cause are his weapons
            gold-wrought, and brown of hue, and that he was by far above other men in courtesy and
            goodly manners, and well-nigh in all things else; and whenas folk tell of all the
            mightiest champions, and the noblest chiefs, then ever is he named the foremost, and his
            name goes wide about on all tongues north of the sea of the Greek-lands, and even so
            shall it be while the world endures. </p>
          <p> Now the hair of this Sigurd was golden-red of hue, fair of fashion, and falling down
            in great locks; thick and short was his beard, and of no other colour, high-nosed he
            was, broad and high- boned of face; so keen were his eyes, that few durst gaze up under
            the brows of him; his shoulders were as broad to look on as the shoulders of two; most
            duly was his body fashioned betwixt height and breadth, and in such wise as was
            seemliest; and this is the sign told of his height, that when he was girt with his sword
            Gram, which same was seven spans long, as he went through the full-grown rye-fields, the
            dew-shoe of the said sword smote the ears of the standing corn; and, for all that,
            ;~greater was his strength than his growth: well could he wield sword, and cast forth
            spear, shoot shaft, and hold shield, bend bow, back horse, and do all the goodly deeds
            that he learned in his youth's days. </p>
          <p> Wise he was to know things yet undone; and the voice of all fowls he knew, wherefore
            few things fell on him unawares. </p>
          <p> Of many words he was and so fair of speech withal, that whensoever he made it his
            business to speak, he never left speaking before that to all men it seemed full sure,
            that no otherwise must the matter be than as he said. </p>
          <p> His sport and pleasure it was to give aid to his own folk, and to prove himself in
            mighty matters, to take wealth from his unfriends, and give the same to his friends. </p>
          <p> Never did he lose heart, and of naught was he adrad. </p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="23">
          <p> Forth Sigurd fides till he comes to a great and goodly dwelling, the lord whereof was
            a mighty chief called Heimir; he had to wife a sister of Brynhild, who was hight
            Bekkhild, because she had bidden at home, and learned handicraft, whereas Brynhild fared
            with helm and byrny, unto the wars, wherefore was she called Brynhild. </p>
          <p> Heimir and Bekkhild had a son called Alswid, the most courteous of men. </p>
          <p> Now at this stead were men disporting them abroad, but when they see the man riding
            thereto, they leave their play to wonder at him, for none such had they ever seen erst,
            so they went to meet him, and gave him good welcome. Alswid bade him abide and have such
            things at his hands as he would; and he takes his bidding blithesomely; due service
            withal was established for him; four men bore the treasure of gold from off the horse,
            and the fifth took it to him to guard the same; therein were many things to behold,
            things of great price, and seldom seen; and great game and joy men had to look on
            byrnies and helms, and mighty rings, and wondrous great golden stoups, and all kinds of
            war weapons. </p>
          <p> So there dwelt Sigurd long in great honour holden; and tidings of that deed of fame
            spread wide through all lands, of how he had slain that hideous and fearful dragon. So
            good joyance had they there together, and each was leal to other; and their sport was in
            the arraying of their weapons, and the shafting of their arrows, and the flying of their
            falcons. </p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="24">
          <p> In those days came home to Heimir, Brynhild, his foster daughter, and she sat in her
            bower with her maidens, and could do more skill in handycraft than other women; she sat,
            overlaying cloth with gold, and sewing therein the great deeds which Sigurd had wrought,
            the slaying of the Worm, and the taking of the wealth of him, and the death of Regin
            withal. </p>
          <p> Now tells the tale, that on a day Sigurd rode into the wood with hawk, and hound, and
            men thronging; and whenas he came home his hawk flew up to a high tower and sat him down
            on a certain window. Then fared Sigurd after his hawk, and he saw where sat a fair
            woman, and knew that it was Brynhild, and he deems all things he sees there to be worthy
            together, both her fairness, and the fair things she wrought: and therewith he goes into
            the hall, but has no more joyance in the games of the men folk. </p>
          <p> Then spake Alswid, "Why art thou so bare of bliss; this manner of thine grieveth us
            thy friends; why then wilt thou not hold to thy gleesome ways? Lo, thy hawks pine now,
            and thy horse Grani droops; and long will it be ere we are booted thereof?" </p>
          <p> Sigurd answered, "Good friend, hearken to what lies on my mind; for my hawk flew up
            into a certain tower; and when I came thereto and took him, lo there I saw a fair woman,
            and she sat by a needlework of gold, and did thereon, my deeds that are passed, and my
            deeds that are to come," </p>
          <p> Then said Alswid, "Thou has seen Brynhild, Budli's daughter, the greatest of great
            women." </p>
          <p> "Yea, verily," said Sigurd; "but how came she hither?" </p>
          <p> Aswid answered, "Short space there was betwixt the coming hither of the twain of you." </p>
          <p> Says Sigurd, "Yea, but a few, days agone I knew her for the best of the world's
            women." </p>
          <p> Alswid said, "Give not all thine heed to one woman, being such a man as thou art; ill
            life to sit lamenting for what we may not have." </p>
          <p> "I shall go meet her," says Sigurd, "and get from her love like my love, and give her
            a gold ring in token thereof." </p>
          <p> Alswid answered, "None has ever yet been known whom she would let sit beside her, or
            to whom she would give drink; for ever will she hold to warfare and to the winning of
            all kinds of fame." </p>
          <p> Sigurd said, "We know not for sure whether she will give us answer or not, or grant us
            a seat beside her." </p>
          <p> So the next day after, Sigurd went to the bower, but Alswid stood outside the bower
            door, fitting shafts to his arrows. </p>
          <p> Now Sigurd spake, "Abide, fair and hale lady, -- how farest thou?" </p>
          <p> She answered, "Well it fares; my kin and my friends live yet: but who shall say what
            goodhap folk may bear to their life's end?" </p>
          <p> He sat him down by her, and there came in four damsels with great golden beakers, and
            the best of wine therein; and these stood before the twain. </p>
          <p> Then said Brynhild, "This seat is for few, but and if my father come." </p>
          <p> He answered, "Yet is it granted to one that likes me well." </p>
          <p> Now that chamber was hung with the best and fairest of hanging, and the floor thereof
            was all covered with cloth. </p>
          <p> Sigurd spake, "Now has it come to pass even as thou didst promise." </p>
          <p> "O be thou welcome here!" said she, and arose there with, and the four damsels with
            her, and bore the golden beaker to him, and bade him drink; he stretched oui his hand to
            the beaker, and took it, and her hand withal, and drew her down beside him; and cast his
            arms round about her neck and kissed her, and said -- </p>
          <p> "Thou art the fairest that was ever born!" </p>
          <p> But Brynhild said, "Ah, wiser is it not to cast faith and troth into a woman's power,
            for ever shall they break that they have promised." </p>
          <p> He said, "That day would dawn the best of days over our heads whereon each of each
            should be made happy." </p>
          <p> Brynhild answered, "It is not fated that we should abide together; I am a shield-may,
            and wear helm on head even as the kings of war, and them full oft I help, neither is the
            battle become loathsome to me." </p>
          <p> Sigurd answered, "What fruit shall be of our life, if we live not together: harder to
            bear this pain that lies hereunder, than the stroke of sharp sword." </p>
          <p> Brynhild answers, "I shall gaze on the hosts of the war kings, but thou shalt wed
            Gudrun, the daughter of Giuki." </p>
          <p> Sigurd answered, "What king's daughter lives to beguile me? Neither am I
            double-hearted herein; and now I swear by the Gods that thee shall I have for mine own,
            or no woman else. </p>
          <p> And even suchlike wise spake she. </p>
          <p> 8igurd thanked her for her speech, and gave her a gold ring, and now they swore oath
            anew, and so he went his ways to his men, and is with them awhile in great bliss. </p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="25">
          <p> There was a king hight Giuki, who ruled a realm south of the Rhine; three sons he had,
            thus named: Gunnar, Hogni, and Guttorm, and Gudrun was the name of his daughter, the
            fairest of maidens; and all these children were far before all other king's children in
            all prowess, and in goodliness and growth withal; ever were his sons at the wars and
            wrought many a deed of fame. But Giuki had wedded Grimhild the Wise-wife. </p>
          <p> Now Budli was the name of a king mightier than Giuki, mighty though they both were:
            and Atli was the brother of Brynhild: Atli was a fierce man and a grim, great and black
            to look on, yet noble of mien withal, and the greatest of warriors. Grimhild was a
            fierce-heart woman. </p>
          <p> Now the days of the Giukings bloomed fair, and chiefly because of those children, so
            far before the sons of men. </p>
          <p> On a day Gudrun says to her mays that she may have no joy of heart; then a certain
            woman asked her wherefore her joy was departed. </p>
          <p> She answered, "Grief came to me in my dreams, therefore is there sorrow in my heart,
            since thou must needs ask thereof." </p>
          <p> "Tell it me, then, thy dream," said the woman, "for dreams oft forecast but the
            weather." </p>
          <p> Gudrun answers, "Nay, nay, no weather is this; I dreamed that I had a fair hawk on my
            wrist, feathered with feathers of gold." </p>
          <p> Says the woman, "Many have heard tell of thy beauty, thy wisdom, and thy courtesy;
            some king's son abides thee, then." </p>
          <p> Gudrun answers, "I dreamed that naught was so dear to me as this hawk, and all my
            wealth had I cast aside rather than him." </p>
          <p> The woman said, "Well, then, the man thou shalt have will be of the goodliest, and
            well shalt thou love him." </p>
          <p> Gudrun answered, "It grieves me that I know not who he shall be; let us go seek
            Brynhild, for she belike will wot thereof." </p>
          <p> So they arrayed them in gold and many a fair thing, and she went with her damsels till
            they came to the hall of Brynhild, and that hall was dight with gold, and stood on a
            high hill; and whenas their goings were seen, it was told Brynhild, that a company of
            women drove toward the burg in gilded waggons. </p>
          <p> "That shall be Gudrun, Giuki's daughter," says she: "I dreamed of her last night; let
            us go meet her! No fairer woman may come to our house." </p>
          <p> So they went abroad to meet them, and gave them good greeting, and they went into the
            goodly hall together; fairly painted it was within, and well adorned with silver vessel;
            cloths were spread under the feet of them, and all folk served them, and in many wise
            they sported. </p>
          <p> But Gudrun was somewhat silent. </p>
          <p> Then said Brynhild, "Ill to abash folk of their mirth; prithee do not so; let us talk
            together for our disport of mighty kings and their great deeds." </p>
          <p> "Good talk," says Gudrun, "let us do even so; what kings deemest thou to have been the
            first of all men?" </p>
          <p> Brynhild says, "The sons of Haki, and Hagbard withal; they brought to pass many a deed
            of fame in the warfare." </p>
          <p> Gudrun answers, "Great men certes, and of noble fame! Yet Sigar took their one sister,
            and burned the other, house and all; and they may be called slow to revenge the deed;
            why didst thou not name my brethren who are held to be the first of men as at this
            time?" </p>
          <p> Brynhild says, "Men of good hope are they surely though but little proven hitherto;
            but one I know far before them, Sigurd, the son of Sigmund the king; a youngling was he
            in the days when he slew the sons of Hunding, and revenged his father, and Eylimi, his
            mother's father." </p>
          <p> Said Gudrun, "By what token tellest thou that?" </p>
          <p> Brynhild answered, "His mother went amid the dead and found Sigmund the king sore
            wounded, and would bind up his hurts; but he said he grew over old for war; and bade her
            lay this comfort to her heart, that she should bear the most famed of sons; and wise was
            the wise man's word therein: for after the death of King Sigmund, she went to King Alf,
            and there was Sigurd nourished in great honour, and day by day he wrought some deed of
            fame, and is the man most renowned of all the wide world." </p>
          <p> Gudrun says, "From love hast thou gained these tidings of him; but for this cause came
            I here, to tell thee dreams of mine which have brought me great grief." </p>
          <p> Says Brynhild, "Let not such matters sadden thee: abide with thy friends who wish thee
            blithesome, all of them!" </p>
          <p> "This I dreamed," said Gudrun, "that we went, a many of us in company, from the bower,
            and we saw an exceeding great hart, that far excelled all other deer ever seen, and the
            hair of him was golden; and this deer we were all fain to take, but I alone got him; and
            he seemed to me better than all things else; but sithence thou, Byrnhild, didst shoot
            and slay my deer even at my very knees, and such grief was that to me that scarce might
            I bear it; and then afterwards thou gavest me a wolf-cub, which besprinkled me with the
            blood of my brethren." </p>
          <p> Brynhild answers, "I will arede thy dream, even as things shall come to pass
            hereafter; for Sigurd shall come to thee, even he whom I have chosen for my
            well-beloved; and Grimhild shall give him mead mingled with hurtful things, which shall
            cast us all into mighty strife. Him shalt thou have, and him shalt thou quickly miss;
            and Atli the king shalt thou wed; and thy brethren shalt thou lose, and slay Atli withal
            in the end." </p>
          <p> Dudrun answers, "Grief and woe to know that such things shall be!" </p>
          <p> And therewith she and hers get them gone home to King Giuki. </p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="26">
          <p> Now Sigurd goes his ways with all that great treasure, and in friendly wise he departs
            from them; and on Grani he rides with all his war-gear and the burden withal; and thus
            he rides until he comes to the hall of King Giuki; there he rides into the burg, and
            that sees one of the king's men, and he spake withal -- </p>
          <p> "Sure it may be deemed that here is come one of the Gods, for his array is all done
            with gold, and his horse is far mightier than other horses, and the manner of his
            weapons is most exceeding goodly, and most of all the man himself far excels all other
            men ever seen." </p>
          <p> So the king goes out with his court and greets the man, and asks -- </p>
          <p> "Who art thou who thus ridest into my burg, as none has durst hitherto without the
            leave of my sons?" </p>
          <p> He answered, "I am called Sigurd, son of King Sigmund." </p>
          <p> Then said King Giuki, "Be thou welcome here then, and take at our hands whatso thou
            wiliest." </p>
          <p> So he went into the king's hall, and all men seemed little beside him, and all men
            served him, and there he abode in great joyance. </p>
          <p> Now oft they all ride abroad together, Sigurd and Gunnar and Hogni, and ever is Sigurd
            far the foremost of them, mighty men of their hands though they were. </p>
          <p> But Grimhild finds how heartily Sigurd loved Brynhild, and how oft he talks of her;
            and she falls to thinking how well it were, if he might abide there and wed the daughter
            of King Giuki, for she saw that none might come anigh to his goodliness, and what faith
            and goodhelp there was in him, and how that he had more wealth withal than folk might
            tell of any man; and the king did to him even as unto his own sons, and they for their
            parts held him of more worth than themselves. </p>
          <p> So on a night as they sat at the drink, the queen arose, and went before Sigurd, and
            said -- </p>
          <p> "Great joy we have in thine abiding here, and all good things will we put before thee
            to take of us; lo now, take this horn and drink thereof." </p>
          <p> So he took it and drank, and therewithal she said, "Thy father shall be Giuki the
            king, and I shall be thy mother, and Gunnar and Hogni shall be thy brethren, and all
            this shall be sworn with oaths each to each; and then surely shall the like of you never
            be found on earth." </p>
          <p> Sigurd took her speech well, for with the drinking of that drink all memory of
            Brynhild departed from him. So there he abode awhile. </p>
          <p> And on a day went Grimhild to Giuki the king, and cast her arms about his neck, and
            spake -- </p>
          <p> "Behold, there has now come to us the greatest of great hearts that the world holds;
            and needs must he be trusty and of great avail; give him thy daughter then, with
            plenteous wealth, and as much of rule as he will; perchance thereby he will be well
            content to abide here ever." </p>
          <p> The king answered, "Seldom does it befall that kings offer their daughters to any; yet
            in higher wise will it be done to offer her to this man, than to take lowly prayers to
            her from others." </p>
          <p> On a night Gudrun pours out the drink, and Sigurd beholds her how fair she is and how
            full of all courtesy. </p>
          <p> Five seasons Sigurd abode there, and ever they passed their days together in good
            honour and friendship. </p>
          <p> And so it befell that the king held talk together, and Giuki said -- </p>
          <p> "Great good thou givest us, Sigurd, and with exceeding strength thou strengthenest our
            realm." </p>
          <p> Then Gunnar said, "All things that may be will we do for thee, so thou abidest here
            long; both dominion shall thou have, and our sister freely and unprayed for, whom
            another man would not get for all his prayers." </p>
          <p> Sigurd says, "Thanks have ye for this wherewith; ye honour me, and gladly will I take
            the same." </p>
          <p> Therewith they swore brotherhood together, and to be even as if they were children of
            one father and one mother; and a noble feast was holden, and endured many days, and
            Sigurd drank at the wedding of him and Gudrun; and there might men behold all manner of
            game and glee, and each day the feast was better and better. </p>
          <p> Now fare these folk wide over the world, and do many great deeds, and slay many kings'
            sons, and no man has ever done such works of prowess as did they; then home they come
            again with much wealth won in war. </p>
          <p> Sigurd gave of the serpent's heart to Gudrun, and she ate thereof, and became
            greater-hearted, and wiser than ere before: and the son of these twain was called
            Sigmund. </p>
          <p> Now on a time went Grimhild to Gunnar her son, and spake -- </p>
          <p> "Fair blooms the life and fortune of thee, but for one thing only, and namely whereas
            thou art unwedded; go woo Brynhild; good rede is this, and Sigurd will ride with thee." </p>
          <p> Gunnar answered, "Fair in she certes, and I am fain enow to win her;" and therewith he
            tells his father, and his brethren, and Sigurd, and they all prick him on to that
            wooing. </p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="27">
          <p> Now they array them joyously for their journey, and ride over hill and dale to the
            house of King Budli, and woo his daughter of him; in a good wise he took their speech,
            if so be that she herself would not deny them, but he said withal that so high- minded
            was she, that that man only might wed her whom she would. </p>
          <p> Then they ride to Hlymdale, and there Heimir gave them good welcome; so Gunnar tells
            his errand; Heimir says, that she must needs wed but him whom she herself chose freely;
            and tells them how her abode was but a little way thence, and that he deemed that him
            only would she have who should ride through the flaming fire that was drawn round about
            her hall; so they depart and come to the hall and the fire, and see there a castle with
            a golden roof-ridge, and all round about a fire roaring up. </p>
          <p> Now Gunnar rode on Goti, but Hogni on Holkvi, and Gunnar smote his horse to face the
            fire, but he shrank aback. </p>
          <p> Then said Sigurd, "Why givest thou back, Gunnar?" </p>
          <p> He answered, "The horse will not tread this fire; but lend me thy horse Grani." </p>
          <p> "Yea, with all my good will," says Sigurd. </p>
          <p> Then Gunnar rides him at the fire, and yet nowise will Gram stir, nor may Gunnar any
            the more ride through that fire. So now they change semblance, Gunnar and Sigurd, even
            as Grimhild had taught them; then Sigurd in the likeness of Gunnar mounts and rides,
            Gram in his hand, and golden spurs on his heels; then leapt Grani into the fire when he
            felt the spurs; and a mighty roar arose as the fire burned ever madder, and the earth
            trembled, and the flames went up even unto the heavens, nor had any dared to ride as he
            rode, even as it were through the deep mirk. </p>
          <p> But now the fire sank withal, and he leapt from his horse and went into the hall, even
            as the song says -- <quote>
              <lg>
                <l>"The flame flared at its maddest,</l>
                <l>Earth's fields fell a-quaking</l>
                <l>As the red flame aloft</l>
                <l>Licked the lowest of heaven.</l>
                <l>Few had been fain,</l>
                <l>Of the rulers of folk,</l>
                <l>To ride through that flame,</l>
                <l>Or athwart it to tread.</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>"Then Sigurd smote</l>
                <l>Grani with sword,</l>
                <l>And the flame was slaked</l>
                <l>Before the king;</l>
                <l>Low lay the flames</l>
                <l>Before the fain of fame;</l>
                <l>Bright gleamed the array</l>
                <l>That Regin erst owned.</l>
              </lg>
            </quote> Now when Sigurd had passed through the fire, he came into a certain fair
            dwelling, and therein sat Brynhild. </p>
          <p> She asked, "What man is it?" </p>
          <p> Then he named himself Gunnar, son of Giuki, and said -- "Thou art awarded to me as my
            wife, by the good will and word of thy father and thy foster-father, and I have ridden
            through the flame of thy fire, according to thy that thou hast set forth." </p>
          <p> "I wot not clearly," said she, "how I shall answer thee." </p>
          <p> Now Sigurd stood upright on the hall floor, and leaning on the hilt of his sword, and
            he spake to Brynhild -- </p>
          <p> "In reward thereof, shall I pay thee a great dower in gold and goodly things?" </p>
          <p> She answered in heavy mood from her seat, whereas she sat like unto swan on billow,
            having a sword in her hand and a helm on her head, and being clad in a byrny, "O
            Gunnar," she says, "speak not to me of such things unless thou be the first and best of
            all men; for then shall thou slay those my wooers, if thou hast heart thereto; I have
            been in battles with the king of the Greeks, and weapons were stained with red blood,
            and for such things still I yearn." </p>
          <p> He answered, "Yea, certes many great deeds hast thou done; but yet call thou to mind
            thine oath, concerning the riding through of this fire, wherein thou didst swear that
            thou wouldst go with the man who should do this deed." </p>
          <p> So she found that he spoke but the sooth, and she paid heed to his words, and arose,
            and greeted him meetly, and he abode there three nights, and they lay in one bed
            together; but he took the sword Gram and laid it betwixt them: then she asked him why he
            laid it there; and he answered, that in that wise must he needs wed his wife or else get
            his bane. </p>
          <p> Then she took from off her the ring Andvari's loom, which he had given her aforetime,
            and gave it to him, but he gave her another ring out of Fafnir's hoard. </p>
          <p> Thereafter he rode away through the same fire unto his Fellows, and he and Gunnar
            changed semblances again, and rode unto Hlymdale, and told how it had gone with them. </p>
          <p> That same day went Brynhild home to her foster-father, and tells him as one whom she
            trusted, how that there had come a king to her; "And he rode through my flaming fire,
            and said he was come to woo me, and named himself Gunnar; but I said that such a deed
            might Sigurd alone have done, with whom I plighted troth on the mountain; and he is my
            first troth-plight, and my well-beloved." </p>
          <p> Heimir said that things must needs abide even as now they had now come to pass. </p>
          <p> Brynhild said, "Aslaug the daughter of me and Sigurd shall be nourished here with
            thee." </p>
          <p> Now the kings fare home, but Brynhild goes to her father; Grimhild welcomes the kings
            meetly, and thanks Sigurd for his fellowship; and withal is a great feast made, and many
            were the guests thereat; and thither came Budli the King with his daughter Brynhild, and
            his son Atli, and for many days did the feast endure: and at that feast was Gunnar
            wedded to Brynhild: but when it was brought to an end, once more has Sigurd memory of
            all the oaths that he sware unto Brynhild, yet withal he let all things abide in rest
            and peace. </p>
          <p> Brynhild and Gunnar sat together in great game and glee, and drank goodly wine. </p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="28">
          <p> On a day as the Queens went to the river to bathe them, Brynhild waded the farthest
            out into the river; then asked Gudrun what that deed might signify. </p>
          <p> Brynhild said, "Yea, and why then should I be equal to thee in this matter more than
            in others? I am minded to think that my father is mightier than thine, and my true love
            has wrought many wondrous works of fame, and hath ridden the flaming fire withal, while
            thy husband was but the thrall of King Hjalprek." </p>
          <p> Gudrun answered full of wrath, "Thou wouldst be wise if thou shouldst hold thy peace
            rather than revile my husband: lo now, the talk of all men it is, that none has ever
            abode in this world like unto him in all matters soever; and little it beseems thee of
            all folk to mock him who was thy first beloved: and Fafnir he slew, yea, and he rode thy
            flaming fire, whereas thou didst deem that he was Gunnar the King, and by thy side he
            lay, and took from thine hand the ring Andvari's-loom; -- here mayst thou well behold
            it!" </p>
          <p> Then Brynhild saw the ring and knew it, and waxed as wan as a dead woman, and she went
            home and spake no word the evening long. </p>
          <p> So when Sigurd came to bed to Gudrun she asked him why Brynhild's joy was so departed. </p>
          <p> He answered, "I know not, but sore I misdoubt me that soon we shall know thereof
            overwell." </p>
          <p> Gudrun said, "Why may she not love her life, having wealth and bliss, and the praise
            of all men, and the man withal that she would have?" </p>
          <p> "Ah, yea!" said Sigurd, "and where in all the world was she then, when she said that
            she deemed she had the noblest of all men, and the dearest to her heart of all?" </p>
          <p> Gudrun answers, "Tomorn will I ask her concerning this, who is the liefest to her of
            all men for a husband." </p>
          <p> Sigurd said, "Needs must I forbid thee this, and full surely wilt thou rue the deed if
            thou doest it." </p>
          <p> Now the next morning they sat in the bower, and Brynhild was silent; then spake Gudrun
            -- </p>
          <p> "Be merry, Brynhild! Grievest thou because of that speech of ours together, or what
            other thing slayeth thy bliss?" </p>
          <p> Brynhild answers, "With naught but evil intent thou sayest this, for a cruel heart
            thou hast." </p>
          <p> "Say not so," said Gudrun; "but rather tell me all the tale." </p>
          <p> Brynhild answers, "Ask such things only as are good for thee to know -- matters meet
            for mighty dames. Good to love good things when all goes according to thy heart's
            desire!" </p>
          <p> Gudrun says, "Early days for me to glory in that; but this word of thine looketh
            toward some foreseeing. What ill dost thou thrust at us? I did naught to grieve thee." </p>
          <p> Brynhild answers, "For this shalt thou pay, in that thou hast got Sigurd to thee, --
            nowise can I see thee living in the bliss thereof, whereas thou hast him, and the wealth
            and the might of him." </p>
          <p> But Gudrun answered, "Naught knew I of your words and vows together; and well might my
            father look to the mating of me without dealing with thee first." </p>
          <p> "No secret speech had we," quoth Brynhild, "though we swore oath together; and full
            well didst thou know that thou wentest about to beguile me; verily thou shalt have thy
            reward!" </p>
          <p> Says Gudrun, "Thou art mated better than thou are worthy of; but thy pride and rage
            shall be hard to slake belike, and there for shall many a man pay." </p>
          <p> "Ah, I should be well content," said Brynhild, "if thou hadst not the nobler man!" </p>
          <p> Gudrun answers, "So noble a husband hast thou, that who knows of a greater king or a
            lord of more wealth and might?" </p>
          <p> Says Brynhild, "Sigurd slew Fafnir, and that only deed is of more worth than all the
            might of King Gunnar." </p>
          <p> (Even as the song says) -- <quote>
              <l>"The worm Sigurd slew,</l>
              <l>Nor ere shall that deed</l>
              <l>Be worsened by age</l>
              <l>While the world is alive.</l>
              <l>But thy brother the King</l>
              <l>Never durst, never bore</l>
              <l>The flame to ride down</l>
              <l>Through the fire to fare."</l>
            </quote> Gudrun answers, "Grani would not abide the fire under Gunnar the King, but
            Sigurd durst the deed, and thy heart may well abide without mocking him." </p>
          <p> Brynhild answers, "Nowise will I hide from thee that I deem no good of Grimhild." </p>
          <p> Says Gudrun, "Nay, lay no ill words on her, for in all things she is to thee as to her
            own daughter." </p>
          <p> "Ah," says Brynhild, "she is the beginning of all this hale that biteth so; an evil
            drink she bare to Sigurd, so that he had no more memory of my very name." </p>
          <p> "All wrong thou talkest; a lie without measure is this," quoth Gudrun. </p>
          <p> Brynhild answered, "Have thou joy of Sigurd according to the measure of the wiles
            wherewith ye have beguiled me! Unworthily have ye conspired against me; may all things
            go with you as my heart hopes!" </p>
          <p> Gudrun says, "More joy shall I have of him than thy wish would give unto me: but to no
            man's mind it came, that he had aforetime his pleasure of me; nay not once." </p>
          <p> "Evil speech thou speakest," says Brynhild; "when thy wrath runs off thou wilt rue it;
            but come now, let us no more cast angry words one at the other!" </p>
          <p> Says Gudrun, "Thou wert the first to cast such words at me, and now thou makest as if
            thou wouldst amend it, but a cruel and hard heart abides behind." </p>
          <p> "Let us lay aside vain babble," says Brynhild. "Long did I hold my peace concerning my
            sorrow of heart, and, lo now, thy brother alone do I love; let us fall to other talk." </p>
          <p> Gudrun said, "Far beyond all this doth thine heart look." </p>
          <p> And so ugly ill befell from that going to the river, and that knowing of the ring,
            wherefrom did all their talk arise. </p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="29">
          <p> After this talk Brynhild lay a-bed, and tidings were brought to King Gunnar that
            Brynhild was sick; he goes to see her thereon, and asks what ails her; but she answered
            him naught, but lay there as one dead: and when he was hard on her for an answer, she
            said -- </p>
          <p> "What didst thou with that ring that I gave thee, even the one which King Budli gave
            me at our last parting, when thou and King Giuki came to him and threatened fire and the
            sword, unless ye had me to wife? Yea, at that time he led me apart, and asked me which I
            had chosen of those who were come; but I prayed him that I might abide to ward the land
            and be chief over the third part of his men; then were there two choices for me to deal
            betwixt either that I should be wedded to him whom he would, or lose all my weal and
            friendship at his hands; and he said withal that his friendship would be better to me
            than his wrath: then I bethought me whether I should yield to his will, or slay many a
            man; and therewithal I deemed that it would avail little to strive with him, and so it
            fell out, that I promised to wed whomsoever should ride the horse Grani with Fafnir's
            Hoard, and ride through my flaming fire, and slay those men whom I called on him to
            slay, and now so it was, that none durst ride, save Sigurd only, because he lacked no
            heart thereto; yea, and the Worm he flew, and Regin, and five kings beside; but thou,
            Gunnar, durst do naught; as pale as a dead man didst thou wax, and no king thou art, and
            no champion; so whereas I made a vow unto my father, that him alone would I love who was
            the noblest man alive, and that this is none save Sigurd, lo, now have I broken my oath
            and brought it to naught, since he is none of mine, and for this cause shall I compass
            thy death; and a great reward of evil things have I wherewith to reward Grimhild; --
            never, I wot, has woman lived eviler or of lesser heart than she." </p>
          <p> Gunnar answered in such wise that few might hear him, "Many a vile word hast thou
            spoken, and an evil-hearted woman art thou, whereas thou revilest a woman far better
            than thou; never would she curse her life as thou dost; nay, nor has she tormented dead
            folk, or murdered any; but lives her life well praised of all." </p>
          <p> Brynhild answered, "Never have I dwelt with evil things privily, or done loathsome
            deeds; -- yet most fain I am to slay thee." </p>
          <p> And therewith would she slay King Gunnar, but Hogni laid her in fetters; but then
            Gunnar spake withal -- </p>
          <p> "Nay, I will not that she abide in fetters." </p>
          <p> Then said she, "Heed it not! For never again seest thou me glad in thine hall, never
            drinking, never at the chess-play, never speaking the words of kindness, never
            over-laying the fair cloths with gold, never giving thee good counsel; -- ah, my sorrow
            of heart that I might not get Sigurd to me!" </p>
          <p> Then she sat up and smote her needlework, and rent it asunder, and bade set open her
            bower doors, that far away might the wailings of her sorrow be heard; then great
            mourning and lamentation there was, so that folk heard far and wide through that abode. </p>
          <p> Now Gudrun asked her bower-maidens why they sat so joyless and downcast. "What has
            come to you, that ye fare ye as witless women, or what unheard-of wonders have befallen
            you?" </p>
          <p> Then answered a waiting lady, hight Swaflod, "An untimely, an evil day it is, and our
            hall is fulfilled of lamentation." </p>
          <p> Then spake Gudrun to one of her handmaids, "Arise, for we have slept long; go, wake
            Brynhild, and let us fall to our needlework and be merry." </p>
          <p> "Nay, nay," she says, "nowise may I wake her, or talk with her; for many days has she
            drunk neither mead nor wine; surely the wrath of the Gods has fallen upon her." </p>
          <p> Then spake Gudrun to Gunnar, "Go and see her," she says, "and bid her know that I am
            grieved with her grief." </p>
          <p> "Nay," says Gunnar, "I am forbid to go see her or to share her weal." </p>
          <p> Nevertheless he went unto her, and strives in many wise to have speech of her, but
            gets no answer whatsoever; therefore he gets him gone and finds Hogni, and bids him go
            see her: he said he was loth thereto, but went, and gat no more of her. </p>
          <p> Then they go and find Sigurd, and pray him to visit her; he answered naught thereto,
            and so matters abode for that night. </p>
          <p> But the next day, when he came home from hunting, Sigurd went to Gudrun, and spake -- </p>
          <p> "In such wise do matters show to me, as though great and evil things will betide from
            this trouble and upheaving; and that Brynhild will surely die." </p>
          <p> Gudrun answers, "O my lord, by great wonders is she encompassed, seven days and seven
            nights has she slept, and none has dared wake her." </p>
          <p> "Nay, she sleeps not," said Sigurd, "her heart is dealing rather with dreadful intent
            against me." </p>
          <p> Then said Gudrun, weeping, "Woe worth the while for thy death! Go and see her; and wot
            if her fury may not be abated; give her gold, and smother up her grief and anger
            therewith!" </p>
          <p> Then Sigurd went out, and found the door of Brynhild's chamber open; he deemed she
            slept, and drew the clothes from off her, and said -- </p>
          <p> "Awake, Brynhild! The sun shineth now over all the house, and thou hast slept enough;
            cast off grief from thee, and take up gladness!" </p>
          <p> She said, "And how then hast thou dared to come to me? In this treason none was worse
            to me than thou." </p>
          <p> Said Sigurd, "Why wilt thou not speak to folk? For what cause sorrowest thou?" </p>
          <p> Brynhild answers, "Ah, to thee will I tell of my wrath!" </p>
          <p> Sigurd said, "As one under a spell art thou, if thou deemest that there is aught cruel
            in my heart against thee; but thou hast him for husband whom thou didst choose." </p>
          <p> "Ah, nay," she said, "never did Gunnar ride through the fire to me, nor did he give me
            to dower the host of the slain: I wondered at the man who came into my hall; for I
            deemed indeed that I knew thine eyes; but I might not see clearly, or divide the good
            from the evil, because of the veil that lay heavy on my fortune." </p>
          <p> Says Sigurd, "No nobler men are there than the sons of Giuki, they slew the king of
            the Danes, and that great chief, the brother of King Budli." </p>
          <p> Brynhild answered, "Surely for many an ill-deed must I reward them; mind me not of my
            griefs against them! But thou, Sigurd, slewest the Worm, and rodest the fire through;
            yea, and for my sake, and not one of the sons of King Giuki." </p>
          <p> Sigurd answers, "I am not thy husband, and thou art not my wife; yet did a farfamed
            king pay dower to thee." </p>
          <p> Says Brynhild, "Never looked I at Gunnar in such a wise that my heart smiled on him;
            and hard and fell am I to him, though I hide it from others." </p>
          <p> "A marvellous thing," says Sigurd, "not to love such a king; what angers thee most?
            For surely his love should be better to thee than gold." </p>
          <p> "This is the sorest sorrow to me," she said, "that the bitter sword is not reddened in
            thy blood." </p>
          <p> "Have no fear thereof!" says he, "no long while to wait or the bitter sword stand deep
            in my heart; and no worse needest thou to pray for thyself, for thou wilt not live when
            I am dead; the days of our two lives shall be few enough from henceforth." </p>
          <p> Brynhild answers, "Enough and to spare of bale is in thy speech, since thou bewrayedst
            me, and didst twin (1) me and all bliss; -- naught do I heed my life or death." </p>
          <p> Sigurd answers, "Ah, live, and love King Gunnar and me withal! And all my wealth will
            I give thee if thou die not." </p>
          <p> Brynhild answers, "Thou knowest me not, nor the heart that is in me; for thou art the
            first and best of all men, and I am become the most loathsome of all woman to thee." </p>
          <p> "This is truer," says Sigurd, "that I loved thee better than myself, though I fell
            into the wiles from whence our lives may not escape; for whenso my own heart and mind
            availed me, then I sorrowed sore that thou wert not my wife; but as I might I put my
            trouble from me, for in a king's dwelling was I; and withal and in spite of all I was
            well content that we were all together. Well may it be, that that shall come to pass
            which is foretold; neither shall I fear the fulfilment thereof." </p>
          <p> Brynhild answered, and said, "Too late thou tellest me that my grief grieved thee:
            little pity shall I find now." </p>
          <p> Sigurd said, "This my heart would, that thou and I should go into one bed together;
            even so wouldst thou be my wife." </p>
          <p> Said Brynhild, "Such words may nowise be spoken, nor will I have two kings in one
            hall; I will lay my life down rather than beguile Gunnar the King." </p>
          <p> And therewith she call to mind how they met, they two, on the mountain, and swore oath
            each to each. </p>
          <p> "But now is all changed and I will not live." </p>
          <p> "I might not call to mind thy name," said Sigurd, "or know time again, before the time
            of thy wedding; the greatest of all griefs is that." </p>
          <p> Then said Brynhild, "I swore an oath to wed the man who should ride my flaming fire,
            and that oath will I hold to, or die." </p>
          <p> "Rather than thou die, I will wed thee, and put away Gudrun." said Sigurd. </p>
          <p> But therewithal so swelled the heart betwixt the sides of him, that the rings of his
            byrny burst asunder. </p>
          <p> "I will not have thee," says Brynhild, "nay, nor any other!" </p>
          <p> Then Sigurd got him gone. </p>
          <p> So saith the song of Sigurd -- <quote>
              <l>"Out then went Sigurd,</l>
              <l>The great kings' well-loved,</l>
              <l>From the speech and the sorrow,</l>
              <l>Sore drooping, so grieving,</l>
              <l>That the shirt round about him</l>
              <l>Of iron tings woven,</l>
              <l>From the sides brake asunder</l>
              <l>Of the brave in the battle."</l>
            </quote> So when Sigurd came into the hall, Gunnar asked if he had come to a knowledge
            of what great grief lay heavy on her, or if she had power of speech: and Sigurd said
            that she lacked it not. So now Gunnar goes to her again, and asked her, what wrought her
            woe, or if there were anything that might amend it. </p>
          <p> "I will not live," says Brynhild, "for Sigurd has bewrayed me, yea, and thee no less,
            whereas thou didst suffer him to come into my bed: lo thou, two men in one dwelling I
            will not have; and this shall be Sigurd's death, or thy death, or my death; -- for now
            has he told Gudrun all, and she is mocking me even now!" </p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="30">
          <p> Thereafter Brynhild went out, and sat under her bower-wall, and had many words of
            wailing to say, and still she cried that all things were loathsome to her, both land and
            lordship alike, so she might not have Sigurd. </p>
          <p> But therewith came Gunnar to her yet again, and Brynhild spake, "Thou shalt lose both
            realm and wealth, and thy life and me, for I shall fare home to my kin, and abide there
            in sorrow, unless thou slayest Sigurd and his son; never nourish thou a wolfcub." </p>
          <p> Gunnar grew sick at heart thereat, and might nowise see what fearful thing lay beneath
            it all; he was bound to Sigurd by oath, and this way and that way swung the heart within
            him; but at the last he bethought him of the measureless shame if his wife went from
            him, and he said within himself, "Brynhild is better to me than all things else, and the
            fairest woman of all women, and I will lay down my life rather than lose the love of
            her." And herewith he called to him his brother and spake, -- </p>
          <p> "Trouble is heavy on me," and he tells him that he must needs slay Sigurd, for that he
            has failed him where in he trusted him; "so let us be lords of the gold and the realm
            withal." </p>
          <p> Hogni answers, "Ill it behoves us to break our oaths with wrack and wrong, and withal
            great aid we have in him; no kings shall be as great as we, if so be the King of the
            Hun-folk may live; such another brother-in-law never may we get again; bethink thee how
            good it is to have such a brother-in-law, and such sons to our sister! But well I see
            how things stand, for this has Brynhild stirred thee up to, and surely shall her counsel
            drag us into huge shame and scathe." </p>
          <p> Gunnar says, "Yet shall it be brought about: and, lo, a rede thereto; -- let us egg on
            our brother Guttorm to the deed; he is young, and of little knowledge, and is clean out
            of all the oaths moreover." </p>
          <p> "Ah, set about in ill wise," says Hogni, "and though indeed it may well be compassed,
            a due reward shall we gain for the bewrayal of such a man as is Sigurd." </p>
          <p> Gunnar says, "Sigurd shall die, or I shall die." </p>
          <p> And therewith he bids Brynhild arise and be glad at heart: so she arose, and still
            ever she said that Gunnar should come no more into her bed till the deed was done. </p>
          <p> So the brothers fall to talk, and Gunnar says that it is a deed well worthy of death,
            that taking of Brynhild's maidenhead; "So come now, let us prick on Guttorm to do the
            deed." </p>
          <p> Therewith they call him to them, and offer him gold and great dominion, as they well
            have might to do. Yea, and they took a certain worm and somewhat of wolf's flesh and let
            seethe them together, and gave him to eat of the same, even as the singer sings -- <quote>
              <l>"Fish of the wild-wood,</l>
              <l>Worm smooth crawling,</l>
              <l>With wolf-meat mingled,</l>
              <l>They minced for Guttorm;</l>
              <l>Then in the beaker,</l>
              <l>In the wine his mouth knew,</l>
              <l>They set it, still doing</l>
              <l>More deeds of wizards.</l>
            </quote> Wherefore with the eating of this meat he grew so wild and eager, and with all
            things about him, and with the heavy words of Grimhild, that he gave his word to do the
            deed; and mighty honour they promised him in reward thereof. </p>
          <p> But of these evil wiles naught at all knew Sigurd, for he might not deal with his
            shapen fate, nor the measure of his life-days, neither deemed he that he was worthy such
            things at their hands. </p>
          <p> So Guttorm went in to Sigurd the next morning as he lay upon his bed, yet durst he not
            do aught against him, but shrank back out again; yea, and even so he fared a second
            time, for so bright and eager were the eyes of Sigurd that few durst look upon him. But
            the third time he went in, and there lay Sigurd asleep; then Guttorm drew his sword and
            thrust Sigurd through in such wise that the sword point smote into the bed beneath him;
            then Sigurd awoke with that wound, and Guttorm gat him unto the door; but therewith
            Sigurd caught up the sword Gram, and cast it after him, and it smote him on the back,
            and struck him asunder in the midst, so that the feet of him fell one way, and the head
            and hands back into the chamber. </p>
          <p> Now Gudrun lay asleep on Sigurd's bosom, but she woke up unto woe that may not be told
            of, all swimming in the blood of him, and in such wise did she bewail her with weeping
            and words of sorrow, that Sigurd rose up on the bolster, and spake. </p>
          <p> "Weep not," said he, "for thy brothers live for thy delight; but a young son have I,
            too young to be ware of his foes; and an ill turn have these played against their own
            fortune; for never will they get a mightier brother-in-law to ride abroad with them;
            nay, nor a better son to their sister, than this one, if he may grow to man's estate.
            Lo, now is that come to pass which was foretold me long ago, but from mine eyes has it
            been hidden, for none may fight against his fate and prevail. Behold this has Brynhild
            brought to pass, even she who loves me before all men; but this may I swear, that never
            have I wrought ill to Gunnar, but rather have ever held fast to my oath with him, nor
            was I ever too much a friend to his wife. And now if I had been forewarned, and had been
            afoot with my weapons, then should many a man have lost his life or ever I had fallen,
            and all those brethren should have been slain, and a harder work would the slaying of me
            have been than the slaying of the mightiest bull or the mightiest boar of the
            wild-wood." </p>
          <p> And even therewithal life left the King; but Gudrun moaned and drew a weary breath,
            and Brynhild heard it and laughed when she heard her moaning. </p>
          <p> Then said Gunnar, "Thou laughest not because thy heart-roots are gladdened, or else
            why doth thy visage wax so wan? Sure an evil creature thou art; most like thou art nigh
            to thy death! Lo now, how meet would it be for thee to behold thy brother Atli slain
            before thine eyes, and that thou shouldst stand over him dead; whereas we must needs now
            stand over our brother-in-law in such a case our brother-in-law and our brother's bane." </p>
          <p> She answered, "None need mock at the measure of slaughter being unfulfilled; yet
            heedeth not Atli your wrath or your threats; yea, he shall live longer than ye, and be a
            mightier man." </p>
          <p> Hogni spake and said, "Now hath come to pass the soothsaying of Brynhild; an ill work
            not to be atoned for." </p>
          <p> And Gudrun said, "My kinsmen have slain my husband; but ye, when ye next ride to the
            war and are come into the battle, then shall ye look about and see that Sigurd is
            neither on the fight hand nor the left, and ye shall know that he was your good-hap and
            your strength; and if he had lived and had sons, then should ye have been strengthened
            by his offspring and his kin." </p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="31">
          <p>
            <quote>
              <lg>
                <l>Gudrun of old days</l>
                <l>Drew near to dying</l>
                <l>As she sat in sorrow</l>
                <l>Over Sigurd;</l>
                <l>Yet she sighed not</l>
                <l>Nor smote hand on hand,</l>
                <l>Nor wailed she aught</l>
                <l>As other women.</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then went earls to her.</l>
                <l>Full of all wisdom,</l>
                <l>Fain help to deal</l>
                <l>To her dreadful heart:</l>
                <l>Hushed was Gudrun</l>
                <l>Of wail, or greeting,</l>
                <l>But with a heavy woe</l>
                <l>Was her heart a-breaking.</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Bright and fair</l>
                <l>Sat the great earls' brides,</l>
                <l>Gold arrayed</l>
                <l>Before Gudrun;</l>
                <l>Each told the tale</l>
                <l>Of her great trouble,</l>
                <l>The bitterest bale</l>
                <l>She erst abode.</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then spake Giaflaug,</l>
                <l>Giuki's sister:</l>
                <l>"Lo upon earth</l>
                <l>I live most loveless</l>
                <l>Who of five mates</l>
                <l>Must see the ending,</l>
                <l>Of daughters twain</l>
                <l>And three sisters,</l>
                <l>Of brethren eight,</l>
                <l>And abide behind lonely."</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Naught gat Gudrun</l>
                <l>Of wail and greeting,</l>
                <l>So heavy was she</l>
                <l>For her dead husband,</l>
                <l>So dreadful-hearted</l>
                <l>For the King laid dead there.</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then spake Herborg</l>
                <l>Queen of Hunland --</l>
                <l>"Crueller tale</l>
                <l>Have I to tell of,</l>
                <l>Of my seven sons</l>
                <l>Down in the Southlands,</l>
                <l>And the eighth man, my mate,</l>
                <l>Felled in the death-mead.</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>"Father and mother,</l>
                <l>And four brothers,</l>
                <l>On the wide sea</l>
                <l>The winds and death played with;</l>
                <l>The billows beat</l>
                <l>On the bulwark boards.</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>"Alone must I sing o'er them,</l>
                <l>Alone must I array them,</l>
                <l>Alone must my hands deal with</l>
                <l>Their departing;</l>
                <l>And all this was</l>
                <l>In one season's wearing,</l>
                <l>And none was left</l>
                <l>For love or solace.</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>"Then was I bound</l>
                <l>A prey of the battle,</l>
                <l>When that same season</l>
                <l>Wore to its ending;</l>
                <l>As a tiring may</l>
                <l>Must I bind the shoon</l>
                <l>Of the duke's high dame,</l>
                <l>Every day at dawning.</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>"From her jealous hate</l>
                <l>Gat I heavy mocking,</l>
                <l>Cruel lashes</l>
                <l>She laid upon me,</l>
                <l>Never met I</l>
                <l>Better master</l>
                <l>Or mistress worser</l>
                <l>In all the wide world."</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Naught gat Gudrun</l>
                <l>Of wail or greeting,</l>
                <l>So heavy was she</l>
                <l>For her dead husband,</l>
                <l>So dreadful-hearted</l>
                <l>For the King laid dead there.</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then spake Gullrond,</l>
                <l>Giuki's daughter --</l>
                <l>"O foster-mother,</l>
                <l>Wise as thou mayst be,</l>
                <l>Naught canst thou better</l>
                <l>The young wife's bale."</l>
                <l>And she bade uncover</l>
                <l>The dead King's corpse.</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>She swept the sheet</l>
                <l>Away from Sigurd,</l>
                <l>And turned his cheek</l>
                <l>Towards his wife's knees --</l>
                <l>"Look on thy loved one</l>
                <l>Lay lips to his lips,</l>
                <l>E'en as thou wert clinging</l>
                <l>To thy king alive yet!"</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Once looked Gudrun --</l>
                <l>One look only,</l>
                <l>And saw her lord's locks</l>
                <l>Lying all bloody,</l>
                <l>The great man's eyes</l>
                <l>Glazed and deadly,</l>
                <l>And his heart's bulwark</l>
                <l>Broken by sword-edge.</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Back then sank Gudrun,</l>
                <l>Back on the bolster,</l>
                <l>Loosed was her head array,</l>
                <l>Red did her cheeks grow,</l>
                <l>And the rain-drops ran</l>
                <l>Down over her knees.</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then wept Gudrun,</l>
                <l>Giuki's daughter,</l>
                <l>So that the tears flowed</l>
                <l>Through the pillow;</l>
                <l>As the geese withal</l>
                <l>That were in the homefield,</l>
                <l>The fair fowls the may owned,</l>
                <l>Fell a-screaming.</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then spake Gullrond,</l>
                <l>Giuki's daughter --</l>
                <l>"Surely knew I</l>
                <l>No love like your love</l>
                <l>Among all men,</l>
                <l>On the mould abiding;</l>
                <l>Naught wouldst thou joy in</l>
                <l>Without or within doors,</l>
                <l>O my sister,</l>
                <l>Save beside Sigurd."</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then spake Gudrun,</l>
                <l>Giuki's daughter --</l>
                <l>"Such was my Sigurd</l>
                <l>Among the sons of Giuki,</l>
                <l>As is the king leek</l>
                <l>O'er the low grass waxing,</l>
                <l>Or a bright stone</l>
                <l>Strung on band,</l>
                <l>Or a pearl of price</l>
                <l>On a prince's brow.</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>"Once was I counted</l>
                <l>By the king's warriors</l>
                <l>Higher than any</l>
                <l>Of Herjan's mays;</l>
                <l>Now am I as little</l>
                <l>As the leaf may be,</l>
                <l>Amid wind-swept wood</l>
                <l>Now when dead he lieth.</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>I miss from my seat,</l>
                <l>I miss from my bed,</l>
                <l>My darling of sweet speech.</l>
                <l>Wrought the sons of Giuki,</l>
                <l>Wrought the sons of Giuki,</l>
                <l>This sore sorrow,</l>
                <l>Yea, for their sister,</l>
                <l>Most sore sorrow.</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>"So may your lands</l>
                <l>Lie waste on all sides,</l>
                <l>As ye have broken</l>
                <l>Your bounden oaths!</l>
                <l>Ne'er shalt thou, Gunnar,</l>
                <l>The gold have joy of;</l>
                <l>The dear-bought rings</l>
                <l>Shall drag thee to death,</l>
                <l>Whereon thou swarest</l>
                <l>Oath unto Sigurd.</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Ah, in the days by-gone</l>
                <l>Great mirth in the homefield</l>
                <l>When my Sigurd</l>
                <l>Set saddle on Grani,</l>
                <l>And they went their ways</l>
                <l>For the wooing of Brynhild!</l>
                <l>An ill day, an ill woman,</l>
                <l>And most ill hap!"</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then spake Brynhild,</l>
                <l>Budli's daughter --</l>
                <l>"May the woman lack</l>
                <l>Both love and children,</l>
                <l>Who gained greeting</l>
                <l>For thee, O Gudrun!</l>
                <l>Who gave thee this morning</l>
                <l>Many words!"</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then spake Gullrond,</l>
                <l>Giuki's daughter --</l>
                <l>"Hold peace of such words</l>
                <l>Thou hated of all folk!</l>
                <l>The bane of brave men</l>
                <l>Hast thou been ever,</l>
                <l>All waves of ill</l>
                <l>Wash over thy mind,</l>
                <l>To seven great kings</l>
                <l>Hast thou been a sore sorrow,</l>
                <l>And the death of good will</l>
                <l>To wives and women."</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>Then spake Brynhild,</l>
                <l>Budli's daughter --</l>
                <l>"None but Atli</l>
                <l>Brought bale upon us,</l>
                <l>My very brother</l>
                <l>Born of Budli.</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>When we saw in the hall</l>
                <l>Of the Hunnish people</l>
                <l>The gold a-gleaming</l>
                <l>On the kingly Giukings;</l>
                <l>I have paid for that faring</l>
                <l>Oft and Full,</l>
                <l>And for the sight</l>
                <l>That then I saw."</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>By a pillar she stood</l>
                <l>And strained its wood to her;</l>
                <l>From the eyes of Brynhild,</l>
                <l>Budli's daughter,</l>
                <l>Flashed out fire,</l>
                <l>And she snorted forth venom,</l>
                <l>As the sore wounds she gazed on</l>
                <l>Of the dead-slain Sigurd.</l>
              </lg>
            </quote>
          </p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="32">
          <p> And now none might know for what cause Brynhild must bewail with weeping for what she
            had prayed for with laughter: but she spake -- </p>
          <p> "Such a dream I had, Gunnar, as that my bed was acold, and that thou didst ride into
            the hands of thy foes: lo now, ill shall it go with thee and all thy kin, O ye breakers
            of oaths; for on the day thou slayedst him, dimly didst thou remember how thou didst
            blend thy blood with the blood of Sigurd, and with an ill reward hast thou rewarded him
            for all that he did well to thee; whereas he gave unto thee to be the mightiest of men;
            and well was it proven how fast he held to his oath sworn, when he came to me and laid
            betwixt us the sharp-edged sword that in venom had been made hard. All too soon did ye
            fall to working wrong against him and against me, whenas I abode at home with my father,
            and had all that I would, and had no will that any one of you should be any of mine, as
            ye rode into our garth, ye three kings together; but then Atli led me apart privily, and
            asked me if I would not have him who rode Grani; yea, a man nowise like unto you; but in
            those days I plighted myself to the son of King Sigmund and no other; and lo, now, no
            better shall ye fare for the death of me." </p>
          <p> Then rose up Gunnar, and laid his arms about her neck, and besought her to live and
            have wealth from him; and all others in likewise letted her from dying; but she thrust
            them all from her, and said that it was not the part of any to let her in that which was
            her will. </p>
          <p> Then Gunnar called to Hogni, and prayed him for counsel, and bade him go to her, and
            see if he might perchance soften her dreadful heart, saying withal, that now they had
            need enough on their hands in the slaking of her grief, till time might get over. </p>
          <p> But Hogni answered, "Nay, let no man hinder her from dying; for no gain will she be to
            us, nor has she been gainsome since she came hither! </p>
          <p> Now she bade bring forth much gold, and bade all those come thither who would have
            wealth: then she caught up a sword, and thrust it under her armpit, and sank aside upon
            the pillows, and said, "Come, take gold whoso will!" </p>
          <p> But all held their peace, and she said, "Take the gold, and be glad thereof!" </p>
          <p> And therewith she spake unto Gunnar, "Now for a little while will I tell of that which
            shall come to pass hereafter; for speedily shall ye be at one again with Gudrun by the
            rede of Grimhild the Wise-wife; and the daughter of Gudrun and Sigurd shall be called
            Swanhild, the fairest of all women born. Gudrun shall be given to Atli, yet not with her
            good will. Thou shalt be fain to get Oddrun, but that shall Atli forbid thee; but
            privily shall ye meet, and much shall she love thee. Atli shall bewray thee, and cast
            thee into a worm-close, and thereafter shall Atli and his Sons be slain, and Gudrun
            shall be their slayer; and afterwards shall the great waves bear her to the burg of King
            Jonakr, to whom she shall bear sons of great fame: Swanhild shall be sent from the land
            and given to King Jormunrek; and her shall bite the rede of Bikki, and therewithal is
            the kin of you clean gone; and more sorrow therewith for Gudrun. </p>
          <p> "And now I pray thee, Gunnar, one last boon. -- Let make a great bale on the plain
            meads for all of us; for me and for Sigurd, and for those who were slain with him, and
            let that be covered over with cloth dyed red by the folk of the Gauls, (1) and burn me
            thereon on one side of the King of the Huns, and on the other those men of mine, two at
            the head and two at the feet, and two hawks withal; and even so is all shared equally;
            and lay there betwixt us a drawn sword, as in the other days when we twain stepped into
            one bed together; and then may we have the name of man and wife, nor shall the door
            swing to at the heel of him as I go behind him. Nor shall that be a niggard company if
            there follow him those five bond-women and eight bondmen, whom my father gave me, and
            those burn there withal who were slain with Sigurd. </p>
          <p> "Now more yet would I say, but for my wounds, but my life-breath flits; the wounds
            open, -- yet have I said sooth." </p>
          <p> Now is the dead corpse of Sigurd arrayed in olden wise, and a mighty bale is raised,
            and when it was somewhat kindled, there was laid thereon the dead corpse of Sigurd
            Fafnir's-bane, and his son of three winters whom Brynhild had let slay, and Guttorm
            withal; and when the bale was all ablaze, thereunto was Brynhild borne out, when she had
            spoken with her bower-maidens, and bid them take the gold that she would give; and then
            died Brynhild, and was burned there by the side of Sigurd, and thus their life- days
            ended. </p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="33">
          <p> Now so it is, that whoso heareth these tidings sayeth, that no such an one as was
            Sigurd was left behind him in the world, nor ever was such a man brought forth because
            of all the worth of him, nor may his name ever minish by eld in the Dutch Tongue nor in
            all the Northern Lands, while the world standeth fast. </p>
          <p> The story tells that, on a day, as Gudrun sat in her bower, she fell to saying,
            "Better was life in those days when I had Sigurd; he who was far above other men as gold
            is above iron, or the leek over other grass of the field, or the hart over other wild
            things; until my brethren begrudged me such a man, the first and best of all men; and so
            they might not sleep or they had slain him. Huge clamour made Grani when he saw his
            master and lord sore wounded, and then I spoke to him even as with a man, but he fell
            drooping down to the earth, for he knew that Sigurd was slain." </p>
          <p> Thereafter Gudrun gat her gone into the wild woods, and heard on all ways round about
            her the howling of wolves, and deemed death a merrier thing than life. Then she went
            till she came to the hall of King Alf, and sat there in Denmark with Thora, the daughter
            of Hakon, for seven seasons, and abode with good welcome. And she set forth her
            needlework before her and did thereinto many deeds and great, and fair plays after the
            fashion of those days, swords and byrnies, and all the gear of kings, and the ship of
            King Sigmund sailing along the land; yea, and they wrought there how they fought, Sigar
            and Siggeir, south in Fion. Such was their disport; and now Gudrun was somewhat solaced
            of her grief. </p>
          <p> So Grimhild comes to hear where Gudrun has take up her abode, and she calls her sons
            to talk with her, and asks whether they will make atonement to Gudrun for her son and
            her husband, and said that it was but meet and right to do so. </p>
          <p> Then Gunnar spake, and said that he would atone for her sorrows with gold. </p>
          <p> So they send for their friends, and array their horses, their helms, and their
            shields, and their byrnies, and all their war- gear; and their journey was furnished
            forth in the noblest wise, and no champion who was of the great men might abide at home;
            and their horses were clad in mail-coats, and every knight of them had his helm done
            over with gold or with silver. </p>
          <p> Grimhild was of their company, for she said that their errand would never be brought
            fairly to pass if she sat at home. </p>
          <p> There were well five hundred men, and noble men rode with them. There was Waldemar of
            Denmark, and Eymod and Jarisleif withal. So they went into the hall of King Alf, and
            there abode them the Longbeards and Franks, and Saxons: they fared with all their war-
            gear, and had over them red fur-coats. Even as the song says -- <quote>
              <l>"Byrnies short cut,</l>
              <l>Strong helms hammered,</l>
              <l>Girt with good swords,</l>
              <l>Red hair gleaming."</l>
            </quote> They were fain to choose good gifts for their sister, and spake softly to her,
            but in none of them would she trow. Then Gunnar brought unto her a drink mingled with
            hurtful things, and this she must needs drink, and with the king thereof she had no more
            memory of their guilt against her. </p>
          <p> But in that drink was blended the might of the earth and the sea with the blood of her
            son; and in that horn were all letters cut and reddened with blood, as is said hereunder
            -- <quote>
              <lg>
                <l>"On the horn's face were there</l>
                <l>All the kin of letters</l>
                <l>Cut aright and reddened,</l>
                <l>How should I rede them rightly?</l>
                <l>The ling-fish long</l>
                <l>Of the land of Hadding,</l>
                <l>Wheat-ears unshorn,</l>
                <l>And wild things' inwards.</l>
              </lg>
              <lg>
                <l>In that beer were mingled</l>
                <l>Many ills together,</l>
                <l>Blood of all the wood</l>
                <l>And brown-burnt acorns,</l>
                <l>The black dew of the hearth,</l>
                <l>The God-doomed dead beast's inwards,</l>
                <l>And the swine's liver sodden</l>
                <l>Because all wrongs that deadens.</l>
              </lg>
            </quote> And so now, when their hearts are-brought anigh to each other, great cheer they
            made: then came Grimhild to Gudrun, and spake. </p>
          <p> "All hail to thee, daughter! I give thee gold and all kinds of good things to take to
            thee after thy father, dear bought rings and bed-gear of the maids of the Huns, the most
            courteous and well dight of all women; and thus is thy husband atoned for: and
            thereafter shalt thou be given to Atli, the mighty king, and be mistress of all his
            might. Cast not all thy friends aside for one man's sake, but do according to our
            bidding." </p>
          <p> Gudrun answers, "Never will I wed Atli the King; unseemly it is for us to get
            offspring betwixt us." </p>
          <p> Grimhild says, "Nourish not thy wrath; it shall be to thee as if Sigurd and Sigmund
            were alive when thou hast borne sons." </p>
          <p> Gudrun says, "I cannot take my heart from thoughts of him, for he was the first of all
            men." </p>
          <p> Grimhild says, "So it is shapen that thou must have this king and none else." </p>
          <p> Says Gudrun, "Give not this man to me, for an evil thing shall come upon thy kin from
            him, and to his own sons shall he deal evil, and be rewarded with a grim revenge
            thereafter." </p>
          <p> Then waxed Grimhild fell at those words, and spake, "Do even as we bid thee, and take
            therefore great honour, and our friendship, and the steads withal called Vinbjorg and
            Valbjorg." </p>
          <p> And such might was in the words of her, that even so must it come to pass. </p>
          <p> Then Gudrun spake, "Thus then must it needs befall, howsoever against the will of me,
            and for little joy shall it be and for great grief." </p>
          <p> Then men leaped on their horses, and their women were set in wains. So they fared four
            days a-riding and other four a-shipboard, and yet four more again by land and road, till
            at the last they came to a certain high-built hall; then came to meet Gudrun many folk
            thronging; and an exceedingly goodly feast was there made, even as the word had gone
            between either kin, and it passed forth in most proud and stately wise. And at that
            feast drinks Atli his bridal with Gudrun, but never did her heart laugh on him, and
            little sweet and kind was their life together. </p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="34">
          <p> Now tells the tale that on a night King Atli woke from sleep and spake to Gudrun -- </p>
          <p> "Medreamed," said he, "that thou didst thrust me through with a sword." </p>
          <p> Then Gudrun areded the dream, and said that it betokened fire, whenas folk dreamed of
            iron. "It befalls of thy pride belike, in that thou deemest thyself the first of men," </p>
          <p> Atli said, "Moreover I dreamed that here waxed two sorb-tree (1) saplings, and fain I
            was that they should have no scathe of me; then these were riven up by the roots and
            reddened with blood, and borne to the bench, and I was bidden eat thereof. </p>
          <p> "Yea, yet again I dreamed that two hawks flew from my hand hungry and unfed, and fared
            to hell, and meseemed their hearts were mingled with honey, and that I ate thereof. </p>
          <p> "And then again I dreamed that two fair whelps lay before me yelling aloud, and that
            the flesh of them I ate, though my will went not with the eating." </p>
          <p> Gudrun says, "Nowise good are these dreams, yet shall they come to pass; surely thy
            sons are nigh to death, and many heavy things shall fall upon us." </p>
          <p> "Yet again I dreamed," said he, "and methought I lay in a bath, and folk took counsel
            to slay me." </p>
          <p> Now these things wear away with time, but in nowise was their life together fond. </p>
          <p> Now falls Atli to thinking of where may be gotten that plenteous gold which Sigurd had
            owned, but King Gunnar and his brethren were lords thereof now. </p>
          <p> Atli was a great king and mighty, wise, and a lord of many men; and now he falls to
            counsel with his folk as to the ways of them. He wotted well that Gunnar and his
            brethren had more wealth than any others might have, and so he falls to the rede of
            sending men to them, and bidding them to a great feast, and honouring them in diverse
            wise, and the chief of those messengers was hight Vingi. </p>
          <p> Now the queen wots of their conspiring, and misdoubts her that this would mean some
            beguiling of her brethren: so she cut runes, and took a gold ring, and knit therein a
            wolf's hair, and gave it into the hands of the king's messengers. </p>
          <p> Thereafter they go their ways according to the king's bidding: and or ever they came
            aland Vingi beheld the runes, and turned them about in such wise as if Gudrun prayed her
            brethren in her runes to go meet King Atli. </p>
          <p> Thereafter they came to the hall of King Gunnar, and had good welcome at his hands,
            and great fires were made for them, and in great joyance they drank of the best of
            drink. </p>
          <p> Then spake Vingi, "King Atli sends me hither, and is fain that ye go to his house and
            home in all glory, and take of him exceeding honours, helms and shields, swords and
            byrnies, gold and goodly raiment, horses, hosts of war, and great and wide lands, for,
            saith he, he is fainest of all things to bestow his realm and lordship upon you." </p>
          <p> Then Gunnar turned his head aside, and spoke to Hogni -- </p>
          <p> "In what wise shall we take this bidding? Might and wealth he bids us take; but no
            kings know I who have so much gold as we have, whereas we have all the hoard which lay
            once on Gnitaheath; and great are our chambers, and full of gold, and weapons for
            smiting, and all kinds of raiment of war, and well I wot that amidst all men my horse is
            the best, and my sword the sharpest and my gold the most glorious." </p>
          <p> Hogni answers, "A marvel is it to me of his bidding, for seldom hath he done in such a
            wise, and ill counselled will it be to wend to him; lo now, when I saw those dear-bought
            things the king sends us I wondered to behold a wolfs hair knit to a certain gold ring;
            belike Gudrun deems him to be minded as a wolf towards us, and will have naught of our
            faring." </p>
          <p> But withal Vingi shows him the runes which he said Gudrun had sent. </p>
          <p> Now the most of folk go to bed, but these drank on still with certain others; and
            Kostbera, the wife of Hogni, the fairest of women, came to them, and looked on the
            runes. </p>
          <p> But the wife of Gunnar was Glaumvor, a great hearted wife. </p>
          <p> So these twain poured out, and the kings drank and were exceeding drunken, and Vingi
            notes it, and says -- </p>
          <p> "Naught may I hide that King Atli is heavy of foot and over-old for the warding of his
            realm; but his sons are young and of no account: now will he give you rule over his
            realms while they are yet thus young, and most fain will he be that ye have the joy
            thereof before all others." </p>
          <p> Now so it befell both that Gunnar was drunk, and that dominion was held out to him,
            nor might he work against the fate shapen for him; so he gave his word to go, and tells
            Hogni his brother thereof. </p>
          <p> But he answered, "Thy word given must even stand now, nor will I fail to follow thee,
            but most loth am I to journey." </p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="35">
          <p> So when men had drunk their fill, they fared to sleep; then falls Kostbera to
            beholding the runes, and spelling over the letters, and sees that beneath were other
            things cut, and that the runes are guileful, yet because of her wisdom she had skill to
            read them aright. So then she goes to bed by her husband; but when they awoke, she spake
            unto Hogni -- </p>
          <p> "Thou art minded to wend away from home -- ill-counselled is that; abide till another
            time! Scarce a keen reader of runes art thou, if thou deemest thou hast beheld in them
            the bidding of thy sister to this journey: lo, I read them the runes, and had marvel of
            so wise a woman as Gudrun is, that she should have miscut them; but that which lieth
            underneath beareth your bane with it, -- yea, either she lacked a letter, or others have
            dealt guilefully with the runes. </p>
          <p> "And now hearken to my dream; for therein methought there fell in upon us here a river
            exceeding strong, and brake up the timbers of the hall." </p>
          <p> He answered, "Full oft are ye evil of mind, ye women, but for me, I was not made in
            such wise as to meet men with evil who deserve no evil; belike he will give us good
            welcome." </p>
          <p> She answered, "Well, the thing must ye yourselves prove, but no friendship follows
            this bidding: -- but yet again I dreamed that another river fell in here with a great
            and grimly rush, and tore up the dais of the hall, and brake the legs of both you
            brethren; surely that betokeneth somewhat." </p>
          <p> He answers, "Meadows along our way, whereas thou didst dream of the river; for when we
            go through the meadows, plentifully doth the seeds of the hay hang about our legs." </p>
          <p> "Again I dreamed," she says, "that thy cloak was afire, and that the flame blazed up
            above the hall." </p>
          <p> Says he, "Well, I wot what that shall betoken; here lieth my fair-dyed raiment, and it
            shall burn and blaze, whereas thou dreamedst of the cloak." </p>
          <p> "Methought a bear came in," she says, "and brake up the king's high-seat, and shook
            his paws in such a wise that we were all adrad thereat, and he gat us all together into
            the mouth of him, so that we might avail us naught, and thereof fell great horror on
            us." </p>
          <p> He answered, "Some great storm will befall, whereas thou hadst a white bear in thy
            mind." </p>
          <p> "An erne methought came in," she says, "and swept adown the hall, and drenched me and
            all of us with blood, and ill shall that betoken, for methought it was the double of
            King Atli." </p>
          <p> He answered, "Full oft do we slaughter beasts freely, and smite down great neat for
            our cheer, and the dream of the erne has but to do with oxen; yea, Atli is heart-whole
            toward us." </p>
          <p> And therewithal they cease this talk. </p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="36">
          <p> Now tells the tale of Gunnar, that in the same wise it fared with him; for when they
            awoke, Glaumvor his wife told him many dreams which seemed to her like to betoken guile
            coming; but Gunnar areded them all in other wise. </p>
          <p> "This was one of them," said she; "methought a bloody sword was borne into the hall
            here, wherewith thou wert thrust through, and at either end of that wolves howled." </p>
          <p> The king answered, "Our dogs shall bite me belike; blood-stained weapons oft betoken
            dogs' snappings." </p>
          <p> She said, "Yet again I dreamed -- that women came in, heavy and drooping, and chose
            thee for their mate; may-happen these would be thy fateful women." </p>
          <p> He answered, "Hard to arede is this, and none may set aside the fated measure of his
            days, nor is it unlike that my time is short." (1) </p>
          <p> So in the morning they arose, and were minded for the journey, but some letted them
            herein. </p>
          <p> Then cried Gunnar to the man who is called Fjornir -- </p>
          <p> "Arise, and give us to drink goodly wine from great tuns, because may happen this
            shall be very last of all our feasts; belike if we die the old wolf shall come by the
            gold, and that bear shall nowise spare the bite of his war-tusks." </p>
          <p> Then all the folk of his household brought them on their way weeping. </p>
          <p> The son of Hogni said -- </p>
          <p> "Fare ye well with merry tide." </p>
          <p> The more part of their folk were left behind; Solar and Gnoevar, the sons of Hogni,
            fared with them, and a great champion, named Orkning, who was the brother of Kostbera. </p>
          <p> So folk followed them down to the ships, and all fetted them of their journey, but
            attained to naught therein. </p>
          <p> Then spake Glaumvor, and said -- </p>
          <p> "O Vingi, most like that great ill hap will come of thy coming, and mighty and evil
            things shall betide in thy travelling." </p>
          <p> He answered, "Hearken to my answer; that I lie not aught: and may the high gallows and
            all things of grame have me, if I lie one word!" </p>
          <p> Then cried Kostbera, "Fare ye well with merry days." </p>
          <p> And Hogni answered, "Be glad of heart, howsoever it may fare with us!" </p>
          <p> And therewith they parted, each to their own fate. Then away they rowed, so hard and
            fast, that well-nigh the half of the keel slipped away from the ship, and so hard they
            laid on to the oars that thole and gunwale brake. </p>
          <p> But when they came aland they made their ship fast, and then they rode awhile on their
            noble steeds through the murk wild-wood. </p>
          <p> And now they behold the king's army, and huge uproar, and the clatter of weapons they
            hear from thence; and they see there a mighty host of men, and the manifold array of
            them, even as they wrought there: and all the gates of the burg were full of men. </p>
          <p> So they rode up to the burg, and the gates thereof were shut; then Hogni brake open
            the gates, and therewith they ride into the burg. </p>
          <p> Then spake Vingi, "Well might ye have left this deed undone; go to now, bide ye here
            while I go seek your gallows-tree! Softly and sweetly I base you hither, but an evil
            thing abode thereunder; short while to bide ere ye are tied up to that same tree!" </p>
          <p> Hogni answered, "None the more shall we waver for that cause; for little methinks have
            we shrunk aback whenas men fell to fight; and naught shall it avail thee to make us
            afeard, -- and for an ill fate hast thou wrought." </p>
          <p> And therewith they cast him down to earth, and smote him with their axe-hammers till
            he died. </p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="37">
          <p> Then they rode unto the king's hall, and King Atli arrayed his host for battle, and
            the ranks were so set forth that a certain wall there was betwixt them and the brethren. </p>
          <p> "Welcome hither," said he. "Deliver unto me that plenteous gold which is mine of
            right; even the wealth which Sigurd once owned, and which is now Gudrun's of right." </p>
          <p> Gunnar answered, "Never gettest thou that wealth; and men of might must thou meet
            here, or ever we lay by life if thou wilt deal with us in battle; ah, belike thou
            settest forth this feast like a great man, and wouldst not hold thine hand from erne and
            wolf!" </p>
          <p> "Long ago I had it in my mind," said Atli, to take the lives of you, and be lord of
            the gold, and reward you for that deed of shame, wherein ye beguiled the best of all
            your affinity; but now shall I revenge him." </p>
          <p> Hogni answered, "Little will it avail to lie long brooding over that rede, leaving the
            work undone." </p>
          <p> And therewith they fell to hard fighting, at the first brunt with shot. </p>
          <p> But therewithal came the tidings to Gudrun, and when she heard thereof she grew
            exceeding wroth, and cast her mantle from her, and ran out and greeted those new-comers,
            and kissed her brethren, and showed them all love, -- and the last of all greetings was
            that betwixt them. </p>
          <p> Then said she, "I thought I had set forth counsel whereby ye should not come hither,
            but none may deal with his shapen fate." And withal she said, "Will it avail aught to
            seek for peace?" </p>
          <p> But stoutly and grimly they said nay thereto. So she sees that the game goeth sorely
            against her brethren, and she gathers to her great stoutness of heart, and does on her a
            mail-coat and takes to her a sword, and fights by her brethren, and goes as far forward
            as the bravest of man-folk; and all spoke in one wise that never saw any fairer defence
            than in her. </p>
          <p> Now the men fell thick, and far before all others was the fighting of those brethren,
            and the battle endured a long while unto midday; Gunnar and Hogni went right through the
            folk of Atli, and so tells the tale that all the mead ran red with blood; the sons of
            Hogni withal set on stoutly. </p>
          <p> Then spake Atli the king, "A fair host and a great have we, and mighty champions
            withal, and yet have many of us fallen, and but evil am I apaid in that nineteen of my
            champions are slain, and but left six alive." </p>
          <p> And therewithal was there a lull in the battle. </p>
          <p> Then spake Atli the king, "Four brethren were we, and now am I left alone; great
            affinity I gat to me, and deemed my fortune well sped thereby; a wife I had, fair and
            wise, high of mind, and great of heart; but no joyance may I have of her wisdom, for
            little peace is betwixt us, -- but ye -- ye have slain many of my kin, and beguiled me
            of realm and riches, and for the greatest of all woes have slain my sister withal." </p>
          <p> Quoth Hogni, "Why babblest thou thus? Thou wert the first to break the peace. Thou
            didst take my kinswoman and pine her to death by hunger, and didst murder her, and take
            her wealth; an ugly deed for a king! -- meet for mocking and laughter I deem it, that
            thou must needs make long tale of thy woes; rather will I give thanks to the Gods that
            thou fallest into ill." </p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="38">
          <p> Now King Atli eggs on his folk to set on fiercely, and eagerly they fight; but the
            Giukings fell on so hard that King Atli gave back into the hall, and within doors was
            the fight, and fierce beyond all fights. </p>
          <p> That battle was the death of many a man, but such was the ending thereof, that there
            fell all the folk of those brethren, and they twain alone stood up on their feet, and
            yet many more must fare to hell first before their weapons. </p>
          <p> And now they fell on Gunnar the king, and because of the host of men that set on him
            was hand laid on him, and he was cast into fetters; afterwards fought Hogni, with the
            stoutest heart and the greatest manlihood; and he felled to earth twenty of the stoutest
            of the champions of King Atli, and many he thrust into the fire that burnt amidst the
            hall, and all were of one accord that such a man might scarce be seen; yet in the end
            was he borne down by many and taken. </p>
          <p> Then said King Atli, "A marvellous thing how many men have gone their ways before him!
            Cut the heart from out of him, and let that be his bane!" </p>
          <p> Hogni said, "Do according to thy will; merrily will I abide whatso thou writ do
            against me; and thou shalt see that my heart is not adrad, for hard matters have I made
            trial of ere now, and all things that may try a man was I fain to bear, whiles yet I was
            unhurt; but now sorely am I hurt, and thou alone henceforth will bear mastery in our
            dealings together." </p>
          <p> Then spake a counsellor of King Atli, "Better rede I see thereto; take we the thrall
            Hjalli, and give respite to Hogni; for this thrall is made to die, since the longer he
            lives the less worth shall he be." </p>
          <p> The thrall hearkened, and cried out aloft, and fled away anywhither where he might
            hope for shelter, crying out that a hard portion was his because of their strife and
            wild doings, and an ill day for him whereon he must be dragged to death from his sweet
            life and his swine-keeping. But they caught him, and turned a knife against him, and he
            yelled and screamed or ever he felt the point thereof. </p>
          <p> Then in such wise spake Hogni as a man seldom speaketh who is fallen into hard need,
            for he prayed for the thrall's life, and said that these shrieks he could not away with,
            and that it were a lesser matter to him to play out the play to the end; and therewithal
            the thrall gat his life as for that time: but Gunnar and Hogni are both laid in fetters. </p>
          <p> Then spake King Atli with Gunnar the king, and bade him tell out concerning the gold,
            and where it was, if he would have his life. </p>
          <p> But he answered, "Nay, first will I behold the bloody heart of Hogni, my brother." </p>
          <p> So now they caught hold of the thrall again, and cut the heart from out of him, and
            bore it unto King Gunnar, but he said -- </p>
          <p> "The faint heart of Hjalli may ye here behold, little like the proud heart of Hogni,
            for as much as it trembleth now more by the half it trembled whenas it lay in the breast
            of him." </p>
          <p> So now they fell on Hogni even as Atli urged them, and cut the heart from out of him,
            but such was the might of his manhood, that he laughed while he abode that torment, and
            all wondered at his worth, and in perpetual memory is it held sithence. (1) </p>
          <p> Then they showed it to Gunnar, and he said -- </p>
          <p> "The mighty heart of Hogni, little like the faint heart of Hjalli, for little as it
            trembleth now, less it trembled whenas in his breast it lay! But now, O Atli, even as we
            die so shalt thou die; and lo, I alone wot where the gold is, nor shall Hogni be to tell
            thereof now; to and fro played the matter in my mind whiles we both lived, but now have
            I myself determined for myself, and the Rhine river shall rule over the gold, rather
            than that the Huns shall bear it on the hands of them." </p>
          <p> Then said King Atli, "Have away the bondsman;" and so they did. </p>
          <p> But Gudrun called to her men, and came to Atli, and said -- </p>
          <p> "May it fare ill with thee now and from henceforth, even as thou hast ill held to thy
            word with me!" </p>
          <p> So Gunnar was cast into a worm-close, and many worms abode him there, and his hands
            were fast bound; but Gudrun sent him a harp, and in such wise did he set forth his
            craft, that wisely he smote the harp, smiting it with his foes, and so excellently well
            he played, that few deemed they had heard such playing, even when the hand had done it.
            And with such might and power he played, that all worms fell asleep in the end, save one
            adder only, great and evil of aspect, that crept unto him and thrust its sting into him
            until it smote his heart; and in such wise with great hardihood he ended his life days.
          </p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="39">
          <p> Now thought Atli the King that he had gained a mighty victory, and spake to Gudrun
            even as mocking her greatly, or as making himself great before her. "Gudrun," saith he,
            "thus hast thou lost thy brethren, and thy very self hast brought it about." </p>
          <p> She answers, "In good liking livest thou, whereas thou thrustest these slayings before
            me, but mayhappen thou wilt rue it, when thou hast tried what is to come hereafter; and
            of all I have, the longest-lived matter shall be the memory of thy cruel heart, nor
            shall it go well with thee whiles I live." </p>
          <p> He answered and said, "Let there be peace betwixt us; I will atone for thy brethren
            with gold and dear-bought things, even as thy heart may wish." </p>
          <p> She answers, "Hard for a long while have I been in our dealings together, and now I
            say, that while Hogni was yet alive thou mightest have brought it to pass; but now
            mayest thou never atone for my brethren in my heart; yet oft must we women be overborne
            by the might of you men; and now are all my kindred dead and gone, and thou alone art
            left to rule over me: wherefore now this is my counsel that we make a great feast;
            wherein I will hold the funeral of my brother and of thy kindred withal." </p>
          <p> In such wise did she make herself soft and kind in words, though far other things
            forsooth lay thereunder, but he hearkened to her gladly, and trusted in her words,
            whereas she made herself sweet of speech. </p>
          <p> So Gudrun held the funeral feast for her brethren, and King Atli for his men, and
            exceeding proud and great was this feast. </p>
          <p> But Gudrun forgat not her woe, but brooded over it, how she might work some mighty
            shame against the king; and at nightfall she took to her the sons of King Atli and her
            as they played about the floor; the younglings waxed heavy of cheer, and asked what she
            would with them. </p>
          <p> "Ask me not," she said; "ye shall die, the twain of you!" </p>
          <p> Then they answered, "Thou mayest do with thy children even as thou wilt, nor shall any
            hinder thee, but shame there is to thee in the doing of this deed." </p>
          <p> Yet for all that she cut the throats of them. </p>
          <p> Then the king asked where his sons were, and Gudrun answered, "I will tell thee, and
            gladden thine heart by the telling; lo now, thou didst make a great woe spring up for me
            in the slaying of my brethren; now hearken and hear my rede and my deed; thou hast lost
            thy sons, and their heads are become beakers on the board here, and thou thyself hast
            drunken the blood of them blended with wine; and their hearts I took and roasted them on
            a spit, and thou hast eaten thereof." </p>
          <p> King Atli answered, "Grim art thou in that thou hast murdered thy sons, and given me
            their flesh to eat, and little space passes betwixt ill deed of thine and ill deed." </p>
          <p> Gudrun said, "My heart is set on the doing to thee of as great shame as may be; never
            shall the measure ill be of full to such a king as thou art." </p>
          <p> The king said, "Worser deeds hast thou done than men have to tell of, and great
            unwisdom is there in such fearful redes; most meet art thou to be burned on bale when
            thou hast first been smitten to death with stones, for in such wise wouldst thou have
            what thou hast gone a weary way to seek." </p>
          <p> She answered, "Thine own death thou foretellest, but another death is fated for me." </p>
          <p> And many other words they spake in their wrath. </p>
          <p> Now Hogni had a son left alive, hight Niblung, and great wrath of heart he bare
            against King Atli; and he did Gudrun to wit that he would avenge his father. And she
            took his words well, and they fell to counsel together thereover, and she said it would
            be great goodhap if it might be brought about. </p>
          <p> So on a night, when the king had drunken, he gat him in bed, and when he was laid
            asleep, thither to him came Gudrun and the son of Hogni. </p>
          <p> Gudrun took a sword and thrust it through the breast of King Atli, and they both of
            them set their hands to the deed, both she and the son of Hogni. </p>
          <p> Then Atli the king awoke with the wound, and cried out; "No need of binding or salving
            here! -- who art thou who hast done the deed?" </p>
          <p> Gudrun says, "Somewhat have I, Gudrun, wrought therein, and somewhat withal the son of
            Hogni." </p>
          <p> Atli said, "Ill it beseemed to thee to do this, though somewhat of wrong was between
            us; for thou wert wedded to me by the rede of thy kin, and dower paid I for thee; yea,
            thirty goodly knights, and seemly maidens, and many men besides; and yet wert thou not
            content, but if thou should rule over the lands King Budli owned: and thy mother-in-law
            full oft thou lettest sit a-weeping." </p>
          <p> Gudrun said, "Many false words hast thou spoken, and of naught I account them; oft,
            indeed, was I fell of mood, but much didst thou add thereto. Full oft in this thy house
            did frays befall, and kin fought kin, and friend fought friend, and made themselves big
            one against the other; better days had I whenas I abode with Sigurd, when we slew kings,
            and took their wealth to us, but gave peace to whomso would, and the great men laid
            themselves under our hands, and might we gave to him of them who would have it; then I
            lost him, and a little thing was it that I should bear a widow's name, but the greatest
            of griefs that I should come to thee -- I who had aforetime the noblest of all kings,
            while for thee, thou never barest out of the battle aught but the worser lot." </p>
          <p> King Atli answered, "Naught true are thy words, nor will this our speech better the
            lot of either of us, for all is fallen now to naught; but now do to me in seemly wise,
            and array my dead corpse in noble fashion." </p>
          <p> "Yea, that will I," she says, "and let make for thee a goodly grave, and build for
            thee a worthy abiding place of stone, and wrap thee in fair linen, and care for all that
            needful is." </p>
          <p> So therewithal he died, and she did according to her word: and then they cast fire
            into the hall. </p>
          <p> And when the folk and men of estate awoke amid that dread and trouble, naught would
            they abide the fire, but smote each the other down, and died in such wise; so there Atli
            the king, and all his folk, ended their life-days. But Gudrun had no will to live longer
            after this deed so wrought, but nevertheless her ending day was not yet come upon her. </p>
          <p> Now the Volsungs and the Giukings, as folk tell in tale, have been the
            greatest-hearted and the mightiest of all men, as ye may well behold written in the
            songs of old time. </p>
          <p> But now with the tidings just told were these troubles stayed. </p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="40">
          <p> Gudrun had a daughter by Sigurd hight Swanhild; she was the fairest of all women,
            eager-eyed as her father, so that few durst look under the brows of her; and as far did
            she excel other woman-kind as the sun excels the other lights of heaven. </p>
          <p> But on a day went Gudrun down to the sea, and caught up stones in her arms, and went
            out into the sea, for she had will to end her life. But mighty billows drave her forth
            along the sea, and by means of their upholding was she borne along till she came at the
            last to the burg of King Jonakr, a mighty king, and lord of many folk. And he took
            Gudrun to wife, and their children were Hamdir, and Sorli, and Erp; and there was
            Swanhild nourished withal. </p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="41">
          <p> Jormunrek was the name of a mighty king of those days, and his son was called Randver.
            Now this king called his son to talk with him, and said, "Thou shalt fair on an errand
            of mine to King Jonakr, with my counsellor Bikki, for with King Jonakr is nourished
            Swanhild, the daughter of Sigurd Fafnir's-bane; and I know for sure that she is the
            fairest may dwelling under the sun of this world; her above all others would I have to
            my wife, and thou shalt go woo her for me" </p>
          <p> Randver answered, "Meet and right, fair lord, that I should go on thine errands." </p>
          <p> So the king set forth this journey in seemly wise, and they fare till they come to
            King Jonakr's abode, and behold Swanhild, and have many thoughts concerning the treasure
            of her goodliness. </p>
          <p> But on a day Randver called the king to talk with him, and said, "Jormunrek the King
            would fain be thy brother-in-law, for he has heard tell of Swanhild, and his desire it
            is to have her to wife, nor may it be shown that she may be given to any mightier man
            than he is one." </p>
          <p> The King says, "This is an alliance of great honour, for a man of fame he is." </p>
          <p> Gudrun says, "A wavering trust, the trust in luck that change not!" </p>
          <p> Yet because of the king's furthering, and all the matters that went herewith, is the
            wooing accomplished; and Swanhild went to the ship with a goodly company, and sat in the
            stem beside the king's son. </p>
          <p> Then spake Bikki to Randver, "How good and right it were if thou thyself had to wife
            so lovely a woman rather than the old man there." </p>
          <p> Good seemed that word to the heart of the king's son, and he spake to her with sweet
            words, and she to him like wise. </p>
          <p> So they came aland and go unto the king, and Bikki said to him, "Meet and right it is,
            lord, that thou shouldst know what is befallen, though hard it be to tell of, for the
            tale must be concerning thy beguiling, whereas thy son has gotten to him the full love
            of Swanhild, nor is she other than his harlot; but thou, let not the deed be unavenged." </p>
          <p> Now many an ill rede had he given the king or this, but of all his ill redes did this
            sting home the most; and still would the king hearken to all his evil redes; wherefore
            he, who might nowise still the wrath within him, cried out that Randver should be taken
            and tied up to the gallows-tree. </p>
          <p> And as he was led to the gallows he took his hawk and plucked the feathers from off
            it, and bade show it to his father; and when the king saw it, then he said, "Now may
            folk behold that he deemeth my honour to be gone away from me, even as the feathers of
            this hawk;" and therewith he bade deliver him from the gallows. </p>
          <p> But in that while had Bikki wrought his will, and Randver was dead-slain. </p>
          <p> Ane, moreover, Bikki spake, "Against none hast thou more wrongs to avenge thee of than
            against Swanhild; let her die a shameful death." </p>
          <p> "Yea," said the king, "we will do after thy counsel." </p>
          <p> So she was bound in the gate of the burg, and horse were driven at her to tread her
            down; but when she opened her eyes wide, then the horses durst not trample her; so when
            Bikki beheld that, he bade draw a bag over the head of her; and they did so, and
            therewith she lost her life. (1) </p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="42">
          <p> Now Gudrun heard of the slaying of Swanhild, and spake to her sons, "Why sit ye here
            in peace amid many words, whereas Jormunrek hath slain your sister, and trodden her
            under foot of horses in shameful wise? No heart ye have in you like to Gunnar or Hogni;
            verily they would have avenged their kinswoman!" </p>
          <p> Hamdir answered, "Little didst thou praise Gunnar and Hogni, whereas they slew Sigurd,
            and thou wert reddened in the blood of him, and ill were thy brethren avenged by the
            slaying of thine own sons: yet not so ill a deed were it for us to slay King Jormunrek,
            and so hard thou pushest on to this that we may naught abide thy hard words." </p>
          <p> Gudrun went about laughing now, and gave them to drink from mighty beakers, and
            thereafter she got for them great byrnies and good, and all other weed (1) of war. </p>
          <p> Then spake Hamdir, "Lo now, this is our last parting, for thou shalt hear tidings of
            us, and drink one grave-ale (2) over us and over Swanhild." </p>
          <p> So therewith they went their ways. </p>
          <p> But Gudrun went unto her bower, with heart swollen with sorrow, and spake -- </p>
          <p> "To three men was I wedded, and first to Sigurd Fafnir's-bane, and he was bewrayed and
            slain, and of all griefs was that the greatest grief. Then was I given to King Atli, and
            so fell was my heart toward him that I slew in the fury of my grief his children and
            mine. Then gave I myself to the sea, but the billows thereof cast me out aland, and to
            this king then was I given; then gave I Swanhild away out of the land with mighty
            wealth; and lo, my next greatest sorrow after Sigurd, for under horses feet was she
            trodden and slain; but the grimmest and ugliest of woes was the casting of Gunnar into
            the Worm-close, and the hardest was the cutting of Hogni's heart from him. </p>
          <p> "Ah, better would it be if Sigurd came to meet me, and I went my ways with him, for
            here bideth now behind with me neither son nor daughter to comfort me. Oh, mindest thou
            not, Sigurd, the words we spoke when we went into one bed together, that thou wouldst
            come and look on me; yea, even from thine abiding place among the dead? </p>
          <p> And thus had the words of her sorrow an end. </p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="43">
          <p> Now telleth the tale concerning the sons of Gudrun, that she had arrayed their
            war-raiment in such wise, that no steel would bite thereon; and she bade them play not
            with stones or other heavy matters, for that it would be to their scathe if they did so. </p>
          <p> And now, as they went on their way, they met Erp, their brother, and asked him in what
            wise he would help them. </p>
          <p> He answered, "Even as hand helps hand, or foot helps foot." </p>
          <p> But that they deemed naught at all, and slew him there and then. Then they went their
            ways, nor was it long or ever Hamdir stumbled, and thrust down his hand to steady
            himself, and spake therewith -- </p>
          <p> "Naught but a true thing spake Erp, for now should I have fallen, had not hand been to
            steady me." </p>
          <p> A little after Sorli stumbled, but turned about on his feet, and so stood, and spake
            -- </p>
          <p> "Yea now had I fallen, but that I steadied myself with both feet." </p>
          <p> And they said they had done evilly with Erp their brother. </p>
          <p> But on they fare till they come to the abode of King Jormunrek, and they went up to
            him and set on him forthwith, and Hamdir cut both hands from him and Sorli both feet.
            Then spake Hamdir -- </p>
          <p> "Off were the head if Erp were alive; our brother whom we slew on the way, and found
            out our deed too late." Even as the Song says, -- <quote>
              <l>"Off were the head</l>
              <l>If Erp were alive yet,</l>
              <l>Our brother the bold,</l>
              <l>Whom we slew by the way,</l>
              <l>The well-famed in warfare."</l>
            </quote> Now in this must they turn away from the words of their mother, whereas they
            had to deal with stones. For now men fell on them, and they defended themselves in good
            and manly wise, and were the scathe of many a man, nor would iron bite on them. </p>
          <p> But there came thereto a certain man, old of aspect and one-eyed, (1) and he spake -- </p>
          <p> "No wise men are ye, whereas ye cannot bring these men to their end." </p>
          <p> Then the king said, "Give us rede thereto, if thou canst." </p>
          <p> He said, "Smite them to the death with stones." </p>
          <p> In such wise was it done, for the stones flew thick and fast from every side, and that
            was the end of their life-days. </p>
          <p> And now has come to an end the whole root and stem of the Giukings. (2) <quote>
              <l>NOW MAY ALL EARLS</l>
              <l>BE BETTERED IN MIND,</l>
              <l>MAY THE GRIEF OF ALL MAIDENS</l>
              <l>EVER BE MINISHED,</l>
              <l>FOR THIS TALE OF TROUBLE</l>
              <l>SO TOLD TO ITS ENDING.</l>
            </quote>
          </p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
