<?xml version="1.0"?>





<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
	<title>Polygnotos and His Group</title>
	<author>Susan Matheson</author>
	<sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor><principal>Gregory Crane</principal><respStmt><resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp><name>Lisa Cerrato</name></respStmt>
	&fund.NEA;
      </titleStmt>
	<publicationStmt><publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher><pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace><authority>Perseus Project</authority></publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
	<note anchored="true">Susan Matheson, Yale University</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
	<p>Created in electronic form.
      </p></sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>

    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl>
	<refState unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
	<language ident="en">English
	</language><language ident="greek">Greek
	</language><language ident="xgreek">Transliterated Greek
      </language></langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
    
    <revisionDesc><!--
      <change><date>24 September 1999</date>
	<respStmt><name>DAS</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>
	$Log: vp.poly.xml,v $
	Revision 1.1  2009-12-09 18:06:56  rsingh04
	moved more xml files around based on copyright status

	Revision 1.3  2009/03/04 21:44:15  lcerrato
	fixing bad bibls

	Revision 1.2  2005/08/18 13:56:34  packel
	fixed item tags

	Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 15:06:22  packel
	Converted to XML
	
Revision 1.5  2003/07/01 22:18:53  yorkc
Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)

Revision 1.4  2000/06/19 21:39:29  dasmith
Make all FIGURES REND="float".

Revision 1.3  2000/03/04 20:35:23  dasmith
Added separate funder entity to TEI header.

Revision 1.2  1999/09/24 22:19:50  dasmith
Converted to TEI2 tagging.


</item></change>
    --> <change when="2014-11-13" who="Stella Dee">edited markup and assigned CTS URN</change></revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
<text><body>
<div type="section" n="1"><head>Introduction</head>

<p>Among the groups of vase painters active in the time of Pericles, one of the largest and most important was that named for the vase painter Polygnotos.<note anchored="true" n="1"><p>On the painter, <bibl>VA 171, 1027-33, 1678-79, 1707</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 442</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 2 154-5</bibl>. The Group as defined by Beazley (<bibl>ARV2, 1033-64, 1679-80</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 442-46</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 2 155-58</bibl>) includes the following painters: Peleus Painter, Hector Painter, Coghill Painter, Lykaon Painter, Christie Painter, Midas Painter, Curti Painter, Guglielmi Painter, Epimedes Painter, Pantoxena Painter, and the one or more hands in the Group of Brussels A 3096 and the Group of Bologna PU 289. Beazley also considered the Kleophon Painter and the Dinos Painter and their associates part of the Polygnotan Group (<bibl>ARV2, 1143-58, 1684-85</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 455-58</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 2164-65</bibl>). For subsequent discussions of the Group, see <bibl>Cornelia Isler-Kerenyi, "Chronologie und 'Synchronologie' der attischen Vasenmaler der Parthenonzeit," <title>AntK</title> Beiheft 9 (1973) 23-33</bibl>; <bibl>Matheson 1986, 101-14</bibl>; <bibl>Matheson 1993</bibl>.</p></note> Around 700 vases have now been ascribed to this Group, and its period of activity has been defined as spanning most of the second half of the fifth century, from Polygnotos to the Dinos Painter. Nearly a dozen named painters comprise the Group, some of whom, such as the Kleophon Painter, the Peleus Painter, and the Hector Painter, are well known. There are, in addition, about two hundred vases by unnamed painters which are sufficiently close in style to those by the named painters to merit incorporation in the Polygnotan Group.</p></div>

<div type="section" n="2"><head>The Group</head>

<p>The workshop structure of the Group of Polygnotos was apparently complex, and as Beazley admitted, the boundaries defining individual hands in this Group are often hard to delineate.<note anchored="true" n="2"><p><bibl>ARV2, 1027</bibl>; see further Martin Robertson, <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, xvi-xvii</bibl>, on Beazley's use of the terms "group" and "workshop."</p></note> The large number of vases that Beazley called "Group of Polygnotos, undetermined" can be viewed as a reflection of this difficulty and perhaps as evidence for a broader Polygnotan style that may exceed the specific parameters of a workshop. Associations between the Polygnotan Group and other painters outside it have also been traced through similarities of ornament and potting, and further connections have been derived from inscriptions.<note anchored="true" n="3"><p><bibl>Philippaki 1967, 151</bibl></p></note> Archaeological evidence has suggested some chronological relationships as well.<note anchored="true" n="4"><p>For example, a neck amphora by Polygnotos and a hydria by the Coghill Painter found together in the same Capua tomb with three vases by the Niobid Painter and one by the Painter of the Berlin Hydria; see <bibl>J.D. Beazley, "The Brygos Tomb at Capua," <title>AJA</title> 49 (1945) 154-55</bibl>; Capua Group III, with additions by <bibl>D.J.R. Williams, "The Brygos Tomb Reassembled and 19th-Century Commerce in Capuan Antiquities," <title>AJA</title> 96 (1992) 621-22</bibl>; additional evidence comes from other Capuan tombs and from tombs at Spina.</p></note> Within the workshop, developments in the potting of stamnoi, for example, suggest relationships among painters of these vases that confirm associations suggested by painting style.<note anchored="true" n="5"><p><bibl>Philippaki 1967, 123-47, 151-52.</bibl></p></note></p>

<milestone ed="JG" unit="Card"/>

<p>As defined by Beazley, the Group of Polygnotos does have a convincing homogeneity. The Group concentrated on large pots, although almost every common shape was decorated at least once, and Polygnotan painters did manifest certain preferences for subject matter, although the variety of subjects that they represented was extensive. In spite of its size, the Group does have an underlying stylistic consistency that keeps it distinct from contemporary vase painting workshops.</p>

<p>The Polygnotos who is the eponymous leader of the Group was one of three painters who signed this name on vases. J.D. Beazley recognized that the other two, whom he named the Lewis Painter<note anchored="true" n="6"><p>An Early Classical painter of skyphoi, also called "Polygnotos II" by Beazley, <bibl>ARV2, 972-79</bibl>.</p></note> and the Nausicaa Painter,<note anchored="true" n="7"><p>A "Later Mannerist": <bibl>ARV2, 1106-11</bibl>.</p></note> were distinct both from each other and from Polygnotos I, as Beazley called him, and because he was the most important and prolific of the three, it is Polygnotos I to whom Beazley and others refer when using the name.</p></div>

<div type="section" n="3"><head>The Niobid Painter and the Group of Polygnotos</head>

<p>Polygnotos signed five vases. Beazley considered him to have been a pupil of the Niobid Painter,<note anchored="true" n="8"><p>On the Niobid Painter, see <bibl>ARV2, 598-608, 1661</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 394-96</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 265-67</bibl>; <bibl>Webster 1935</bibl>; <bibl>M. Prange, <title>Der Niobidenmaler und seine Werkstatt</title> (Frankfurt 1989)</bibl>.</p></note> and to have inherited a preference for large pots and epic combat subjects from his famous Early Classical teacher. Subjects such as the Amazonomachy, Centauromachy, and scenes from Trojan epic, popular with the Niobid Painter and his workshop, were taken over by Polygnotos,<note anchored="true" n="9"><p>For lists of such subjects in the two workshops, see <bibl>Matheson 1993, Appendix 2</bibl>.</p></note> as were more restrained subjects, including, for example, the departure of a warrior. Vases by Polygnotos such as his pelike in the Louvre with Apollo and Tityos (<rs key="Perseus:object:Louvre G 375" type="vase">Louvre G 375</rs>)<note anchored="true" n="10"><p><bibl>ARV2, 1032, no. 54</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 318</bibl>; <bibl>CVA, Paris, Musée du Louvre 6 (France 9) pl. 42, 1-4 and 6-8</bibl>; <bibl>LIMC, II, 311, Apollo no. 1073, and 628, pl. 523, Artemis no. 1009 (side B)</bibl>.</p></note> and his calyx krater in Duke University (<rs key="Perseus:object:Durham 1964.27" type="vase">Durham 1964.27</rs>)<note anchored="true" n="11"><p><bibl>Para., 442</bibl>; <bibl>LIMC, IV, 874, Demeter no. 362</bibl>.</p></note> with the Mission of Triptolemos are close in style to the Niobid Painter and are therefore probably early works.</p>

<p>Some of the other members of the Group of Polygnotos appear to have learned directly from the Niobid Painter as well. The Hector Painter and the Lykaon Painter, for example, paint in a style that is still close to the Niobid Painter's work, and also to early work by Polygnotos, suggesting that these three trained side by side in the Niobid Painter's shop. The Hector and Lykaon Painters continue some of the Niobid Painter's subjects as well, among them the departure of a warrior. These rather typical Athenian family scenes were sometimes "heroized" by giving the figures names from Trojan epic, as on the Lykaon Painter's amphora in New York (<rs key="Perseus:object:New York 06.1021.116" type="vase">New York 06.1021.116</rs>)<note anchored="true" n="12"><p><bibl>ARV2, 1044, no. 1</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 444</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 320</bibl>; <bibl>LIMC, I, 839, pl. 667, Antimachos (unique), and 852, pl. 677, Antiochos no. 2</bibl>. The figures are all named: <foreign xml:lang="greek">*N*E*P*T*O*L*E*M*O*S</foreign>... <foreign xml:lang="greek">*A*N*T*I*M*A*X*O*S</foreign>... <foreign xml:lang="greek">*K*A*L*L*I*O*P*E</foreign>... <foreign xml:lang="greek">*A*N*T*I*O*X*O*S</foreign>.</p></note> and the Hector Painter's name vase in the Vatican (<rs key="Perseus:object:Vatican City, Museo Gregoriano Etrusco Vaticano 16570" type="vase">Vatican City, Museo Gregoriano Etrusco Vaticano 16570</rs>),<note anchored="true" n="13"><p><bibl>ARV2, 1036, no. 1, 1679</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 318</bibl>; <bibl>LIMC, IV, 476, Hekabe no. 17, and 485, pl. 284, Hektor no. 19</bibl>. Two of the figures are named: <foreign xml:lang="greek">*K*A*L*O*S *E*K*T*W*R  ... *E*K*A*B*H</foreign>.</p></note> a practice followed as well by anonymous members of the group such as the painter of an amphora in Philadelphia (<rs key="Perseus:object:Philadelphia 30-44-4" type="vase">Philadelphia 30-44-4</rs>; <figure n="1991.07.0001" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1991.07.0009" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1991.07.0010" rend="float"></figure>)<note anchored="true" n="14"><p><bibl>ARV2, 1058, no. 113</bibl>; <bibl>LIMC, IV, 485, Hektor no. 18</bibl>; the other figures are not named.</p></note> where the warrior's father is named Priamos.</p>

<milestone ed="JG" unit="Card"/>

<p>All of these early Polygnotan painters showed an originality that distinguished them from other members of the Niobid Painter's workshop, inventing compositions or choosing subjects not seen among the works of their teacher or his fellows. The stamnos by the Hector Painter in Munich showing Nike giving water to a bull (<rs key="Perseus:object:Munich 2412" type="vase">Munich 2412</rs>; <figure n="1990.34.0548" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1993.01.0151" rend="float"></figure>),<note anchored="true" n="15"><p><bibl>ARV2, 1936, no. 5, 1679</bibl>; <bibl>CVA, Munich, Museum Antiker Kleinkunst 5 (Germany 20) pl. 247,2, pl. 249,3-4</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 443</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 318</bibl>.</p></note> a late work by the painter which will be discussed further below, is an example. Similarly, the Lykaon Painter has given us a unique representation of Odysseus and the shade of Elpenor, a scene from the Odyssey, on his pelike in Boston (<rs key="Perseus:object:Boston 34.79" type="vase">Boston 34.79</rs>; <bibl>CB no. 111</bibl>; <figure n="1992.11.0266" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1992.11.0267" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1992.11.0268" rend="float"></figure>).<note anchored="true" n="16"><p><bibl>ARV2, 1045, no. 2</bibl>; <bibl>C&amp; B, II 86-93, 103</bibl>;  <bibl>Para., 444</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 320</bibl>.</p></note> The Elpenor scene is one of the few Polygnotan compositions to show the variations of groundline that were characteristic of the famous wall painter Polygnotos, for whom our vase painter may well have been named. This treatment of landscape may have been transmitted to the Lykaon Painter through the vases of the Niobid Painter, who uses uneven groundlines on his name vase, and if so it provides further evidence for the direct association of the two painters and for an early chronological position for the Lykaon Painter within the Polygnotan Group.</p>

<p>The mature style of Polygnotos developed from its Early Classical sources to a more Classical form under the influence of the sculptures of the Parthenon, especially its Frieze (see the <rs key="Perseus:object:Parthenon Frieze" type="sculpture">Parthenon Frieze</rs>). The influence is apparent in drapery style and details of pose, in the relative proportions of horses and men, and in a quiet calm that pervades even active narrative subjects. Vases such as the stamnos in Oxford by Polygnotos with the Dioskouroi (<rs key="Perseus:object:Oxford 1916.68" type="vase">Oxford 1916.68</rs>)<note anchored="true" n="17"><p>Oxford, Ashmolean Museum 1916.68; <bibl>ARV2, 1028, no. 6</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 317</bibl>; <bibl>CVA, Oxford, Ashmolean Museum 1 (Great Britain 3) pls. 29, 1-2, and 30, 1-2</bibl>; <bibl>LIMC, III, 569, pl. 456, Dioskouroi no. 2</bibl>.</p></note> owe an obvious debt to the horsemen of the Parthenon Frieze. Drapery on vases such as his amphora in London with the Mission of Triptolemos (<rs key="Perseus:object:London E 281" type="vase">London E 281</rs>)<note anchored="true" n="18"><p><bibl>ARV2, 1030, no. 36</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 317</bibl>; <bibl>CVA, London, British Museum 3 (Great Britain 4) pl. 16, 2</bibl>.</p></note> clearly shows a development from that of his Duke University krater, and this can, in its increased complexity and fluidity, also be traced to the Parthenon. The classical restraint with which Kassandra faces her attacker on the krater by Polygnotos in the Getty Museum<note anchored="true" n="19"><p><bibl>Matheson 1993, figs 1a-c</bibl>.</p></note> reflects the Olympian calm of the Parthenonian procession. Other members of the Group of Polygnotos were even more profoundly affected by the Parthenon sculptures than was Polygnotos. The Peleus Painter, for example, whom Beazley saw as very close in style to the Hector Painter,<note anchored="true" n="20"><p>On the Peleus and Hector Painters, see also <bibl>Y. Korshak, "Der Peleusmaler und sein Gefährte, der Hektormaler," <title>AntK</title> 23 (1980) 124-36</bibl>.</p></note> adopts the three-quarter view of figures and faces and the stately rhythms of the Parthenon Frieze in vases such as his name vase with the wedding procession of Peleus and Thetis in Ferrara (<rs key="Perseus:object:Ferrara, Museo Archeologico Nazionale di Spina 2893 (T 617)" type="vase">Ferrara, Museo Archeologico Nazionale di Spina 2893 (T 617)</rs>).<note anchored="true" n="21"><p><bibl>ARV2, 1038, no. 1, 1679</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 443</bibl>; <bibl>E.G. Pemberton, "The Name Vase of the Peleus Painter," <title>JWalt</title> (1977) 63-72, figs. 1-5</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 319</bibl>; <bibl>LIMC, II, 144, Aphrodite no. 1505, and 287, pl. 259, Apollo no. 245; LIMC V 323, Hermes no. 434</bibl>.</p></note> The Kleophon Painter,<note anchored="true" n="22"><p>In addition to Beazley and Isler-Kerenyi (supra n. 1) see <bibl>M. Gaulandi, "Il Pittore di Kleophon," <title>Arte Antica e Moderne</title> 5 (1962) 341-83, and "Il Pittore di Kleophon rinvenute a Spina," <title>Arte Antica e Moderne</title> 5 (1962) 227-60</bibl>; <bibl>K.F. Felten, <title>Thanatos- und Kleophon Maler: Weissgründige und rotfigurige Vasenmalerei der Parthenonzeit</title> (Munich 1971)</bibl>; <bibl>E. De Miro, "Nuovi Contributi sul Pittore di Kleophon," <title>ArchCl</title> 20 (1968) 239-48</bibl>.</p></note> who was the leading member of the second generation of Polygnotan painters, was the painter most thoroughly imbued with the spirit of the Parthenon sculpture, either inside the Polygnotan workshop or outside it. The procession to Apollo on his famous volute krater in Ferrara echoes the feeling of the Parthenon Frieze procession more closely than any other surviving vase, while the same painter's stamnoi in Munich (<rs key="Perseus:object:Munich 2415" type="vase">Munich 2415</rs>; <figure n="1990.34.0572" rend="float"></figure>)<note anchored="true" n="23"><p><bibl>ARV2, 1143, no. 2, 1684</bibl>; <bibl>CVA, Munich, Museum Antiker Kleinkunst 5 (Germany 20) 41, pl. 256, 1 and 257, 1-2, pl. 258, 1-3</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 455</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 334</bibl>; <bibl>LIMC, IV, 486, pl. 285, Hektor no. 27 (as Hektor, Andromache, Priam, and Hekabe; the figures are not inscribed)</bibl>.</p></note> and St. Petersburg (<rs key="Perseus:object:St. Petersburg, Hermitage Museum 1148 (formerly 809 and St. 1428)" type="vase">St. Petersburg, Hermitage Museum 1148 (formerly 809 and St. 1428)</rs>)<note anchored="true" n="24"><p><bibl>ARV2, 1143, no. 3</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 455</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 334</bibl>; <bibl>Gaulandi, "Il Pittore di Kleophon" (supra n. 27) pl. 107a-b</bibl>.</p></note> showing the departure of a warrior are the essence of classical idealism.</p></div>

<div type="section" n="4"><head>The Departure of a Warrior</head>

<p>The departure of a warrior was a subject much favored by Polygnotan painters, originally inherited from the Niobid Painter, whose compositions are repeated in representations of the subject by Polygnotos, the Hector Painter, the Peleus Painter, and some anonymous Polygnotans (e.g., an amphora in Philadelphia, <rs key="Perseus:object:Philadelphia 30-44-4" type="vase">Philadelphia 30-44-4</rs>; <figure n="1991.07.0009" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1991.07.0019" rend="float"></figure>)<note anchored="true" n="25"><p><bibl>ARV2, 1058, no. 113</bibl>; <bibl>LIMC, IV, 485, Hektor no. 18</bibl>; the other figures are not named.</p></note>. In the hands of the Kleophon Painter and his followers (e.g., a fragment in the manner of the Kleophon Painter in the University of Chicago (<rs key="Perseus:object:University of Chicago 1967.115.244" type="vase">University of Chicago 1967.115.244</rs>))<note anchored="true" n="26"><p><bibl>Moon 1979, 213, cat. no. 120</bibl>; <bibl>Gaulandi, "Il Pittore di Kleophon" (supra, n. 22) 361, no. 4 (as Kleophon Painter)</bibl>.</p></note>, the departure became a vehicle for showing human emotion under stress but suitably restrained.</p></div>

<div type="section" n="5">
<head>Other Subjects: Amazonomachies and Centauromachies</head>

<p>Other subjects, such as the Amazonomachy, that were favored by the Niobid Painter and his shop appear throughout the span of the Polygnotan workshop. Polygnotos painted Greeks battling Amazons, as noted above, but he limited his compositions to restricted groupings of two or three figures. In some, such as his amphora in London (<rs key="Perseus:object:London E 280" type="vase">London E 280</rs>),<note anchored="true" n="27"><p><bibl>ARV2, 1030, no. 35</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 317</bibl>; <bibl>CVA, London, British Museum 3 (Great Britain 4) pls. 12, 3 and 16, 1</bibl>; <bibl>LIMC, I, 164, Achilles no. 732, and 598, pl. 465, Amazons no. 179</bibl>.</p></note> he names the figures Achilles and Penthesilea, adding an epic dimension that gave a specific dramatic focus to the scene as well. The Christie Painter, the Guglielmi Painter, and others painted similar two-, three-, or four-figure Amazonomachies, in a limited and fairly consistent range of compositions.<note anchored="true" n="28"><p>Amazonomachies on Greek vases are categorized and discussed by <bibl>von Bothmer 1957</bibl>. The Christie Painter's examples are on stamnoi in London (<rs key="Perseus:object:London 1898.7-15.1" type="vase">London 1898.7-15.1</rs>) and Copenhagen (<rs key="Perseus:object:Copenhagen, Ny Carlsberg Glyptothek 2694" type="vase">Copenhagen, Ny Carlsberg Glyptothek 2694</rs>) and on pelikai in the Musées Royaux d'Art et d'Histoire, Brussels (<rs key="Perseus:object:Brussels A 133" type="vase">Brussels A 133</rs>) and <rs key="Perseus:object:St. Petersburg 3374" type="vase">St. Petersburg 3374</rs>, the latter pair virtual replicas (<bibl>ARV2, 1048, nos. 35, 36, 39, and 40, respectively</bibl>). The Guglielmi Painter's Amazonomachies are on a stamnos in the Vatican (<rs key="Perseus:object:Museo Gregoriano Etrusco Vaticano 16" type="vase">Museo Gregoriano Etrusco Vaticano 16</rs>) and a bell krater in the Museo Archeologico Nazionale, Naples (<rs key="Perseus:object:Naples 1768" type="vase">Naples 1768</rs>) (<bibl>ARV2, 1043, nos. 1 and 3 respectively</bibl>).</p></note></p>

<milestone ed="JG" unit="Card"/>

<p>The most complex Polygnotan Amazonomachies were big battle scenes with a dozen or more combatants, such as the dinos by an unnamed Polygnotan in London (<rs key="Perseus:object:London 1899.7-21.5" type="vase">London 1899.7-21.5</rs>; <figure n="1993.01.0335" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1993.01.0336" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1993.01.0337" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1993.01.0338" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1993.01.0339" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1993.01.0340" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1993.01.0341" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1993.01.0342" rend="float"></figure>).<note anchored="true" n="29"><p><bibl>ARV2, 1052, no. 29</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 322</bibl>; <bibl>CVA, London, British Museum 6 (Great Britain 8) pl. 103</bibl>; <bibl>LIMC, I, 439, pl. 339, Akamas no. 22 and 602, pl. 470, Amazons no. 233</bibl>. Some of the figures are named: <foreign xml:lang="greek">*Q*E*S*E*U*S</foreign>;<foreign xml:lang="greek">*A[*N*D]*R*O*M*A[*X*H]</foreign>; <foreign xml:lang="greek">[*P*E*I]*R*I*Q*O[*O]*S</foreign>; <foreign xml:lang="greek">&epig-rough;*I*P*P*O*L[*U*T]*E</foreign>; <foreign xml:lang="greek">*A[*K]*A*M*A*S</foreign>; <foreign xml:lang="greek">*M*E*L*A...*U*S</foreign>; <foreign xml:lang="greek">*L*A*S</foreign>; <foreign xml:lang="greek">*S*Q*E[*N*E*L*O*S]</foreign></p></note> Here Greeks and Amazons, both mounted and on foot, battle one another in a series of small groups that combine to create a frieze encircling the entire vessel. The varied groundlines echo monumental painting, while the feeling of depth created by the overlapping mounted Amazons recalls riders on the Parthenon Frieze. The centauromachy was another subject popular with members of the Niobid Painter's workshop that may have links to monumental painting. The episode with Kaineus and the centaurs is treated twice by Polygnotos, on a signed stamnos in Brussels (<rs key="Perseus:object:Brussels A 134" type="vase">Brussels A 134</rs>)<note anchored="true" n="30"><p><bibl>ARV2, 1027, no. 1</bibl>; <bibl>CVA, Brussels, Musée de Cinquantenaire 1 (Belgium 1) pl. 7, no. 2</bibl>; <bibl>Arias &amp; Hirmer 1962, pl. 100</bibl>;  <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 317</bibl>; <bibl>LIMC, V, 887, pl. 571, Kaineus no. 44</bibl>. The vase is signed <foreign xml:lang="greek">*P*O*L*U*G*N*O*T*O*S *E*G*R*A*Y*S*E*N</foreign> on side A, and Kaineus is named: <foreign xml:lang="greek">*K*A*I*N*E*U*S</foreign>.</p></note> and on a late volute krater in Bologna (<rs key="Perseus:object:Bologna, Museo Civico Archeologico 16557 (Pell. 275)" type="vase">Bologna, Museo Civico Archeologico 16557 (Pell. 275)</rs>),<note anchored="true" n="31"><p><bibl>ARV2, 1029, no. 18</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 317</bibl>; <bibl>CVA, Bologna 4 (Italy 27) pls. 59 (below), 67, and 68, 8-10</bibl>; <bibl>LIMC, V, 887, pl. 571, Kaineus no. 45</bibl>.</p></note> and a fragment of another representation is preserved from a double-register calyx krater by an unnamed Polygnotan hand in the University of Chicago collection (<rs key="Perseus:object:University of Chicago 1967.115.390" type="vase">University of Chicago 1967.115.390</rs>).<note anchored="true" n="32"><p><bibl>ARV2, 1057, no. 107</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 323</bibl>; <bibl>Moon 1979, cat. no. 118</bibl>; <bibl>LIMC, V, 887, Kaineus no. 46</bibl>.</p></note> The double-register calyx krater was one of a number of decorative formats adopted by Polygnotan painters from the Niobid Painter and his shop.<note anchored="true" n="33"><p>For the double-register format and its development, see <bibl>Brijder 1984, 119-27 (J. H. Oakley, "Double-Register Calyx Kraters: A Study in Workshop Tradition").</bibl>.</p></note></p></div>

<div type="section" n="6"><head>Dionysiac Scenes</head>

<p>Judging from surviving vases, the most popular subject matter among Polygnotan painters was that associated with Dionysos. In this the Polygnotan Group diverges from the Niobid Painter's workshop, where Dionysiac subjects were rare. The god and his thiasos of satyrs and maenads were treated by virtually every member of the Group, in combination with a long list of subjects, both mythological and generic.</p>

<p>Representations by the Curti Painter, whom Beazley connected with the Peleus Painter and whose work forms a bridge to that of the Kleophon Painter, are typical.<note anchored="true" n="34"><p>On the Curti Painter, in addition to Beazley (supra n. 1), see <bibl>M. Halm-Tisserant, "Le Peintre de Curti," <title>REA</title> 86 (1984) 135-70</bibl>.</p></note> On the Curti Painter's name vase, a stamnos in Harvard (<rs key="Perseus:object:Harvard 1925.30.40" type="vase">Harvard 1925.30.40</rs>; <figure n="1990.01.0927" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1990.01.0927" rend="float"></figure>),<note anchored="true" n="35"><p><bibl>ARV2, 1042, no. 1</bibl>; <bibl>CVA, Hoppin Collection (U.S.A. 1) pls. 14-15</bibl>; <bibl>LIMC, III, 455, pl. 336, Dionysos no. 350</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda, 320</bibl>.</p></note> the bearded god walks to the right, accompanied in a torch-lit procession by two satyrs and two maenads. The god of wine bears his attributes, a thyrsos and a kantharos. The satyrs provide music on the double flute (<foreign xml:lang="xgreek">aulos</foreign>) and lyre (<foreign xml:lang="xgreek">barbiton</foreign>). One maenad carries the torch, while the other carries a second kantharos, her head thrown back in song. The procession continues on the reverse of the vase, in a less detailed style, with satyrs and a maenad carrying thyrsoi, another kantharos, and a wineskin. Such Dionysiac processions accompanying a bearded figure of the god are typical of both Early Classical and Classical representations of Dionysos. The tall, somewhat angular figures as well as the facial type of the torch-bearing maenad on the Curti Painter's stamnos derive from the Niobid Painter, but the monumental feeling and the weighty, statuesque quality of the figures show the influence of sculpture and are closer to work by the Kleophon Painter. Still later in the Polygnotan Group, in works by the Dinos Painter and his associates, Dionysiac scenes introduce the youthful unbearded Dionysos reclining with Ariadne, a type that is characteristic of fourth-century vase painting.</p></div>

<div type="section" n="7"><head>Return of Hephaistos</head>

<p>Often in the Classical period, Dionysiac processions such as those just discussed are given a specific narrative context by being transformed into scenes of the return of Hephaistos.<note anchored="true" n="36"><p>On the subject, see <bibl>Brommer 1978a</bibl>, and <bibl>M. Halm-Tisserant, "La représentation du retour d'Hephaistos dans l'Olympe," <title>AntK</title> 29 (1986) 8-22</bibl>.</p></note> This was a particularly popular subject among Polygnotan painters, notably with the Kleophon Painter and the unnamed hands in the Group. Two vases bearing this subject, now in the San Antonio and Toledo Museums of Art, have recently been attributed to the Curti Painter (<rs key="Perseus:object:San Antonio, Tex., San Antonio Museum of Art 86.134.77" type="vase">San Antonio, Tex., San Antonio Museum of Art 86.134.77</rs>; <rs key="Perseus:object:Toledo 82.88" type="vase">Toledo 82.88</rs>).<note anchored="true" n="37"><p>Calyx krater in San Antonio, Halm-Tisserant (supra n. 35) pl. 1; <bibl>LIMC, IV, 644, pl. 398, Hephaistos no. 164b</bibl>. Skyphos, Toledo, Ohio, Toledo Museum of Art 82.88; <bibl>CVA, Toledo 2 (U.S.A. 20) pl. 84-87</bibl>, as Kleophon Painter; Halm-Tisserant (supra n. 34) pl. III, as Curti Painter; <bibl>LIMC, IV, 638, pl. 392, Hephaistos no. 119</bibl>.</p></note> Both show Hephaistos mounted on a mule and preceded by Dionysos, who appears on foot. The figure of Dionysos in both cases is very close to that on the Harvard stamnos, as is the Dionysos on another version by an unnamed Polygnotan, on a calyx krater now in Munich (<rs key="Perseus:object:Munich 2384" type="vase">Munich 2384</rs>; <figure n="1990.34.0559" rend="float"></figure>).<note anchored="true" n="38"><p><bibl>ARV2, 1057, no. 98</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 445</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 322</bibl>; <bibl>LIMC, IV, 644, pl. 398, Hephaistos no. 164a</bibl>.</p></note> The seated figure of Hera, awaiting release by Hephaistos, appears on the Toledo skyphos, an unusually complete narrative version echoed among the Polygnotans only in a fragmentary representation by the Hector Painter in Bologna (<rs key="Perseus:object:Bologna, Museo Civico Archeologico 16498 (Pell. 282)" type="vase">Bologna, Museo Civico Archeologico 16498 (Pell. 282)</rs>).<note anchored="true" n="39"><p><bibl>ARV2, 1036, no. 11</bibl>; <bibl>CVA, Bologna, Museo Civico 4 (Italy 27) pl. 70</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 318</bibl>; <bibl>LIMC, IV, 645, Hephaistos no. 172d</bibl>.</p></note> More commonly the scene is abbreviated to eliminate Hera, although her presence is always implied and would certainly have been provided in the ancient viewer's imagination. A variant type of the return also used by Polygnotan painters shows Hephaistos on foot, as on the Kleophon Painter's pelike in Munich.<note anchored="true" n="40"><p><rs key="Perseus:object:Munich 2361" type="vase">Munich 2361</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 1145, no. 36</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 456</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 335</bibl>; <bibl>LIMC, IV, 645, pl. 401, Hephaistos no. 172c</bibl>; <bibl>Arias &amp; Hirmer 1962, pls. 196-99</bibl>.</p></note></p></div>

<div type="section" n="8">
<head>Scenes of Theatrical and Poetic Competitions</head>

<p>Both the theater and dithyrambic competitions are associated with Dionysos, and both themes are found on Polygnotan vases. Some scholars have related the return of Hephaistos scenes and their remarkable popularity in the Classical period to a satyr play on that subject.<note anchored="true" n="41"><p><bibl>Brommer 1959b, 72, no. 12</bibl>; and <bibl>Webster 1967, 165</bibl>, link a bell krater by an unnamed Polygnotan once in the Hope collection and formerly on the Paris art market (<bibl>ARV2, 1053, no. 39</bibl>) to the <bibl><title>Hephaistos</title> by Achaios of Eretria</bibl>. On the vase, a satyr dances on a table in front of Hephaistos and Dionysos.</p></note> Beazley suggested that the Prometheus Fire-lighter scenes, of which some are by Polygnotan painters, might relate to a satyr play as well.<note anchored="true" n="42"><p><bibl>J.D. Beazley, "Prometheus Fire-Lighter," <title>AJA</title> 43 (1939) 618-39.</bibl></p></note> One of these, a bell krater fragment by the Lykaon Painter in Oxford (<rs key="Perseus:object:Oxford 1927.4" type="vase">Oxford 1927.4</rs>)<note anchored="true" n="43"><p><bibl>ARV2, 1046, no. 10</bibl>; Beazley (supra n. 41) 631-32, 634, fig. 9; <bibl>CVA, Oxford, Ashmolean Museum 2 (Great Britain 9) pl. 66, 40</bibl>.</p></note>, shows a satyr costume and can thus definitely be linked to this genre. Representations of subjects known from Greek tragedy are also found on Polygnotan vases, and two in particular have been linked to specific dramas. A fragment of a bell krater in Adria by Polygnotos (<rs key="Perseus:object:Adria, Museo Civico Bc 104" type="vase">Adria, Museo Civico Bc 104</rs>)<note anchored="true" n="44"><p><bibl>ARV2, 1029, no. 19</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 442</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 317</bibl>; <bibl>CVA, Adria 1 (Italy 28) pl. 42, 1</bibl>.</p></note> shows part of a scene of the death of Laios (the scene is identified on the basis of inscriptions) which has been associated with a lost play on that subject by Aeschylus.<note anchored="true" n="45"><p>Webster (supra n. 40) 142.</p></note></p>

<milestone ed="JG" unit="Card"/>

<p>Fragments of a late double-register calyx krater by Polygnotos in the University of Vienna collection (<rs key="Perseus:object:Vienna, University 505" type="vase">Vienna, University 505</rs>)<note anchored="true" n="46"><p><bibl>ARV2, 1030, no. 33</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 442</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 317</bibl>; <bibl>CVA, Vienna 1 (Germany 5) Universität pl. 24</bibl>; <bibl>Hedwig Kenner, "Zur <title>Achilleis</title> des Aischylos," <title>ÖJh</title> 33 (1941) 1-24</bibl>; <bibl>LIMC, I, 117, Achilles no. 480, and 125, Achilles no. 524</bibl>; <bibl>LIMC, III, 161, pl. 136, Briseis no. 18</bibl>.</p></note> combine the ransom of Hektor, the arming of Achilles, and Achilles mourning Patroklos, a combination found on one other vase, the large three-register squat lekythos by the Eretria Painter in New York (<rs key="Perseus:object:New York 31.11.13" type="vase">New York 31.11.13</rs>).<note anchored="true" n="47"><p><bibl>ARV2, 1248, no. 9</bibl>; <bibl>Lezzi-Hafter 1988, pls. 150, 154, 155</bibl>.</p></note> The same combination occurred in the <bibl><title>Achilleis</title> of Aeschylus</bibl>, from which the vase painters apparently drew their inspiration.<note anchored="true" n="48"><p><bibl>Kenner (supra n. 45) 1-24</bibl>; Webster (supra n. 40) 142-43; <bibl>Kossatz-Deissmann 1978, 10-32</bibl>.</p></note> Dithyrambic competitions are to be associated with vases that show the tripods and bulls awarded as prizes in these contests.<note anchored="true" n="49"><p>See <bibl>Heidi Froning, <title>Dithyrambos und Vasenmalerei in Athen</title> (Würzburg 1971)</bibl>.</p></note> Typical representations show the altar and sanctuary and often the contestants or winners along with their prizes. The Hector Painter's picture on his stamnos in Munich (<rs key="Perseus:object:Munich 2412" type="vase">Munich 2412</rs>; <figure n="1990.34.0548" rend="float"></figure>)<note anchored="true" n="50"><p><bibl>ARV2, 1936, no. 5, 1679</bibl>; <bibl>CVA, Munich, Museum Antiker Kleinkunst 5 (Germany 20) pl. 247,2, pl. 249,3-4</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 443</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 318</bibl>.</p></note> of Nike pouring water from a hydria for the prize bull to drink can be read as dithyrambic because of the monumental tripod that dominates the central axis of the scene. This vase remains unique in the repertoire of such dithyrambic sacrifice scenes.</p></div>

<div type="section" n="9"><head>Scenes of Competiteion and Sacrifice</head>

<p>Both competition and sacrifice scenes were frequently represented by Polygnotan painters. One of the most unusual of the former is the torch race on a bell krater in the manner of the Peleus Painter in the Harvard University collection (<rs key="Perseus:object:Harvard 1960.344" type="vase">Harvard 1960.344</rs>; <figure n="1990.01.1917" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1990.01.1928" rend="float"></figure>).<note anchored="true" n="51"><p><bibl>ARV2, 1041, no. 10</bibl>; <bibl>CVA, Baltimore, Robinson Collection 2 (U.S.A. 6) pls. 48, 1 and 47, 2</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 443</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 319</bibl>; <bibl>Neils 1992, 178-79, cat. no. 50</bibl>.</p></note> The bearded man standing next to the altar should be the archon basileus, wearing the <foreign xml:lang="xgreek">ependytes</foreign> indicative of his ritual role here. The bronze hydria, known to have been awarded as a prize for the <foreign xml:lang="xgreek">lampadedromion</foreign>, should signify that this is the race shown. The increasing frequency of sacrifice scenes that typifies Classical vase painting in general is also reflected in the Polygnotan workshop, as is the parallel growth in popularity of departure-of-warrior scenes. Sacrifices to Apollo appear on a number of Polygnotan vases, notably on a stamnos by Polygnotos (<rs key="Perseus:object:Gotha, Schlossmuseum 51" type="vase">Gotha, Schlossmuseum 51</rs>),<note anchored="true" n="52"><p><bibl>ARV2, 1028, no. 10</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 442</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 317</bibl>; <bibl>CVA, Gotha 2 (Germany 29) pls. 56-58</bibl>; <bibl>LIMC, II, 298, Apollo no. 935</bibl>; <bibl>LIMC, III, 398, pl. 283, Diomedes I, no. 3</bibl>; the sacrificer is named: <foreign xml:lang="greek">*D*I*O*M*E*D*E*S</foreign>.</p></note> on the Kleophon Painter's Ferrara krater (<rs key="Perseus:object:Ferrara, Museo Archeologico Nazionale di Spina 44894 (T.57 C VP)" type="vase">Ferrara, Museo Archeologico Nazionale di Spina 44894 (T.57 C VP)</rs>),<note anchored="true" n="53"><p><bibl>ARV2, 1143, no. 1, 1684</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 455</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 334</bibl>; <bibl>N. Alfieri, P.E. Arias, M. Hirmer, <title>Spina</title> (Munich 1958) pls. 82-87</bibl>; <bibl>LIMC, II, 220, pl. 208, Apollo no. 303</bibl>.</p></note> and on a bell krater also by the Kleophon Painter in Agrigento (<rs key="Perseus:object:Agrigento, Museo Regionale AG 4688" type="vase">Agrigento, Museo Regionale AG 4688</rs>).<note anchored="true" n="54"><p>De Miro (supra n. 22) 238-48, pls. 85-96.</p></note></p>

<milestone ed="JG" unit="Card"/>

<p>A sacrifice on a third krater by the Kleophon Painter now in Boston has been associated with the Oligarchs because of the names the painter has given to the sacrificers (<rs key="Perseus:object:Boston 95.25" type="vase">Boston 95.25</rs>; <bibl>CB no. 167</bibl>).<note anchored="true" n="55"><p><bibl>ARV2, 1149, no. 9, 1588</bibl>; <bibl>C &amp; B, III 76-78, pl. 101 and supplementary pl. 25,1</bibl>;  <bibl>Para., 457</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 335</bibl>; De Miro (supra n. 22) 243-45, pl. 95. The sacrificers are named: <foreign xml:lang="greek">*A*R*E*S*I*A*S</foreign>; <foreign xml:lang="greek">*M*A*N*T*I*Q*E*O*S</foreign>; <foreign xml:lang="greek">*K*A*L*L*I*A*S</foreign>; <foreign xml:lang="greek">*I*P*P*O*K*L*E*S</foreign> <foreign xml:lang="greek">...*S</foreign> (<foreign xml:lang="greek">*K*R*I*T*I*A*S</foreign>?)</p></note></p></div>

<div type="section" n="10"><head>Scenes of the Eleusinian Mysteries</head>

<p>Eleusinian subjects also receive the attention of Polygnotan painters. These range from the traditional Mission of Triptolemos scene exemplified by the early version by Polygnotos (<rs key="Perseus:object:Durham 1964.27" type="vase">Durham 1964.27</rs>)<note anchored="true" n="56"><p><bibl>Para., 442</bibl>; <bibl>LIMC, IV, 874, Demeter no. 362</bibl>.</p></note> to the procession of Eleusinian initiates with a torch-bearing <foreign xml:lang="xgreek">dadouchos</foreign> found at Eleusis itself.<note anchored="true" n="57"><p>Stamnos, <rs key="Perseus:object:Eleusis, Archaeological Museum 636" type="vase">Eleusis, Archaeological Museum 636</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 1052, no. 23, 1680</bibl>; <bibl>K. Kourouniwtou, " <foreign xml:lang="greek">)*Eleusiniakh\ daidouxi/a</foreign>," <title>EphArch</title> 103 (1937) 223-53, figs. 1-4, 9-10</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 321</bibl>.</p></note> Eleusinian vases which could be said to be more emblematic than narrative in character include representations of Triptolemos and Demeter stripped of the apparatus of the Mission scenes, such as the amphora by an unnamed Polygnotan in the Harvard University collection (<rs key="Perseus:object:Harvard 1959.187" type="vase">Harvard 1959.187</rs>; <figure n="1990.01.0338" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1990.01.0342" rend="float"></figure>)<note anchored="true" n="58"><p><bibl>ARV2, 1059, no. 126</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 323</bibl>; <bibl>S. Doeringer, <title>The Frederick M. Watkins Collection</title>, exhibition catalogue, Fogg Art Museum (1973) 72-73, cat. no. 29</bibl>; <bibl>LIMC, IV, 374, pl. 212, Hades no. 38, and 874 , pl. 587, Demeter no. 363</bibl>.</p></note> and the amphora by Polygnotos with Eleusinian initiates in the Mount Holyoke College collection (<rs key="Perseus:object:Mount Holyoke 1929.BS.II.4" type="vase">Mount Holyoke 1929.BS.II.4</rs>; <figure n="1990.25.0001" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1990.25.0005" rend="float"></figure>).<note anchored="true" n="59"><p>South Hadley, Mass., Mount Holyoke College Art Museum 1929 BS II.4; <bibl>ARV2, 1031, no. 44</bibl>; <bibl>Buitron 1972, 124-25, cat. no. 69 (before cleaning)</bibl>. On this change in the iconography of Triptolemos scenes, see <bibl>C. Dugas, "La Mission de Triptolème d'après l'imagerie Athénienne," <title>Recueil Charles Dugas</title> (Paris 1960) 123-39</bibl>; see also <bibl>Metzger 1965, 7-32</bibl>.</p></note></p></div>

<div type="section" n="11"><head>Scenes of Daily Life: Symposium</head>

<p>The representations of participants in sacrifices, rituals, departures, and competitions already described are only part of a large corpus of scenes of daily life that occur on Polygnotan vases. Scenes from symposia are less frequent than during the Archaic period, perhaps because these are pot painters rather than painters of cups. The popular Dionysiac subjects, however, may have been suitable for the symposion as well as for the tomb. Komos scenes are far more common among the Polygnotans, and they are often associated with Dionysiac subjects on individual vases. The Polygnotan komos features both youths and their bearded elders and often includes music in the form of flutes and lyres. Many of the komasts' poses are reminiscent of dance. A bell krater by the Christie Painter in the Harvard collection (<rs key="Perseus:object:Harvard 1970.108" type="vase">Harvard 1970.108</rs>; <figure n="1990.01.0404" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1990.01.0400" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1990.01.0408" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1990.01.0407" rend="float"></figure>)<note anchored="true" n="60"><p><rs key="Perseus:object:Cambridge, Mass., Harvard University Art Museums 1970.108" type="vase">Cambridge, Mass., Harvard University Art Museums 1970.108</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 1047, 20</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 321</bibl>; <bibl>; E. H. Dohan, "A Bell-Krater by the Christie Painter," The University Museum Bulletin, 6 (1936) 126-8, no. 4</bibl>; <bibl>Buitron 1972, 128-9, no. 71</bibl>.</p></note> is a typical example, its torch-bearing komast responding with a dance pose to the flute player beside him. Similar is another bell krater by the same hand in the J. Paul Getty Museum (<rs key="Perseus:object:Malibu 71.AE.250" type="vase">Malibu 71.AE.250</rs>).<note anchored="true" n="61"><p><bibl>ARV2, 1047, no. 24</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 321</bibl>; <bibl>Boardman 1989, fig. 154</bibl>.</p></note> Occasionally satyrs and maenads are shown in komos-like scenes, as on a bell krater by an unnamed Polygnotan in London (<rs key="Perseus:object:London E 462" type="vase">London E 462</rs>),<note anchored="true" n="62"><p><bibl>ARV2, 1057, no. 103</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 323</bibl>.</p></note> and once Herakles performs as a komast, playing the flutes for two satyrs on a stamnos in Florence by Polygnotos that has been associated with a satyr play (<rs key="Perseus:object:Florence 4227" type="vase">Florence 4227</rs>).<note anchored="true" n="63"><p><bibl>ARV2, 1028, no. 11</bibl>; <bibl>CVA, Florence 2 (Italy 13) pls. 54 and 47, 5 (now cleaned)</bibl>; <bibl>LIMC, IV, 814, pl. 542, Herakles no. 1477</bibl>. On the association of this vase with a satyr play, see Brommer (supra n. 40) 77.</p></note></p></div>

<div type="section" n="12"><head>Scenes of Daily Life: Athletic</head>

<p>Like symposion scenes, scenes of athletes are less common in the Classical period and in this particular Group than they were among Archaic vase painters. Among the few surviving examples, fragments of a calyx krater by Polygnotos in Florence<note anchored="true" n="64"><p><rs key="Perseus:object:Florence, Museo Archeologico Etrusco 13 B 10-13, 18-22, 24-25, 28-30, 32-34, 38-41, and 19 B 21" type="vase">Florence, Museo Archeologico Etrusco 13 B 10-13, 18-22, 24-25, 28-30, 32-34, 38-41, and 19 B 21</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 1030, no. 29</bibl>; <bibl>CVA, Florence 1 (Italy 8) pl. 13 and 19</bibl>.</p></note> show a complex athletic scene with both draped and nude figures, some standing, others seated, two wrestling. The figures are shown on groundlines at multiple levels, recalling the Niobid Painter and suggesting that Polygnotos's krater is an early work. The remaining athletic scenes by other Polygnotans are generally also fragmentary, making assessment of compositions and relative dating difficult.</p></div>

<div type="section" n="13"><head>Scenes of Daily Life: Women</head>

<p>Scenes of women, on the other hand, especially as represented on hydriai, become a virtual industry for some of the Polygnotan painters and account for a large proportion of the Polygnotan scenes of daily life. The Christie Painter was a special practitioner of such scenes, as were the Kleophon Painter and others working in his manner. Vases by the Christie Painter such as his hydria in Providence (<rs key="Perseus:object:RISD 22.114" type="vase">RISD 22.114</rs>; <figure n="1990.03.1149" rend="float"></figure>)<note anchored="true" n="65"><p><bibl>ARV2, 1049, no. 47</bibl>; <bibl>CVA, Providence, R. I., Rhode Island School of Design Museum (U.S.A. 2) pl. 22, 1</bibl>.</p></note> and his krater in Würzburg (<rs key="Perseus:object:Wrzburg L 521" type="vase">Würzburg L 521</rs> (HA 168); <figure n="1992.09.0312" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1992.09.0316" rend="float"></figure>)<note anchored="true" n="66"><p><bibl>ARV2, 1046, no. 7</bibl>; <bibl>CVA, Würzburg, Martin von Wagner Museum 2 (Germany 46) pls. 19, 5-11, and 20, 1-2</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 2 320</bibl>.</p></note> are characteristic. The women are generally shown in groups, often with a seated central figure playing a musical instrument, performing some task related to woolworking, selecting jewelry, or occasionally reading. Other women stand by this central figure, participating in her activity in some way. Whether these scenes should be viewed as snapshots of the women's quarters or whether they are better interpreted as emblematic images of women's proper roles in life, or both, is debated.<note anchored="true" n="67"><p>See, e.g., <bibl>Dyfri Williams, "Women on Athenian vases: problems of interpretation," in A. Cameron and A. Kurht, eds., <title>Images of Women in Antiquity</title> (London 1983) 92-106</bibl>.</p></note> Numerous hydriai with such scenes have been found in tombs.<note anchored="true" n="68"><p>For the use of hydriai as cremation urns, see <bibl>Kurtz &amp; Boardman 1971, 98</bibl>, and  <bibl>Diehl 1964, 146-68</bibl>.</p></note> Sometimes Eros is present, suggesting association with preparations for a wedding.<note anchored="true" n="69"><p>On weddings, see <bibl>J.H. Oakley and R.H. Sinos, <title>The Wedding in Ancient Athens</title> (Madison, WI 1993)</bibl>.</p></note></p>

<milestone ed="JG" unit="Card"/>

<p>Similar scenes, again often with Eros, appear on loutrophoroi and lebetes gamikoi, offering more direct associations with weddings through the functions of the vases themselves; both of these shapes are rare among the Polygnotans but common enough in the work of contemporaries like the Washing Painter.<note anchored="true" n="70"><p>On the Washing Painter, see <bibl>ARV2, 1126-33</bibl>. A dissertation on the Washing Painter by Victoria Sebatai, University of Cincinnati, is near completion (1993).</p></note> Babies or children are rare in such scenes, although an unattributed hydria in the Polygnotan style at Harvard University (<rs key="Perseus:object:Harvard 1960.342" type="vase">Harvard 1960.342</rs>; <figure n="1990.01.1531" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1990.01.1529" rend="float"></figure>) shows two women with a baby in a scene marked as a domestic interior by the loom behind the figures.</p>

<milestone ed="JG" unit="Card"/>

<p>Occasionally the women are named, some as Muses, or Nereids, or poets, as the reading figure on a hydria by an unnamed Polygnotan in Athens, who is named Sappho (<rs key="Perseus:object:Athens 1260" type="vase">Athens 1260</rs>).<note anchored="true" n="71"><p><bibl>ARV2, 1060, no. 145</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 445</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 323</bibl>. The woman reading is named <foreign xml:lang="greek">*S*A*P*P*W*S</foreign>, her companions <foreign xml:lang="greek">*N*I*K*O*P*O*L*I*S</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="greek">*K*A*L*L*I*S</foreign>. On the book roll she is reading, see <bibl>J.D. Beazley, ""Hymn to Hermes," <title>AJA</title> 52 (1948) 336-40</bibl>; <bibl>H. Immerwahr, "Book Rolls on Attic Vases," <title>Classical, Mediaeval, and Renaissance Studies in Honor of Berthold Louis Ullmann</title>, vol. 1 (Rome 1964) 26</bibl>; <bibl>H. Immerwahr, "More Book Rolls on Attic Vases," <title>AntK</title> 16 (1973) 143-47</bibl>.</p></note> When the figures are named as muses, the scene may be envisioned as outdoors, although on the most impressive of these, where Terpsichore plays for Mousaios on the Peleus Painter's amphora in London (<rs key="Perseus:object:London E 271" type="vase">London E 271</rs>; <figure n="1990.14.0232" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1990.14.0233" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1993.01.0660" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1993.01.0661" rend="float"></figure>),<note anchored="true" n="72"><p><bibl>ARV2, 1039, no. 13</bibl>; <bibl>CVA, London, British Museum 3 (Great Britain 4) pl. 11,1 and 12,2</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 443</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 319</bibl>. The figures are named: <foreign xml:lang="greek">*T*E*R*Y*I*C*O*R*A</foreign>; <foreign xml:lang="greek">*M*O*S*A*I*O*S</foreign>; <foreign xml:lang="greek">*M*E*L*E*L*O*S*A</foreign>.</p></note> there is no indication of landscape. The Peleus Painter has shown remarkable attention to detail in the rendering of the musical instruments on this vase, as well as to the <foreign xml:lang="xgreek">klismos</foreign> on which Terpsichore sits while she plays her harp.</p>

<milestone ed="JG" unit="Card"/>

<p>A man or men are occasionally present in these scenes, and the meaning of their presence is debated. Some have suggested that the presence of men in scenes of woolworking distinguishes these women as hetairai, in contrast to the respectable women in the scenes without men.<note anchored="true" n="73"><p>E.g., <bibl>Moon 1983, 209-31 (E. Keuls, "Attic Vase-Painting and the Home Textile Industry")</bibl>.</p></note> Such an interpretation would be hard to accept for the hydria at Harvard mentioned above, where a man joins the women in their loom-filled interior, but where there is also a baby, an unlikely witness to the negotiations between hetairai and their customers. Scenes of men pursuing women have been associated with weddings as well.<note anchored="true" n="74"><p><bibl>C. Sourvinou-Inwood, "Menace and Pursuit: Differentiation and the Creation of Meaning," in C. Bérard et al., eds., <title>Images et société en grèce ancienne</title> (Lausanne 1987) 41-58</bibl>; and <bibl>Sourvinou-Inwood 1987, 131-53</bibl>.</p></note> There are many mythological paradigms for these mortal pursuits, and pursuits by Zeus and Poseidon are among those shown by Polygnotan painters. Eos pursuing Kephalos was a favorite of this Group, as typified by the Christie Painter's bell krater in the Johns Hopkins University collection (<rs key="Perseus:object:Baltimore, Hopkins BMA 51.486" type="vase">Baltimore, Hopkins BMA 51.486</rs>; <figure n="1990.06.0401" rend="float"></figure>).<note anchored="true" n="75"><p><bibl>ARV2, 1048, no. 27</bibl>; <bibl>CVA, Baltimore, Robinson Collection 2 (U.S.A. 6) pl. 45</bibl>; <bibl>E. R. Williams 1984, 7, 178-79</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 321</bibl>; <bibl>LIMC, III, 762, Eos no. 99</bibl>.</p></note> The abduction of Kephalos by Eos may have been a metaphor for sudden death,<note anchored="true" n="76"><p><bibl>Maas &amp; Snyder 1989, 83</bibl>.</p></note> making such vases particularly appropriate as tomb offerings.</p>

<milestone ed="JG" unit="Card"/>

<p>Women bathing, as represented by an unnamed hand in the Group on a stamnos in Munich (<rs key="Perseus:object:Munich 2411" type="vase">Munich 2411</rs>; <figure n="1990.34.0541" rend="float"></figure>; drawing <figure n="1990.33.0513.sm" rend="float"></figure>), is a far less common subject.<note anchored="true" n="77"><p>On the subject, see <bibl>R. Ginouvès, <title>Balaneutiké. Recherches sur le bain dans l'antiquité grecque</title> (Paris 1962)</bibl>.</p></note> This painter is clearly comfortable with his ability to draw the nude female body, in contrast to the often abortive attempts of early red-figure vase painters, and he has made the distinctions of age relatively clear. Such scenes may record the custom of allowing women access to the public baths at certain restricted hours.</p></div>

<div type="section" n="14"><head>Conclusion</head>

<p>In this brief essay it has been possible to mention only a selection of the broad range of subjects represented by Polygnotan painters and to introduce only a few of the individual painters in the Group. There are gifted painters among them, who show originality in style, in subject matter, and in their ability to convey emotional responses. As the defining stylistic presence in the Group, active with others from its beginning but continuing through the second of its three generations, and as the only member of the Group whose name is known from signatures, Polygnotos has been rightly given the role of eponymous hero.</p>
</div>
</body></text></TEI>
