<?xml version="1.0"?>





<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Attic Vase Painting in New England Collections</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Diana Buitron-Oliver</author>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState n="chunk" unit="entry"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    	<revisionDesc><!--
    		<change><date>5/27/09</date><respStmt><name>RS</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt>
    			<item>  
    				$Log: buitron.xml,v $
    				Revision 1.1  2009-10-08 19:10:56  rsingh04
    				began reorganizing texts module by collection.  created separate work directory in texts module to keep hopper files separate from in progress files

    				Revision 1.6  2009/06/19 19:02:02  lcerrato
    				fixed bad bibls

    				Revision 1.5  2009/05/27 15:55:16  rsingh04
    				added cvs log keyword

    			</item>
    		</change>
    	--> <change when="2014-11-13" who="Stella Dee">edited markup and assigned CTS URN</change></revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div n="1" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Bowdoin 1913.10" type="vase">Bowdoin
                        1913.10</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>UPPER PART OF A BLACK-FIGURE AMPHORISKOS</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Bowdoin College Museum of Art; gift of E. P. Warren
                        (1913.10)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 4 3/8 in. (11 cm.); <hi rend="bold">Diameter:</hi> 4 3/8 in. (11 cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Broken and repaired; missing pieces restored and painted; surface
                        worn in places.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="preservation" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Neck, handles, and part of shoulder and belly of one side
                        preserved.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">On the shoulder:</hi> panther and
                        swan. On one side, a panther with body in profile, face frontal; on the
                        other side, a swan with wings outstretched. In the field, incised dot
                        rosettes. At the handles, palmettes with tendrils ending in a lotus bud. On
                        each side of the neck, dot rosettes bracketed by pairs of vertical wavy
                        lines.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">On the body:</hi> animal friezes. In
                        the upper zone, a griffin-bird (head, neck, and part of wing preserved), a
                        panther, and a ram (forepart of body). In the field, dot rosettes. In the
                        zone below, the upper parts of a swan and a panther.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red:</hi> worn in places, used for
                        anatomical articulation, e. g. shoulder of panther, wings of crane.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Unattributed ca. 610 - 550 B. C.</p>
                    <p>The black-figure technique, characterized by decoration in black
                        glaze with added red and white paint as well as incision, originated in
                        Corinth during the early seventh century B. C. and was introduced into
                        Attica about a generation later where it flourished until the end of the
                        sixth century. This fragment shows much Corinthian influence and is dated by
                        comparison with Corinthian vases. The application of the palmettes to the
                        base of the handles was infrequent before the second quarter of the sixth
                        century, and the type of panther and swan also support this date (<bibl>Payne 1931, 67, 76, 152</bibl>). The shape
                        is paralleled by Corinthian amphoriskoi.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p>
                        <bibl>Herbert 1964, 56, no. 141</bibl>
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Yale 1913.102" type="vase">Yale
                    1913.102</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>BLACK-FIGURE KOMAST CUP</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Yale University Art Gallery; gift of Rebecca
                        Darlington Stoddard (1913.102)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 3 7/16 in. (8.7 cm.);
                            <hi rend="bold">Width:</hi> 7 9/16 in. (19.3 cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Broken and repaired.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Interior:</hi> black.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Exterior, side A:</hi> komos. Three
                        youths dancing; the central youth holds a drinking horn. In the field,
                        rosettes.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side B:</hi> a man and two youths
                        dancing; the central youth holds a drinking horn. In the field, rosettes.</p>
                    <p>Under the handles, rosettes with volutes; on the lip, rosettes;
                        at the base, rays.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red:</hi> costumes of the dancers,
                        parts of the rosettes and palmettes.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to the KY Painter of the Komast Group [Beazley] ca.
                        590 - 570 B. C.</p>
                    <p>Komast cups are the earliest Attic kylikes in black-figure. The
                        form of the cup, with short offset lip and short conical foot, is similar to
                        that of Corinthian cups but lightened and improved. The komasts, or padded
                        dancers, are also of Corinthian origin; they are one of the favorite
                        subjects on these cups and give the group its name (<bibl>Beazley 1951, 19-21</bibl>). The palmette ornament
                        beneath the handle is also Corinthian, but the thin stems and heavy ends of
                        the volutes are distinctly Attic (<bibl>Payne
                            1931, 198</bibl>).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p>
                        <bibl>Baur 1922, 69, no. 102, pl. III below,
                            fig. 21 right.</bibl>
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Bowdoin 1913.25.1-3" type="vase">Bowdoin
                        1913.25.1-3</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>THREE FRAGMENTS OF A "TYRRHENIAN" AMPHORA</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Bowdoin College Museum of Art; gift of E. P. Warren
                        (1913.25.1 - 3)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>1. <hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 4 3/4 in. (12 cm.);
                            <hi rend="bold">Width:</hi> 8 1/4 in. (21 cm.)</p>
                    <p>.2 <hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 5 1/2 in. (14 cm.);
                            <hi rend="bold">Width:</hi> 7 1/4 in. (18.5 cm.)</p>
                    <p>.3 <hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 5 1/8 in. (13 cm.);
                            <hi rend="bold">Width:</hi> 4 3/4 in. (12 cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>All three fragments broken and repaired; missing pieces restored
                        and painted on .2 and .3; evidence of misfiring on .1. From Cervetri.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="preservation" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Part of the shoulder on both sides and part of the belly on one
                        side preserved.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Shoulder:</hi> on both sides, a
                        fight.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Fragment .1:</hi> a group of three
                        warriors and a horseman. Two warriors, attacking a third between them, are
                        nude save for greaves (shin guards), helmets, baldric, and scabbard. The
                        warrior on the left holds his shield with his right arm and his javelin with
                        his left, a reversal of the usual hoplite position. The decorated armband
                        (porpax) and leather handle (antilabe) of his shield are thus evident. The
                        warrior on the right holds his shield, properly, on his left arm and attacks
                        with javelin in his right hand. He wears a Chalcidian helmet; the other two
                        helmets are Corinthian. The warrior in the center, dressed in a short tunic
                        (chitoniskos) with baldric and scabbard visible, holds out an empty right
                        hand, and his shield is on the ground. On the far right a horseman
                        approaches.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Fragment .2:</hi> three warriors. A
                        warrior wearing corslet and greaves, carrying a shield (device: rosette),
                        attacks a warrior of whom only one leg is preserved. In the center a warrior
                        dressed in greaves and Corinthian helmet, sword swinging behind him, and
                        javelin in hand, grasps the crest of a warrior who tries to run away. Since
                        he holds his shield with his right arm, the inside is again visible.
                        Meaningless inscriptions.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Fragment .3:</hi> horsemen. This
                        fragment preserves a piece of the narrower register below the shoulder
                        scene; the knee of a fallen warrior in the upper frieze is visible. The
                        subsidiary band is here decorated with galloping horsemen and a meaningless
                        inscription.</p>
                    <p>Above and below the shoulder scene are double borders of ivy
                        leaves, alternately red and black.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red:</hi> pieces of the armor, e. g.
                        helmet, shield, corslet; parts of the horse's anatomy, e.g. breast,
                    mane.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to the "Tyrrhenian" Group [Beazley] ca. 575 - 550 B.
                        C.</p>
                    <p>"Tyrrhenian" vases have been found almost exclusively in Etruria,
                        and although they were at first mistakenly associated with Corinth, their
                        Attic character has been clearly demonstrated by Thiersch (<bibl>Thiersch 1899</bibl>). These vases were made
                        in Attica for the Etruscan market. Their characteristics have been redefined
                        by D. von Bothmer (<bibl><title>AJA</title> 48 [1944] 161 ff</bibl>). The production of
                        "Tyrrhenian" vases is limited to the second quarter of the sixth century.
                        The shape is generally an ovoid neck-amphora with echinus foot. The
                        decorative formula consists of a narrative shoulder frieze with subsidiary
                        bands of animals or secondary narrative friezes below; at the bottom are
                        rays. D. von Bothmer has observed (orally) that this vase is unusual in its
                        use of ivy borders above and below the shoulder scenes, as well as the
                        subsidiary narrative frieze on the belly (cf <rs type="vase">Berlin F 1712</rs>; <bibl>ABV, 96, no.
                        12</bibl>). The style is lively though frequently rough and careless, and
                        the inscriptions do not usually make sense as in this case.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>ABV, 100, no. 71</bibl>; <bibl>Herbert 1964, 56-57, no. 142.</bibl></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:RISD 35.013" type="vase">RISD 35.013</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>BLACK-FIGURE SIANA CUP</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Museum of Art, Rhode Island School of Design
                        (1935.013)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 5 1/16 in. (12.9 cm.);
                            <hi rend="bold">Diameter:</hi> 10 7/8 in. (27.6 cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Broken and repaired; worn especially on side B. At one handle
                        evidence of ancient repair; a small piece of bronze rivet remains.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Interior:</hi> lion. His head is
                        turned back with mouth opened as if roaring. A border of framed tongues
                        alternating red and black circles the tondo.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Exterior, side A:</hi> departure of
                        a warrior. A youth dressed in chitoniskos and holding a javelin rides a
                        horse moving to the right. In front, a gesticulating nude youth and a youth
                        wrapped in a mantle; behind, a gesticulating nude youth and a youth wrapped
                        in a mantle and holding a javelin. At the handles, two sphinxes. Behind the
                        rider, a bird.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side B:</hi> the same. However, the
                        nude youth behind the rider carries a javelin, and neither of the draped
                        figures is armed. Below the scene, a reserved line; at the handles, inverted
                        lotus buds; at the base, rays.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red:</hi> the lion's mane, fillets
                        and parts of the wings of the sphinxes, parts of the drapery, hair of three
                        youths.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">White:</hi> parts of the drapery,
                        chiton of central rider, sphinxes' flesh, horses' manes and tails (much
                        worn).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Unattributed ca. 550 - 540 B. C.</p>
                    <p>Siana cups, so named because two well-known examples were found
                        at Siana on Rhodes, are the dominant type of kylix in the second quarter of
                        the sixth century. The shape is a continuation of the Komast cup (<rs type="vase">Yale 1913.102</rs>), but the foot and lip are
                        longer. Unlike the Komast cup, the inside of the Siana cup is also
                        decorated, beginning the long tradition of tondo pictures. The decoration on
                        this cup is of the overlap type with the scene extending into the offset
                        lip. J. Frel suggested a comparison with a Siana cup in Prague (<rs type="vase">Prague 18,52 K 1241</rs>; <bibl>ABV, 682</bibl>) by the Civico Painter which shows a
                        similar scene.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p>
                        <bibl>Luce 1936, no. 3, p. 36, fig. 1.</bibl>
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:RISD 34.858" type="vase">RISD 34.858</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>BLACK-FIGURE LIP CUP</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Museum of Art, Rhode Island School of Design; gift of
                        Mrs. Murray S. Danforth (1934.858)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 3 3/16 in. (8.1 cm.);
                            <hi rend="ital">diameter of lip:</hi> 4 3/4 in. (12.1
                    cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>One handle broken and repaired; glaze flaking in places.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Interior:</hi> small reserved disk
                        with a black dot and circle.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Exterior, on the lip, side A:</hi>
                        winged lion between two men. One man is hard to make out as the glaze has
                        worn off. The other, with chlamys over one shoulder, attacks a winged lion
                        with stones. The lion, which has a partially obliterated head, turns
                        backwards toward the man attacking from its rear.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">On the lip, side B:</hi> man between
                        dog and sphinx. A man, nude except for a chlamys draped over one shoulder,
                        defends himself against a sphinx at whom he seems to throw a rock. Behind
                        him is a dog who is either helping or attacking the man.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Handle zone, on both sides:</hi> an
                        inscription, <foreign xml:lang="greek">xaire kai pi'
                        thnde</foreign> (welcome and drink this); beside the handles, small upright
                        palmettes supported by volute tendrils which develop from the base of the
                        handles.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red:</hi> details of wings, breasts,
                        hair, and tail of the sphinxes; ruff and anatomical articulation of the dog;
                        chlamys and hair of the men; details of the palmettes.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">White:</hi> breasts and faces of the
                        sphinxes, details of their wings; traces of white on the chlamides of the
                        men; details of the palmettes.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Unattributed ca. 540 - 530 B. C.</p>
                    <p>The decoration corresponds to one of the usual formulas for lip
                        cups (see <bibl>Beazley, <title>JHS</title> 52 [1932] 167 ff</bibl>). The inscription in the handle
                        zone is often a welcoming toast as here; it may also tell us who the potter
                        or painter was. Little Master cups, so called because of their miniature
                        style of drawing, were the dominant cup form in the middle through the third
                        quarter of the sixth century. The Attic Siana cup is their forerunner (see
                        No. 4), and their descendants are the great red-figure cups of the fifth
                        century.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Luce 1936, no. 3, p. 36, fig.
                        2</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Bowdoin 1930.35" type="vase">Bowdoin
                        1930.35</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>FRAGMENT OF A LIP CUP</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Bowdoin College Museum of Art; gift of E. P. Warren
                        (1930.35)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 13/16 in. (2 cm.); <hi rend="bold">Width:</hi> 2 in. (5.1 cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Fragment from the lip showing a ram walking to the right.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red:</hi> ruff of neck, top of head,
                        breast, back, rear, and thigh muscles.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Unattributed ca. 540 - 530 B. C.</p>
                    <p>This ram is a more sturdy version of a ram on the lip cup in the
                        Louvre by the Tleson Painter (<rs type="vase">Louvre F 86</rs>;
                            <bibl>Pottier 1922, pl. 69</bibl>).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Herbert 1964, 57, no.
                        145</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Bowdoin 1915.45" type="vase">Bowdoin
                        1915.45</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>BLACK-FIGURE BAND CUP</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Bowdoin College Museum of Art; gift of E. P. Warren
                        (1915.45)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 4 1/16 in. (10.3 cm.);
                            <hi rend="ital">diameter of lip:</hi> 5 1/2 in. (14
                    cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Broken and repaired at handles; missing piece at the rim;
                        restored and painted.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Interior:</hi> small, reserved disk
                        with a black dot and circle.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Exterior:</hi> the lip is glazed
                        black. In the handle zone on either side, two horsemen dressed in tunics
                        gallop to the right, the manes and tails of their mounts streaming behind
                        them. Exhaustion is suggested by open mouths and starting eyes.</p>
                    <p>Small upright palmettes develop from the bases of the handles.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red:</hi> the mane of one horse,
                        hearts and central leaf of palmettes.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Unattributed ca. 540 - 530 B. C.</p>
                    <p>The brief decoration of the handle zone is uncommon; more
                        characteristic is a many-figured picture running from handle to handle
                            (<bibl>Beazley, <title>JHS</title> 52 [1932] 187</bibl>). There is also frequently a fillet
                        between the base and the stem. A band cup (<rs type="vase">Copenhagen 61</rs>; <bibl>ABV, 190, no.
                        16</bibl>) by the Centaur Painter is similar to this one — the horses
                        have the same weighty tails, and the decoration of the handle zone is
                        similarly brief.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Herbert 1964, 57-58, no. 146,
                            pl. 21 below</bibl>; <bibl>P. B. Wilson,
                            "Home Forum," <title>Christian Science Monitor</title>
                            (March 12, 1971) 12</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Harvard 1925.30.125" type="vase">Harvard
                        1925.30.125</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>BLACK-FIGURE COLUMN-KRATER</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Fogg Art Museum, Harvard University; bequest of J. C.
                        Hoppin (1925.30.125)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 13 2/16 in. (33.4 cm.);
                            <hi rend="ital">diameter of rim:</hi> 14 in. (35.6 cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Broken and repaired; glaze worn in places. The numerous rivet
                        holes result from ancient repairs; bronze rivets would have connected the
                        broken pieces.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side A:</hi> frontal chariot. The
                        charioteer, in long chiton and brimmed hat, holds the chariot in readiness.
                        On either side a group of warriors fight; on the left one attacks and the
                        other tries to escape; on the right one lunges against the other who has
                        fallen to his knee. All wear corslets, greaves, Corinthian helmets, and
                        carry Boeotian shields. The shield of the warrior on the far right has a
                        particularly noteworthy device; it consists of the forepart of a threatening
                        snake shown in the round. Two birds fill the spandrils between the horses'
                        heads. The symmetry is pervasive but varied.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side B:</hi> a sphinx between two
                        lions with averted heads. The symmetry is enhanced by the balancing curves
                        of the lions' tails and the tendrils ending in lotus buds which fill the
                        space beneath the lions. Incision describes the texture of the lions' manes.
                        On both handle plates, sphinxes; around the rim, lotus buds. Above the
                        figured panels, alternating red and black framed tongues; below, two red
                        lines which circle the vase.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red, side A:</hi> helmets and
                        greaves of the warriors, the insides of two shields, the upper part of the
                        charioteer's chiton, and the wings of the birds. <hi rend="bold">Side B:</hi> wings and thigh muscles of the sphinx, her
                        fillet; faces, breasts, and thigh muscles of the lions. <hi rend="bold">On the rim:</hi> wings, faces, and muscles of the sphinxes,
                        buds of the lotuses.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to Lydos [Rumpf] ca. 565 B. C.</p>
                    <p>The name of Lydos is known from two vases, one in Athens (<rs type="vase">Athens, Acr. 607</rs>; <bibl>ABV, 107, no. 1</bibl>) and one in the Louvre (<rs type="vase">Louvre F 29</rs>; <bibl>ABV, 109, no. 21</bibl>); in each case he signs as
                        painter. Payne places the vase with the early work of Lydos, probably in the
                        middle of the second quarter of the sixth century (<bibl>Payne 1931, 346, n. 1</bibl>). Beazley in his discussion
                        of this krater says that the motif of the frontal chariot may have been
                        originally Corinthian; it reached Attica early in the sixth century and was
                        greatly favored by black-figure artists (<bibl>Beazley 1951, 43</bibl>). The shape, so called because of its columnar
                        handles, is probably also of Corinthian origin. The wide body, short neck,
                        and echinus foot of the present example point to an early stage of
                        development.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>CVA, USA 1, pl. 3</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley, Review <title>CVA</title> USA 1 by Hoppin, <hi rend="ital">JHS</hi> 47
                            (1927) 148-149</bibl>; <bibl>C. Albizzati,
                            "Tre Opere d'un Ceramografo d'Atene ai tempi di Pisistrato," <title>Historia</title> 3 (Milan 1929) 81 ff, fig. 2, p.
                        83</bibl>; <bibl>Thieme &amp; Becker 1929,
                            23, 491, no. 9</bibl>; <bibl>Deonna 193,
                            234, fig. 3, 6, p. 235, fig. 4, 7</bibl>; <bibl>Rumpf 1947, pl. 12 c</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley 1951, 43-44</bibl>; <bibl>ABV, 108, no. 9</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Bowdoin 1930.36" type="vase">Bowdoin
                        1930.36</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>BLACK-FIGURE FRAGMENT</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Bowdoin College Museum of Art; gift of E. P. Warren
                        (1930.36)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 1 3/8 in. (3.5 cm.);
                            <hi rend="bold">Width:</hi> 2 9/16 in. (6.5 cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>The fragment has been burned. The inside is glazed black.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>The head of a horse is preserved with the muzzle of a second
                        horse beyond. On the right a detail is visible of the cumbersome yoke
                        equipment with which the horses will be harnessed.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Unattributed ca. 550 - 540 B. C.</p>
                    <p>The fabric of this fragment is quite thick and suggests a large
                        vase, probably a calyx-krater. The horses recall those by Exekias (<bibl>Beazley 1951, pl. 29, 31</bibl>). The shape,
                        identified by D. von Bothmer, supports a date in the third quarter of the
                        sixth century. The bridle running over the mane, rather than under it, is
                        unusual and must be taken into consideration for any attribution. The yoke
                        equipment (identified by D. von Bothmer) suggests that the subject is a
                        harnessing scene.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Herbert 1964, 58-59, no.
                        150</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Harvard 1972.42" type="vase">Harvard
                        1972.42</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>BLACK-FIGURE PANEL AMPHORA (TYPE B)</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by Frederick M. Watkins</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 17 in. (43.2 cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Broken and repaired; missing pieces restored and painted.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side A:</hi> Herakles and Geryon.
                        Herakles, dressed in lion skin over chitoniskos, fights Geryon, the triple
                        bodied monster who lived in regions farthest west and was rich in cattle
                            (<bibl n="Apollod. 2.10">Apollod.
                        2.10</bibl>). Herakles was sent to fetch the cattle as his tenth labor and
                        succeeded in killing not only Geryon's herdsman, Eurytion, shown fallen at
                        Herakles' feet, but also the monster's two-headed dog, Orthros, at Geryon's
                        feet, and Geryon himself. Geryon is conceived as having three bodies joined
                        at the waist. Each wears greaves and a high crested Corinthian helmet (two
                        are visible; the top of the third is partly hidden), and each carries a
                        shield.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side B:</hi> arming. In the center a
                        man puts on a greave; at his feet is his Corinthian helmet. On either side
                        are spectators: to the left a man in himation and a man in chiton and
                        himation, to the right a woman in peplos and a nude man.</p>
                    <p>Above on side A, palmette festoon; on side B, palmette chain; at
                        the base are rays.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red, on side A:</hi> Herakles'
                        chiton and the edge of the lion skin; Eurytion's beard and chiton; Geryon's
                        greaves, helmets, and shield rims; Orthros' ruff. <hi rend="bold">On side B:</hi> the men's hair and two beards, parts of
                        their drapery, the woman's hair and parts of her peplos. The cuffs of the
                        palmettes, the frames of the panels, the edge of the base, and the edge of
                        the mouth.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to Group E [Beazley] ca. 550 - 530 B. C.</p>
                    <p>Group E is the name given by Beazley to "a large and compact
                        group which is very closely related to the work of the painter Exekias,
                        though earlier. . ., the soil from which the art of Exekias springs" (<bibl>ABV, 133</bibl>). The battle of Herakles and
                        Geryon is one of their favorite subjects and is found on at least nine other
                        amphorae with much the same composition. Compare <rs type="vase">Würzburg L 245</rs> (<bibl>Langlotz 1932, pl. 79</bibl>) where the drawing is
                        neater, the shepherd Eurytion is partly fallen and the dog Orthros is
                        missing.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>ABV, 133, no. 8</bibl>; <bibl>Hôtel Drouot, <title>Collection Hirsch</title> (June 30 - July 2, 1921) 20, no. 141, pl.
                            6</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Harvard 1960.312" type="vase">Harvard
                        1960.312</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>BLACK-FIGURE NECK-AMPHORA</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Fogg Art Museum, Harvard University; bequest of D. M.
                        Robinson (1960.312)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 16 1/8 in. (41 cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Broken and repaired; missing pieces restored and painted.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side A:</hi> Theseus and the
                        Minotaur. Theseus, the legendary hero of Attica, battles the Minotaur, the
                        monster kept by King Minos at Crete and to whom fourteen Athenians, seven
                        men and seven girls, were sent as tribute every nine years. Theseus, dressed
                        in chitoniskos and animal skin, grasps the Minotaur with one arm and stabs
                        it with a short sword. The Minotaur, a man with a bull's head, has fallen to
                        one knee and turns its head away from Theseus. On either side is a female
                        spectator, probably two of the seven girls sent as tribute. They are dressed
                        in embroidered peploi.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side B:</hi> Herakles and the Nemean
                        Lion. The first labor of Herakles was to fight the invulnerable Nemean Lion.
                        The hero is shown nude except for baldric and scabbard. He holds the lion
                        around the neck and strangles it to death (<bibl n="Apollod. 2.1">Apollod. 2.1</bibl>). On the left, Iolaos,
                        Herakles' companion, moves away looking back; on the right Athena, in peplos
                        and helmet, holds a shield (device: tripod).</p>
                    <p>On the shoulder on either side, two cocks between two hens. Above
                        them, alternating red and black framed tongues. On the neck, palmette-lotus
                        chain. At the handles, tendrils, palmettes, and lotuses. Below the scene,
                        bands of decoration separated by lines: crosses inside half circles
                        separated by vertical lines, lotus buds, red band, rays.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red:</hi> hair and beard of Theseus,
                        beard of Herakles and Iolaos, face and breast of the Minotaur, mane of the
                        lion, parts of the women's peploi, Theseus' chitoniskos, parts of the wings
                        of the fowl, combs and gullets of the roosters, leaves of the palmettes,
                        cuffs of the lotuses, wreath of Athena, upper edge of mouth.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">White:</hi> female flesh, spots on
                        the Minotaur, hilts of the swords, baldrics of the heroes, dots on the edges
                        of the drapery, device on Athena's shield, base of her helmet plume.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>"Near Exekias" [Beazley] ca. 550 - 530 B. C.</p>
                    <p>The subjects on both sides are especially popular during the
                        middle and third quarter of the sixth century. (On Theseus and the Minotaur
                        see <rs type="vase">Harvard 1963.69</rs>.) Apollodoros tells us
                        that after Herakles strangled the lion, he skinned it with its own claws. He
                        very frequently appears dressed in the lion skin in vase paintings (see
                            <bibl>Buitron 1972, no. 10</bibl>).</p>
                    <p>A neck-amphora (<rs type="vase">Berlin F 1720</rs>;
                            <bibl>ABV, 143, no. 1</bibl>) signed by
                        Exekias as potter and painter might be compared with this vase. The greater
                        care with detail and more vigorous action show the difference between the
                        master and the follower.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>ABV, 148</bibl>; <bibl>Robinson 1956, 60 (1956) 7-9, no. 8, pl.
                        5</bibl>; <bibl>Robinson Exhibition 1961, no.
                        66</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 62</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Harvard 1963.69" type="vase">Harvard
                        1963.69</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>BLACK-FIGURE HYDRIA</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Fogg Art Museum, Harvard University; bequest of Edith
                        J. Purrington (1963.69)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 17 5/16 in. (44
                    cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Broken and repaired; missing pieces restored and painted.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Theseus and the Minotaur. Theseus, dressed in loincloth with a
                        fillet in his long hair, grasps the horn of the Minotaur with one hand and
                        stabs him with a short sword. The Minotaur falls to one knee, raising one
                        arm to throw a rock. On either side stand a youth and a girl, the companions
                        of Theseus, raising their arms in alarm. Each youth is nude but for a
                        chlamys over his arm; the girls wear peploi, mantles, and fillets in their
                        hair.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">On the shoulder:</hi> komos. Four
                        pairs of dancing satyrs and maenads. The satyrs are nude and have bushy
                        tails. The maenads wear peploi and have fillets in their hair. Double rows
                        of ivy and corymboi (ivy berries) frame the main panel laterally. Above the
                        shoulder scene, alternately red and black framed tongues.</p>
                    <p>Red is used in the design areas and to articulate parts of the
                        shape.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red:</hi> the men's hair, the
                        Minotaur's mane, fillets, upper parts of peploi, traces on mantles of girls,
                        loincloth of Theseus, breast of the Minotaur and youth to far right. Two
                        lines running all around the vase at the base of the scene, narrow ridges on
                        the upper and lower edges of the mouth, ends of the half spools attaching
                        the vertical handle to the lip, three narrow mouldings on the foot, line on
                        comes of foot, fillet between base and foot.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">White:</hi> traces on female
                    flesh.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Unattributed 550 - 530 B.C.</p>
                    <p>In shape and in style this hydria is close to two hydriai in the
                        Louvre (<rs type="vase">Louvre F 38</rs> and <rs type="vase">Louvre F 39</rs>) signed by Timagoras as potter and
                        attributed to the Taleides Painter. The shape with broad belly and sloping
                        shoulder, gently offset, is popular just after the middle of the sixth
                        century. The mouth, handles, and foot which are sturdy and elaborate imply
                        metal work prototypes. The subject, the legendary slaying of the Minotaur
                        which ended the tribute Athens paid to Crete, reached its height of
                        popularity with Attic vase painters during the third quarter of the sixth
                        century. At this time a canonical scheme for its representation was
                        established. This hydria is an excellent example of the canon. The action
                        has lost its vigor and has acquired a ceremonial character. (Compare with
                            <rs type="vase">Harvard 1960.312</rs> which is more
                        vigorous.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Unpublished.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Harvard 1977.216.2244" type="vase">Harvard
                        1977.216.2244</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>BLACK-FIGURE PANEL AMPHORA (TYPE B)</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Fogg Art Museum, Harvard University; bequest of H.W.
                        Haynes (CC 2244)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 14 13/16 in. (37.7
                    cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Broken and repaired; missing pieces restored and painted.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side A:</hi> assembly of gods. Zeus
                        is seated on a throne and holds a javelin in one hand. Hermes with caduceus
                        approaches from the right; Poseidon holding trident and fish stands to the
                        left. At the far right stands another god, perhaps Dionysos since he wears
                        the skin of a feline. At the far left is a youth with garlands, perhaps
                        Ganymede. Zeus sits on an elegant throne with a slightly curved back ending
                        in a swan's head; it has low hand rails supported on columns, and a sphinx
                        resting on stretchers between legs which end in lion's paws. On the ground
                        beneath the throne is a hare. Hanging above from their forepaws are a dead
                        hare and fox. Suspended in the field are fillets.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side B:</hi> assembly of gods. Zeus
                        with javelin and Poseidon with trident and fish face each other in the
                        center. To the right is a nude youth; to the left, a youth with a javelin.
                        Behind him is a bearded man carrying a fish. He may be Nereus, the old man
                        of the sea. Again the field is punctuated with hanging fillets. A dead hare
                        hangs by his forepaws at one side of the scene. Both panels are framed above
                        by a lotus chain with points downward. On side B there are dots in the
                        interstices above the lotus flowers. At the base are staggered rays which
                        are a favorite of this painter.</p>
                    <p>Red and white are used profusely to articulate parts of the shape
                        as well as of the figure scenes.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red:</hi> drapery ornament and
                        folds, fillets, hair, petasos, animal skins, breasts of the nude men, tails
                        and breasts of the animals, wings and hair of the sphinx, and the fillets
                        which litter the field. On the upper rim and base of the lip, on the foot, a
                        line around the inside of the lip, lines circling the vase at the base of
                        the scene, lines above and below the zone with rays.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">White:</hi> frame of the throne,
                        dots of the wreaths, fillets, dots of the rosettes on the drapery, dots on
                        the baldrics, face of the sphinx, and breast of the fox and hare.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to the Affecter [Chase] ca. 550 - 530 B.C.</p>
                    <p>The Affecter is chief among the black-figure mannerists, a group
                        of painters who carry formalism to an extreme and who retain traditional
                        stylistic elements (e. g. profuse use of red and white, attention to
                        decorative detail). Although his oeuvre is large, there is little variation
                        within it, and one finds the same large trunks and long skinny limbs
                        everywhere. His figured panels are frequently crowded and unclear, and
                        narrative clarity tends to give way before the emphasis on decorative detail
                        (see <bibl>Beazley 1928a, 23, 37-38</bibl> and
                            <bibl>Karo 1899, 147-163</bibl>).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>CVA, USA 8, pl. 7, 2</bibl>;
                            <bibl>ABV, 245, no. 64</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Boston 01.8037" type="vase">Boston
                    01.8037</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>PANEL AMPHORA (TYPE A)</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Museum of Fine Arts, Boston (01.8037)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 21 13/16 in. (55.36
                        cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Missing parts restored and repainted. Beneath the foot, Etruscan
                        graffito. From Orvieto.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Bilingual:</hi>one side red-figure,
                        one side black-figure.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side A:</hi> red-figure, Achilles
                        and Ajax playing. The two heroes sit at a gaming table on which small disks
                        (pessoi) are arranged. On the left is Achilles and on the right, Ajax. This
                        identification is suggested by the earliest inscribed representation of the
                        scene on an amphora by Exekias (<rs type="vase">Vatican
                        344</rs>; <bibl>ABV, 145, no. 13</bibl>). The
                        game consisted of throwing dice and moving according to the cast. On this
                        vase Achilles is preparing to move, while Ajax, who has just finished,
                        indicates his score with his fingers. Both heroes wear black chitoniskoi,
                        elaborately decorated cloaks, bronze corslets, greaves, and Corinthian
                        helmets with crest overlapping into the palmette chain above. Each holds two
                        javelins. Behind each, a shield. The gaming table is topped with a slab
                        ending in volutes beneath which there is a band of egg pattern between two
                        bands of dots.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Restored:</hi> the shields; parts of
                        the stools; the back, shoulder, right calf, and foot of Achilles; the lower
                        back of Ajax. The restorations are visible in the photographs.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side B:</hi> black-figure, the same
                        subject with minor differences in details. A simpler gaming table topped
                        with a slab with torus molding. Ajax and Achilles sit on stools and are
                        dressed in the same armor as on side A with the addition of cushes (thigh
                        guards). Ajax has a short sword at his waist. Behind, shields with helmets
                        above them. The device on Ajax's shield is a rosette between lions
                        regardant.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Restored:</hi> the heads of both
                        heroes, the device on Achilles' shield, part of Ajax's helmet.</p>
                    <p>Side A is framed above by a lotus-palmette chain; laterally, by a
                        net pattern with two knots; and below, by lotus buds and dots. Side B is
                        similarly framed above and below, but there are no lateral borders. On the
                        handles, ivy; below the handles, hanging palmettes; at the base, rays. The
                        ornament on both sides is probably by the Lysippides Painter.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red, side A:</hi> beards, dots of
                        the drapery, rectangles of stools, edges of shields, attachments for the
                        helmets, the eight pessoi on the gaming table, the hearts of the palmettes,
                        the cuffs of the lotuses. <hi rend="bold">Side B:</hi>
                        decoration of the drapery and armor, Achilles' beard, fillets, edges of
                        helmets, plumes, shields, the twelve pessoi on the table, the line on the
                        table. Line at the base of the scene, two lines around the vase below the
                        framing ornament, line above the zone with rays, the fillet between base and
                        foot, edges of the handles, upper edge of the lip.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">White, side B:</hi> the lions on
                        Ajax's shield.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to the Andokides Painter [Furtwängler] [Beazley
                        at first attributed both sides to the Lysippides Painter; he later decided
                        that only side B was by the Lysippides Painter, and side A was by the
                        Andokides Painter (<bibl>ABV, 254</bibl>)] ca.
                        530 B.C.</p>
                    <p>The shape of this amphora is close to nine amphorae signed by
                        Andokides as potter, and it is possible that the artist who painted the
                        red-figure side of this vase, the Andokides Painter, is the same man. The
                        Andokides Painter was one of the first to use the red-figure technique, and
                        it is likely that he was its originator (<bibl>von Bothmer 1966, 201-212</bibl>). The red-figure technique is seen
                        here in its early stages: there is more red and more incision than in the
                        developed technique; the relief line work is imperfect, and contour bands
                        are scarcely used (<bibl>Caskey &amp;
                            Beazley, 3, p. 7</bibl>). The detail is meticulous; note the tiny
                        palmettes in the corners of the helmets. The vase has been placed
                        stylistically in the middle period of the Andokides Painter's oeuvre, during
                        the second decade of the sixth century (<bibl>D.
                            von Bothmer, <title>BMMA</title> [February, 1966]
                        212</bibl> and <bibl>Caskey &amp; Beazley,
                            3, p. 7</bibl>). The Lysippides Painter, so called for a kalos or love
                        name on a neck-amphora in London (<rs type="vase">London B
                        211</rs>), was a black-figure artist and a follower of Exekias. He
                        collaborated with the Andokides Painter on six amphorae and one cup and was
                        also a prominent black-figure artist in his own right.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Norton 1896, 40-41, figs.
                        15-16</bibl>; <bibl>Caskey 1922, 60-61</bibl>;
                            <bibl>Richter 1926, fig. 122, p. 44</bibl>;
                            <bibl>Fairbanks &amp; Chase 1948, fig.
                            72</bibl>; <bibl>Rumpf 1953, 60-61, pl. 16,
                            1-2</bibl>; <bibl>ABV, 254, no. 2</bibl>;
                            <bibl>Schauenburg 1961, 64-65, figs.
                        20-21</bibl>; <bibl>ARV2, 4, no. 7 and p.
                        1617</bibl>; <bibl>Caskey &amp; Beazley, 3,
                            p. 1-7</bibl>; <bibl>Richter 1966, fig.
                        259</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 113, 320</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Harvard 1960.308" type="vase">Harvard
                        1960.308</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>FRAGMENT OF A PANEL AMPHORA</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Fogg Art Museum, Harvard University; bequest of D. M.
                        Robinson (1960.308)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 11 1/2 in. (24.2 cm.);
                            <hi rend="bold">Width:</hi> 18 3/4 in. (47.6 cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Broken and repaired; missing pieces restored and painted; the
                        grooves or channels for rivets on right and left are presumably for ancient
                        repairs. From Athens?</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Harnessing a chariot. At the left, a nude man holds the reins of
                        the two pole horses. A warrior, armed in Corinthian helmet and greaves,
                        leads a trace horse forward to be harnessed. Next to him the charioteer, in
                        long white chiton, works on the reins of the pole horses. Only the legs are
                        preserved of the fourth man who stands to the right at the horses' heads.
                        Above, palmette-lotus chain; below, leftward key meander and two red lines.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red:</hi> manes of two horses, the
                        tail of one horse, the box of the chariot, the beards of two men, the
                        chiton, greaves, and plume of the warrior, hearts of the palmettes, cuffs of
                        the lotuses.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">White:</hi> the charioteer's
                    chiton.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to the Antimenes Painter [D. M. Robinson] ca. 530 -
                        500 B.C.</p>
                    <p>The bridle of the trace horse being led up for harnessing runs
                        over the mane rather than under it. This is rare, as has been indicated (see
                            <rs type="vase">Bowdoin 1930.36</rs>).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>CVA, USA 4, pl. 30, p. 46,
                        2</bibl>; <bibl>ABV, 274, no. 129</bibl>; <bibl>Robinson Exhibition 1961, no. 67</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Wellesley 1961.5" type="vase">Wellesley
                        1961.5</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>BLACK-FIGURE HYDRIA</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Wellesley College Art Museum (1961.5)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 17 1/2 in. (44.4
                    cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Broken and repaired at lip, handles, and neck. Under foot,
                        graffito.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Women at the fountain. Seven women, all but one carrying hydriae
                        on their heads, gossip animatedly on their way to and from a fountain house.
                        They are dressed in richly embroidered peploi, and four of them wear himatia
                        as well. The two at the left have arrived at the fountain house, and one is
                        filling her hydria from the lion's head water-spout. Her companion, with
                        empty hydria still on her head, waits her turn. The fountain house is
                        represented by a white Doric column with entablature, a base on which to put
                        the hydria, a trough running beside this base, and a lion's head waterspout.
                        Of the other women, two are approaching with empty hydriae, and three are
                        leaving, their vertically balanced hydriae on their heads.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">In the predella:</hi> a hunt. Four
                        youths attack a hapless doe; one javelin has already pierced her breast.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">On the shoulder:</hi> a fight. Two
                        warriors attack a third. All wear Corinthian helmets and carry shields and
                        javelins. The warrior to the right has a raven device on his shield. At the
                        right and left two women, gesticulating anxiously and looking back, run away
                        from the fight.</p>
                    <p>The main scene is framed laterally by double rows of ivy and
                        below by a red line. Two red lines circling the vase form the base of the
                        predella. The shoulder scene is bordered above by framed tongues,
                        alternately red and black. At the base of the vase are rays enclosed by a
                        red line above and a fillet painted red at the juncture of base and foot.
                        The upper edge of the foot is also red.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red:</hi> ornaments and edges of the
                        women's clothing, fillets, and the irises of their eyes; on the scene below,
                        the horses' manes and the doe's neck; on the shoulder scene, the warrior's
                        crests, one chitoniskos, the javelins, and the edges of the shields.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">White:</hi> women's flesh, dot
                        rosettes on the dresses, and the raven emblem on the shield on the shoulder,
                        Doric column of fountain house.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Unattributed ca. 530 B. C.</p>
                    <p>The hydria has been related to the Antimenes Painter by D. von
                        Bothmer. Close stylistic parallels are found in two hydriae also showing
                        women at the fountain and inscribed with the kale name Anthyle (<rs type="vase">Würzburg L 304</rs>, <rs type="vase">London B 33</rs>; <bibl>ABV,
                            676</bibl>). The subject of the main panel is closely related to the use
                        of the vessel and provides a glimpse into the everyday life of late
                        sixth-century Athens. The subject was popular with the Antimenes Painter,
                        his contemporary the Lysippides Painter, and a host of other late
                        sixth-century black-figure vase painters. A hydria in the Museum of Fine
                        Arts, Boston (<rs type="vase">Boston 61.195</rs>; <bibl>Para., 147, no. 5 bis</bibl>) published by
                        Herbert Hoffmann (<bibl><title>BMFA</title> 61 [1963] 12 ff</bibl>), shows us the actual
                        appearance of an Archaic Greek fountain house: a three-sided, colonnaded
                        court with three waterspouts on the wall of each side.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p>
                        <bibl>Shell &amp; McAndrew 1964, 113-114
                            ill.</bibl>
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Worcester 1956.83" type="vase">Worcester
                        1956.83</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>BLACK-FIGURE AMPHORA (TYPE A)</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Worcester Art Museum; Austin S. and Sarah C. Garver
                        Funds (1956.83)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 24 1/2 in. (62.2
                    cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Missing small piece of lip on reverse; abrasions on glaze on
                        reverse. Under foot, graffito.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side A:</hi> Leto mounting a
                        four-horse chariot. She is attended by her children, Apollo playing a
                        kithara, and Artemis holding a flower. Hermes stands at the heads of the
                        horses.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side B:</hi> Dionysos with satyrs
                        and maenads. The god, holding a drinking horn, stands between two maenads,
                        dressed in chitons and playing castanets (krotala), and two ithyphallic
                        satyrs. Sprays of ivy provide a festive background.</p>
                    <p>The figured panels are framed by a lotus-palmette chain above,
                        alternately upright and hanging palmettes below. On the handles are ivy
                        leaves, and below each handle is a small hanging palmette. At the base are
                        rays.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red, side A:</hi> the manes of the
                        horses, two of their tails, their harnesses, parts of the chariot, edges of
                        the garments. <hi rend="ital">Side B:</hi> the beards of the
                        men, tails of the satyrs, and the wreath of the god.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">White:</hi> the chitons of Dionysos
                        and Hermes, the flesh of the women, and parts of the kithara.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to the Rycroft Painter [Beazley] ca. 515 - 500 B.C.</p>
                    <p>Beazley has attributed thirty-three vases to the hand of the
                        Rycroft Painter, who was named for an amphora formerly in the Rycroft
                        Collection (now in the Ashmolean [<rs type="vase">Oxford
                            1965.118</rs>]; <bibl>ABV, 335, no.
                        1</bibl>). This vase also shows Leto mounting a chariot. M. H. Swindler in
                        her publication of this amphora describes the style as characterized by very
                        careful drawing and by a fine understanding of the anatomy of the horse,
                        which is rendered almost without inner detail. She compares the reverse with
                        the work of Psiax (<rs type="vase">Hartford 1961.8</rs>) and
                        places the amphora somewhere between 515 and 500 B. C., a late work of the
                        Rycroft Painter.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl><title>Worcester Art Museum Exhibitions, Films, Lectures, Concerts,
                                Classes</title> (1956)</bibl>; <bibl><title>Worcester News Bulletin and Calendar</title>
                            no. 1 (1957) ill. and no. 5 (1962) ill.</bibl>; <bibl><title>Worcester Art Museum Annual
                            Report</title> 61 (1957) 14 ill.</bibl>; <bibl>Faison 1958, 185 ill.</bibl>; <bibl>Swindler 1958, 1-7, figs. 1-9</bibl>; <bibl>Schoder 1960, no. 17 ill.</bibl></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Hartford 1961.8" type="vase">Hartford
                        1961.8</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>BLACK-FIGURE HYDRIA</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Wadsworth Athenaeum, Hartford, Connecticut; the Ella
                        Gallup Sumner and Mary Catlin Sumner Collection (1961.8)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height with handle:</hi>18 1/2 in.
                        (47 cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Broken and repaired around upper part of vertical handle; some
                        inpainting including minor details of design areas.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">On the body:</hi> harnessing a
                        four-horse chariot. On the left a man, stepping into the chariot, holds a
                        goad and the reins of the two pole horses, while a youth looks on. Another
                        youth leads a muzzled trace horse forward to be harnessed. The charioteer
                        busies himself with the harnesses of the pole horses, and a third youth
                        stands at the heads of these horses to calm them. At the charioteer's feet
                        is a dog; a bird flies in the sky above.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">On the shoulder:</hi> Herakles
                        battles Triton. Nereus, the old man of the sea, is seated to the right, and
                        two of his daughters, the Nereids, run up on the left. Herakles, astride
                        Triton, holds the monster in an iron grip from which he vainly tries to free
                        himself.</p>
                    <p>Below the main scene are alternating hanging palmettes and
                        upright lotuses; on the sides are small horizontal palmettes. The shoulder
                        is framed below by a ribbon motif, laterally, by double rows of connected
                        dots, and above, by tongues alternating red and black.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red:</hi> parts of the men's hair
                        and beards, the horses' tails and manes, drapery edges, parts of the chariot
                        and harness, and the dog's collar and tail. On the shoulder, parts of the
                        hair, Triton's scales, and edges of the drapery.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">White:</hi> the charioteer's chiton,
                        spots on the trace horse. On the shoulder, female flesh, the tender belly of
                        Triton, and the beard and hair of Nereus.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to Psiax [Beazley] ca. 530 - 500 B. C.</p>
                    <p>Psiax, though largely a black-figure artist, also painted in the
                        red-figure style; his name is known from two signed red-figure alabastra in
                        Karlsruhe and Odessa (<bibl>ARV2, 7, nos. 4 and
                            5</bibl>). He is known to have collaborated with three potters, Menon,
                        Hilinos, and Andokides, and is the stylistic brother of the prolific
                        black-figure artist, the Antimenes Painter. Compare with <rs type="vase">Harvard 1960.308</rs>; the compositions are quite similar.
                        C. C. Vermeule, in his publication of this hydria, remarks that scenes
                        involving horses are favorites with Psiax and his contemporaries. The
                        subject is probably chariot racing as the participants are not in armor. In
                        the sixth century B. C. chariots were no longer used in battle. When they
                        appear in connection with warriors, mythological heroes are suggested.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl><title>Archaeology</title> 14 (1961) 295 ill.</bibl>; <bibl><title>The Hartford Times</title> (June
                            20, 1961)</bibl>; <bibl>Vermeule 1961, 1-9,
                            figs. 2-4 and cover</bibl>; <bibl><title>Christian Science Monitor</title> (November 16,
                            1962)</bibl>; <bibl>Levi 1963, 209
                        ill.</bibl>; <bibl>Vermeule 1968, 414 ff, fig.
                        1</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 127.</bibl></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Worcester 1966.63" type="vase">Worcester
                        1966.63</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>BLACK-FIGURE NECK-AMPHORA</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Worcester Art Museum; Austin S. Garver Fund
                    (1966.63)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 17 3/8 in. (44.15
                    cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Broken and repaired; missing pieces restored and painted.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side A:</hi> Herakles and Kyknos.
                        Herakles, wearing a lion skin over his chiton, grasps Kyknos, a villain who
                        robbed Apollo of his victims for sacrifice. The hero holds him by a crest of
                        his helmet, and stabs him with a sword. Kyknos, fallen to the ground, faces
                        outward, a sword in one hand, and a shield (device: white balls) in the
                        other. He is dressed in greaves, corslet, and Corinthian helmet. Each
                        protagonist is accompanied by an allied spectator. Behind Herakles is his
                        patron Athena in chiton and himation and behind Kyknos is his father Ares
                        carrying a shield (device: tripod) and javelin. Between Herakles and Ares is
                        a thunderbolt showing the intervention of Zeus.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side B:</hi> Herakles playing a
                        kithara between Athena and Hermes. Herakles, dressed in lion skin, stands on
                        a podium playing the kithara. Athena, on the left, is dressed in chiton,
                        himation, aegis, and Attic helmet. She carries a shield and a javelin. On
                        the right, Hermes leans on his caduceus, entranced by the music. He wears
                        his hat (petasos), winged boots, and chlamys over short chiton. Herakles'
                        club, his usual weapon, leans against the podium on the left.</p>
                    <p>On the neck, palmette-lotus chain; on the shoulder, framed
                        tongues alternately red and black; at the handles, palmettes and volutes;
                        around the base of the scene, lotus buds; below, rays.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red:</hi> details of Herakles' lion
                        skin, Athena's crest, parts of the decoration.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">White:</hi> Athena's flesh, the
                        shield devices, helmet plumes, helms of swords, end of the scabbard, the
                        teeth of the lion skin on side A, and parts of the lyre on side B.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to a painter of the Leagros Group [Bothmer] ca. 515 -
                        500 B. C.</p>
                    <p>Leagros is the kalos name from which a group of black-figure
                        artists derives its name. The painters in the group are contemporary with
                        the red-figure `Pioneer' painters (see <bibl>Buitron 1972, no. 37</bibl>). The representations of the myths on both
                        sides show characteristics of the later sixth century. The battle of
                        Herakles and Kyknos was a favorite subject with vase painters from the
                        mid-sixth century on. In its early stages it included the two protagonists,
                        Zeus, and generally Athena and Ares as well. From ca. 525 on, the scene is
                        simplified, and as in this vase a thunderbolt replaces the figure of Zeus
                            (<bibl>Karouzou 1963, 132-141</bibl>). D.
                        von Bothmer suggests a vase in Athens (<rs type="vase">Athens
                            517</rs>) as parallel for the thunderbolt.</p>
                    <p>Herakles playing the kithara was also popular in the last quarter
                        of the century, although kithara and flute players had been depicted
                        earlier. The Lysippides Painter was especially fond of the subject (<bibl>ABV, 255, no. 9 and p. 256, no. 16</bibl>;
                        see also <bibl>Schauenburg 1961, 57 ff</bibl>).
                        For a list of other vases showing Herakles playing a musical instrument see
                            <bibl>Brommer 1960, 46</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Denver Art Museum, <title>Collector's Choice No.</title> 5, exhibition
                            catalogue (April 25 - June 6, 1965) no. 5 ill.</bibl>; <bibl>Fort Worth Art Center, <title>Classic Art of Antiquity,</title> exhibition
                            catalogue (November 1 - December 5, 1965)</bibl>; <bibl><title>Art Quarterly</title> 29 (1966)
                            no. 3-4, p. 289 (mentioned in accessions list)</bibl>; <bibl><title>Worcester Art Museum
                                Annual Report</title> (1967) xiv.</bibl></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Amherst 1950.59" type="vase">Amherst
                        1950.59</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>BLACK-FIGURE NECK-AMPHORA</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Museum of Art, Amherst College (1950.59)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 12 1/2 in. (31.75
                    cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Broken and repaired at base and body.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side A:</hi> symposion. A man and
                        woman, perhaps Dionysos and Ariadne, recline on a couch (kline). They wear
                        ivy wreaths in their hair and richly decorated chitons pulled down to the
                        waist. At the left is a flute player in himation with an ivy wreath in his
                        hair. On either side are two nude, bearded men dancing. The couch has
                        rectangular legs with cut out designs in the form of double palmettes. The
                        upper leg is higher than the lower and crowned with volutes. On the couch
                        are a mattress and cushions, richly embroidered. In front of the couch is a
                        low, three-legged eating table with a drinking cup and strips of meat on it.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side B:</hi> three couples, all in
                        chitons and embroidered himatia. Two bearded men embrace women while the
                        third couple looks on.</p>
                    <p>Under the handles, palmettes and volutes; below the scene, a
                        leftward meander, then ivy, then rays, each separated by double lines; above
                        the scene, alternating red and black framed tongues; on the neck,
                        lotus-palmette chain.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red:</hi> edges of the drapery and
                        cushions, fillets and wreaths, the men's beards, hearts of palmettes.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">White:</hi> female flesh, rosettes
                        on drapery, dots on mattresses, volutes, and palmettes of couch.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to the Medea Group [H. R. W. Smith] ca. 530 - 500 B.
                        C.</p>
                    <p>The Medea Group was named by H. R. W. Smith after a similar
                        amphora in the British Museum (<rs type="vase">London B
                        221</rs>; <bibl>ABV, 321, no. 4</bibl>) showing
                        Medea and the ram. Seven small neck amphorae have thus far been ascribed to
                        the group (<bibl>H.R.W. Smith 1945,
                        465-479</bibl>). The association of revelers, or komasts, with a reclining
                        couple supports the identification of the couple as Dionysos and Ariadne
                        with their cohorts.</p>
                    <p>Depicted here is a typical example of the Greek couch which was
                        used both for eating and sleeping. The frame was generally made of wood with
                        interlacings of leather or vegetable fiber and decorated with inlay of
                        tortoise shell, silver, or ivory, as seems likely here (see <bibl>Richter 1966, 52 ff</bibl>).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Georges Petit, <title>Catalogue des objets d'art antique... collection de
                                feu le Dr. Prof. S. Pozzi</title> (Paris June 25-27, 1919) pl. 15,
                            no. 456</bibl>; <bibl>ABV, 321</bibl>; <bibl>C. H. Morgan, "The Classical Collection at
                            Amherst College," <title>Archaeology</title> 20 (1967)
                            2-8, fig. p. 7</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 141, no.
                            1</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Yale 1913.111" type="vase">Yale
                    1913.111</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>BLACK-FIGURE LEKYTHOS</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Yale University Art Gallery; gift of Rebecca
                        Darlington Stoddard (1913.111)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 12 11/16 in. (32.1
                    cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Intact.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>The chariot of Admetos. Apollo mounts a chariot drawn by lions
                        and boars. He is dressed in a chlamys, and his lyre is tied on his back.
                        Hermes and two women (goddesses?) look on. Apollo, having displeased Zeus,
                        was forced to spend a year on earth in the service of Admetos, king of
                        Pherae. Admetos wished to wed Alkestis, who could only be won by the man who
                        yoked a lion and a boar to a chariot. Apollo, wishing to help Admetos,
                        accomplished the task for him, and Admetos won his bride (<bibl n="Apollod. 1.9.14">Apollod.
                        1.9.14-15</bibl>).</p>
                    <p>Above, double row of dots between lines; on the shoulder, seven
                        palmettes with tendrils; at the neck, tongues; below the scene, three red
                        lines circling the vase.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red:</hi> folds of the drapery;
                        fillet of Apollo, edge of his lyre case; part of the chariot; beard of
                        Hermes; tongues of the lions and boars; rear, ribs, and neck of the lion;
                        fillet of the woman on the right.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">White:</hi> female flesh (traces can
                        be seen overlapping the black base).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Related to the Edinburgh Painter [Haspels]</p>
                    <p>The shape and decoration are characteristic of the Edinburgh
                        Painter: his lekythoi are big and tall, there is a fillet at the base, and
                        the foot is a thick torus with the side reserved. The palmettes on the
                        shoulder follow one of his usual systems, as does the double row of dots
                            (<bibl>Haspels 1936, 88</bibl>). The choice
                        of this myth is unusual; it is rarely found in Attic red or black-figure
                        vase painting.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>P. Hartwig, <title>Ausonia</title> (Rome 1906-1921)</bibl>; <bibl>Baur 1922, 76, fig. 19</bibl>; <bibl>Haspels 1936, 221, no. 1</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Mount Holyoke 1925.BS.II.3" type="vase">Mount Holyoke 1925.BS.II.3</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>BLACK-FIGURE SKYPHOS</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by Mount Holyoke College Art Museum (1925 BS II.3)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 6 13/16 in. (17.2 cm.);
                            <hi rend="bold">Diameter:</hi> 8 11/16 in. (22 cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Broken and repaired.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side A:</hi> Herakles regaled by
                        Athena. Herakles, in a lion skin with his club between his knees and his
                        quiver at his waist, sits on a stone seat. One hand is raised in greeting,
                        one extended with a phiale. Athena, in chiton, himation, and Attic helmet,
                        approaches from the right and extends her oinochoe to fill his cup. At the
                        left is Hermes playing flutes. Behind Herakles is a dwarfed tree with
                        branches extending in the background.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side B:</hi> the same, except the
                        tree trunk is not visible.</p>
                    <p>Under the handles, bearded goats; around the lip, a double row of
                        dots between bands; below, red and black alternating tongues between lines.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red:</hi> the brim of Hermes' pilos,
                        his beard, belt, and shoes; the edge of Herakles' lion skin, his belt;
                        Athena's hair; ornaments on the drapery; the wine; the fillet at the base.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">White:</hi> Athena's flesh, helmet
                        crest; Hermes' hat and chiton; dots on the edges of Herakles' cup, the
                        meander on his rock seat; the fruits of the tree; the goat's horn, his
                        belly, and mouth.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to the Theseus Painter [Vanderpool] ca. 500 B. C.</p>
                    <p>The Theseus Painter, so named because he often chose the deeds of
                        Theseus for his subject, was above all a painter of skyphoi, most of which
                        can be dated by their style as ca. 500 B. C. (<bibl>Haspels 1936, 163</bibl>). Four others are known showing
                        Herakles regaled by Athena (<bibl>ABV,
                        519</bibl>). The subject is probably Herakles resting after one of his
                        twelve labors. Athena, his patron, brings him wine or nectar to refresh him.
                        Many vases are known showing Herakles with Athena and Hermes, but Athena
                        serving the hero wine does not appear until the beginning of the fifth
                        century (<bibl>Beazley 1961, 56</bibl>).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Mount Holyoke College, <title>Nancy Everett Dwight Foundation Catalogue</title>
                            ill.</bibl>; <bibl>E. Vanderpool, "The
                            Rectangular Rock-cut Shaft," <title>Hesperia</title> 15
                            (1946) 289-290</bibl>; <bibl>ABV, 519 (with
                            no. 18)</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Worcester 1935.39" type="vase">Worcester
                        1935.39</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>BLACK-FIGURE OINOCHOE (OLPE)</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Worcester Art Museum; bequest of Charlotte E. W.
                        Buffington (1935.59)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 8 15/16 in. (22.17
                    cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Broken and repaired; missing pieces restored and painted.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>The twelfth labor which Eurystheus set for Herakles was to fetch
                        Cerberus, the guardian of Hades. Herakles, in lion skin, is shown
                        approaching Cerberus from behind and grasping his tail which ends in a snake
                        head. The monster turns one of his heads towards Herakles while Hermes
                        grasps the snake forelock of his other head and prepares to throw a noose
                        around him. Two of the monster's feet end in snakes, and two are lion claws;
                        a "mane" runs down his neck and back. Above the scene is a palmette lotus
                        chain.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red:</hi> parts of Herakles' lion
                        skin, Cerberus' ruff, Hermes' chlamys, the heart and one leaf of each
                        palmette, the two lines circling the vase below the scene, the line on the
                        upper edge of the foot.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to the Honolulu Class [Beazley] ca. 530 - 500 B. C.</p>
                    <p>The guardian monster Cerberus was generally reputed to have many
                        dog heads, the tail of a dragon, and on his back the heads of snakes (<bibl n="Apollod. 2.5.12">Apollod. 2.5.12</bibl>).
                        Representations on vases almost always show Cerberus with only two heads, as
                        is the case on the famous representation of the scene by the Andokides
                        Painter (<rs type="vase">Louvre F 204</rs>; <bibl>ABV, 4, no. 11</bibl>).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl><title>Worcester Art Museum Annual Report</title> (1936) 19</bibl>; <bibl>D. von Bothmer, Review <title>Herakles</title> by Brommer, <hi rend="ital">AJA</hi> 58 (1954) 63-64</bibl>; <bibl>Schauenburg 1961, 63, figs. 18-19 and p. 67, n.
                        41</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 193, no. 2</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Williams 19.1.2" type="vase">Williams
                        19.1.2</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>BLACK-FIGURE OINOCHOE</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Williams College Museum of Art; gift of Anna Stetson
                        (1919 CG 42)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 9 5/16 in. (23.5
                    cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Broken and repaired at base and lip; some restoration on lip.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Nuptial chariot. The bridal couple stand in a four-horse chariot.
                        Before them are a goddess (perhaps Artemis) with torches, Dionysos with
                        drinking horn and ivy wreath, and Hermes in chlamys and winged boots with
                        the tip of his caduceus running over the lateral frame. Meaningless
                        inscription above. Around the neck, a double row of ivy between ridges;
                        below, tongues; lateral frames, two rows of large dots between lines at the
                        base of the scene; two red lines circling the vase.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red:</hi> fillet and beard of the
                        groom; wreath, beard, tip of the drinking horn of Dionysos; fillet of
                        Artemis; edges and folds of the drapery; the winged boots of Hermes; parts
                        of the chariot; the tails, manes, and bridles of the horses; the flames of
                        the torch; the inscription.<hi rend="bold">White:</hi> female
                        flesh.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Unattributed ca. 500 - 475 B. C.</p>
                    <p>As has been indicated by Joan Mertens, this vase belongs in the
                        class of Vatican G 47. A vase in the Louvre (<rs type="vase">Louvre F 345</rs>; <bibl>ABV, 429, no.
                        2</bibl>) is close to it. We know from literary sources that wedding
                        processions took place at night, hence the torches, generally carried by the
                        mother of the bride (<bibl>von Bothmer 1960, no.
                            2, p. 71 ff</bibl>; on weddings see <bibl>W.
                            Erdmann, <title>Die Ehe im alten Griechenland, Münchner Beiträge zur Papyrusforschung und antiken
                                Rechtsgeschichte,</title> Heft 20 [Munich 1934]</bibl>). The
                        presence of two readily identifiable gods, Dionysos and Hermes, suggests a
                        mythological subject, probably the wedding of Peleus and Thetis, one of the
                        few mortal weddings the gods attended.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Gerhard 1840-1858, 85, pl. 312,
                            1 and 3</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Yale 1909.12" type="vase">Yale 1909.12</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>PANATHENAIC AMPHORA</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Yale University Art Gallery; gift of Frederic W.
                        Stevens (1909.12)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 25 11/16 in. (65.2
                    cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Restored from fragments. The fragments constituting the front and
                        back of this vase are connected on one side, proving that they go together.
                        The entire lower part of the vase, the handles, neck, and part of the lip
                        are plaster. The vase was reconstructed from the original fragments and then
                        heavily repainted. The repaint, which had covered the original drawing, was
                        removed by the Fogg Conservation Department in 1971, and the original
                        fragments were revealed.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side A:</hi> the statue of Athena
                        Polias stands between two columns surmounted by cocks. The statue, which was
                        an ancient wooden one, is dressed in chiton, wool peplos, aegis, and helmet
                        (missing top of crest). In one hand is a javelin and in the other a shield
                        with a Pegasos device (head and forequarters missing). The two fragments
                        with the top of the left column, the cock, part of the shield, and four
                        letters of the inscription are from another vase and have been cut to
                        register.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side B:</hi> chariot race. The
                        charioteer (missing face) in long white chiton spurs on his team. Only the
                        hindquarters and hooves of the horses remain.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red, side A:</hi> rim of Athena's
                        shield, edge of her helmet, and border of her peplos; combs, gullets, and
                        breasts of cocks. <hi rend="bold">Side B:</hi> the charioteer's
                        beard, part of the chariot, the horses' tails. Line circling the vase at the
                        base of the panel.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">White:</hi> Athena's flesh and
                        shield device, the charioteer's chiton.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to the Kleophrades Painter [Beazley] ca. 500 - 475 B.
                        C.</p>
                    <p>Panathenaic amphorae filled with olive oil were given as prizes
                        for athletic events at the Panathenaic games. The series begins in the
                        second quarter of the sixth century and continues into the Hellenistic
                        period. The black-figure technique was retained for these vases well past
                        its disappearance on any other kind of vase. The shape and subjects remain
                        constant: Athena on the front, an athletic event on the back. Although the
                        Kleophrades Painter worked primarily in the red-figure technique, he also
                        executed black-figure pieces (<bibl>ABV,
                        404</bibl>). A Panathenaic amphora in New York (<rs type="vase">New York 07.286.79</rs>; <bibl>ABV, 404,
                            no. 6</bibl>) which is similar to this example has bold lettering,
                        powerful forms, and the Pegasos shield device, all characteristic of the
                        Kleophrades Painter (<bibl>Beazley 1951,
                        94</bibl>).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Beazley 1951, 111, n.
                        37</bibl>; <bibl>ABV, 404, no. 4</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Dartmouth c.959.53" type="vase">Dartmouth
                        c.959.53</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>PANATHENAIC AMPHORA</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Trustees of Dartmouth College; gift of Mr. and Mrs.
                        Ray Winfield Smith (c.959.53)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 24 1/2 in. (62.2
                    cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Broken and repaired.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side A:</hi> same as <rs type="vase">Yale 1909.12</rs>. Athena's shield device is a Gorgoneion;
                        around the rim are closely set red dots.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side B:</hi> wrestlers. A judge
                        stands on the left holding a forked stick which he uses to score any
                        infractions of the rules. On the right, two nude wrestlers. Each wrestler
                        has tried to seize his opponent by the neck, but the one on the left has not
                        been quick enough; his opponent has grasped him just below the elbow (<bibl>D. von Bothmer, "A Panathenaic Prize
                            Amphora," <title>Dartmouth Alumni Bulletin</title>
                            [June, 1959] 24-25</bibl>). On the neck, lotus-palmette chain; below the
                        neck, framed tongues alternately red and black.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red, side A:</hi> edges of Athena's
                        drapery, dots around rim of shield, wings of cocks.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side B:</hi> wreath of judge.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">White:</hi> Athena's flesh and
                        shield device.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to the Berlin Painter [Bothmer] ca. 500 - 475 B. C.</p>
                    <p>In his publication of this amphora D. von Bothmer points to the
                        painter's understanding of corporeal perspective as exhibited by his
                        figures. "The bodies are no longer composed of straight front views and
                        straight profiles, joined together in the inorganic manner of early archaic
                        art." (ibid. 25) The Berlin Painter, also primarily a red-figure artist,
                        painted eight known Panathenaic amphorae.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>D. von Bothmer, "A Panathenaic
                            Prize Amphora," <title>Dartmouth Alumni Bulletin</title>
                            (June, 1959) 24-26</bibl>; <bibl>ARV2,
                        214</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 177, no. 2
                    ter</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Wellesley (Buitron No. 27)" type="vase">Wellesley (Buitron No. 27)</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>BLACK-FIGURE LEKYTHOS, WHITE-GROUND</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Wellesley College Art Museum</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 8 5/16 in. (21.2
                    cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Repaired and restored at handle and base.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Three Amazons. One Amazon is ready; she is fully armed in
                        high-crested Attic (?) helmet, corslet, chitoniskos, greaves, and scabbard.
                        She holds two javelins and leads her horse to the right while waiting for
                        her companions. In front of her another Amazon is lifting her shield
                        (device: white balls). Behind, the third Amazon with her Corinthian helmet
                        pulled down over her face holds her shield (device: coiled snake) and seems
                        to be testing her javelin. An animated dog is at her feet. Behind the horse
                        is a tree and under his tail is an inscription with five pseudo letters;
                        another inscription with seven pseudo letters is between the first two
                        Amazons.</p>
                    <p>On the shoulder, lotus buds connected by tendrils with tongues
                        above; above the scene, leftward meander between black lines.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red:</hi> the horse's tail and base
                        of mane, crests of the helmets, edge of one shield, upper edge of mouth,
                        dots on borders of drapery, collar of dog.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Reserved</hi> neck and shoulder,
                        under handle, two bands below scene, edge of upper disk of foot.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to the Diosphos Painter [Beazley] ca. 500 - 475 B. C.</p>
                    <p>Amazons as shown here, arming and preparing to leave for battle,
                        do not become popular until the period of developed black-figure.
                        Previously, they had been shown mainly in the context of mythological battle
                        scenes with Herakles or at Troy (see <bibl>von
                            Bothmer 1957, 91</bibl>). The Diosphos Painter is a light-hearted but
                        careful draftsman with a fondness for child-like figures and pets but
                        lacking unity in his compositions (<bibl>Haspels
                            1936, 94 ff</bibl>). The shape and decoration of this lekythos is
                        typical of him, and he shares an affinity for it with the Sappho Painter.
                        The inscription of pseudo letters is also characteristic (ibid).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Rudolf Lepke, <title>Auktion 1707</title> (Berlin March 11, 1914)
                            Sammlung des verstorbenen Herrn Ludwig Freiherrn von Schalky und
                            Schönfeld pl. 36, no. 467</bibl>; <bibl>von Bothmer 1957, 11, no. 97, p. 100</bibl>; <bibl>ABV, 510, no. 12</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:RISD 34.1374a and b" type="vase">RISD
                        34.1374a and b</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>BLACK-FIGURE PYXIS WITH LID</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Museum of Art, Rhode Island School of Design (34.1374
                        a and b)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height with lid:</hi> 7 1/16 in.
                        (17.9 cm.)</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height without lid:</hi> 3 5/8 in.
                        (9.2 cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Chipped at rim of base; lid broken and repaired with some plaster
                        restoration. Glazed inside.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Body:</hi> symposion. Five bearded
                        men recline on cushions and mattresses placed on the ground. One holds a
                        kylix, and the other four play musical instruments, flutes and lyres.
                        Behind, a leafless spray of ivy with only the berries (korymboi) depicted.
                        The white of the cushions and dots of the drapery are mostly worn off.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">On the lid:</hi> hunt. A youth with
                        club and chlamys over one arm hunts a hare with the aid of three large dogs.</p>
                    <p>The scene on the body is framed above and below by a double row
                        of dots between lines. The outer rim of the lid has a similar double row of
                        black and white dots between lines; at the base of the knob, ray-like
                        tongues. The edge of the lid is glazed.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to the Manner of the Haimon Painter [Bothmer]ca. 500 -
                        474 B. C.</p>
                    <p>This pyxis is similar to two in Berlin (<rs type="vase">Berlin F 2034</rs> and <rs type="vase">Berlin
                            F 2035</rs>; <bibl>ABV, 556, no. 442 bis and
                            442 ter</bibl>) ascribed to the Manner of the Haimon Painter. They are
                        distinct from a number of pyxides of the Haimon Painter group which are
                        variants of the Nicosthenic form with a black bowl and the picture confined
                        to the lid (<bibl>Para., 284</bibl>). The scanty
                        incision on the vague figures of the pyxis is characteristic of the Haimon
                        Painter (<bibl>Haspels 1936, 131</bibl>).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Luce 1936, no. 2, p. 40, fig.
                        5</bibl>; <bibl>C. A. Robinson, Jr., "Greek and
                            Roman Vases," <title>BullRhode</title> 27 (1939,
                            reprinted 1951) no. 3, p. 7, fig 7</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Mount Holyoke 1967.BS.II.11" type="vase">Mount Holyoke 1967.BS.II.11</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>RED-FIGURE KYLIX (TYPE B, decorated inside only)</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Mount Holyoke College Art Museum (1967 BS II.11)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 3 5/8 in. (9.2 cm.);
                            <hi rend="bold">Diameter:</hi> 9 7/8 in. (25 cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Broken and repaired.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Inside:</hi> a woman, playing
                        castanets (krotala) and dancing, runs to the right, her head turned to the
                        left over her shoulder. She wears a peplos, bracelets, and a fillet in her
                        hair. Around the tondo near the border is inscribed <foreign xml:lang="greek">*K*A*L*O*S *K*A*L*O*S</foreign> (beautiful,
                        beautiful). A reserved line forms the tondo.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red:</hi> the inscription,
                        bracelets, and fillet.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to Oltos [Beazley] ca. 525 - 500 B. C.</p>
                    <p>Oltos, whose name is known from his signature as painter on two
                        kylikes, was a contemporary of the Andokides Painter, the inventor of the
                        red-figure technique (see <rs type="vase">Boston 01.8037</rs>).
                        On this vase, the new technique is seen in its early stages. The use of
                        added color is reduced, resulting in a more sober color scheme. The figure
                        is outlined with relief lines and occasionally with a contour stripe. Inner
                        details are painted with firm black relief lines. The figure is thus
                        spotlighted against the black background. This kylix belongs with the early
                        to middle work of Oltos (see <bibl>Bruhn
                        1943</bibl>).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl><title>Hesperia
                                Art Bulletin</title> 39 (1967) no. A 13</bibl>; <bibl>E. Finkenstaedt, "A Red-Figure Kylix by Oltos at Mount
                            Holyoke College," <title>AJA</title> 72 (1968) 383, pl.
                            129</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 328, no. 127
                        ter.</bibl></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Bowdoin 1913.14" type="vase">Bowdoin
                        1913.14</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>FRAGMENT OF A RED-FIGURE KYLIX</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Bowdoin College Museum of Art; gift of E. P. Warren
                        (1913.14)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 1 1/8 in. (2.9 cm.);
                            <hi rend="bold">Width:</hi> 2 3/16 in. (5.6 cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Girl playing flutes. Her shoulders and head are preserved as well
                        as part of her hands. A fillet ties up her hair.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red:</hi> the flutes and fillet.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to Oltos [Beazley] ca. 525 - 500 B. C.</p>
                    <p>Other fragments of this cup are in Florence, Heidelberg,
                        Brunswick (Germany), and Baltimore (see <rs type="vase">Baltimore, Hopkins AIA B1</rs>). The joins were observed by Beazley,
                        and the cup was restored in photographs (<bibl>Beazley 1933a, pl. x, reproduced here</bibl>). Our piece is from side
                        B, flute girl between two men. On side A are satyrs and maenads, and inside
                        is Pegasos.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Beazley 1933a, 7, pl. x, pl. 1,
                            21, and 23</bibl>; <bibl>ARV2, 59, no.
                        55</bibl>; <bibl>Herbert 1964, 60-61, no.
                        159</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Yale 1913.169" type="vase">Yale
                    1913.169</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>RED-FIGURE PLATE</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Yale University Art Gallery; gift of Rebecca
                        Darlington Stoddard (1913.169)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 1 1/16 in. (2.7 cm.);
                            <hi rend="bold">Diameter:</hi> 7 3/8 in. (18.7 cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Broken and repaired; missing pieces restored and painted.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Ajax and Kassandra. Ajax drags Kassandra away from the statue of
                        Athena where she had taken refuge during the sack of Troy. The statue,
                        representing Athena in warlike attitude, portrays her almost as a living
                        goddess. Kassandra, shown nude, futilely grasps at the drapery of the image
                        as Ajax drags her away. The three figures stand on a thin reserved line.
                        Inscribed behind Ajax, <foreign xml:lang="greek">*)Aias</foreign> (Ajax); below the ground line, <foreign xml:lang="greek">*Katadra</foreign> (Kassandra); behind the statue,
                            <foreign xml:lang="greek">*)Aqenaia</foreign>
                    (Athena).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red:</hi> Ajax's baldric.</p>
                    <p>Attributed to Paseas [Beazley] ca. 520 - 510 B. C.</p>
                    <p>The name of Paseas is known from a black-figure plaque found on
                        the Acropolis in Athens (<rs type="vase">Athens, Acr.
                        2583</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 164, no. 3</bibl>; <bibl>Boardman 1955, 154</bibl>). His style is
                        related to that of Psiax (<rs type="vase">Hartford 1961.8</rs>)
                        and is still strongly influenced by black-figure. The small Kassandra also
                        recalls black-figure painting. She is shown small perhaps because the early
                        archaic artists wished to emphasize the atrocity of the rape by making her
                        very young (<bibl>Caskey &amp; Beazley, 1,
                            p. 2</bibl>). Late archaic representations tend to show her normal in
                        size as on the hydria by the Kleophrades Painter in Naples (<rs type="vase">Naples 2422</rs>; <bibl>ARV2,
                            189, no. 74</bibl>).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Beazley 1918, 13-14</bibl>;
                            <bibl>Baur 1922, 111-112, pl. 15</bibl>;
                            <bibl>Davreux 1942, fig. 45</bibl>; <bibl>ARV2, 163, no. 4</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Yale 1913.170" type="vase">Yale
                    1913.170</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>RED-FIGURE PLATE</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Yale University Art Gallery; gift of Rebecca
                        Darlington Stoddard (1913.170)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 15/16 in. (2.4 cm.);
                            <hi rend="bold">Diameter:</hi> 7 3/8 in. (18.7 cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Broken and repaired; missing pieces restored and painted. The
                        edge of the ring base is pierced with two holes set close together at 12
                        o'clock for suspension. From Chiusi.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Dionysos and a satyr. Dionysos, holding ivy spray in one hand and
                        kantharos in the other, stands on the left. A dancing satyr (missing right
                        leg except for the toe, lower right arm, and lower part of torso) is before
                        him. His hand is to his forehead as if he is peering into the distance
                        (aposkopeion). Both stand on a thin reserved line.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red:</hi> leaves of the ivy
                    branch.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to Paseas [Beazley] ca. 520 - 510 B. C.</p>
                    <p>The somewhat irregular contour lines of the figures on both
                        plates are indicative of an early stage in the development of red-figure;
                        later the lines are wider and more even. The plate is an archaic form and,
                        as in this example, was decorated sparsely by several artists, mainly
                        followers of the Andokides Painter such as Oltos and Psiax (<bibl>H.R.W. Smith 1929, 59</bibl>). Two plates in
                        Boston can be compared (<rs type="vase">Boston 03.785</rs> and
                            <rs type="vase">Boston 01.8025</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 163</bibl>).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Beazley 1918, 13</bibl>; <bibl>Baur 1922, 112, pl. 15</bibl>; <bibl>ARV2, 163, no. 3</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:RISD 25.077" type="vase">RISD 25.077</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>FRAGMENTS OF A KYLIX</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Museum of Art, Rhode Island School of Design; museum
                        appropriation and special gift (Mrs. Gustav Radeke) (25.077)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Approximate diameter:</hi> 11 3/4
                        in. (29.8 cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Interior:</hi> satyr and maenad.
                        Only the feet and tail of the satyr remain. Inscribed at the right, <foreign xml:lang="greek">*O [*P]*A*I*S</foreign> (the boy) and at
                        the left, <foreign xml:lang="greek">*K*A*L*O[*S]</foreign>
                        (beautiful). The tondo is framed by two reserved lines.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side A:</hi> satyrs and maenads. At
                        the left a maenad in chiton, himation, and sakkos brandishes her thyrsos,
                        her head turned backwards. In front of her a satyr with a wineskin and
                        drinking horn moves to the right. Between the two is inscribed <foreign xml:lang="greek">*K*A*L*O*S</foreign> (beautiful). In the
                        center was the figure of Dionysos. Only the right arm, holding a drinking
                        horn, and the right foot remain. Behind are sprays of vine. The figure after
                        the gap to the right is missing except for one hand holding a drinking horn.
                        At the far right is a satyr dancing towards the left, his back turned
                        outwards as he circles around.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side B:</hi> at the left an
                        ithyphallic satyr follows a maenad who turns to attack him. She is dressed
                        in chiton, himation, and sakkos and carries a thyrsos. In the center is a
                        satyr with a leopard skin cape on his shoulders and a drinking horn in one
                        hand. At the right is another maenad with chiton and leopard skin cape,
                        followed by a satyr. To the left of the central satyr is inscribed <foreign xml:lang="greek">*P*A*I*S *K*A*L*O*S</foreign> (boy is
                        beautiful) and to the right, <foreign xml:lang="greek">*K*A*L*O*S</foreign> (beautiful).</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Dilute glaze:</hi> one maenad's
                        hair, folds of the chitons.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red:</hi> inscriptions, ivy wreaths,
                        vine sprays.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to Epiktetos [Beazley] ca. 520 - 500 B. C.</p>
                    <p>The name of Epiktetos is known from forty signed vases. On a
                        plate in Athens (<rs type="vase">Athens, Acr. 6</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 78, no. 102</bibl>) he signs with both
                            <foreign xml:lang="greek">*E*P*O*I*E*S*E*N</foreign> (made
                        it) and <foreign xml:lang="greek">*E*G*R*A*F*S*E*N</foreign>
                        (painted it), so we know he was both potter and painter. One can compare
                        this kylix with one by Oltos (see <rs type="vase">Mount Holyoke
                            1967.BS.II.11</rs>) which is slightly earlier. The figures drawn by
                        Epiktetos are more elegant and move with a lighter grace. This cup must
                        belong in his early period.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Banks 1928, 50</bibl>; <bibl>S. B. Luce, "Two Kylikes in Providence,"
                                <title>AJA</title> 32 (1928) 442-444</bibl>; <bibl>S. B. Luce, "What Can Be Learned from Greek
                            Vases," <title>BullRhode</title> 16 (1928) 46</bibl>;
                            <bibl>Kraiger 1929, 198, no. 55</bibl>;
                            <bibl>C. Dugas, "Céramique. Peinture.
                            Mosaique." <title>Revue des Etudes grecques</title> 43
                            (1930) 123</bibl>; <bibl>CVA, USA 2, pp.
                            23-24, pl. 14</bibl>; <bibl>ARV2, 73, no.
                        34</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Bowdoin 1913.2" type="vase">Bowdoin
                    1913.2</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>RED-FIGURE EYE-CUP (TYPE A)</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Bowdoin College Museum of Art; gift of E. P. Warren
                        (1913.2)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 5 5/16 in. (13.5 cm.);
                            <hi rend="bold">Diameter:</hi> 12 3/4 in. (32.4 cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Broken and repaired in several places; some restoration around
                        handles. Under foot, graffito.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Inside:</hi> hoplitodromos. An
                        athlete wearing greaves runs to the left carrying a shield (device: raven)
                        and a Corinthian helmet. A reserved line forms the tondo. The absence of
                        offensive armor indicates that this is not a warrior but a hoplitodromos
                        participating in the race in armor.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side A:</hi> between eyes, a jumper.
                        A nude athlete strides to the left carrying jumping weights (halteres).</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side B:</hi> between eyes, a jumper.
                        A nude athlete carrying halteres bends down in preparation for a jump. Above
                        is inscribed <foreign xml:lang="greek">*K*A*L*O*S</foreign>
                        (beautiful).</p>
                    <p>The eyes have well-marked tear ducts and above them eyebrows. At
                        the handles are palmettes. Those on side A are shut and have sixteen fronds;
                        those on side B are open and have nine fronds. The ornament, therefore,
                        combines the palmette type characteristic of Beazley's earlier Class I and
                        later Class III.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red:</hi> a ring of each eye, the
                        inscription.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to the Bowdoin-Eye Painter, his name piece [Beazley]
                        ca. 520 - 500 B. C.</p>
                    <p>The eye-cup became a favorite form during this period. The eyes,
                        though mainly decorative, may originally have had an apotropaic meaning.</p>
                    <p>Two athletes are pictured preparing for their events: the race in
                        armor and the broad jump with weights.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Beazley 1918, 13, no. 2</bibl>;
                            <bibl>Bloesch 1940, 36, no. 3</bibl>; <bibl>Richter 1958, 53</bibl>; <bibl>Herbert, <title>The Walker Art Museum
                                Bulletin</title> 1 (1962) no. 4, p. 9</bibl>; <bibl>ARV2, 167, no. 5</bibl>; <bibl>Herbert 1964, 61, no. 160</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Smith 1955.45" type="vase">Smith
                    1955.45</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>RED-FIGURE KYLIX (TYPE A)</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Smith College Museum of Art (1955.45)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 4 15/16 in. (10 cm.);
                            <hi rend="bold">Diameter:</hi> 13 3/16 in. (33.5 cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Reassembled from many fragments; some repaint on palmettes and on
                        tondo figure.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Inside:</hi> a youth prepares to
                        hurl a discus. Inscribed behind him retrograde is <foreign xml:lang="greek">*K*A*L*O*S</foreign> (beautiful).</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side A:</hi> drinking party. A
                        reclining satyr holds a skyphos and reaches for the wine-skin held out by a
                        smaller satyr who approaches him. Above is inscribed <foreign xml:lang="greek">*O *P*A*I*S *K*A*L*O*S</foreign> (the boy is
                        beautiful).</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side B:</hi> drinking party. A youth
                        fills his skyphos from a column-krater in which the wine has been mixed with
                        water. To the left, a youth with skyphos; to the right, a youth with
                        drinking horn and a wineskin. Inscribed above, <foreign xml:lang="greek">*O *P*A*I*S *K*A*L*O*S</foreign> (the boy is
                        beautiful).</p>
                    <p>At the handles are palmettes and volutes; on side A, palmettes
                        with nine fronds; on side B, palmettes with ten fronds.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Dilute glaze:</hi> hair and beards.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red:</hi> the wreaths and
                        inscriptions.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to the Manner of the Epeleios Painter [Beazley] ca.
                        520 - 500 B.C.</p>
                    <p>The minimal detail, emphasis on silhouette, and the heavy fronds
                        of the palmettes suggest a date of ca. 510 B. C. (<bibl>P. W. Lehmann, "An Attic Kylix," <title>Smith College Museum of Art Bulletin</title> 37 [1957] 3-9, figs.
                            1-6</bibl>). Mrs. Lehmann compares this cup to one in Cambridge (<rs type="vase">Cambridge 1.27</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 124, no. 3</bibl>). Bloesch considers the form of
                        the Cambridge cup extremely rare (<bibl>Bloesch
                            1940, 38, pl. 11, 1</bibl>).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl><title>Smith
                                Quarterly</title> (Winter, 1956) 86 ill.</bibl>; <bibl><title>Art Quarterly</title> 19 (Summer,
                            1956) no. 2, ill.</bibl>; <bibl>P. W.
                            Lehmann, "An Attic Kylix," <title>Smith College Museum
                                of Art Bulletin</title> 37 (1957) 3-9, figs. 1-6</bibl>; <bibl>ARV2, 153</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Dartmouth c.970.35" type="vase">Dartmouth
                        c.970.35</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>RED-FIGURE KYLIX</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Trustees of Dartmouth College; gift of Mr. and Mrs.
                        R. W. Smith (c.970.35)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 3 1/8 in. (8 cm.); <hi rend="bold">Diameter:</hi> 10 1/4 in. (26 cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Broken, repaired, and restored at left handle and foot.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Type B Kylix, decorated inside only.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Inside:</hi> boxer. A nude athlete
                        sits on the ground binding his hand and wrist with boxing thongs in
                        preparation for a match. At his feet are two jumping weights; beside him, a
                        discus and pick for loosening the earth. Suspended in the field is his bath
                        equipment: sponge for the shower, oil and strigil for afterwards. Inscribed
                        above, <foreign xml:lang="greek">*E*P*I*D*R*O*M*O*S
                        *K*A*L*O*S</foreign> (Epidromos is beautiful). Traces of preliminary sketch
                        appear around the head and near the ground. A reserved line forms the tondo,
                        and a glaze line strengthens the frame where the ground is reserved.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Dilute glaze:</hi> abdominal
                        muscles, texture of the sponge.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red:</hi> the inscription and the
                        strings of the aryballos.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to the Epidromos Painter [Cahn] ca. 520 - 500 B. C.</p>
                    <p>The Epidromos Painter, named after his favorite kalos name,
                        belongs in the neighborhood of Epiktetos, although his nervous drawing style
                        is in contrast to the latter's tranquility (cf. <rs type="vase">Bowdoin 1913.2</rs>). He is also closely related to Apollodoros and may
                        even represent an early stage of his oeuvre (<bibl>ARV2, 117</bibl>).</p>
                    <p>In this cup the Epidromos Painter displays two noteworthy
                        artistic features. In choosing to show a seated figure from the front, he
                        suggests a real interest in the representation of human anatomy and in the
                        problem of foreshortening. Furthermore, he has arranged the athlete's
                        equipment so as to respect the curve of the tondo and make the objects stand
                        out against their respective light and dark backgrounds.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Münzen, 18 (Basel
                            November 29, 1958) 37-38</bibl>; <bibl>ARV2,
                            117, no. 6</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Harvard 1972.40" type="vase">Harvard
                        1972.40</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>RED-FIGURE HYDRIA (KALPIS)</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by Frederick M. Watkins</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 15 1/16 in. (38.1
                    cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Intact, except for restoration of one side handle and part of the
                        mouth.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Ransom of Hector. The artist has followed the description of the
                        scene in the <hi rend="ital">Iliad.</hi> Achilles "had just now
                        got through with his dinner/ with eating and drinking, and the table still
                        stood by. Tall Priam/ came in unseen by the other men and stood close beside
                        him/ and caught the knees of Achilles in his arms..." (<bibl n="Hom. Il. 24.475-478">Hom. Il.
                        24.475-478</bibl>, R. Lattimore trans. [Chicago 1951]). Hector lies at the
                        foot of the table; the thongs with which he was tied to Achilles' chariot
                        and dragged around Troy still bind his ankles. His hair is disheveled and
                        his body covered with wounds. At the right are the shield and helmet of
                        Achilles. Inscribed between Priam and Achilles, <foreign xml:lang="greek">*P*R*I*A*M*O*S</foreign> (Priam); the other
                        inscriptions are meaningless: <foreign xml:lang="greek">*I*X*E*X, *I*O*T*E*X, *T*I*N*I, *X*E*T*E*I</foreign> (retrograde). The
                        scene is restricted to the shoulder and framed above and on the sides with a
                        net pattern knotted twice; below, with dentils and dots. Running from handle
                        to handle is a band of alternately rightward and leftward palmettes
                        interspersed with teardrop ornaments; the band is open on the left, closed
                        on the right.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Dilute glaze:</hi> blood on Hector's
                        body, folds of Priam's drapery, shading on Achilles' shield.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red:</hi> fillet of Achilles,
                        inscriptions, lines falling from the table onto Hector's body (blood of the
                        meat being cut?).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Said by Beazley to recall Euthymides and earliest Kleophrades
                        Painter ca. 525 - 500 B. C.</p>
                    <p>This vase is related by both shape and style to a group of
                        kalpides ascribed to the Pioneer Group (<bibl>ARV2, 33</bibl>), red-figure artists led by Euphronios, Euthymides, and
                        Phintias, who form the transition from the more restricted style of early
                        red-figure (see <rs type="vase">Boston 01.8037</rs>) to the
                        broader ripe archaic style (see <rs type="vase">Williams
                        1964.9</rs>). The abrupt combination of frontal and profile forms, incised
                        contour of the hair, and sparing use of dilute glaze for inner details
                        indicate an early stage in the development of the red-figure style. The
                        subject is relatively rare; Brommer lists only twelve examples in
                        black-figure and red-figure (<bibl>Brommer 1960,
                            330</bibl>) to which one more can be added (<bibl>Münzen, [Basel May 6, 1967] 76</bibl>). Compare
                        especially the kylix in Munich (<rs type="vase">Munich
                        2618</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 61, no. 74</bibl>) by
                        Oltos. Noteworthy in our piece is the large size of Hector's body with
                        respect to the other figures and the composition.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Münzen, (Basel May 6,
                            1967) 75-76, no. 149, pls. 46, 47</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 324</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Vermeule Collection (Buitron No. 38)" type="vase">Vermeule Collection (Buitron No. 38)</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>FRAGMENT OF A CALYX-KRATER</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by Mr. and Mrs. Cornelius C. Vermeule, III</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 3 5/8 in. (9.2 cm.);
                            <hi rend="bold">Width:</hi> 1 9/16 in. (3.9 cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Funerary mound. An elaborately decorated Corinthian helmet sits
                        on a stand which lies on plugs protruding from a mound. Below is the rim of
                        a shield and to the left, the upper part of a greave and a fillet tied
                        around another plug. Behind, the contour of the mound is visible. Above, a
                        detail of the band of decoration is preserved.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Unattributed ca. 500 - 475 B.C.</p>
                    <p>The shape has been identified as that of an archaic calyx-krater,
                        and the decoration is of a Kleophradean type (D. von Bothmer). For a
                        funerary mound with the departed's equipment compare a white lekythos in New
                        York (<rs type="vase">New York 35.11.5</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 744, no. 1</bibl>).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p>Unpublished.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Yale 1913.133" type="vase">Yale
                    1913.133</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>RED-FIGURE NOLAN AMPHORA</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Yale University Art Gallery; gift of Rebecca
                        Darlington Stoddard (1913.133)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 12 15/16 in. (32.7
                    cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Intact save for chip on rim; surface dented on A.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side A:</hi> Athena. Athena stands
                        to left holding a javelin. In her extended right arm she holds an Attic
                        helmet. She is dressed in chiton, himation, and aegis with her hair in a
                        diadem with upright leaves and the ends rolled in a snood.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side B:</hi> Hermes. Holding his
                        caduceus in one hand, he advances towards Athena on the other side. His
                        petasos is slung on his back, and his chlamys caught up at the right
                        shoulder. He wears a chitoniskos decorated with crosses under his chlamys,
                        boots, and an ivy wreath in his hair.</p>
                    <p>Both figures stand on strips of simple key pattern to the right.
                        Under the handles, hanging palmettes and tendrils. On the neck on A, upright
                        and inverted palmettes, tendrils, and dots; on B, three palmettes with egg
                        pattern below.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Dilute glaze:</hi> pattern and folds
                        of Athena's chiton, scales of her aegis, her necklace; anatomical details of
                        Hermes.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red:</hi> Athena's bracelets, string
                        on her snood, ties of Hermes' hat and boots, his ivy wreath.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to the Berlin Painter [Beazley] ca. 480 B. C.</p>
                    <p>The Berlin Painter applies a new principle to the decoration of
                        amphorae: a single figure on each side standing on a ground line but
                        otherwise unframed. He is a master of the system of "bare decoration" (<bibl>Beazley 1964, 2</bibl>). Although on
                        opposite sides, Athena and Hermes can be thought of as together. The vase
                        has been placed by Beazley in the middle period of the Berlin Painter's
                        oeuvre. The drawing of the floral band on the neck is unusual and seems to
                        be a carry-over from his early period (<bibl>ARV2, 219</bibl>).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Beazley 1918, 38</bibl>; <bibl>Hoppin 1919, p. 63, no. 30</bibl>; <bibl>Hambidge 1920, 57, fig. 19</bibl>; <bibl>Baur 1922, 89, pl. 8</bibl>; <bibl>Poulsen 1927, pl. 10, 17</bibl>; <bibl>ARV2, 201, no. 71 and p. 219</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:RISD 15.005" type="vase">RISD 15.005</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>RED-FIGURE NECK-AMPHORA</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Museum of Art, Rhode Island School of Design; museum
                        appropriation and special gift (Mrs. Gustav Radeke) (15.005)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 20 in. (50.8 cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Broken and repaired; plaster restoration especially on B; one
                        handle restored; part of foot restored; abrasions of glaze on B. Under foot,
                        graffito.</p>
                    <p>From Vulci.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side A:</hi> Apollo. The god stands
                        with head turned to the left. He extends his right arm with phiale in hand
                        and holds a kithara in the other arm. Over his chiton he wears a himation
                        fastened at the shoulder with a brooch. His long curled hair is dressed with
                        a fillet and laurel wreath. A dotted sash with a crenelated border and a
                        fringe is attached to the lyre and provides a festive air.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side B:</hi> woman (Artemis?). Only
                        the lower part of her body is preserved. She holds an oinochoe, presumably
                        to fill Apollo's phiale. She wears a chiton and himation. On A, the ground
                        line consists of pairs of meanders alternating in direction and interrupted
                        with cross-squares. On B, it consists of meanders only. At the base of the
                        handles are tongues.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Dilute glaze:</hi> strands of hair,
                        step pattern on the fillet attaching the lyre to Apollo's hand, design on
                        the sash.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red:</hi> Apollo's wreath, lyre
                        strings on black background, string for the plectrum of the lyre.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to the Providence Painter; his name piece [Beazley]
                        ca. 500 - 475 B.C.</p>
                    <p>The shape as well as the style of this amphora are derived from
                        the Berlin Painter (<rs type="vase">Yale 1913.133</rs>), who
                        must have been the Providence Painter's teacher (<bibl>Beazley 1918, 76</bibl>). Although there are no
                        inscriptions, the heavy kithara, long hair, and serene pose all suggest
                        Apollo. By implication, the figure on the reverse should be his sister
                        Artemis (<bibl>Beazley 1922, 70</bibl>).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>C. Lenormant and J. de Witte,
                                <title>Elite des monuments
                            céramographiques</title> 2 (Paris 1837-1861) 33-34, pl.
                        XIII</bibl>; <bibl>Gerhard 1840-1858, 85-88, pl.
                            24</bibl>; <bibl>Reinach 1900, 27, nos. 1,
                        2</bibl>; <bibl>S. B. Luce, <title>AJA</title> 21 (1917) 411 passim</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley 1918, 76</bibl>; <bibl>Hoppin 1919, vol. 2, p. 394, no. 38</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley 1922, 70</bibl>; <bibl>S. B. Luce, <title>AJA</title> 28 (1924)
                            73 passim</bibl>; <bibl><title>BullRhode</title> 16 (1928) 37, fig. 1, p.
                        50</bibl>; <bibl><title>BullRhode</title> 19 (1931) 38</bibl>; <bibl>CVA, USA 2, p. 26, pl. 18</bibl>; <bibl><title>BullRhode</title> 27 (1939)
                        32-33</bibl>; <bibl>Simon 1953, 43, no.
                        43</bibl>; <bibl>J. H. C. Kern, "Two Vases by
                            the Providence Painter in Leyden," <title>Oudheidkundige
                                Medelingen vit het Rijksmuseum van Oudheden to Leiden</title> 42
                            (1961)</bibl>; <bibl>ARV2, 635, no.
                        1</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Williams 64.9" type="vase">Williams
                    64.9</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>RED-FIGURE STAMNOS</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Williams College Museum of Art (1964.9)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 14 in. (35.5 cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Broken and repaired; some restoration. Graffito on shoulder.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side A:</hi> Poseidon vs. Polybotes.
                        This is a scene from the war between the gods and the giants. On the left
                        Poseidon wields his trident and a huge rock, which, Apollodoros tells us
                            (<bibl n="Apollod. 1.5.2">Apollod.
                        1.5.2</bibl>), he broke from the island of Cos to throw at the giant
                        Polybotes, who was buried under it. When the rock fell into the sea, it
                        became the island of Nisyros. Poseidon steps on Polybotes who is falling
                        back, javelin in left hand and shield (device: lion) on left arm. In his
                        right hand he holds a saber (machaira), the common weapon of cavalrymen,
                        foreigners, and barbarians.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side B:</hi> komos. Three drunken
                        youths make merry. The youth on the left has a pointed amphora; the one in
                        the middle, a skyphos. The youth on the right seems to be asking for a
                        drink.</p>
                    <p>Below on A, rightward swastika meander; on B, simple rightward
                        key; above, framed tongues.<hi rend="bold">Red:</hi> fillets in
                        hair of youths and Polybotes.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to the Troilos Painter [Beazley] ca. 500 - 475 B.C.</p>
                    <p>Barbara Philippaki places this stamnos near one in the Louvre
                            (<rs type="vase">Louvre G 55</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 187, no. 58</bibl>) by the Kleophrades Painter,
                        strengthening the connection between him and the Troilos Painter (<bibl>Philippaki 1967, 48</bibl>). According to
                        Beazley, the Williams vase was found together with a stamnos by the
                        Kleophrades Painter now in the Astarita Collection in the Vatican (<rs type="vase">Vatican 735</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 1632, no. 58 bis</bibl>).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl><title>Antike
                                Kunst</title> 6 (1963) no. 1, advertisement p. iii</bibl>; <bibl>ARV2, 1643, no. 10 bis</bibl>; <bibl>Andre Emmerich Gallery, Inc., <title>Masterpieces of Greek Vase Painting,</title>
                            exhibition catalogue (April 22 - May 30, 1964) no. 24</bibl>; <bibl>American Heritage, <title>Horizon Book of Ancient Greece</title> (New York 1966) 28</bibl>;
                            <bibl>Philippaki 1967, 48, 56</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Dewing Collection (Buitron No. 20)" type="vase">Dewing Collection (Buitron No. 20)</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>RED-FIGURE PELIKE</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Trustees of the Dewing Numismatic Foundation</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 12 3/4 in. (32.4
                    cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Broken and repaired; missing pieces restored and painted.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side A:</hi> komos. Two youths on
                        their way home from a revel. One has a chlamys draped over one arm; the
                        other holds a skyphos.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side B:</hi> jumper and youth. A
                        nude youth holds a jumping weight in one hand and prepares to make a jump.
                        At the right, a youth dressed in a himation and leaning on a stick.</p>
                    <p>Above on both sides, lotus buds with dots in the interstices; on
                        the sides, net pattern with two knots; below, broad reserved band.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Dilute glaze:</hi> fringes of the
                        hair, handles of the skyphos.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Unattributed ca. 500 - 475 B.C.</p>
                    <p>D. von Bothmer has related this vase to the work of the painter
                        Myson, the originator of the red-figure mannerist movement. One can compare
                        especially two pelikai, one in Syracuse (<rs type="vase">Syracuse 15709</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 238, no.
                        3</bibl>) and one in Naples (<rs type="vase">Naples 3051</rs>;
                            <bibl>ARV2, 238, no. 4</bibl>). The long
                        limbs, affected poses, and rhythmic composition are characteristic of the
                        mannerist movement, which can be traced from the ripe archaic period well
                        into the free period (see <rs type="vase">Bowdoin 1913.30</rs>
                        and <rs type="vase">Harvard 1959.188</rs>).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Fogg Art Museum, Harvard
                            University, <title>The Coins and Vases of Arthur Stone
                                Dewing</title>, exhibition catalogue (March 11 - April 15, 1971) 14,
                            no. 20</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Hartford 1963.40" type="vase">Hartford
                        1963.40</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>RED-FIGURE LEKYTHOS</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Wadsworth Athenaeum, Hartford, Connecticut; the Ella
                        Gallup Sumner and Mary Catlin Sumner Collection (1963.40)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 13 1/2 in. (34.2
                    cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Intact; some repainting in design areas.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Goddess and a ram. The goddess holds a phiale and a scepter
                        ending in a lotus bud. She is dressed in a dotted chiton and in a
                        black-bordered himation weighted at the corners to make it hang well. Her
                        hair is looped up in a krobylos under a leafed diadem. She is accompanied by
                        a ram with fleece indicated by fine dots. Above, pairs of rightward meanders
                        alternating with one cross-square and two saltires; below, rightward
                        meanders. On the shoulder, palmettes with tendrils culminating in lotuses;
                        above, eggs and darts.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Dilute glaze:</hi> folds of the
                        chiton, ends of the hair, most of the dots and lines indicating the ram's
                        fleece (many have been retouched), the wash of the phiale.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to the Brygos Painter [Beazley] ca. 480 - 475 B.C.</p>
                    <p>The scene is perhaps an extract from the Judgment of Paris; the
                        goddess might be Hera and the ram one of Paris' flock (<bibl>ARV2, 384</bibl>). Beazley has called this a late work by
                        the Brygos Painter (ibid.).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Richter, "A Lekythos by the
                            Brygos Painter," <title>Charites</title> (Bonn 1957) 140
                            ff, pl. 19</bibl>; <bibl><title>Archaeology</title> 16 (1963) 211 ill.</bibl>; <bibl>ARV2, 384, no. 209</bibl>; <bibl>Vermeule 1968, 114 ff, fig. 2</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 366</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Bowdoin 1913.21" type="vase">Bowdoin
                        1913.21</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>FRAGMENT OF A KYLIX</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Bowdoin College Museum of Art; gift of E. P. Warren
                        (1913.21)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 1 1/8 in. (2.8 cm.);
                            <hi rend="bold">Width:</hi> 2 1/4 in. (5.7 cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>This fragment from the inside of the kylix preserves the head and
                        shoulders of a woman dressed in a chiton and with a sakkos covering her
                        hair. To the left on a stick or staff (?) is a piece of drapery or, perhaps,
                        a lyre bag. Beazley suggests that she is a cup bearer.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to the Brygos Painter [Beazley] ca. 480 - 475 B. C.</p>
                    <p>Also a late work (cf. <rs type="vase">Hartford
                            1963.40</rs>)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>ARV2, 378, no. 136</bibl>;
                            <bibl>Herbert 1964, 62, no. 164</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Amherst 1962.74" type="vase">Amherst
                        1962.74</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>RED-FIGURE KYLIX (TYPE C, Acro-cup)</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Mead Art Building, Amherst College (1962.74)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 4 3/8 in. (11.1 cm.);
                            <hi rend="bold">Diameter:</hi> 8 1/2 in. (21.6 cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Acquired in fragments; heavily restored.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Inside:</hi> youth with lyre. He is
                        dressed in a himation. To the right, palaestra equipment: sponge, strigil,
                        and aryballos. The tondo is framed with a reserved line.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side A:</hi> music. In the center a
                        youth sits on a stool (diphros) and tunes his lyre. On the left another
                        youth gives the note on his flute, and on the right a youth, also on a
                        stool, holds out a lyre. All three wear himatia, and the central youth wears
                        shoes as well. At the right, a Doric column; suspended in the field, cases
                        for the flute and lyre; under handle AB, a dog.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side B:</hi> fragmentary. On the
                        left, a male figure to left with staff; the middle figure is missing; on the
                        right, a man's heel. A reserved band forms the ground line.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red:</hi> strings of lyres, dog's
                        collar, edge of mantle, fillets.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to the Dokimasia Painter [Beazley] ca. 500 - 475 B. C.</p>
                    <p>The painter is named after the subject of a kylix in Berlin (<rs type="vase">Berlin F 2296</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 412, no. 1</bibl>) which shows an inspection
                            (<foreign xml:lang="greek">*D*O*K*I*M*A*S*I*A</foreign>)
                        of horses. He belonged to the circle of the Brygos Painter (<rs type="vase">Hartford 1963.40</rs> and <rs type="vase">Bowdoin 1913.21</rs>).</p>
                    <p>The subjects of the interior and exterior of the cup were often
                        related. The youth on the inside can be thought of as part of the musical
                        gathering outside.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>ARV2, 1651, no. 22 bis</bibl>;
                            <bibl><title>Hesperia Art
                                Bulletin</title> 17 (1961) no. 108, pp. 6-7</bibl>; <bibl>C. H. Morgan, "The Classical Collection at
                            Amherst College," <title>Archaeology</title> 20 (1967) 2
                            ff, fig. p. 7</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Bowdoin 1913.26" type="vase">Bowdoin
                        1913.26</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>FRAGMENT OF A KYLIX (TYPE B, decorated inside
                    only)</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Bowdoin College Museum of Art; gift of E. P. Warren
                        (1913.26)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 2 3/8 in. (6 cm.); <hi rend="bold">Width:</hi> 6 1/2 in. (16.5 cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>The bottom of the bowl, part of one handle, part of the foot
                        preserved; some restoration. From Cervetri.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Inside:</hi> athletes. On the left,
                        an athlete sits on the ground holding a javelin. Behind, another athlete
                        moves to the left looking back; his javelin is behind him, the thong for
                        adjusting it visible. Both athletes are nude and wear apicate fillets in
                        their hair. Around the tondo near the border is a meaningless inscription.
                        Leftward meander border.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red:</hi> fillets, inscription.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to the Foundry Painter [Beazley] ca. 500 - 475 B. C.</p>
                    <p>The Foundry Painter belongs to the circle of the Brygos Painter.
                        He was named for a cup in Berlin (<rs type="vase">Berlin F
                        2294</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 400, no. 1</bibl>) which
                        depicts a foundry. His works display an acute observation of everyday
                        scenes, a trait which led Beazley to characterize the Foundry Painter as "a
                        Greek realist" (<bibl>Beazley 1966, no. 3, pp.
                            53-60</bibl>).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>ARV2, 403, no. 32</bibl>; <bibl>Herbert 1964, 64, no. 170</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Bowdoin 1923.30" type="vase">Bowdoin
                        1923.30</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>RED-FIGURE ASKOS (SHAPE I)</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Bowdoin College Museum of Art; gift of E. P. Warren
                        (1923.30)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 2 7/16 in. (6.2 cm.);
                            <hi rend="bold">Diameter:</hi> 3 1/4 in. (8.2 cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Broken and repaired; missing some pieces.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>On one side Eros flies to the left with a tendril in his left
                        hand and a flower in his right. Inscribed beneath him, <foreign xml:lang="greek">[epig-rough]*O *P*A*I*S</foreign> (the boy).</p>
                    <p>On the other side a second Eros flies to the right, arms extended
                        in greeting. Inscribed beneath him, <foreign xml:lang="greek">*K*A*L*O*S</foreign> (beautiful).</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Dilute glaze:</hi> secondary inner
                        markings.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red:</hi> one wreath and the flower.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">White:</hi> one wreath, the tendril,
                        and the inscription.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to Makron [Beazley] ca. 490 - 480 B. C.</p>
                    <p>The Bowdoin askos is the earliest known red-figure askos; the
                        shape is not yet canonical but is an early form of shape I (<bibl>Beazley, "An Askos by Macron," <title>AJA</title> 25 [1921] 326</bibl>). The function of
                        askoi is not known. It has been suggested that they contained oil, but it is
                        also likely that they contained vinegar and were used together with lekythoi
                        as oil and vinegar containers on the table (D. von Bothmer, orally).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Beazley, "An Askos by Macron,"
                                <title>AJA</title> 25 (1921) 325 ff</bibl>; <bibl>Greifenhagen 1957, 21, figs. 15-16, p. 88,
                            fig. 54</bibl>; <bibl>ARV2, 480, no.
                        339</bibl>; <bibl>Herbert 1964, 63, no.
                        166</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:RISD 25.074" type="vase">RISD 25.074</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>RED-FIGURE ASKOS (SHAPE II)</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Museum of Art, Rhode Island School of Design; museum
                        appropriation and special gift (Mrs. Gustav Radeke) (25.074)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 2 3/16 in. (5.6 cm.);
                            <hi rend="bold">Diameter:</hi> 2 7/8 in. (7.2 cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Missing handle; minor abrasions on one side.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>On both sides, reclining maenads. Both wear chitons with a kolpos
                        overfold. They have ivy wreaths in their hair and recline against gaily
                        colored cushions. Behind one of the maenads is a thyrsos; the other holds a
                        skyphos.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red:</hi> wreaths, tassels of belts,
                        rim of skyphos.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to Makron [Beazley] ca. 490 - 480 B. C.</p>
                    <p>The abrupt transition between frontal and profile views on the
                        maenads, as on the Erotes of the Bowdoin askos, helps place both askoi
                        within the early work of Makron. The subjects (reclining maenads, flying
                        Erotes) are both well suited to the narrow fields of decoration provided by
                        the vessel.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl><title>BullRhode</title> 16 (1928) 50 passim</bibl>; <bibl>S. B. Luce, "Four Red-Figured Vases in Providence,"
                                <title>AJA</title> 35 (1931) 298 ff</bibl>; <bibl>CVA, USA 2, p. 26, pl. 17, 4</bibl>; <bibl>ARV2, 480, no. 338</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:E. Vermeule Collection (Buitron No. 49)" type="vase">E. Vermeule Collection (Buitron No. 49)</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>FRAGMENTS OF A KYLIX</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by Emily Dickinson Blake Vermeule</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <l><hi rend="bold">a. Height:</hi> 3 3/8 in.
                        (8.5 cm.); <hi rend="bold">length:</hi> 8 1/4 in. (21 cm.)</l>
                    <l><hi rend="bold">b. Height:</hi>1 9/16 in.
                        (4 cm.); <hi rend="bold">length:</hi> 3 3/4 in. (9.5 cm.)</l>
                    <l><hi rend="bold">c. Height:</hi>1 3/4 in.
                        (4.5 cm.); <hi rend="bold">length:</hi> 4 3/8 in. (11 cm.)</l>
                    <l><hi rend="bold">d. Height:</hi>7/8 in. (2.3
                        cm.); <hi rend="bold">length:</hi> 2 in. (5 cm.)</l>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Interior (not shown):</hi> two feet
                        to right and the tail of a satyr preserved, meander border.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Fragments a and b</hi> from side A
                        show Herakles and Alkyoneus. Herakles, wearing lion skin and scabbard,
                        approaches the giant Alkyoneus. He holds his sword in one hand (the tip of
                        the scabbard visible behind) and a bow and two arrows in the other hand.
                        Alkyoneus is asleep, his face frontal, one leg bent, his right arm behind
                        his head, and his huge club beside him. Hypnos, Sleep, a tiny winged youth,
                        crouches on his chest. Inscribed behind, <foreign xml:lang="greek">*L*E*A*G*R*O*S *K</foreign> (Leagros is [beautiful]).
                        Fragment b preserves the top of Alkyoneus' head, his hand, and the upper
                        part of the club, as well as handle AB.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Fragments c and d</hi> from side B
                        depict Herakles and Antaios (?). Fragment c preserves the torso, part of the
                        beard and face of Herakles and the beard and hand of Antaios. Fragment d
                        preserves the lower leg and heel of Herakles.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Unattributed ca. 500 - 480 B. C.</p>
                    <p>The battle of Herakles and Alkyoneus took place during the war of
                        the gods and giants. Since no giant could perish at the hands of the gods, a
                        mortal, Herakles, was enlisted to help. With the help of Hypnos, Herakles
                        slew the giant Alkyoneus. The myth is depicted on twenty-five known vases.
                        In the earliest versions Hypnos was not shown, but by ca. 510 B. C. he has
                        appeared in the scene and is especially popular on red-figure vases (<bibl>B. Andreae, "Herakles und Alkyoneus," <title>JdI</title> 71 [1962] 130 ff</bibl>). The vase has
                        been related to the Proto-Panaitian Group (D. von Bothmer). It will be
                        published by Penelope Truitt.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p>Unpublished.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="50" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:E. Vermeule Collection (Buitron No. 50)" type="vase">E. Vermeule Collection (Buitron No. 50)</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>FRAGMENT OF A KYLIX</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by Emily Dickinson Blake Vermeule</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Diameter of tondo:</hi>3 1/2 in.
                        (8.9 cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Interior:</hi> youth holding a hare.
                        A youth with a chlamys draped over his arms, an ivy wreath in his hair, and
                        an anklet on his left leg holds a hare by its ears and hind legs. He is
                        ready to start the hare for coursing. Behind him is his palaestra equipment:
                        sponge and aryballos. Inscribed above, <foreign xml:lang="greek">[*K]*A*L*O]*S</foreign> (beautiful).</p>
                    <p>A reserved line frames the tondo.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red:</hi> wreath, inscription,
                        anklet, fillet.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Unattributed ca. 500 - 475 B. C.</p>
                    <p>The subject, starting a hare for coursing, is popular with late
                        archaic artists. For style one can compare a kyathos in Brussels (<rs type="vase">Brussels A 2323</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 333, no. 2</bibl>) attributed to the Manner of
                        Onesimos (P. Truitt), as well as a cup in Heidelberg (<rs type="vase">Heidelberg B 52</rs>) attributed to the Antiphon Group (D.
                        von Bothmer).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p>Unpublished.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="51" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Bowdoin 1930.1" type="vase">Bowdoin
                    1930.1</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>FRAGMENT OF A KYLIX</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Bowdoin College Museum of Art; gift of E.P. Warren
                        (1930.1)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Width:</hi>6 3/8 in. (16.2 cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Missing pieces restored and painted. From Cervetri.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Interior:</hi> a nude girl holds a
                        skyphos in one hand, which she will fill, presumably with a ladle, from a
                        column-krater at her feet. Inscribed around the border of the scene,
                            <foreign xml:lang="greek">[*P]*A*N*A*I[*T]*I*O*S
                            *K*A*L*O[*S]</foreign> (Panaitios is beautiful) and on the skyphos,
                            <foreign xml:lang="greek">*D*O*R*I*S</foreign> (Douris).
                        The krater is wreathed with ivy. The tondo is framed by a leftward meander.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Dilute glaze:</hi> necklace, creases
                        at girl's waist.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red:</hi> fillet in the girl's hair,
                        the inscriptions.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to Onesimos [Beazley] ca. 490 - 480 B. C.</p>
                    <p>The two fragments showing the legs of the girl and the bottom of
                        the krater were found by A. Rumpf and added later. The three fragments
                        showing the back of the girl's head, her right arm, and part of the
                        inscription were added by Dietrich von Bothmer and given by him to Bowdoin
                        College. The name of Onesimos is known from a cup in the Louvre (<rs type="vase">Louvre G 105</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 324, no. 60</bibl>) on which he signs as painter
                        and Euphronios signs as potter. The early work of Onesimos was attributed by
                        Beazley to the Panaitios Painter, who takes his name from the kalos name
                        Panaitios. Later he decided that the work of this painter was actually an
                        early stage in the development of Onesimos (<bibl>ARV2, 313</bibl>).</p>
                    <p>The use of the kalos name Panaitios on this fragment, along with
                        the forceful and unrefined style help to place it as an early work by
                        Onesimos. The name on the skyphos is possibly that of the vase painter
                        Douris, or as D. von Bothmer has suggested, it may be the name of the girl
                        since Douris is also the name of one of the Nereids as well as a common name
                        for hetairae.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Beazley 1918, 86, fig.
                        54</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley, "Three Red-Figured
                            Cups," <title>JHS</title> 39 (1919) 83, pl. 2, 1</bibl>;
                            <bibl>Richter 1958, 62, fig. 21</bibl>;
                            <bibl>Cook 1960, 171, pl. 40</bibl>; <bibl>ARV2, 328, no. 114</bibl>; <bibl>Herbert 1964, 62-63, no. 165</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="52" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Boston 98.930" type="vase">Boston
                    98.930</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>RED-FIGURE KYLIX (TYPE B)</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Museum of Fine Arts, Boston; H. L. Pierce Fund
                        (98.930)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 4 in. (10.1 cm.); <hi rend="bold">Diameter:</hi> 10 1/16 in. (25.5 cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Handles modern.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Interior:</hi> komast. A nude man
                        stands on one leg and lifts the other over a cup which stands on a low
                        block. He is in the process of performing a trick. His himation rests on top
                        of a folded seat at the left. Inscribed above, <foreign xml:lang="greek">*D*O*R*I*S *E*G*R*A*F*S*E*N</foreign> (Douris painted
                        this).</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side A:</hi> komos. In the center a
                        man in a chlamys plays a flute; facing him is a man with a skyphos. Two men
                        with kylikes follow the flute player. On the left another man prepares for a
                        trick; beside him a man in chlamys holds out a kylix.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side B:</hi> komos. A man dances in
                        the center; his friend holds his skyphos as well as his own cup. Behind are
                        two men (heads missing) with cups; one with an oinochoe as well. On the left
                        are a lyre player (edge of lyre preserved; head of man missing) and his
                        companion with a kylix.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Dilute glaze:</hi> anatomical
                        details.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red:</hi> fillets.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Signed by Douris ca. 490 - 480 B. C.</p>
                    <p>The signature of Douris, nearly always as painter, is known on
                        forty vases. Over two hundred have been attributed to him on stylistic
                        grounds. He was evidently active for many years. His oeuvre has been divided
                        into four periods on the basis of his kalos name and his decorative scheme.</p>
                    <p>The bare decoration and simple borders of this kylix place it in
                        his early middle period. Early in his career Douris began an association
                        with the potter Python. The form of the foot on vases by this potter is
                        distinguished by a sharp ridge in the profile of the foot (<bibl>Caskey &amp; Beazley, 3, p. 19</bibl>;
                        see also <bibl>Bloesch 1940, 97</bibl>).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Beazley 1918, 98</bibl>; <bibl>Hoppin 1919, 1, pp. 226-227</bibl>; <bibl>Langlotz 1922, pls. 22, 23</bibl>; <bibl>P. Duell, "The Tomba del Triclinio at
                            Tarquinia," <title>MAAR</title> 6 (1927) pl. 12 B,
                        a</bibl>; <bibl>ARV2, 431, no. 45</bibl>; <bibl>Caskey &amp; Beazley, 3, pl. 72, p. 19,
                            no. 126</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="53" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Harvard 1925.30.129" type="vase">Harvard
                        1925.30.129</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>RED-FIGURE KYLIX (TYPE B)</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Fogg Art Museum, Harvard University; bequest of J. C.
                        Hoppin (1925.30.129)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 4 1/4 in. (10.7 cm.);
                            <hi rend="bold">Diameter:</hi> 11 5/8 in. (29.4 cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Broken and repaired; missing piece of foot had been replaced with
                        a foreign piece, now removed. From Capua.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Interior:</hi> satyr and maenad. A
                        maenad with thyrsos in one hand walks to the right looking back at a satyr
                        who grasps her wrist and shoulder. She wears an Ionic chiton, black-bordered
                        himation, and a sakkos on her head. The satyr is nude except for a fillet in
                        his hair. Behind the satyr are a rock and a drinking horn. Between the rock
                        and satyr is an inscription <foreign xml:lang="greek">[epig-rough]*E *P*A*I*S *K*A*L*E</foreign> (the girl is beautiful). The
                        tondo is framed by opposed meanders interrupted with saltires.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side A:</hi> Dionysos, satyrs, and
                        maenads. The bearded god holds an ivy branch in one hand and, presumably, a
                        drinking cup in the other. A satyr advancing from the left lifts his
                        oinochoe to fill the cup. Behind him is a maenad (missing head and part of
                        body). On the right a satyr with face frontal and a maenad with thyrsos.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side B:</hi> satyrs and maenads. In
                        the center a satyr threatens a maenad who walks away from him. At the left a
                        maenad repulses a satyr, and on the right stands a third maenad (missing
                        face). At the handles, palmettes and volutes.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Dilute glaze:</hi> anatomical
                        details of satyr.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red:</hi> fillets of satyrs and
                        maenads.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to Douris [Hoppin] ca. 480 B. C.</p>
                    <p>The meander-saltire border of the tondo and the handle palmettes
                        are characteristic Dourian types and help place this kylix in the middle
                        period of his oeuvre. Close to this is a kylix in Boston (<rs type="vase">Boston 00.499</rs>; <bibl>ARV2,
                            435, no. 89</bibl>) inscribed ``Hippodamas is beautiful," the kalos name
                        popular with Douris during this period. The same border is used, and a
                        remarkably similar composition is on the outside: quintets of revelling
                        satyrs and maenads. Python was the potter of this vase (D. von Bothmer).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Hoppin, <title>AJA</title> 6 (1902) 24, no. 1</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley 1918, 99</bibl>; <bibl>Hoppin 1918, 1, p. 280, no. 59</bibl>; <bibl>Caskey 1922, 203, fig. 156</bibl>; <bibl>Walston 1924, 242, fig. 14, 1 and 2</bibl>; <bibl>CVA, USA 1, p. 7, pls. 9, 10</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley, Review CVA USA 1, by Hoppin, <title>JHS</title> 47 (1927) 148</bibl>; <bibl>D. C. Rich, Review <title>CVA</title> USA
                            1 by Hoppin, <hi rend="ital">AJA</hi> 33 (1929) 338</bibl>;
                            <bibl>ARV2, 436, no. 112</bibl>; <bibl>Wegner 1968, 149, 154 ff, 246</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="54" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Rosenberg Collection (Buitron No. 54)" type="vase">Rosenberg Collection (Buitron No. 54)</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>RED-FIGURE STEMLESS CUP</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by Professor and Mrs. Jakob Rosenberg</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 1 3/8 in. (3.4 cm.);
                            <hi rend="bold">Diameter:</hi> 5 1/2 in. (3.9 cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Intact save for chip on one handle.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Interior:</hi> a youth wearing shoes
                        and a dark bordered himation stands in a wine shop. In his right hand he
                        holds a sponge with which he tests the taste and bouquet of the wine. In his
                        other hand is his purse. Wine merchants bought their wine after testing a
                        sample in this way (<bibl>R. J. Forbes, <title>Studies in Ancient Technology</title> 3 [Leyden
                            1955] 112</bibl>). The wine is stored in a large amphora set in a
                        cylindrical stand. On the right is the upper part of another storage vase
                        (pithos) and hanging on the wall is a small oinochoe for ladling. The
                        inscription on the left reads <foreign xml:lang="greek">*T*R*I*K*O*T*U*L*O*S</foreign> (three measures, either the amount he
                        wants to buy or an estimate of the quality of the wine; <bibl>H. Immerwahr, "An Athenian Wine-Shop," <title>Proceedings of the American Philological
                            Association</title> 79 [1948] 184-190</bibl>). The tondo is framed with
                        pairs of opposed meanders alternating with saltires.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Dilute glaze:</hi> lower part of the
                        hair; anatomical details on neck, shoulder, arm, and chest; texture of the
                        sponge.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to Douris [Holland, Chase] ca. 480 B. C.</p>
                    <p>The composition of the tondo is similar to that of the kylix in
                        Boston (<rs type="vase">Boston 00.499</rs>) previously cited.
                        The solution to the problem of the round area is somewhat more successful in
                        our example: the round wine vessels echo the shape of the tondo, and a more
                        harmonious space results. This vase must be close in date to the Boston
                        piece; both belong to Douris' middle period (<bibl>B. M. Holland, "A Kylix in the Fogg Art Museum," <title>Harvard Studies in Classical Philology</title> 52
                            [1941] 56</bibl>).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>B. M. Holland, "A Kylix in the
                            Fogg Art Museum," <title>Harvard Studies in Classical
                                Philology</title> 52 (1941) 41 ff, pl. 1</bibl>; <bibl>CVA, USA 8, pp. 35-36, pl. 19,2</bibl>; <bibl>R. J. Forbes, <title>Studies
                                in Ancient Technology</title> 3 (Leyden 1955) 113</bibl>; <bibl>ARV2, 445, no. 252</bibl>; <bibl>Wegner 1968, 215 (attribution
                        questioned)</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="55" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:E. Vermeule Collection (Buitron No. 55)" type="vase">E. Vermeule Collection (Buitron No. 55)</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>FRAGMENT OF A KYLIX</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by Emily Dickinson Blake Vermeule</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 3 3/16 in. (8 cm.); <hi rend="bold">Width:</hi> 2 5/8 in. (6.7 cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Three pieces preserved.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>The fragment, from the interior of a kylix, preserves the head
                        and shoulders of two youths. One wears a himation over one shoulder and
                        holds a sprouting staff; the other wears his mantle over the back of his
                        head. Both wear broad fillets. Inscribed above <foreign xml:lang="greek">[*K*A]*L*O*S</foreign> (beautiful). A border of
                        stopped meanders with cross-squares frames the tondo.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Dilute glaze:</hi> details of the
                        abdominal muscles of one youth.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red:</hi> fillets, the
                    inscription.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to Douris [Bothmer] ca. 480 - 470 B. C.</p>
                    <p>The meander border and use of a kalos name suggest that the
                        fragment belongs to Douris' middle period. The subject is probably a
                        courting scene.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p>Unpublished.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="56" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Bowdoin 1913.18" type="vase">Bowdoin
                        1913.18</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>FRAGMENT FROM THE RIM OF A KYLIX</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Bowdoin College Museum of Art; gift of E. P. Warren
                        (1913.18)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 1 1/8 in. (2.8 cm.);
                            <hi rend="bold">Width:</hi> 2 1/8 in. (5.3 cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>The head of a bearded man and three fingers of his right hand are
                        preserved. To the left is the rim of a warrior's shield. To the right is the
                        tendril from a handle palmette and the top of the man's stick.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red:</hi> fillet of the man.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to Douris [Beazley] ca. 480 - 470 B. C.</p>
                    <p>This fragment joins on in Florence (<rs type="vase">Florence 7 B25</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 439, no.
                            152</bibl>), possibly two others also in Florence, and three in the
                        Villa Giulia (<bibl>ARV2, 439, nos.
                        153-157</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley 1933a, 14, pl. 7,
                            nos. 25, 31-34, 38</bibl>). The scene depicts warriors and men. The
                        careful treatment of hair, eyes, beard as well as the use of palmettes at
                        the handle suggest that this fragment belongs in Douris' late period.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Beazley 1933a, 14, pl. 7, no.
                            25</bibl>; <bibl>ARV2, 439, no.
                    152</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="57" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Boston 1970.233" type="vase">Boston
                        1970.233</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>RED-FIGURE KYLIX (TYPE B)</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Museum of Fine Arts, Boston; gift of Landon T. Clay
                        (1970.233)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 3 1/16 in. (7.8 cm.);
                            <hi rend="bold">Diameter:</hi> 8 5/16 in. (21.2 cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Broken and repaired; missing pieces restored and painted.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Interior:</hi> lovemaking. At the
                        left is part of a couch (kline) with a striped pillow on it; at the right, a
                        foot stool on which the girl's chiton is folded; suspended above, an
                        aryballos. Inscribed above, <foreign xml:lang="greek">h( pais
                            kale</foreign> (the girl is beautiful); across the girl's waist <foreign xml:lang="greek">h(xe h(si[x]os</foreign> (hold still).
                        The tondo is framed by pairs of facing meanders alternating with
                        cross-squares.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Dilute glaze:</hi> ornament on post,
                        anatomical details of man.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red:</hi> inscription.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to Douris [Beazley] ca. 480 - 470 B. C.</p>
                    <p>The inscription on this vase, <foreign xml:lang="greek">h(xe h(si[x]os</foreign>, provides the earliest
                        evidence for the expression, "hold still," in the Greek language (<bibl>ARV2, 444, no. 241</bibl>). Conversational
                        inscriptions, although rare, are known on other vases, e. g. the cup in
                        Richmond (Virginia) attributed to the manner of Douris (<bibl>ARV2, 450, no. 24</bibl>) where a man says <foreign xml:lang="greek">a)podos</foreign> (go away) to a boy
                            (<bibl>Münzen, 40 [Basel December 13,
                            1969] 56</bibl>) and a cup in Boston (<rs type="vase">Boston 65.873</rs>; <bibl>E. Vermeule, "A
                            Love Scene by the Panaitios Painter," <title>AJA</title>
                            71 [1967] 311 ff</bibl>) where the man says <foreign xml:lang="greek">e)ason</foreign> (let me) and the boy says <foreign xml:lang="greek">ou) pausei</foreign> (won't you stop). D.
                        G. Mitten refers for the scheme to a cup by the Briseis Painter in Tarquinia
                            (<bibl>ARV2, 408, no. 36</bibl>).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>ARV2, 444, no. 241</bibl>;
                            <bibl>Münzen, 40 (Basel December 13,
                            1969) 56, no. 93</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="58" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Harvard 1959.193" type="vase">Harvard
                        1959.193</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>RED-FIGURE LEKYTHOS</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Fogg Art Museum, Harvard University; gift of
                        Frederick M. Watkins (1959.193)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 11 13/16 in. (30
                    cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Intact. From Sicily.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>A woman dressed in chiton, himation, and sakkos looks to the
                        right. In her out-stretched hand she holds an alabastron. Behind her is a
                        small chest. On the neck, tongues; at the base, two stopped meanders, a
                        cross-square, then four stopped meanders.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Dilute glaze:</hi> the folds on the
                        upper part of the chiton.</p>
                    <p>Traces of preliminary sketch can be seen at the shoulder.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to the Manner of Douris [Beazley]</p>
                    <p>ca. 480 - 470 B. C.</p>
                    <p>The shape and decoration of this lekythos relate it to Douris'
                        late period. Compare lekythoi in Vienna (<rs type="vase">Vienna
                            Univ. 526 a</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 447, no.
                        272</bibl>) and in Boston (<rs type="vase">Boston 95.41</rs>;
                            <bibl>ARV2, 447, no. 270</bibl>). All three
                        are characterized by sparse decoration on the neck, no decoration on the
                        shoulder, and a rather careless meander ground line.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl><title>Collection de feu M. Jean P. Lambros</title> (Athens) <hi rend="ital">et de M. Giovanni Dattari</hi> (Cairo)
                            (Paris June 17-19, 1912) pl. 7, no. 51</bibl>; <bibl>Hôtel Drouet, <title>Collection
                                Hirsch</title> (Paris June 30 - July 2, 1921) pl. 3, no. 169</bibl>;
                            <bibl>ARV2, 451, no. 34</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="59" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Yale 1913.143" type="vase">Yale
                    1913.143</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>RED-FIGURE OINOCHOE (OLPE)</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Yale University Art Gallery; gift of Rebecca
                        Darlington Stoddard (1913.143)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 16 in. (40.6 cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Broken and repaired.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Poseidon and Theseus. Poseidon, wearing a black-bordered himation
                        and holding a trident, greets Theseus, dressed for travel in chlamys and
                        petasos and holding two spears in one hand. Below, triple rightward meanders
                        alternating with cross-squares; on the lip, egg pattern.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to the Painter of the Yale Oinochoe, his name piece
                        [Beazley] ca. 470 - 460 B. C.</p>
                    <p>The broader arrangement of the figures and less schematic folds
                        of the drapery are characteristic of the early free style. The subject is
                        also treated in a new way. The story, as told by Bacchylides (<bibl n="Bacchyl. Dith. 17">Bacchyl. 17</bibl>), took
                        place during the voyage to Crete. Minos challenged Theseus to prove that
                        Poseidon was his father by throwing his gold ring into the sea and ordering
                        Theseus to find it. With the aid of his divine father, Theseus retrieved the
                        ring. Earlier representations of the meeting of Theseus and Poseidon had
                        included several of the denizens of Poseidon's underwater palace, such as
                        Nereus and Amphitrite on a column-krater in the Fogg (<rs type="vase">Harvard 1960.339</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 274, no. 39</bibl>) and Triton and the Nereids on a kylix in New
                        York (<rs type="vase">New York 53.11.4</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 406, no. 7</bibl>). On this vase, most of the
                        mythological details have been eliminated, and the god and hero are shown
                        much as an ordinary father greeting or bidding farewell to his son.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Beazley 1918, 61</bibl>; <bibl>Hoppin 1919, 2, p. 484, no. 6</bibl>; <bibl>Baur 1922, 96, no. 143</bibl>; <bibl>ARV2, 503, no. 25</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="60" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Bowdoin 1913.30" type="vase">Bowdoin
                        1913.30</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>RED-FIGURE NOLAN AMPHORA</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Bowdoin College Museum of Art; gift of E. P. Warren
                        (1913.30)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 12 3/16 in. (31
                    cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Broken and repaired at lip. From Gela.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side A:</hi> a youth, himation
                        covering the lower half of his body, sits on a chair and plays flutes.
                        Another youth, leaning on a cane and holding a flute, looks on.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side B:</hi> a youth with a walking
                        stick runs to the right, his head turned back and his right arm stretched
                        out to the left.</p>
                    <p>Pairs of meanders to right, alternating with cross-squares,
                        saltires, and checkerboards, circle the entire vase. Under the handles,
                        hanging palmettes and tendrils.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Dilute glaze:</hi> anatomical
                        details.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red:</hi> fillets of the three
                        youths.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to the Pan Painter [Beazley] ca. 470 - 460 B. C.</p>
                    <p>Beazley has described the drawing of the Pan Painter as "a blend
                        of late archaic daintiness and early classical grandeur" <bibl>Caskey &amp; Beazley, 2, p. 46</bibl>). Elements of
                        the mannerist tradition of Myson, to which the Pan Painter is heir, are
                        evident on this vase in the rhythmic drapery folds and elegant fingers. At
                        the same time, the figures are imbued with a new freedom, and posture and
                        movement are more fully understood. This vase is a late work by the Pan
                        Painter.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Beazley, <title>JHS</title> 32 (1912) 360, no. 30</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley 1918, 115</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley 1931, 17, pl. 11, 2</bibl>; <bibl>ARV2, 553, no. 43</bibl>; <bibl>Herbert 1964, 68, no. 185, pl. 24, 1</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 386, no. 43</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="61" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Harvard 1959.188" type="vase">Harvard
                        1959.188</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>RED-FIGURE PELIKE</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Fogg Art Museum, Harvard University; gift of
                        Frederick M. Watkins (1959.188)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 14 3/4 in. (37.5
                    cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Broken and repaired; missing pieces restored and painted.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side A:</hi> komos. A woman with a
                        sakkos on her head plays a small cithara; her mouth is open and her head
                        back, indicating that she is singing. On the left is a youth with a walking
                        stick and a barbiton (long-armed lyre); on the right a youth lifts a column
                        krater decorated with a garland of ivy. Between the last youth and the woman
                        is a small stool (diphros) on which drapery is folded.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side B:</hi> komos. Two youths and a
                        man walk to the right. The first youth, carrying a wineskin and an oinochoe,
                        turns back towards his companions. The second youth plays a flute; the man
                        carries a pointed amphora and a lyre. All three wear ivy wreaths in their
                        hair and chlamides over their shoulders.</p>
                    <p>Above on both sides, lotus buds with dots in the interstices;
                        circling the vase below, simple rightward key between double lines.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Dilute glaze:</hi> edge of the
                        woman's hair, edge of the man's beard, inner markings on one youth.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red:</hi> the ivy wreaths, fillet on
                        the woman's sakkos, cords tied to the lyres and cithara, ends of the strings
                        at the pegs of the crossbar.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to the Manner of the Pig Painter [Beazley] ca. 470 -
                        450 B. C.</p>
                    <p>The Pig Painter is also a close follower of Myson (cf. <bibl>Buitron 1972, no. 42</bibl>) and an able
                        mannerist of the early free period. He is named for the two pigs on a pelike
                        in Cambridge (<rs type="vase">Cambridge 9.17</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 564, no. 27</bibl>) showing Odysseus
                        and Eumaios. He was fond of large vases, especially column-kraters and
                        pelikai, as was the mannerist school in general. Characteristic of his style
                        are the small eyes, thin moustache, and stylized ears. He is distinguished
                        for his rhythmical compositions which are especially note-worthy on side B
                        of this vase.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>ARV2, 566, no. 8</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="62" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Harvard 1925.30.130" type="vase">Harvard
                        1925.30.130</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>RED-FIGURE KYLIX (TYPE B)</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Fogg Art Museum, Harvard University; bequest of J. C.
                        Hoppin (1925.30.130)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 4 7/16 in. (11.3 cm.);
                            <hi rend="bold">Diameter:</hi> 10 13/16 in. (27.4 cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Broken and repaired; missing pieces restored and painted. From
                        Capua.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Interior:</hi> a satyr tries to
                        seize a maenad who looks back at him as she walks off to the left. She
                        carries a thyrsos; her right foot projects into the border. Leftward meander
                        border.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side A:</hi> return of a victor. In
                        the center Iris, with wings outspread, holds a caduceus and looks to her
                        left toward an approaching warrior. The warrior, in Thracian helmet and
                        carrying a shield (device: open eye), bends forward to place a laurel branch
                        at her feet, a gift of thanks. Iris seems to be presenting the warrior to
                        the bearded man at the left who is sitting on a diphros and holding a
                        scepter. Perhaps he is Zeus, in which case the scene might depict the thank
                        offering to Zeus after the Persian war (<bibl>Beazley, Review <title>CVA</title> USA 1 by Hoppin, <hi rend="ital">JHS</hi> 47 [1927] 148</bibl>). Behind Zeus
                        is a peg for the helmet.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side B:</hi> departure of a warrior.
                        In the center is a nude bearded warrior carrying a shield with its shield
                        apron (decorated with an open eye) and a staff. At the right, Iris carrying
                        a caduceus. At the left, a bearded man wrapped in a mantle, perhaps the
                        warrior's father sunk in grief. Under the handles, single palmettes with
                        tendrils and leaves.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Dilute glaze:</hi> anatomical
                        details, ends of the hair, leaves of the thyrsos, feathers of Iris'
                    wings.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to the Penthesilea Painter [Hoppin] ca. 470 - 460 B.
                        C.</p>
                    <p>The sketchy but lively characterization of the figures on this
                        cup reflects the naturalistic trend in vase painting of which the
                        Penthesilea Painter was the chief exponent. The painter is named for a kylix
                        in Munich (<rs type="vase">Munich 2688</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 879, no. 1</bibl>) which shows Achilles falling in
                        love with the Amazon queen, Penthesilea, as he kills her. The winged goddess
                        is probably Iris since she is carrying a caduceus, her usual attribute (D.
                        von Bothmer).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Beazley 1918, 131</bibl>; <bibl>Hoppin, <title>AJA</title>
                            22 (1918) 69, no. 7</bibl>; <bibl>Hoppin
                            1919, vol. 2, p. 340, no. 13 bis</bibl>; <bibl>CVA, USA 1, p. 8, pl. 11</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley, Review <title>CVA</title> USA 1
                            by Hoppin, <hi rend="ital">JHS</hi> 47 (1927) 148</bibl>;
                            <bibl>ARV2, 881, no. 29</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="63" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Mount Holyoke 1932.BS.II.5" type="vase">Mount Holyoke 1932.BS.II.5</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>RED-FIGURE PYXIS (TYPE A)</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Mount Holyoke College Art Museum (1932 BS II.5)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height with lid:</hi> 6 3/4 in. (17
                        cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Broken and repaired; missing pieces restored and painted; some
                        repainting on design areas.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Woman, youth, and maid. To the right of a large door a woman is
                        seated holding a ball of wool in her hand. In front of her is a wool basket
                        above which is draped a piece of cloth. Next, a youth leaning on a staff
                        extends an arm with a ball of wool. In his other hand is a piece of cloth.
                        Lastly, a maid carrying a mirror and a piece of drapery, runs to the right
                        towards the door. The mirror's top, the hanging drapery, and the drapery of
                        the youth are partly restored. On the lid, laurel wreath and tongue pattern.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">White:</hi> balls of wool, wool in
                        basket, fruit of laurel.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to the Veii Painter [Beazley] <date>ca.
                            470 - 460 B. C.</date></p>
                    <p>The Veii Painter was a member of the Penthesilea workshop. His
                        early work, of which this is an example, is characterized by the lively but
                        careless drawing found on the lesser works of the Penthesilea Painter.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>ARV2, 906, no. 109</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="64" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Bowdoin 1908.3" type="vase">Bowdoin
                    1908.3</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>RED-FIGURE HYDRIA (KALPIS)</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Bowdoin College Museum of Art; gift of E. P. Warren
                        (1908.3)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 15 7/8 in. (40.2
                    cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Boreas and Oreithyia. Oreithyia is said to have been carried off
                        by Boreas, the North Wind, from the banks of the Ilissus where she was
                        dancing or gathering flowers with her playmates. On this vase Boreas, shown
                        with wings and winged boots, swoops down and grasps Oreithyia to carry her
                        off. At the right Athena looks on. The composition continues around the
                        vase. Behind Athena are two of Oreithyia's playmates, one with a small
                        dolphin. On the left two more companions and an old man, probably
                        Erechtheus, Oreithyia's father. Pairs of rightward meanders alternating with
                        saltires circle the vase and form a ground line. On the neck, a band of
                        diagonally placed palmettes; on the lip, egg and dot pattern; at the base of
                        the handles, framed tongues and dots.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to the Niobid Painter [Beazley] ca. 460 - 450 B. C.</p>
                    <p>Noteworthy on this vase is the enlarged field of figure
                        decoration which extends all around the vase. One can compare a hydria in
                        Boston (<rs type="vase">Boston 90.156</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 605, no. 62</bibl>) which is slightly earlier than
                        this example (<bibl>Caskey &amp; Beazley, 2,
                            p. 76</bibl>).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Beazley 1918, 195, no.
                        150</bibl>; <bibl>Jacobsthal 1927, 84, pl. 60
                        a</bibl>; <bibl>Webster 1935, 22, no. 49</bibl>;
                            <bibl>ARV2, 606, no. 68</bibl>; <bibl>Herbert 1964, 68-69, pl. 24, 2</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 395, no. 68</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="65" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Bowdoin 1930.8" type="vase">Bowdoin
                    1930.8</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>FRAGMENT OF A CALYX-KRATER</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Bowdoin College Museum of Art; gift of E. P. Warren
                        (1930.8)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 3 9/16 in. (9 cm.); <hi rend="ital">length:</hi> 7 1/2 in. (19 cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Symposion. On the left is a couch with doubled up striped
                        cushions against which two men recline. Each holds a sash or broad fillet in
                        one hand. Below, a corner of their eating table is visible. To the right a
                        flute girl with an apicate fillet on her short hair puffs away on a flute.
                        She looks to the right towards another couch where two men probably recline,
                        the knees and one arm of one visible. Above are suspended a diptych and
                        another sash.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Dilute glaze:</hi> stripes of the
                        cushions, dots around the nipples of the man.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to the Painter of the Woolly Satyrs [Beazley] ca. 460
                        - 450 B. C.</p>
                    <p>The Painter of the Woolly Satyrs was a follower of the Niobid
                        Painter but less formal. On this fragment his interest in foreshortening and
                        his markedly individual style are evident especially in the hands of the
                        men, which are convincingly foreshortened, and in the expressive but
                        disfiguring distension of the girl's cheeks.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>ARV2, 613, no. 5</bibl>; <bibl>Herbert 1964, 70, no. 189</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="66" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Harvard 1972.46" type="vase">Harvard
                        1972.46</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>RED-FIGURE HYDRIA (KALPIS)</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by Frederick M. Watkins</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 10 7/8 in. (27.7
                    cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Intact; some abrasion of glaze.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>A youth between two women. A nude youth with his cloak over his
                        left shoulder and a stick in one hand stands in the center. On the left a
                        woman runs off, looking back; on the right is a woman with one hand raised.
                        Above and below, triple meanders alternating with cross-squares; on the lip,
                        egg and dot pattern.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Dilute glaze:</hi> anatomical
                        markings, lines on the drapery.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red:</hi> fillet of the youth and of
                        the woman on the left.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to the Villa Giulia Painter [Beazley] ca. 460 - 450 B.
                        C.</p>
                    <p>The Villa Giulia Painter stands in the tradition of Douris and,
                        like him, prefers subdued and refined figures depicted with a polished
                        technique. His harmonious compositions are in opposition to the ambitious
                        efforts of his contemporary, the Niobid Painter (see <rs type="vase">Bowdoin 1908.3</rs>). Fond of scenes of everyday life, he
                        employs certain stock types such as the women and youth on this vase.
                        Although the figures appear serene, the air is tense. The subject, however,
                        remains unexplained. The vase is said to be from Gela but may be the vase
                        described by E. Peterson in <bibl>"Funde,"
                                <title>Mitteilungen des Deutschen archäologischen Instituts. Römische Abteilung</title> 8 (1893)
                            340, no. 26</bibl>, and if so, it is probably from Curti or Capua (<bibl>ARV2, 623, no. 62</bibl>).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>ARV2, 623, no. 62</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="67" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:RISD 25.088" type="vase">RISD 25.088</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>RED-FIGURE ALABASTRON</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Museum of Art, Rhode Island School of Design; museum
                        appropriation and special gift (Mrs. Gustav Radeke) (25.088)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 7 1/4 in. (18.3
                    cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Broken and repaired; missing several pieces. From Greece.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side A:</hi> woman with two
                        children. A woman dressed in chiton with kolpos, her hair worn in a
                        krobylos, looks apprehensively to her right. In her left arm is a child
                        intended to be a baby but shown with the long limbs of an adult. She wears a
                        fillet in her hair. At her side, holding onto the fold of her kolpos, is
                        another child, also looking to the left. On his body is a net pattern,
                        possibly resulting from cloth wrapping on the aryballos. In his right hand
                        is a dagger. Hanging on the wall is a sakkos, and on the ground beside the
                        woman is a wool basket.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side B:</hi> youth and woman. The
                        woman (missing head) in chiton and himation stands on the left holding a
                        mirror. She extends one hand towards a youth who sits in a chair and holds a
                        staff in one hand, extending his other hand towards the woman.</p>
                    <p>Above, below, and on the sides are triple meanders alternating
                        with cross-squares.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to the Villa Giulia Painter [Beazley] ca. 460 - 450 B.
                        C.</p>
                    <p>The pattern on the chest of the boy on side A was tested in the
                        Fogg Conservation Laboratory and found to be resistant to oxalic acid,
                        therefore it is carbonized vegetable matter, not merely a superficial stain.
                        K. Phillips suggested that this might result from the use of the vase as a
                        votive gift at the funeral pyre; we know that alabastra were used for this
                        purpose (<bibl>Richter &amp; Milne 1935,
                        17</bibl>).</p>
                    <p>The vase, intended as a funerary gift, might be said to depict
                        the departure of a loved one. The composition on the reverse, reminiscent of
                        grave stelai of the same period, might represent the farewell of a young
                        wife to her husband. On the observe, other relatives mourn for her. The calm
                        understatement of emotion is characteristic of the classical period.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>CVA, USA 2, p. 29, pl. 22,
                        3</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley, Review <title>CVA</title> USA 2 by S. B. Luce, <hi rend="ital">JHS</hi> 53 (1933) 311, no. 11 bis</bibl>; <bibl>S. B. Luce, "Four Red-Figured Vases in
                            Providence," <title>AJA</title> 35 (1931)
                        301-303</bibl>; <bibl>ARV2, 624, no.
                    88</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="68" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Bowdoin 15.17.1 and .2" type="vase">Bowdoin
                        15.17.1 and .2</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>TWO FRAGMENTS OF A CALYX-KRATER</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Bowdoin College Museum of Art; gift of E. P. Warren
                        (15.17.1 and .2)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">.1 Length:</hi> 3 15/16 in. (10 cm.)</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">.2 Length:</hi> 2 1/16 in. (5.1
                    cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>.1 preserves the body of a satyr (head and feet missing) moving
                        to the right in pursuit of a maenad.</p>
                    <p>.2 shows part of the torso, the left arm, and shoulder of the
                        maenad; she wears a sleeveless chiton and carries a thyrsos.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Dilute glaze:</hi> anatomical
                        details of satyr.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to the Euaion Painter [Beazley] ca. 460 - 450 B. C.</p>
                    <p>The refined style and polished technique of the Euaion Painter
                        continue the tradition of Douris. This special shape of oinochoe, chous, was
                        made especially for drinking wine at the festival of spring, the
                        Anthesteria, at which Dionysos as god of vegetation was worshipped (<bibl>van Hoorn 1951, 10, 15</bibl>).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Beazley 1918, 158</bibl>; <bibl>van Hoorn 1951, 115, no. 396, fig.
                        113</bibl>; <bibl>ARV2, 797, no. 145</bibl>;
                            <bibl>Herbert 1964, 71, no. 190</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="69" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Mount Holyoke 1929.BS.II.4" type="vase">Mount Holyoke 1929.BS.II.4</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>RED-FIGURE NOLAN AMPHORA</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by Mount Holyoke College Art Museum (1929 BS II.4)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 13 in. (33 cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Broken and repaired; some restoration and repainting in drapery.
                        Under foot, graffito. Said to be from Volterra.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side A:</hi> goddess and woman (Hera
                        and Hebe?). On the left, a woman, possibly Hebe, the cup bearer of the gods.
                        She wears a himation over her chiton and extends her right hand with an
                        oinochoe. On the right, a goddess, possibly Hera, with lotus-tipped scepter
                        and phiale. She wears a himation, chiton, and diadem.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side B:</hi> king (Zeus?). A bearded
                        man wearing a himation stands to right holding a lotus-tipped scepter.</p>
                    <p>On A, a strip of meander pairs alternating with saltires; on B, a
                        strip of simple rightward key.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to Polygnotos [Beazley] ca. 450 - 440 B. C.</p>
                    <p>The style of Polygnotos is ultimately derived from that of the
                        Niobid Painter (cf. <rs type="vase">Mount Holyoke
                        1932.BS.II.5</rs>), but it has much that is new in it: the lines are longer
                        and more fluid, the figures softer and fleshier, the whole drawing broader
                        and less archaic (<bibl>Beazley 1918,
                        171</bibl>). The figures on this vase have a certain nobility but are very
                        schematized, and our identification is uncertain. The name of Polygnotos is
                        known from his signature on five vases. Two other artists contemporary with
                        him sign with the same name, and as Beazley suggests, all three may have
                        taken the name from the famous mural painter, Polygnotos of Thasos (<bibl>ARV2, 1027</bibl>). The school of Polygnotos
                        was large; the Christie Painter (<rs type="vase">Harvard
                            1970.108</rs>) was one of his most able associates.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>ARV2, 1031, no. 44</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="70" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Vermeule Collection (Buitron No. 70)" type="vase">Vermeule Collection (Buitron No. 70)</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>FRAGMENTS OF A COLUMN-KRATER</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by Mr. and Mrs. Cornelius C. Vermeule, III</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">a. Height:</hi> 6 5/16 in. (16 cm.);
                            <hi rend="bold">Width:</hi> 6 1/2 in. (16.5 cm.)</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">b. Height:</hi> 6 5/16 in. (16 cm.);
                            <hi rend="bold">Width:</hi> 9 5/8 in. (24.5 cm.)</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">c. Height:</hi> 12 in. (30.4 cm.);
                            <hi rend="bold">Width:</hi> 21 11/16 in. (55 cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Fragments a and b from side A show an arming scene with three
                        figures.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Fragment a:</hi> on the left a youth
                        in a fox skin cap (alopeke) bends forward to put on a greave. In the upper
                        right is the hand of the central figure holding a trumpet. <hi rend="bold">Fragment b:</hi> the shield of the youth is preserved. The
                        device is a raven. On the right is a warrior wearing a black Chalcidian
                        helmet and carrying a shield (device: rosette). <hi rend="bold">Fragment c:</hi> from side B shows two mounted warriors. On the left a
                        warrior, perhaps an Amazon, dressed in a sleeved and trousered combination
                        with short chiton over it, a quiver at the waist, and a black shield. On the
                        right, a mounted hoplite with greaves, corslet with pteryges, chlamys, and
                        Corinthian helmet. He carries a javelin and a black shield.</p>
                    <p>On the neck on side A are lotus buds. On both sides the scenes
                        are bordered by framed tongues above and ivy on the sides; at the base,
                        rays.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Dilute glaze:</hi> strands of hair,
                        pattern on trousers and chiton.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Unattributed ca. 450 - 420 B. C.</p>
                    <p>The fragments have been related to the School of Polygnotos by D.
                        von Bothmer. Close parallels for style are found on a stamnos by the
                        Epimedes Painter (<rs type="vase">London E 450</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 1043, no. 1</bibl>) and a stamnos in
                        London by the Christie Painter (<rs type="vase">London
                            98.7-15.1</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 1048, no.
                        35</bibl>).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p>Unpublished.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="71" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Harvard 1970.108" type="vase">Harvard
                        1970.108</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>RED-FIGURE BELL-KRATER</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Fogg Art Museum, Harvard University; bequest of Ruth
                        Steele Brooks (1970.108)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 12 3/16 in. (30.9
                    cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Intact.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side A:</hi> komos. Three youths
                        proceed to the right. The first carries a torch. He is shown with trunk and
                        one leg frontal, head turned back to the left towards his companions, his
                        left leg turned to the right. He wears a chlamys over one shoulder. In the
                        center is a youth playing flutes. He advances to the right, chlamys draped
                        over his shoulders. At the left is a third youth, also in chlamys, holding a
                        staff in one hand.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side B:</hi> three youths
                        conversing. All three wear himatia; the central youth carries a staff.
                        Suspended in the field is a pair of jumping weights, a common filling
                        ornament.</p>
                    <p>Below, triple rightward meanders alternating with saltires; on
                        the lip, laurel wreath; at the base of the handles, egg pattern.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Dilute glaze:</hi> strands of hair,
                        anatomical details.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Red:</hi> leaves of wreaths on
                    A.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to the Christie Painter [Dohan] ca. 440 - 430 B. C.</p>
                    <p>The Christie Painter was a member of the group of Polygnotos (<rs type="vase">Mount Holyoke 1929.BS.II.4</rs>). His style is
                        characterized by the same fluid figures and naturalistic drawing.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>E. H. Dohan, "A Bell-Krater by
                            the Christie Painter," <title>The University Museum
                                Bulletin</title> 6 (The University of Pennsylvania May 1936) no. 4,
                            pp. 126-128, pl. VII</bibl>; <bibl>ARV2,
                            1047, no. 20</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="72" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Bowdoin 1895.2" type="vase">Bowdoin
                    1895.2</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>RED-FIGURE PELIKE</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Bowdoin College Museum of Art; gift of Harriet and
                        Sophia Walker (1895.2)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 14 7/8 in. (37.7
                    cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Said to be from Thebes.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side A:</hi> horseman arriving home.
                        At the left is a mounted youth wearing a chlamys, petasos slung over his
                        shoulder, and a wreath in his hair. He holds two spears in his right hand.
                        In the center is a woman wearing chiton and diadem, holding an oinochoe and
                        a phiale with which to make a libation. On the right is a Doric column. A
                        bearded man sits on a chair (klismos) to the left of the column. He wears a
                        himation around his waist and holds a staff. At the far right is a youth in
                        a himation, hand raised in greeting.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side B:</hi> youth leaving home. In
                        the center stands a youth dressed in chlamys and petasos and carrying a
                        spear. On the left is a bearded man (perhaps his father) wrapped in a
                        himation and leaning on a staff. On the right is a woman (possibly the
                        mother or wife) in chiton, himation, and sakkos and holding a phiale for the
                        libation.</p>
                    <p>Under the handles are palmettes, volutes, and buds. Circling the
                        vase at the base of the scene are triple rightward meanders alternating with
                        saltires. On the neck, diagonally placed palmettes with tendrils.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">White, on side A:</hi> fruits of
                        horseman's wreath, ornaments of the horse's bridle, spikes of the woman's
                        diadem. <hi rend="bold">Side B:</hi> spikes of the woman's
                        diadem.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to the Dinos Painter [Beazley] ca. 430 - 420 B. C.</p>
                    <p>The Dinos Painter carries the tradition of Polygnotos into the
                        late fifth century. The forms are rounder and fleshier and show a new
                        restlessness when compared with the earlier school (cf. <rs type="vase">Mount Holyoke 1929.BS.II.4</rs>).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>ARV2, 1155, no. 41</bibl>;
                            <bibl>Herbert 1964, 73-74, no. 202, pl.
                        26</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 457, no. 41</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="73" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Vermeule Collection (Buitron No. 73)" type="vase">Vermeule Collection (Buitron No. 73)</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>RED-FIGURE CALYX-KRATER</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by Mr. and Mrs. Cornelius C. Vermeule, III</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 13 13/16 in. (35
                    cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Reconstructed from worn fragments.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side A:</hi> Dionysos in
                        Gigantomachy. In the center Dionysos lifts his thyrsos-ended spear against a
                        giant. Two snakes help in the attack, one biting the giant's leg and one,
                        the giant's arm. Dionysos is dressed in a chiton with kolpos, a chlamys,
                        laced boots, and helmet. The giant, in chiton and corslet with pteryges,
                        holds a shield. On the left a crouching satyr in a helmet advances to aid
                        Dionysos; he has pulled his sword from its scabbard.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Side B:</hi> two chariots drawn by
                        pairs of satyrs in Chalcidian helmets. At the left over the handle is an old
                        papposilenos and a little satyriskos. Next come the two satyr-driven
                        chariots, the troops advancing to help Dionysos. The chariot wheels have
                        eight spokes as opposed to the customary four. One of the satyrs holds a
                        spare thyrsos.</p>
                    <p>Above the scene, upright and reversed ivy leaves; below the
                        scene, triple meanders alternating with saltires, and a band of upright and
                        reversed ivy leaves.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Dilute glaze:</hi> shading on the
                        helmets, hair, beards, leaves of the tree, and satyr tails and harnesses;
                        ornaments of the giant's belt and Dionysos' boots; pattern on the snake.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Unattributed ca. 430 - 420 B. C.</p>
                    <p>Dionysos in the Gigantomachy is frequently aided by lions,
                        panthers, or snakes, as here. The satyr bigas (chariots drawn by two satyrs)
                        are also found on several other vases (<bibl>Caskey &amp; Beazley, 2, pp. 70-71</bibl>). Although the vase is
                        very worn, three of the faces are clearly visible and are remarkably
                        individualistic. Also unusual are the satyrs wearing helmets.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p>Unpublished.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="74" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Worcester 1900.65" type="vase">Worcester
                        1900.65</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>WHITE-GROUND LEKYTHOS</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Worcester Art Museum; gift of Mary Felton Sargent in
                        memory of Mary S. Felton (1900.65)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 13 3/16 in. (33.4
                    cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Broken and repaired; missing pieces restored and painted.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Mistress and maid. On the right stands a woman in a chiton with
                        kolpos overfold, holding her grave gift, a toilet vase (plemochoe) in one
                        hand. Her maid approaches, in a sleeveless chiton with kolpos overfold,
                        carrying a basket with three handles filled with fillets. Behind her a small
                        oinochoe is suspended. Inscribed between them, <foreign xml:lang="greek">*U*G*I*A*I*O*N *K*A*L*O*S</foreign> (Hygiainon is
                        beautiful). Above, alternating leftward and rightward triple meanders
                        alternating with saltires; on the shoulder, palmettes and volutes; at the
                        neck, egg pattern.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to the Achilles Painter [Beazley] ca. 450 - 440 B. C.</p>
                    <p>White-ground lekythoi were produced in Athens from the late sixth
                        century on; only towards the mid-fifth century, however, did they acquire an
                        iconography directly reflecting their use in funerary rites and as offerings
                        at the grave. This lekythos shows one of the most common subjects, two
                        women, a lady and her maid, carrying gifts to a grave. The Achilles Painter,
                        a pupil of the Berlin Painter (cf <bibl>Buitron
                            1972, no. 38</bibl>) exerted a decisive influence on the development of
                        white lekythoi; he seems to have established the canonical design, and he
                        infused his figures with a combination of solemnity and grace. The Worcester
                        lekythos illustrates the technique favored by the Achilles Painter on all
                        but his very latest works. The drawing is in dilute glaze; the colors,
                        including the second white, are ceramic and were applied before the vase was
                        fired. The technique of white lekythoi changed with the Achilles Painter's
                        successors, for the ground tends to become brighter and powdery, the lines
                        and color become matte, and the second white occurs not only for accessories
                        but also for female flesh (see <rs type="vase">RISD
                        25.082</rs>).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl><title>Worcester Art Museum Annual Report</title> (1901) 8</bibl>; <bibl>Fairbanks 1907, 217, no. 35, pl. 9,
                        1</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley 1918, 164, no.
                        24</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley, "The Master of the
                            Achilles Amphora in the Vatican," <title>JHS</title> 34
                            (1914) 221, no. 24</bibl>; <bibl>Luce 1919,
                            30, fig. 7</bibl>; <bibl><title>Worcester Art Museum Annual</title> 2 (1936) 5, 26,
                            n. 2</bibl>; <bibl><title>Worcester Art Museum, Art through Fifty Centuries</title> (1948)
                            15, fig. 14</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="75" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Bowdoin 1913.11" type="vase">Bowdoin
                        1913.11</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>RED-FIGURE LEKYTHOS</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Bowdoin College Museum of Art; gift of E. P. Warren
                        (1913.11)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 14 15/16 in. (37.7
                    cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Intact. From Gela.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Dancing girl and mistress. At the left a young girl, shown nude
                        except for crossed straps on her chest, performs a dance step. Her hair is
                        tied up behind, and she wears hoop earrings. In the field to the left a
                        fillet is suspended. At the right is the dancing mistress wearing chiton,
                        himation, and jewelry: leafed diadem, pendant necklace, hoop earrings, and
                        meander bracelet. She holds the staff of a dancing mistress (also used by
                        other teachers), the narthex or giant fennel stalk. At the base of the
                        scene, a strip of simple rightward key; above, triple rightward meanders
                        alternating with saltires; on the shoulder, palmettes, volutes, and dots; on
                        the neck, egg pattern.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Dilute glaze:</hi> edges of hair,
                        necklace, and bracelet of dancing mistress, anatomical markings.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to the Phiale Painter [Beazley] ca. 330 B. C.</p>
                    <p>The Phiale Painter takes his name from a phiale in Boston (<rs type="vase">Boston 97.371</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 1023, no. 146</bibl>) showing a visit to a music
                        school. This painter seems to have been fond of depicting dancing girls;
                        they occur on his name piece as well as on several other vases (<bibl>Caskey &amp; Beazley, 1, p. 55</bibl>).
                        One can compare especially a lekythos in Brussels (<rs type="vase">Brussels A 3556</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 1021, no. 120</bibl>). Although a pupil of the Achilles Painter
                        and like him a painter of both red and white lekythoi, the Phiale Painter
                        infuses more vivacity into his scenes (cf <rs type="vase">Worcester 1900.65</rs>). The tall, narrow shape of this lekythos
                        reflects the tendency towards refinement which occurred in the later fifth
                        century.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Beazley 1918, 169-170, no.
                        33</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley, "Narthex," <title>AJA</title> 37 (1933) 401, fig. 3</bibl>; <bibl>Richter 1958, 122</bibl>; <bibl>ARV2, 1021, no. 118</bibl>; <bibl>Herbert 1964, 71-72, no. 195, pl, 25, 2</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 441, no. 118</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="76" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Smith 23:5-1" type="vase">Smith 23:5-1</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>WHITE-GROUND LEKYTHOS</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Smith College Art Museum (23:5-1)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 12 1/16 in. (30.6
                    cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Broken and repaired.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Mourners at a grave. At the left a woman kneels before the grave
                        touching her hair and extending her hand in grief. Her garment seems
                        translucent but was probably once painted with matte color which has since
                        worn off. At the right of the grave stele stands a youth wrapped in a
                        himation, probably the deceased. The grave stele is crowned with a palmette,
                        below which is a band of egg pattern. Above were probably meanders
                        alternating with saltires, now very worn. On the shoulder traces of
                        palmettes and volutes remain.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Said by Beazley to be near the Painter of Munich 2335 (letter)
                        ca. 440 - 430 B. C.</p>
                    <p>Besides the "mistress and maid" motif (cf <rs type="vase">Worcester 1900.65</rs>) white-ground lekythoi of the
                        classic period frequently depict a tomb scene, as in this example. White
                        lekythoi are among the best work of the Painter of Munich 2335. Compare in
                        New York (<rs type="vase">New York 09.221.44</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 1168, no. 128</bibl>; and <rs type="vase">New York 99.13.3</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 1169, no. 140</bibl>). The face of Charon on the
                        first is very close to the face of the youth on the Smith lekythos.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl><title>Acquisitions Report, Smith College Museum of Art</title> (1924) pl.
                            115</bibl>; <bibl>S. Mollard, "Une statuette
                            de Tanagra," <title>La Revue des Arts</title> 2 (Paris
                            1955) 116</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="77" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Bowdoin 1923.26" type="vase">Bowdoin
                        1923.26</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>WHITE-GROUND LEKYTHOS</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Bowdoin College Museum of Art; gift of E. P. Warren
                        (1923.26)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 12 5/16 in. (31.2
                    cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Broken and repaired.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Man and girl at a grave. At the left a girl in a chiton with
                        overfold, now faded, carries a tray of fillets and wreaths. At the right
                        stands a man in red himation, holding a staff. The grave stele, crowned with
                        a gable and akroterion, is tied with red dedicatory fillets. Above, leftward
                        stopped meanders; on the shoulder, volutes; on the neck, egg pattern.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to the Bird Painter [Beazley] ca. 440 - 430 B. C.</p>
                    <p>The Bird Painter and his colleagues formed a rather large
                        workshop in which the Painter of Munich 2335 (cf <rs type="vase">Smith 23:5-1</rs>) may also have worked (<bibl>ARV2, 1161</bibl>). The tomb monuments depicted on
                        funerary lekythoi vary considerably in type, but in general they probably
                        reflect contemporary forms in actual use.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>ARV2, 1232, no. 5</bibl>; <bibl>Herbert 1964, 69-70, no. 188, pl. 25
                        a</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="78" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:RISD 25.082" type="vase">RISD 25.082</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>WHITE-GROUND LEKYTHOS</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Museum of Art, Rhode Island School of Design; museum
                        appropriation and special gift (Mrs. Gustav Radeke) (25.082)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 9 1/2 in. (24.1
                    cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Broken and repaired at neck; upper neck and mouth foreign. ??
                        From Greece.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Charon. At the left Charon, the ferryman, prepares to ferry a
                        soul across the River Styx to Hades. He wears a red tunic (exomis) and
                        conical hat (pilos). In one hand he holds an oar, and with the other he
                        steadies himself on the stern of his boat. On the right is his passenger, a
                        woman wearing a black chiton, much faded, and a white himation with red
                        border and belt. Her hair is brown. She holds an aryballos in her right
                        hand. Between the two figures are the tall reeds of the river bank with a
                        red fillet draped in them. Above, meanders, much worn; on the shoulder, red
                        palmettes, black egg and dot pattern, also worn.</p>
                    <p>??considerable repaint in design areas.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to the Reed Painter [Beazley] ca. 420 - 400 B. C.</p>
                    <p>The Reed Painter and the dependent R Group form one of the last
                        major white lekythos workshops. The favored subject is Charon, who had
                        appeared by the middle of the fifth century, but who became popular towards
                        the end of the century. The chalky slip and varied polychromy, now much
                        faded, place this lekythos in the late fifth century. Although the style has
                        changed considerably, such late lekythoi still employ the same basic design
                        (black mouth and neck, palmette motif on shoulder, meander pattern above
                        scene) that was established by the Achilles Painter.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Banks 1928, 51, fig. 15</bibl>;
                            <bibl>S. B. Luce, "Attic White-Ground
                            Vases," <title>BullRhode</title> 20 (1932) 63, fig.
                        4</bibl>; <bibl>CVA, USA 2, p. 34, pl. 25, 5,
                            pl. 25 a</bibl>; <bibl>C. A. Robinson, Jr.,
                            "Greek and Roman Vases," <title>BullRhode</title> 27
                            (1939) 35, fig. 16; ARV2, 1376, no. 5</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="79" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Worcester 1935.148" type="vase">Worcester
                        1935.148</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>RED-FIGURE PYXIS (TYPE A)</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Worcester Art Museum (1935.148)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 4 1/2 in. (11.4
                    cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Broken and repaired; missing pieces restored; missing handle.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Mistresses and maids. Six women are grouped in three pairs; in
                        each, a maid attends her mistress. A woman relaxes in a chair, her feet on a
                        padded foot stool. Her maid approaches carrying a chest. Next, a woman holds
                        out the mirror she has been using to put the finishing touches on her
                        toilet. Her maid approaches and prepares to take something out of the wicker
                        box she carries. Between the two is a chest resting on animal paw supports,
                        with balls of wool in it. Suspended behind the maid is a decorated sakkos.
                        Lastly, a seated woman seems to be directing her maid to put away the fillet
                        and toilet vase (plemochoe) she carries. Below are rightward meanders, and
                        above, egg pattern.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Cover:</hi> four Erotes at play. The
                        first pair engage in a cock fight. Each holds a cock and prepares to set him
                        loose. The second pair start a hare for coursing. One Eros holds his pet
                        while the other with his foot on a rock prepares to give the signal for the
                        start. Behind him are a stake and ball. Around the handle are tongues, eggs,
                        and dots; at the edge of the cover, a reserved band; on the projecting
                        underside of the cover, reserved leaves with white berries.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Attributed to the Eretria Painter [Morgan] ca. 430 - 425 B. C.</p>
                    <p>Although primarily a painter of cups, the Eretria Painter did his
                        finest work on other small vases such as pyxides. Pyxides were made for
                        women as boxes to hold jewelry, toilet articles, and other small objects.
                        Their subject matter generally reflects their use; the main scene here is
                        set in the women's quarters of a house and shows such typical paraphernalia
                        as a chest, mirror, and plemochoe. Women at home at their toilet became a
                        frequent subject after the middle of the fifth century. The Eretria Painter
                        was especially fond of depicting women, and his delicacy of line and
                        detailed drapery are well suited to the subject. The shading on the mirror
                        in imitation of metal work and the careful depiction of the wicker work box
                        show his interest in realistic detail.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl><title>Worcester Art Museum Annual Report</title> (1936) 21</bibl>; <bibl>C. H. Morgan, II, "A Pyxis by the `Eretria
                            Painter'," <title>Worcester Art Museum Annual</title> 2
                            (1936) 29 ff</bibl>; <bibl>ARV2, 1250, no.
                            33</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="80" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Harvard 1960.347" type="vase">Harvard
                        1960.347</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>RED-FIGURE HYDRIA</title>
                </p>
                <div type="collection" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Lent by the Fogg Art Museum, Harvard University; gift of D. M.
                        Robinson (1960.347)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="dimensions" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Height:</hi> 14 in. (35.5 cm.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="condition" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Broken and repaired; missing pieces restored and painted.</p>
                    <p>Said to be from Nola.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="decoration" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Dionysos sits in the center looking to the right and holding a
                        thyrsos. To the left is a satyr also carrying a thyrsos. Between the two is
                        an ivy branch. In the upper left is a seated woman dressed in chiton and
                        himation. An Eros flies towards her with a necklace of beads. At the right
                        of Dionysos a woman in chiton approaches; she pets Dionysos' panther. In the
                        upper right is a seated youth, probably Hermes since he holds a caduceus, or
                        perhaps Oinopion, the human charged with the introduction of wine into
                        Greece (<bibl>ARV2, 1341, no. 2</bibl>). An Eros
                        walks towards him. At the far right is a seated woman, head turned back
                        toward the center. At her left is a lotus bud with volutes. A band of triple
                        leftward meanders alternating with checkerboard squares circles the vase at
                        the base of the scene. Under the lateral handles, upright palmettes; on the
                        back, palmettes, lotus buds, tendrils, and ferns; at the neck, egg pattern;
                        on the lip, eggs and dots; at the base of the three handles, eggs and dots.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">White:</hi> fillets in the hair of
                        Dionysos, the two youths, one Eros, the panther, string of beads, diadems in
                        the hair of the two seated women.</p>
                    <p>Yellow is used for details on the panther and the Eros.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <p>Assigned to the Class of Brussels A 3099 [Beazley] ca. 410 - 400
                        B. C.</p>
                    <p>This hydria is close to a hydria in Brussels (<rs type="vase">Brussels A 3099</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 1341, no. 1</bibl>). "The two vases are connected by shape and
                        patterns; and the elaborate floral designs at the back may be by the same
                        hand. The figure-work has the same general character in both but cannot be
                        said to be by one hand." (<bibl>ARV2,
                        1341</bibl>) The distribution of the figures on different levels and the
                        more profuse use of white are characteristic of the period. If the youth in
                        the upper right is Oinopion, the subject of the vase may be a quasi-mystic
                        allusion to the introduction of wine into Greece (see <bibl>Metzger 1951, 24</bibl>).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Rudolf Lepcke, <title>Auktion 2035</title> (Berlin November 12, 1930)
                            Sammlung A. Loebbecke (Braunschweig) pl. 2, no. 456</bibl>; <bibl>D. M. Robinson, "Some Unpublished Attic
                            Vases," <title>AJA</title> 38 (1934) 188 passim</bibl>;
                            <bibl>CVA, USA 7, p. 22, pl. 13</bibl>;
                            <bibl>Robinson Exhibition 1961, no.
                        107</bibl>; <bibl>ARV2, 1341, no. 2</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
