<?xml version="1.0"?>





<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Art, Myth, and Culture</title>
                <title>Greek Vases from Southern Collections</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Harvey Alan Shapiro</author>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <idno type="ISBN">0894940120</idno>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState n="chunk" unit="entry"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    	<revisionDesc><!--
    		<change><date>5/27/09</date><respStmt><name>RS</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt>
    			<item>  
    				$Log: shapiro.xml,v $
    				Revision 1.1  2009-10-08 19:10:56  rsingh04
    				began reorganizing texts module by collection.  created separate work directory in texts module to keep hopper files separate from in progress files

    				Revision 1.6  2009/06/19 19:02:02  lcerrato
    				fixed bad bibls

    				Revision 1.5  2009/05/27 15:55:16  rsingh04
    				added cvs log keyword

    			</item>
    		</change>
    	--> <change when="2014-11-13" who="Stella Dee">edited markup and assigned CTS URN</change></revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div n="1" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Birmingham 57.263" type="vase">Birmingham
                        57.263</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Red-Figure Amphora of Panathenaic Shape</title>
                <rs type="collection">Collection of the Birmingham Museum of Art, Gift of Mrs. Herbert Rydings, Jr. 
                    and Hirschl and Adler Gallery, New York (57.263)</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Attributed to the Tyszkiewicz Painter [Bothmer]</rs>
                    <date>500-490 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 39.3 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter: 26.3 cm.</measure> Side A: Zeus pursuing a
                    woman. Side B: Man and woman at an altar.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">On side A</hi>, Zeus strides forward,
                    bent over slightly as if swooping down on the woman, who raises her right hand
                    in a gesture of fear and aversion and runs off to the right. The god is
                    identified by the scepter, the symbol of kingly power, and by the wreath of what
                    seem stylized oak leaves on his head. He holds the scepter near its lower end,
                    as if to reach out and bar the woman's way. The identity of the woman is
                    uncertain without an inscription or any distinguishing attributes. Zeus' loves
                    were legendary, in every sense of the word; the younger Olympian gods were his
                    children by various goddesses and nymphs, and his human mistresses were
                    innumerable. Every noble family in the Greek world traced its ancestry back to a
                    hero born of a god and a mortal woman, and more of them claimed Zeus as ancestor
                    than any other god. In a comic interlude in the <hi rend="ital"
                        >Iliad,</hi> Zeus' wife Hera seduces him on a mountaintop in order to
                    distract his attention from the battlefield of Troy. He expresses his sudden
                    lust for her rather tactlessly, giving a list of goddesses and mortal woman he
                    has loved, ``But never with as great a passion as I now feel for you!"</p>
                <p>The scene on the reverse is a complete contrast. A man and a woman
                    stand on either side of an altar on which a fire is burning. He leans on his
                    walking stick and holds out a phiale, a cup for pouring libations to the gods,
                    which she fills with wine from a jug. The figures are at ease, the atmosphere
                    calm; they may be man and wife sacrificing on some family occasion (birth of a
                    child?) or at a family celebration during one of the great Athenian festivals.
                    The contrast between the two scenes is surely intentional: on one side the two
                    mortals, harmoniously and soberly carrying out a traditional rite, an embodiment
                    of the normal pattern of human relationships with one another and with the gods;
                    on the other side, the violent expression of an unequal passion. Zeus' heavily
                    muscled legs, broad shoulders and thick neck embody the irresistible power of
                    the god, but also the equally irresistible power of love, violent in its
                    onslaught and its expression. Against this double force she is helpless; she
                    runs, but there is no escape. In other versions of this scene Zeus carries a
                    thunderbolt, the annihilating weapon of supreme power, a reminder that for
                    mortals (creatures of a day, <hi rend="ital">ephemerai,</hi> the
                    gods call them) even the love of gods is as dangerous as their anger. The
                    painter may have been influenced by early tragic drama, in which the difference
                    in power between gods and mortals is a mainspring of the action. In <hi
                        rend="ital">Prometheus Bound,</hi> produced slightly later than
                    this vase, Aeschylus shows the sufferings of Io, a girl whom Zeus loved and Hera
                    transformed into a cow and drove wandering over the earth in perpetual torment.
                    The horrified chorus of sea nymphs prays, ``May I never share the bed of Zeus or
                    attract a god as lover. Only in an equal match is there no fear."</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>ARV2,292,35</bibl>. For gods as
                        lovers of mortal women: <bibl>Kaempf-Dimitriadou
                            1979</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
                <byline>Lucy Turnbull</byline>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Lemonopoulos Collection (Shapiro No. 2)" type="vase"
                        >Lemonopoulos Collection (Shapiro No. 2)</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Black-Figure Neck-Amphora</title>
                <rs type="collection">Collection of Costas Lemonopoulos, St.
                    Petersburg, courtesy of the Museum of Fine Arts of St. Petersburg</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Unattributed</rs>
                    <date>Ca. 515-505 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 39.4 cm.</measure> Side A: Apollo kitharoidos
                    and four goddesses. Side B: Scythian archer between horsemen.</p>
                <p>Apollo is the patron of the arts, and especially of music. He is
                    closely associated with the nine Muses, whom he often leads in a dance at a
                    gathering of the gods or a celebration for a hero. His favorite instrument is
                    the kithara, or lyre, and whenever the god is shown making music, it is always
                    on the lyre. Other figures are sometimes depicted with a lyre on Attic vases,
                    such as Nike(<rs type="vase">Austin 1980.63</rs>, or the boy
                    Tithonos, who was ravished by the goddess of the dawn, but a stately male
                    lyre-player in a long garment is generally Apollo. Though sometimes portrayed as
                    a nude athletic type, especially in sculpture of the fifth century, Apollo is
                    always draped when he plays the lyre. On side A of the Lemonopoulos amphora he
                    wears a <hi rend="ital">chiton</hi> and, over it, a <hi rend="ital"
                        >himation</hi> decorated with large red dots. He also has a red
                    fillet in his hair, and a cord attached to the instrument hangs from his right
                    hand. The god is surrounded by two pairs of female figures, all dressed alike in
                    a long <hi rend="ital">chiton,</hi> also decorated with red dots.
                    Two hold an object which looks like <hi rend="ital">krotala,</hi>
                    or metal castanets. A graceful doe stands beside each pair of women. It is
                    difficult to say who these might be. The presence both of Apollo and of the does
                    makes one think of Artemis, the god's sister and goddess of the hunt, but
                    presumably she would somehow be singled out from the others. Four of the Muses,
                    perhaps, drawn by an artist concerned more with symmetry than completeness?</p>
                <p>In contrast to this peaceful and musical scene, side B features three
                    warriors preparing to depart. The standing figure in the center carries bow and
                    quiver and wears a short <hi rend="ital">chiton</hi> and a pointed
                    leather cap with long ear flaps. The hat and his pointy beard mark him as a
                    Scythian archer, a native of South Russia probably employed at Athens as a
                    mercenary. In the fifth century, Scythians appear to have served as policemen in
                    Athens, but their frequent earlier appearance on black-figure vases of the later
                    sixth century may reflect a policy of the tyrant Peisistratos in hiring foreign
                    mercenaries from the North. Before the time of the Persian Wars, the Athenians
                    had had little experience of archery (see <rs type="vase">Chapel
                        Hill 66.27.4</rs>), while the Scythian skill with the bow was proverbial.
                    The other two warriors flanking the archer, both mounted, wear Corinthian
                    helmets and appear to be standard Greek soldiers.</p>
                <p>The vase belongs to the period of the Leagros Group, a large body of
                    mostly neck-amphoras and hydriae produced by one or several closely related
                    black-figure workshops contemporary with the red-figure "Pioneers."</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Cat. Sotheby, lot 173,
                        ill.</bibl>. On Scythian archers:<bibl>Vos
                            1963</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Houston 37-19" type="vase">Houston
                        37-19</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Black-Figure Plate</title>
                <rs type="collection">Collection of The Museum of Fine Arts,
                    Houston, the Annette Finnigan Collection (37-19)</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Assigned to the Segment Class [H. Hoffmann]</rs>
                    <date>Ca. 520-510 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Diameter: 23.5 cm.</measure> Athena battling the
                    giant Enkelados.</p>
                <p>The scene is an excerpt from the Battle of Gods and Giants, one of
                    the most popular mythological scenes in Archaic Greek art. The Giants, children
                    of Ge, Mother Earth, tried to storm Mount Olympos, but were repulsed by the
                    combined effort of all the Olympian gods and goddesses, with the help of
                    Herakles. By convention certain gods battle certain giants, and when Athena's
                    opponent is named by inscription, he is Enkelados. Otherwise Enkelados has no
                    distinguishing traits or attributes.</p>
                <p>Athena wears a belted <hi rend="ital">chiton,
                    himation,</hi> and a high-crested Attic helmet. Her aegis is draped over her
                    extended left arm, serving as a shield, and in her right hand, obscured by the
                    drapery, she wields a spear. Enkelados, who has fallen to one knee, tries to
                    protect himself with a shield whose device is a satyr's head. He wears a
                    corselet over a short <hi rend="ital">chiton,</hi> which has short
                    sleeves and a patterned skirt. His helmet is of the Corinthian type, which is
                    meant to be pulled down over nose and cheeks, but has been knocked askew and
                    almost off by the force of Athena's blow. The Giant too holds a spear but is
                    powerless to use it. In Archaic art, the Giants are not represented as
                    monstrous, or even of great stature, but instead look no different from heavily
                    armed Greek hoplites. Only in later art, as on the Pergamon Altar, do they
                    sometimes take on a grotesque appearance, as the poet Hesiod imagined them.</p>
                <p>Attic plates were not functional, but were rather plaques, made for
                    dedicatory purposes. The Houston example has two suspension holes near the top,
                    which suggests that it was perhaps intended to be hung up in a sanctuary. Quite
                    possibly it was dedicated to the city goddess, Athena, on the Acropolis.
                    Certainly the subject is appropriate for such a purpose and is one which occurs
                    on a number of vases and fragments excavated on the Acropolis. The Gigantomachy,
                    including the Athena-Enkelados group, was the subject of several large-scale
                    architectural sculptures in the sixth and fifth centuries. One of the most
                    notable of these is a marble pediment which decorated the Old Temple of Athena
                    on the north side of the Acropolis, also called Doerpfeld's Temple or the
                    Peisistratid Temple, because it was probably built in the time of Hippias and
                    Hipparchos, sons of the Tyrant Peisistratos (ca. 527-510). The splendid striding
                    Athena from that composition is well preserved, and her pose and dress are
                    similar to those of the Athena on this plate. The traditional date for this
                    pediment, about 520, has recently been questioned by some scholars who would
                    push it toward the end of the Peisistratid tyranny, about 510, or even later,
                    regarding it as a product of the young Athenian democracy after 510. If the
                    earlier date is correct, however, it would be reasonable to ask whether the
                    Houston plate could have been inspired by the central group of the pediment and
                    have hung not far from it in Athena's sanctuary on the Acropolis.</p>
                <p>The decoration of this plate is akin to that of the Segment Class, a
                    group of stemless cups in which the picture fills the whole interior and there
                    is often an exergue below the principal scene. Here two leaping dolphins occupy
                    the exergue.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Hoffmann 1971b, 386-87</bibl>.
                        On the Gigantomachy: <bibl>Vian 1952</bibl>. On
                        the Peisistratid pediment: <bibl>Ridgway 1977,
                            205-206</bibl>. Segment Class: <bibl>ABV,
                                212-214</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Denman Collection (Shapiro No. 4)" type="vase"
                        >Denman Collection (Shapiro No. 4)</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Red-Figure Column-Krater</title>
                <rs type="collection">Collection of Gilbert M. Denman, Jr., San
                    Antonio</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Attributed to the Orchard Painter [Bothmer]</rs>
                    <date>Ca. 470-460 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 44.2 c.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter: 41 cm.</measure> Side A: Athena punishing
                    the Daughters of Kekrops. Side B: Youth and two women.</p>
                <p>In the Early Classical period, just after 480, a variety of stories
                    relating to the mythical history of Athens began to appear in Attic red-figure.
                    Among the early legendary kings of Attica, Erechtheus (also called Erichthonios)
                    was popular with the vase-painters, especially the stories surrounding his
                    birth. He was the child of Hephaistos and of Ge, the Earth, who took in his seed
                    after Athena had rejected the god's advances. When the baby Erichthonios was
                    born out of the earth, a scene depicted on several vases, Athena was present and
                    took up the child as foster-mother. She put him in a chest, together with a
                    guardian serpent to protect him, and entrusted the chest to the three daughters
                    of Kekrops, instructing them not to open it. These three sisters, children of
                    the first king of Attica, were named Aglauros, Herse, and Pandrosos. According
                    to Pausanias (<bibl n="Paus. 1.18.2">Paus.
                        1.18.2</bibl>), Pandrosos obeyed Athena's command, but her two sisters, overcome
                    by curiosity, opened the chest. A slightly different version, attested by Ovid
                    (<bibl n="Ov. Met. 2.558">Ovid Met.
                        2.558ff</bibl>), holds that all three were at fault: Aglauros persuaded the
                    other two to open the chest. In any event, the unfortunate sisters, horrified by
                    the sight, were driven mad and jumped from the Acropolis.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">On side A</hi>, Athena chastises the
                    three sisters for disregarding her injunction. Two of the girls try to flee to
                    the left, looking back at Athena, but the goddess takes hold of the nearer one
                    by the shoulder. The third sister, presumably the obedient Pandrosos, observes
                    the others as she moves off to the right. All three wear <hi rend="ital"
                        >chitons,</hi> two of them finely pleated, and over them <hi
                            rend="ital">himatia.</hi> One wears a sakkos on her head, one a
                    simple headband, and the third nothing at all. Athena is particularly splendidly
                    dressed. Her <hi rend="ital">chiton</hi> is embroidered with a
                    three-dot pattern and has a wide hem decorated with leaping dolphins between
                    borders of dots and parallel lines. The dotted border appears at the sleeves and
                    at the neck as well. Over the <hi rend="ital">chiton</hi> she wears
                    a mantle with stiff folds, and her aegis is decorated with a stippled pattern, a
                    dot border, nineteen snakes, and a comical Gorgoneion. The cap of her Attic
                    helmet is embellished with engraved spirals, and the low crest trails down over
                    her shoulder. She carries a long spear in her left hand; the two girls at the
                    left each carry a spiralling branch.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">On side B</hi>, a youth stands between
                    two muffled female figures who run off, looking back toward him. The woman at
                    the right is virtually identical to Pandrosos in dress and pose, though the
                    drawing of the reverse is in general far less careful. The reverse also lacks
                    the frieze of palmettes which decorates the neck on side A. The youth wields a
                    stick with a T-shaped head with which he seems to be threatening one of the
                    girls.</p>
                <p>The story depicted <hi rend="bold">On side A</hi>,
                    Athena punishing the Kekropides, appears on only a few other vases, including a
                    lekythos in Basel, an alabastron in Athens, and fragments from the Acropolis and
                    in Leipzig. The Basel vase includes the chest and the snake, which are omitted
                    from the Denman scene, but on all of these except the Leipzig vase only one of
                    the sisters is shown. Thus this example is the only complete version showing
                    Athena with all three daughters of Kekrops.</p>
                <p>The Denman krater has been attributed by Dietrich von Bothmer to a
                    painter of the Early Classical period who decorated a variety of larger shapes,
                    but favored the column-krater. He is named for an unusual scene on a
                    column-krater in New York showing women in an orchard, picking fruit (<bibl
                        >ARV2, 523, 1</bibl>). Though he is not generally
                    known as a painter of interesting mythological scenes, there is one other from
                    his hand, on a well known column-krater also in New York: Jason stealing the
                    golden fleece (<bibl>ARV2, 524, 28</bibl>). As
                    Bothmer points out, the gorgoneion on Athena's aegis on the Jason krater
                    provides a good comparison with the peculiar gorgoneion on this vase.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Kunst der Antike, no.
                        158</bibl>. For other representations of Athena and the Kekropides: <bibl
                            >Schmidt 1968, 200-212 and pl. 73-74 (Basel
                            lekythos), pl. 76 (alabastron in Athens)</bibl>; <bibl
                                >Kron 1976, 71-72 and pl. 2, 2 (fragmentary vase in
                                Leipzig)</bibl>; <bibl>ARV2, 973, 7-8
                                    (Acropolis fragments)</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Mississippi 1977.3.82" type="vase"
                        >Mississippi 1977.3.82</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Black-Figure Lekythos
                    (White-Ground)</title>
                <rs type="collection">Collection of the University Museums,
                    University of Mississippi Phase I Cultural Center (77.3.82)</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Attributed to the Diosphos Painter</rs>
                    <date>500-490 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 27.4 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter: 9.9 cm.</measure> Hermes and Iris</p>
                <p>The winged messengers of Zeus, each carrying the herald's <hi
                    rend="ital">kerykeion</hi> (caduceus) and wearing a short <hi
                        rend="ital">chiton</hi> and winged boots, walk to the right in
                    animated conversation. Perhaps they are discussing the box that dangles from
                    Iris' left hand — a gift from Zeus to some mortal girl who has caught his
                    fancy? Iris appears comparatively seldom in vase painting. Her name is the Greek
                    word for the rainbow, and in popular fancy, the appearance of a rainbow was a
                    sign that Zeus had sent Iris to earth with a message. There is no story here,
                    however; the painter has merely given us a little vignette from the everyday
                    life of the gods.</p>
                <p>The technique of placing a black silhouette against a white
                    background instead of a red one was a comparative novelty when this lekythos was
                    painted (see <bibl>Shapiro 1981a, no. 26</bibl>),
                    and it must have looked very striking when it was whole and not discolored by
                    fire. The "inscriptions" are nonsense, strings of T's and X's used simply to
                    break up the space around the figures and make a pattern that links them
                    visually to the intricate arrangement of palmettes on either side. There is a
                    strong contrast between the careful organization of the abstract patterns and
                    the spontaneity in the treatment of the figures, produced by the slapdash
                    incision, the jaunty gesture of Hermes and the pert flip of Iris' <hi
                        rend="ital">chiton.</hi></p>
                <p>The Mississippi lekythos is attributed to the Diosphos Painter, a
                    prolific painter of neck-amphoras <rs type="vase">Richmond
                        60.11</rs> and lekythoi, in both conventional black-figure and white-ground
                    techniques, as well as a technique called semi-outline. The latter is a
                    transitional stage in the development toward outline drawing on a white ground
                    (<bibl>Shapiro 1981a, nos. 42-45</bibl>). This
                    example, however, though on a white ground, is purely black-figure.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>CVA, Robinson Collection 1, pl.
                        38, 7</bibl>; <bibl>Haspels 1936, 111 and
                            235</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 248</bibl>; <bibl
                                >Kurtz 1975, 98 and fig. 28a (shoulder
                                palmettes)</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
                <byline>Lucy Turnbull</byline>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Mississippi 1977.3.196" type="vase"
                        >Mississippi 1977.3.196</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Red-Figure Pelike</title>
                    <rs type="collection">Collection of the University Museums,
                        University of Mississippi, Phase I Cultural Center (77.3.196)</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Attributed to the Washing Painter [Turnbull]</rs>
                    <date>430-420 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 12 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter: 10.9 cm.</measure> Side A: Eros and
                    girl.Side B: Youth with phiale.</p>
                <p>The young god of love floats toward the girl, holding two red balls,
                    perhaps fruit or balls of wool. Nude except for the <hi rend="ital"
                        >sakkos</hi> on her head, she holds a box in both hands, and stares at Eros.
                    Between them on the floor is a <hi rend="ital">kalathos,</hi> a
                    basket containing folded cloth or skeins of wool. On side B, a young man holds a
                    phiale, a type of cup used in pouring libations to the gods. Has he been making
                    an offering to Eros?</p>
                <p>Scenes of Eros and women together indoors become common in the late
                    5th century B.C. This Eros is not the embodiment of an irresistible power that
                    not even Zeus can escape, but simply a charming adolescent boy who happens to
                    have wings. Nor is he occupied with the loves of the immortal gods, but only
                    visiting an anonymous mortal girl. The figure of Eros undergoes a curious change
                    in the 5th century. In the beginning he is represented as a young man in
                    miniature, but each generation of painters made him younger in appearance,
                    perhaps in response to the erotic connotations of youthful male beauty in
                    Athenian society. By the middle of the 4th century, the image had evolved of the
                    chubby, mischievous winged baby, familiar to us under his Roman name of Cupid.
                    Since she is naked, the girl must be a <hi rend="ital"
                        >hetaira,</hi> a "companion" of the sort that entertained the guests at men's
                    dinner parties. She is dressing to go out or to receive a client, and the chest
                    she holds must contain clothes or jewelry. Eros here may be thought of as
                    endowing her with greater beauty and sex appeal. The tone is light, rather
                    trivial, mildly erotic, in keeping with the growing contemporary taste for
                    scenes from the daily life of women.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p>Unpublished. On Eros: <bibl
                        >Greifenhagen 1957</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
                <byline>Lucy Turnbull</byline>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Mississippi 1977.3.142" type="vase"
                        >Mississippi 1977.3.142</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Etruscan Alabastron with Applied Color</title>
                <rs type="collection">Collection of The University Museums,
                    University of Mississippi Phase I Cultural Center (1977.3.142)</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Unattributed</rs>
                    <date>Ca. 400 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 9.7 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter: 3.2 cm.</measure> Boreas pursuing a woman.</p>
                <p>A nymph sprints away at top speed, long rubbery hands and feet
                    outstretched. Her hair streams out behind her, and her flimsy <hi rend="ital"
                        >chiton</hi> is pasted to her body by the speed at which she
                    runs. Behind her Boreas, god of the north wind, comes sailing on big wings, his
                    arms reaching out to catch her. An extra note of humor is added by the painter's
                    choice of such a small cylindrical object on which to paint the scene; the nymph
                    in her frantic flight almost trips over the heels of her pursuer. His name,
                    <foreign xml:lang="greek">*B*O*R*E*A*S</foreign> is written
                    below his arms; her name, partly obliterated by abrasion, is written from top to
                    bottom in front of her body: <foreign xml:lang="greek">..*I*A*N ..
                        *A</foreign> — Deianeira? The drawing is in the style of the Meidias
                    Painter and his followers in the last quarter of the 5th century B.C.</p>
                <p>Boreas first appears in Attic vase-painting shortly after the Persian
                    Wars, when the Athenians built him a shrine and paid him special honors in
                    gratitude for the northerly storms that had destroyed a significant part of the
                    Persian fleet. There was also a popular tradition that Boreas had fallen in love
                    with an Athenian princess, Oreithyia, and had snatched her up in a storm of wind
                    to be his wife. Vase-painters frequently represented this subject, but no Attic
                    version is as broadly comic as this one. The wind god on Attic vases may look
                    uncouth, the princess frightened, but they are never made undignified even in
                    the latest works.</p>
                <p>The technique too is not Attic. This is not true red-figure with
                    figures reserved in the natural color of the clay; the figures are painted in
                    yellowish-red paint (now discolored by fire) over the black glaze, with details
                    incised with a sharp point so that the black shows through. This is an Etruscan
                    technique, developed in imitation of Attic red-figure, which like the earlier
                    black-figure were was imported in very large quantities into Etruria. Etruscan
                    painters had produced imitation black-figure too, and when the style changed
                    they were evidently reluctant to give up the familiar incision technique. This
                    compromise method lasts until the end of the 5th century. Etruscan painters
                    often gave a humorous twist to Greek mythological subjects and altered the names
                    of the persons involved. In fact only the style of the drawing on this
                    alabastron looks Attic. The irreverent treatment of the subject and the altered
                    name of the nymph, as well as the metallic luster of the glaze and the Etruscan
                    technique, all suggest an Etruscan origin. This hypothesis is confirmed by a
                    close inspection of the letter forms, which reveals that the N and E are not
                    Greek, but Etruscan. A number of Athenian potters and painters emigrated to
                    South Italy and Etruria in the last years of the 5th century, and it may be that
                    one of them inspired the drawing on this vase.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p>Unpublished. For Boreas and Oreithyia: <bibl
                        >Kaempf-Dimitriadou 1979</bibl>. For the technique: <bibl
                            >Beazley 1947, ch. 12</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
                <byline>Lucy Turnbull</byline>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Sarasota 1600.G2" type="vase">Sarasota
                        1600.G2</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Red-Figure Neck-Amphora with
                    Twisted Handles</title>
                    <rs type="collection">Collection of the John and Mable Ringling
                        Museum of Art, Sarasota (1600.G2)</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Attributed to the Harrow Painter</rs>
                    <date>Ca. 470 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 27.7 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter: 18.1 cm.</measure> Side A: Running Nike
                    with torches.Side B: Standing youth.</p>
                <p>The Harrow Painter, a competent late archaic pot painter, here
                    follows the tradition established by his mentor, the Berlin Painter (see <bibl
                        >Shapiro 1981a, no. 63</bibl>), of placing one
                    figure on either side of an otherwise completely black amphora. The more
                    important figure on side A is a winged female wearing a <hi rend="ital"
                        >chiton</hi> and <hi rend="ital">sakkos.</hi> She
                    is running along to the right on a rough groundline and is carrying a lighted
                    torch in each hand, the flame indicated in red. She is one of the many
                    manifestations of the Victory goddess Nike, in this instance probably hurrying
                    to light an altar (cf. <rs type="vase">Austin 1980.63</rs>).</p>
                <p>The reverse shows a lone draped youth standing in profile to the
                    right on a thin reserved groundline. The majority of amphorae by this painter
                    have such a figure as a filling device on the less important back side of the
                    vase. The Berlin Painter shows his influence here as well, since he often
                    combined a Nike and anonymous youth in his later paintings.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>ARV2, 272, 9</bibl>. On late
                        Nikai by the Berlin Painter: <bibl
                            >Isler-Kerényi 1971, 25-31</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
                <byline>Jenifer Neils</byline>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Austin 1980.63" type="vase">Austin
                        1980.63</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Red-Figure Lekythos</title>
                    <rs type="collection">Collection of the Archer M. Huntington Art
                        Gallery, University of Texas, Austin (1980.63)</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Attributed to the Oionokles Painter</rs>
                    <date>Ca. 470 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 36.5 cm.</measure> Flying Nike with kithara
                    and phiale</p>
                <p>This charming lekythos shows a winged Victory hovering in mid-flight.
                    Her progress is to the left, but momentarily checked, as she looks back to the
                    right. Her ornate wings and her drapery, a <hi rend="ital"
                        >chiton</hi> and diagonal mantle, flutter out behind. She wears a diadem in her
                    flaxen hair, which is rolled up in back. Lightsome as this Nike is, she is
                    burdened with heavy equipment: in her outstretched right hand she holds a plain
                    phiale; in her left is cradled a large kithara or lyre, the strings of which are
                    facing her. A dotted strap with trailing ends attaches the instrument to her
                    left hand, and a long, fringed, diamond-patterned scarf is draped over her
                    forearm. There is a nonsense inscription in the field under the wings. The
                    picture is framed above and below by zones of stopped meander, and as is common
                    on lekythoi of this period, palmettes decorate the shoulder.</p>
                <p>The figure of Nike, while known earlier in Attic vase-painting,
                    becomes especially prevalent after ca. 480 B.C., especially on smaller vases
                    like Nolan amphorae and lekythoi. The victory she alludes to is not always
                    known, unless she is accompanied by other figures, like warriors or athletes, or
                    carries a specific attribute. Here, the presence of the kithara implies a
                    victory in a musical competition. A Nolan amphora formerly in Goluchow by the
                    same hand (<bibl>ARV2, 646, 10</bibl>) details the
                    narrative more fully: a Nike with kithara on one side is presenting the
                    instrument to a young kitharode or lyre-player with outstretched hand on the
                    other. While the musician is missing on the Austin lekythos, his presence is
                    implied by the Nike's glance.</p>
                <p>This painting represents an extremely fine work by the so-called
                    Oionokles Painter, an early classic artist whose name derives from four <hi
                        rend="ital">kalos</hi> inscriptions. Beazley calls him a
                    follower of the Providence Painter, who in turn was a pupil of the Berlin
                    Painter (<bibl>Shapiro 1981a, no. 63</bibl>), and
                    both predecessors produced many pictures of Nike. However, the high quality of
                    this work singles it out, and perhaps the same can be said of it, as Beazley
                    said of an earlier lekythos with a kithara-bearing Nike by the Pan Painter (<rs
                        type="vase">Oxford 312</rs>; <bibl
                            >ARV2, 556, 102</bibl>), "a triumph of technique — pot, figure,
                    patternwork."</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p>Unpublished. On Nike: <bibl
                        >Isler-Kerényi 1969</bibl>. On kithara playing: <bibl
                            >Beazley 1922, 70-98</bibl>. On the Oionokles
                        Painter:<bibl>ARV2, 646-649</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
                <byline>Jenifer Neils</byline>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Mississippi 1977.3.87" type="vase"
                        >Mississippi 1977.3.87</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Red-Figure Neck-Amphora with Lid</title>
                    <rs type="collection">Collection of The University Museums,
                        University of Mississippi Phase I Cultural Center (1977.3.87a-b)</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Attributed to the Harrow Painter</rs>
                    <date>490-480 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 40.4 cm. without lid.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter: 23.5 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Height of lid: 14 cm.</measure> Side A: Dionysos
                    pursuing Ariadne. Side B: Companion of Ariadne, fleeing.</p>
                <p>When the Athenian hero Theseus came to Crete to rescue his companions
                    from the man-eating Minotaur, he needed the help of King Minos' daughter Ariadne
                    to find his way into and out of the impenetrable maze, the Labyrinth, in which
                    the monster was confined. She gave him a golden crown to light his way, or in
                    some versions of the story, a ball of thread; he tied one end of this to the
                    entrance and unrolled it as he went in, then followed it back when he had killed
                    the Minotaur. Ariadne sailed with him for Athens, expecting to become his bride,
                    but he deserted her on the island of Naxos. There Dionysos saw her, fell in love
                    and married her. The Athenians had a version of the story more flattering to
                    their national hero: Theseus left Ariadne only because Dionysos, having fallen
                    in love with her himself, compelled him to sail away without her.</p>
                <p>Like some of his contemporaries, the Harrow Painter liked to
                    concentrate the viewer's attention on the painted figures by isolating them
                    against the black background without a decorative frame or other distracting
                    ornament. This device also allowed the painter to experiment with the expression
                    of complex emotions and psychological states by means of carefully chosen
                    details and gestures, rather than with the broad, energetic pantomime used by
                    many black-figure and early red-figure painters. Here, the pursuit is over
                    almost before it has begun, without violence or panic. A mortal cannot resist
                    the power of a god, but this god has refrained from using his full power;
                    although his parted lips betray his emotion, he does not seize the girl in his
                    arms or struggle with her. He takes one stride forward and grasps her shoulder
                    with his left hand, while with his right hand he gently touches her arm but does
                    not yet clasp it with his fingers. She takes a single step away, her right hand
                    stretched out to the god with an imploring gesture, her left hand fearfully
                    clutching a small round object (a flower, or the ball of thread?) to her bosom.
                    She seems more hesitant and bewildered than frightened; even before the god's
                    hand closes on her wrist, she has begun to turn back toward him, lifting her
                    eyes to his face and gravely meeting his gaze. Soon the faithless mortal lover
                    will be forgotten.</p>
                <p>The god is identified as Dionysos by his wreath of ivy leaves, and
                    the identification of Ariadne is almost equally certain, since in vase painting
                    Dionysos does not appear with any other identifiable female figure. The
                    companion of Ariadne on the reverse is not given any name; such fleeing
                    companions are standard figures in scenes of gods or heroes pursuing women, and
                    the painter of this amphora was not much interested in her. He has drawn her
                    much more loosely than the main figures, with less attention to the details of
                    clothing and jewelry, and her gesture is entirely conventional.</p>
                <p>The Harrow Painter, to whom this vase is attributed, is one of the
                    better Late Archaic and Early Classical painters of large pots, a follower of
                    the Berlin Painter (see <rs type="vase">Sarasota 1600.G2</rs>).</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>CVA, Robinson Collection 2, Pl.
                        29, 2</bibl>; <bibl>ARV2, 272, 2</bibl>;
                        <bibl>Kaempf-Dimitriadou 1979, 30-31; 101,
                            #305</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
                <byline>Lucy Turnbull</byline>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Dallas 1972.22" type="vase">Dallas
                        1972.22</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Black-Figure Column-Krater</title>
                    <rs type="collection">Collection of the Dallas Museum of Fine Arts,
                        Gift of the Jonsson Foundation and Mr. and Mrs. Frederick M. Mayer (1972.22)</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Unattributed</rs>
                    <date>560-550 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 44 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter: 53 cm.</measure> Sides A and B: Dionysiac
                    revelry.</p>
                <p>The main scene (side A) carries a boisterous group of dancing satyrs
                    and maenads who cluster about a single bearded male figure. The revelers are the
                    companions of Dionysos who is recognizable as the central, clad figure holding a
                    drinking horn in his left hand. The reverse scene (side B) displays a single
                    male figure clad in a robe similar to that of Dionysos. He is flanked by two
                    pieces of cloth, which seem to float mystically in midair but are meant to be
                    draped over pegs on the wall, and in turn by two heraldically placed lions with
                    flicking tails and reversed heads. Under each handle a great bird in flight
                    separates the two scenes. Bearded male heads adorn the handle-plates on the vase
                    rim, itself decorated with wavy lines which recall the rippling action created
                    by stirring the vase's contents.</p>
                <p>Dionysiac revelries were popular subjects on Attic vases of the mid
                    sixth century B.C. As seen here the satyrs and maenads gesticulate wildly,
                    drawing the inspiration for their ecstatic mood from Dionysos, the god of
                    ecstasy and abandonment of the rational. The frenzied mood of the revelers,
                    however, is contrasted with the sedate and restrained pose of Dionysos himself.
                    The direction of Dionysos' slow pace indicates a movement of the group to the
                    right with the god in the center of his fold. Such scenes are not infrequently
                    expanded to include the returning outcast, Hephaistos, being led back to Olympos
                    by Dionysos. The Dallas vase does not include an image of the lame god, but the
                    arrangement of Dionysos and his companions on the obverse, the vase's shape, and
                    its date all invite comparison with the well known column krater by Lydos in New
                    York (<bibl>ABV, 108, 5</bibl>).</p>
                <p>Both Lydos and the painter of this vase elected to place Dionysos in
                    the center of his entourage on the obverse scene. While Lydos has depicted
                    Hephaistos in a similar setting on the reverse of the New York krater, thus
                    creating the effect of a continuous movement around the entire vase, this
                    painter has effectively curtailed the impression of a procession by turning the
                    attention of three lead characters back toward Dionysos. Their reverse action
                    focuses our attention on the god and successfully permits the composition of the
                    scene to be complete in itself.</p>
                <p>The soaring birds in the handle zones and the wild creatures on the
                    reverse of the Dallas krater are also familiar Lydan traits. While the painter
                    elected to depict a human between the lions instead of the more common choice of
                    an animal of a different species, he has attempted to segregate the central
                    figure from the snarling beasts by inserting a row of vertical dots on either
                    side of him.</p>
                <p>While the painted style is purely Attic, the bold use of animals in a
                    major scene, the extensive use of color, the dotted lions' manes, and dotted
                    rosettes in the field all testify to a liberal incorporation of Corinthian
                    motifs and practices. These, likewise, are typically Lydan.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Gazette des Beaux-Arts, La
                        Chronique des Arts, No. 1249 (February 1973), 103, no. 367</bibl>; <bibl
                            >On View, A Guide to Museum and Gallery
                            Acquisitions in Great Britain and America, London: Plaiston
                            Publications, 1974 edition, vol. 8,plate 247, p. 79</bibl>. On Lydos:
                        <bibl>ABV, 107ff</bibl>; <bibl
                            >Tiverios 1976</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
                <byline>Karl Kilinski II</byline>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Jacksonville AP.66.21" type="vase"
                        >Jacksonville AP.66.21</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Black-Figure Neck Amphora</title>
                    <rs type="collection">Collection of the Cummer Gallery of Art,
                        Jacksonville</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Group of Toronto 305</rs>
                    <date>Ca. 520-510 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 40.6 cm.</measure> Side A: Dionysos between
                    dancing satyrs. Side B: Maenads.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">On side A</hi>, Dionysos stands in a
                    rigid, statuesque pose, while two bearded satyrs dance about him. The god wears
                    a long <hi rend="ital">chiton</hi> with a pattern on the hem and,
                    over it, a <hi rend="ital">himation.</hi> His beard is long and
                    thick, like those of the satyrs, and an ivy wreath crowns his head. He holds up
                    a large kantharos in his left hand and a vine with three long tendrils in his
                    right. The satyr at left wears a white ribbon hung from his right shoulder
                    across his chest.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">On side B</hi>, a group of women stands
                    aligned in an orderly row. At left and right is an overlapping pair standing
                    side by side; the woman in the center appears to be alone, though it is possible
                    that she too has a companion, completely hidden from view, as Beazley assumed,
                    for a total of six. All are dressed alike in embroidered <hi rend="ital"
                        >chiton</hi> and <hi rend="ital">himation,</hi> and
                    all wear a fillet, with long tresses falling behind and over the shoulder.</p>
                <p>Two carry a pair of castanets (<hi rend="ital"
                    >krotala</hi>), and the woman in the center holds a spreading vine. Though they
                    have none of the identifying attributes of maenads - animal skin, thyrsos - the
                    presence of Dionysos on the other side leads us to suppose that they are his
                    followers.</p>
                <p>A small frieze of lions and boars runs beneath the figured scene, a
                    feature more common on hydrias of this period than on amphoras.</p>
                <p>This vase is one of a large number of amphoras and hydrias of the
                    late sixth century related to the circle of the Antimenes Painter, the most
                    prolific artist of the years ca. 530 - 510 (see <rs type="vase"
                        >Richmond 57.9</rs>). Among several groups distinguished by Beazley, the
                    Group of Toronto 305 includes about 20 amphoras, most of them with a Dionysiac
                    subject. Only one other, in Sydney (<bibl>ABV, 283,
                        8 bis</bibl>), includes the animal frieze.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Para., 125, 5bis</bibl>; <bibl
                        >Sale Catalogue, Christie's London, April 28,
                        1964. Lot. 65, pl. 10</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Diefenthal Collection (Shapiro No. 13)" type="vase"
                        >Diefenthal Collection (Shapiro No. 13)</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Black-Figure Eye-Cup</title>
                    <rs type="collection">Collection of Mr. and Mrs. Edward L.
                        Diefenthal, Metairie, Louisiana</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Attributed to the Krokotos Group [Cahn]</rs>
                    <date>Ca. 520 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 11.5 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter (without handles): 29 cm.</measure>
                    Interior: Gorgoneion Side A: Dionysos and Ariadne, between eyes. Side B:
                    Dionysos and two maenads, between eyes.</p>
                <p>On both sides of the exterior, Dionysos stands to the right, holding
                    up a rhyton in his left hand. He wears a <hi rend="ital"
                        >chiton</hi> and, over it, a striped <hi rend="ital">himation</hi>
                    with a decoration of stippled rosettes. He has an ivy wreath in his hair and a
                    long pointy beard. <hi rend="bold">On side A</hi>, a woman stands
                    in profile to left, facing the god and gesturing with her right hand. She wears
                    a <hi rend="ital">chiton</hi> decorated with an incised scale
                    pattern and a striped <hi rend="ital">himation.</hi> Since she is
                    alone with Dionysos, she is probably to be identified as Ariadne, the Cretan
                    princess who became the god's consort after he discovered her on the island of
                    Naxos, abandoned there by Theseus.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">On side B</hi>, the god is accompanied
                    by two women who stand symmetrically on either side of him. They are dressed
                    like Ariadne and make the same gesture of greeting. They may be unidentified
                    goddesses or, more likely, maenads without the thyrsos or other attributes.
                    Under and around each handle grow clusters of grapes hanging from vines. The
                    vines continue around the eyes and the figural groups, and directly under each
                    handle is a pair of intertwining branches.</p>
                <p>The eyes, for which this type of cup is named, first occur ten to
                    fifteen years before this example, on Exekias' famous cup in Munich (<bibl
                        >ABV, 146,21</bibl>). They regularly occupy this
                    position, next to the handles, allowing room for only a single figure or a small
                    group between them. Though tremendously popular in this period, the eyes' true
                    purpose or meaning is not entirely clear (see <rs type="vase"
                        >Dallas 1972.5</rs>).</p>
                <p>The tondo, as often in eye-cups, is black and decorated in the center
                    with a bearded Gorgon's head painted in outline, rather than black-figure.</p>
                <p>The Diefenthal cup is probably a product of the large Krokotos
                    workshop, which comprises several groups of eye-cups, one of which is the Group
                    of Walters 48.22 <rs type="vase">Dallas 1972.5</rs>. Krokotos
                    refers to the saffron yellow used by some painters of the workshop for animals
                    and garments. Dietrich von Bothmer suggests that this cup may be by the same
                    hand as one in Mannheim (<rs type="vase">Mannheim Cg38</rs>; <bibl
                        >CVA, pl. 17</bibl>).</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p>Unpublished. Krokotos Group: <bibl
                        >ABV, 205-208</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Miami 56.001.000" type="vase">Miami
                        56.001.000</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Black-Figure Neck-Amphora</title>
                    <rs type="collection">Collection of The Lowe Art Museum, University
                        of Miami, Coral Gables, Anonymous Gift (56.001.000)</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Unattributed</rs>
                    <date>520-500 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 37.5 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter: 28 cm.</measure> Side A: Dionysos with
                    satyrs and maenads. Side B: Warrior in a wheeling chariot.</p>
                <p>Most black-figure scenes of Dionysos emphasize his role as giver of
                    the gift of wine. <hi rend="bold">On side A</hi>, two large bunches
                    of grapes hang prominently from vines in the background. The god himself, in the
                    center, holds a kantharos, the wine vessel most closely associated with him, and
                    one of the satyrs holds an oinochoe with high-swung handle, used for serving
                    wine. Dionysos wears an ivy crown and a <hi rend="ital"
                        >himation</hi> over a long <hi rend="ital">chiton.</hi> Both
                    garments are decorated with dots forming diamond patterns, and a row of dots
                    adorns the hem of the <hi rend="ital">chiton.</hi></p>
                <p>The god is framed by two symmetrical pairs of a satyr and a maenad.
                    Often maenads are seen fending off the advances of aroused satyrs, but here the
                    couples are on rather friendly terms, as they stand side by side and casually
                    embrace. It looks as if the influence of the wine may have made the maenads more
                    amenable than usual. Each is dressed in a belted <hi rend="ital"
                        >chiton</hi> decorated in the same manner as Dionysos' garments.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Side B</hi> shows a four horse chariot
                    wheeling around, an especially popular motif on later black-figure neck-amphoras
                    (<rs type="vase">Sarasota 1600.G4</rs>). The driver is a
                    warrior in a low crested Corinthian helmet. He carries several spears and a
                    shield, facing the viewer, which has as its device three white balls. Another
                    shield appears to rest on the warrior's back and is seen in profile.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p>unpublished.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:New Orleans (Shapiro No. 15)" type="vase"
                        >New Orleans (Shapiro No. 15)</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Black-Figure Skyphos</title>
                    <rs type="collection">Collection of the New Orleans Museum of Art</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">CHC Group</rs>
                    <date>Ca. 500 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 14.7 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter: 22.5 cm.</measure> Side A: Dionysos between
                    satyrs and maenads. Side B: The like.</p>
                <p>The skyphos is a drinking vessel, and the ample proportions of this
                    example would have contained a rather generous serving of wine. The Dionysiac
                    subject matter is in keeping with the vase's function.</p>
                <p>On both sides, Dionysos occupies the center of a nearly perfectly
                    symmetrical composition. He stands in profile to the right, holding up a large
                    rhyton in his left hand. The god wears a striped mantle and an ivy wreath in his
                    hair. On either side of him stands a nude satyr, each facing the god, with one
                    hand raised in greeting. Moving outward, next come two maenads also looking
                    toward the center. They wear belted <hi rend="ital">chitons,</hi>
                    and on two of the four, incised lines suggest an animal hide tied over the <hi
                        rend="ital">chiton.</hi> The whole group is framed by a pair of
                    crouching sphinxes facing outward. A large palmette occupies the space between
                    handles and sphinxes.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>ABV, 620, 88</bibl>; <bibl
                        >Cesnola 1885-1903, ii pl. 148, 1099</bibl>;
                        <bibl><title>Cypriote and
                            Classical Antiquities, Duplicates of the Cesnola and other
                            Collections,</title> Sale Catalogue, Anderson Galleries, New York,
                            30-31 March, 1928, i, 107, 395</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Mississippi 1977.3.58" type="vase"
                        >Mississippi 1977.3.58</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Black-Figure Neck-Amphora</title>
                    <rs type="collection">Collection of the University Museums,
                        University of Mississippi, Phase I Cultural Center (77.3.58)</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Attributed to the Diosphos Painter</rs>
                    <date>510-500 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 20.1 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter: 11.3 cm.</measure> Side A: Dionysos, satyr
                    and maenad. Side B: Two maenads with wild animals.</p>
                <p>Red beard wagging briskly, both feet off the ground, the satyr on
                    side A leaps upon the maenad as if to bring her down with a flying tackle. She
                    holds her thyrsos in one hand and extends the other toward Dionysos, begging for
                    help, but the god merely stands and watches. Dionysos was not simply a god of
                    wine; he was a fertility god as well, as the celebrations of the Country
                    Dionysia in Attic villages made clear. Enormous images of human genitalia were
                    carried in procession through the streets, to the accompaniment of obscene jokes
                    and songs. In its primitive beginnings the custom was probably meant to
                    stimulate, by this example, the plants and vines to grow and be fruitful. Even
                    at the more sophisticated City Dionysia, where the god was honored with dramatic
                    presentations, this phallic element was retained in the grotesquely padded
                    costumes and uninhibited obscenity of comedy. In art, the phallic aspect of
                    Dionysos' cult is represented by the satyrs with their half-animal appearance
                    and their extravagant lecherousness. Earlier black-figure painting has some
                    scenes of actual copulation between satyrs and maenads in which the maenads seem
                    to be cooperating enthusiastically, but this amphora shows a more dignified
                    encounter: the maenad tried to escape but does not defend herself very
                    energetically. Later, in the early 5th century, maenads are shown using the
                    thyrsos to hold off attacking satyrs, whose approaches are usually more cautious
                    than the one here, and by the end of the century the subject had gone out of
                    fashion.</p>
                <p>Side B shows another aspect of Dionysiac cult. Two maenads are
                    dancing in an ecstatic trance; possessed by the spirit of the god, they can
                    perform superhuman feats of strength, are impervious to weapons and can handle
                    wild animals and poisonous snakes without harm. Here, one carries a deer on her
                    shoulders and the other dangles a young lion by its tail. The moment is
                    approaching the <hi rend="ital">sparagmos,</hi> the climactic act
                    of communion with the god, when they will tear the animals to pieces with their
                    bare hands and eat the raw flesh. These maenads are to be considered nymphs
                    rather than contemporary mortal worshippers, but this violent form of Dionysiac
                    cult continued to be practiced in Thrace, and possibly in some parts of Greece,
                    in the Classical period.</p>
                <p>This vase is attributed to the Diosphos Painter, a prolific painter
                    of late black-figure lekythoi and neck-amphoras (see <rs type="vase"
                        >Richmond 60-11</rs>).</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>CVA, Robinson Collection 1, pl.
                        30, 1</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 248</bibl>; <bibl
                            >Haspels 1936, 239, #136</bibl>. For Dionysos
                        and his cult: <bibl>Otto 1965</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
                <byline>Lucy Turnbull</byline>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Sarasota 1600.G5" type="vase">Sarasota
                        1600.G5</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Black-Figure Oinochoe
                    (White-Ground)</title>
                <rs type="collection">Collection of the John and Mable Ringling
                    Museum of Art, Sarasota (1600.G5)</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Workshop of the Athena Painter</rs>
                    <date>Ca. 500-480 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 23.8 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter: 41.9 cm.</measure> Two travelling satyrs</p>
                <p>Satyrs are so prevalent on Attic vases that they often appear on
                    their own in a variety of scenes where we might have expected the presence of
                    Dionysos. This pair looks like an excerpt from a lively procession accompanying
                    the god.</p>
                <p>The satyr at left rides on a goat with long curving horns and a long
                    beard. The satyr wears a wide-brimmed traveller's hat, the <hi rend="ital"
                        >petasos,</hi> and carries a rhyton in his raised right hand. He
                    is also dressed in a short-sleeved <hi rend="ital">chiton</hi> and
                    a <hi rend="ital">himation</hi> across his lap. He sits backwards
                    on the animal, his feet dangling on either side, and turns to look ahead. In
                    front a chubby satyr walks slowly as he plays the double flutes. He is nude but
                    for a fillet in his hair, and the flute case hangs from his elbow. The fleshy
                    folds of his belly are marked by incised lines, and his tail is particularly
                    full, both perhaps signs of advancing age. A vine pattern crisscrosses the
                    background.</p>
                <p>The white-ground technique, that is, the application of a thick layer
                    of creamy white to the clay surface before decorating with figures in black
                    glaze, had been experimented with first about 525. Its use was popularized by
                    the Edinburgh Painter, starting about 500 and primarily on lekythoi (<bibl
                        >Shapiro 1981a, no. 26</bibl>), then spread
                    almost immediately to oinochoai and a few other small shapes.</p>
                <p>The Athena Painter was a slightly younger follower of the Edinburgh
                    Painter who eagerly took up the latter's innovative use of white ground for
                    lekythoi and oinochoai. He appears to have been the chief artist in a rather
                    large workshop, and it is not always possible to say if a particular vase, such
                    as the Ringling example, is from his own hand or that of a closely associated
                    painter. The style of the Athena Painter is very close to that of a red-figure
                    lekythos Painter, the Bowdoin Painter (<rs type="vase">Chapel Hill
                        78.15.1</rs>), and it is possible that they are one and the same artist,
                    working in different techniques at different stages of his career.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>ABV, 527, 17</bibl> and <bibl
                        >Para., 264</bibl>. On the Athena and Bowdoin
                        Painters: <bibl>Kurtz 1975, 15-16</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Diefenthal Collection (Shapiro No. 18)" type="vase"
                        >Diefenthal Collection (Shapiro No. 18)</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Red-Figure Miniature Lekythos</title>
                <rs type="collection">Collection of Mr. and Mrs. Edward L.
                    Diefenthal, Metairie, Louisiana</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Unattributed</rs>
                    <date>450-400 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 15 cm.</measure> Satyr at a fountain</p>
                <p>Although the shape and ornament of this vase are commonplace (a
                    secondary lekythos with meander and rays), the scene depicted on it is unusual
                    if not unique. Crouching before an outdoor fountain is a nude figure with equine
                    ears and tail, a satyr. Like most satyrs in Greek art he has a receding
                    hairline, long, ragged beard, snub nose and large phallus. Behind him is his
                    abandoned wine amphora garlanded with ivy. The fountain consists of a masonry
                    structure with an animal head spout. While Greek fountains are usually equipped
                    with feline head spouts, this one, with its stippled hair, heavy lower jaw and
                    pointed ears, appears more canine or porcine in form; perhaps it represents a
                    caricature of a lion head. Thin strokes of paint emerging from the spout and
                    crossing the satyr's extended left arm are no doubt streams of water. Thus, it
                    looks as if the satyr has paused in his heated revelries to take a refreshing
                    shower. In the late sixth and early fifth centuries B.C., the performance of
                    satyr plays in Athens prompted the depiction of many genre-like scenes of
                    satyrs, such as domestic life and athletics. While this reading of the scene
                    would make it unique in Attic vase-painting, another interpretation is possible.</p>
                <p>Mythological sources tell of one particular satyr, Silenos, being
                    ambushed and taken to King Midas. His capture, which took place at a fountain,
                    was facilitated by mixing wine with the water and thus inebriating the
                    susceptible satyr. The most common representation of the myth shows the bound
                    Silenos being led away; a few others show his ambush at the fountain. In the
                    latter case, Silenos is clearly drinking from the spout while his captors crouch
                    nearby. Since the Diefenthal lekythos shows neither the captors nor Silenos
                    drinking, the mythological interpretation of the scene is not assured. In either
                    case, however, the vase is an unusual and engaging piece.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p>Unpublished. On satyrs: <bibl>Brommer
                        1944</bibl>. On the capture of Silenos: <bibl
                            >Brommer 1941</bibl>; <bibl
                                >Brommer 1973, 534-535</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
                <byline>Jenifer Neils</byline>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Mississippi 1977.3.103" type="vase"
                        >Mississippi 1977.3.103</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Red-Figure Cup</title>
                    <rs type="collection">Collection of The University Museums,
                        University of Mississippi Phase I Cultural Center (1977.3.103)</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Attributed to the Bonn Painter [Robinson]</rs>
                    <date>Ca. 510 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 7 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter (with handles): 23 cm.</measure> Interior:
                    Satyr with rhyton and column-krater.</p>
                <p>The satyr, ithyphallic as usual in early red-figure painting,
                    crouches beside an enormous column krater. His right hand, concealed by the rim
                    of the krater, is dipping out wine to fill his rhyton, a drinking cup made from
                    an animal's horn. He wears a red fillet with tassels or flowers over his bald
                    head and horsy ears. To the left of his head, the name <foreign xml:lang="greek"
                        >*L*E*A*G*R*O*S</foreign> (Leagros) is written from right
                    to left.</p>
                <p>As companion of Dionysos, the satyr is an appropriate ornament for a
                    cup; this is one of many grotesque or obscene pictures drawn on the interior of
                    cups, where their emergence as the wine level sank might startle or amuse the
                    drinker. Half animal, half human in appearance, satyrs are spirits of
                    uninhibited sensuality, perpetually drunk, perpetually lustful, totally without
                    intellect (one early poet called them "unemployable loafers"). Their animal
                    nature is indicated by their appearance, with horse tails, ears like pigs or
                    horses, piggy snub noses and bald heads (baldness in antiquity was considered a
                    sign or virility) and, in early black-figure, shaggy coats of hair all over
                    their bodies. In vase painting their chief occupations are drinking, dancing,
                    flute playing and sexually assaulting maenads, goats, goddesses and occasionally
                    each other. In later red-figure, satyrs appear tamer; the maenads ward off their
                    attacks without much trouble, and they begin to appear in scenes of ritual,
                    where it is clear that the women involved are not spirits of nature but human
                    women, and the satyrs behave more quietly. In the later 5th century a new type
                    of satyr appears, youthful, with a more human face and a full head of hair, as
                    well as better manners.</p>
                <p>The name Leagros on this cup does not belong to the satyr but to a
                    young Athenian contemporary of aristocratic birth. The Greeks set a very high
                    value on physical beauty, counting it almost as a virtue in itself, and
                    certainly a quality whose lack somehow diminished even an otherwise admirable
                    person. In a society which approved and encouraged homosexual love affairs
                    between men and youths, the beauty of adolescent boys was admired most of all. A
                    particularly attractive boy could become a popular sensation, courted by many
                    wooers, celebrated by poets and even by vase painters, who would inscribe his
                    name on their products, either by itself or with the adjective <foreign
                        xml:lang="greek">*K*A*L*O*S</foreign> — "beautiful." A
                    very few of these inscribed vases may have been commissioned as gifts or
                    keepsakes, but for the most part the painters must simply have been trying to
                    add a note of fashion and aristocratic elegance to their wares. The Leagros of
                    this cup must have been outstandingly lovely, for his name appears on more than
                    60 surviving vases.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>CVA, Robinson Collection 2, pl.
                        3, 1</bibl>; <bibl>ARV2, 1593, 38</bibl>.
                        For satyrs: <bibl>Brommer 1937</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
                <byline>Lucy Turnbull</byline>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Austin 1980.33" type="vase">Austin
                        1980.33</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Black-Figure Oinochoe</title>
                <rs type="collection">Collection of the Archer M. Huntington Art
                    Gallery, the University of Texas, Austin, James R. Dougherty, Jr. Foundation
                    and Archer M. Huntington Museum Fund Purchase (1980.33)</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Related to the Class of Vatican G47</rs>
                    <date>520-500 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 13.9 cm.</measure> Herakles wrestling the
                    Nemean Lion</p>
                <p>The first of Herakles' labors was the capture and killing of the lion
                    which had ravaged the valley around Nemea, in the northeastern Peloponnesos. The
                    lion's invulnerable pelt rendered all weapons useless and forced the hero to
                    engage the beast in a wrestling match and finally strangle it. Herakles skinned
                    the dead animal and thereafter wore the impervious hide for protection, and in
                    vase-painting it is usually his distinguishing attribute (see for example <rs
                        type="vase">New Orleans 16.38</rs>).</p>
                <p>On this vase, the wrestling match is in full swing and the outcome is
                    still in doubt. Herakles is entirely nude, but for a fillet around his head and
                    a baldric worn diagonally around his chest, to support a sword. His bow, quiver,
                    and sword all rest in the branches of a tree in the background. With his left
                    hand the hero is grasping the lion's belly, while his right holds off a rear paw
                    with which the lion tries to claw Herakles' head. He hunches over the lion's
                    luxuriant mane, leaving his thigh and groin area exposed and dangerously close
                    to the lion's open jaws. Behind Herakles stands Iolaos, his young nephew and
                    frequent companion in his labors. He wears a corselet over a short <hi
                        rend="ital">chiton</hi> and holds Herakles' knotty club. His
                    sword hangs from a baldric, and a second baldric crosses in an X pattern. He
                    stretches out his left hand over the wrestling pair as a weak gesture of fright,
                    or of encouragement for the hero.</p>
                <p>In early black-figure, before about 540, Herakles and the lion
                    regularly wrestle standing up. The great master Exekias apparently first showed
                    them wrestling on the ground, as John Boardman has recently demonstrated, on a
                    vase, fragments of which are at Ensérune. After that this version became
                    increasingly popular in the last quarter of the sixth century, the period of the
                    Austin oinochoe.</p>
                <p>This vase is similar in shape to a large class of late sixth century
                    oinochoai designated by Beazley the Class of Vatican G47. The term 'class'
                    refers to shape and proportions, not to drawing style.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>ABV, 431, 9</bibl>; <bibl
                        >Brommer 1973, 136,40</bibl>; <bibl
                            >CVA, Castle Ashby (Great Britain 15) 13-14
                            and pl. 22.5-7</bibl>; <bibl>Christie's Sale
                                Catalogue, lot. 78, p. 119, ill</bibl>. On Herakles and the Lion: <bibl
                                    >Brommer 1974, 7-11</bibl>; for the wrestling
                        match on the ground and the Ensérune fragments: <bibl
                            >Boardman 1978, 14-15</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Polmer Collection (Shapiro No. 21)" type="vase"
                        >Polmer Collection (Shapiro No. 21)</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Black-Figure Cup</title>
                <rs type="collection">Collection of Mrs. Nathan Polmer, New Orleans</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Attributed to a Painter of the Leafless Group
                        [Bothmer]</rs>
                    <date>Ca. 500-480 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 6.9 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter (without handles): 15.8 cm.</measure>
                    Interior: Running Satyr Side A: Herakles wrestling the Nemean Lion. Side B: The
                    like.</p>
                <p>The same scene is repeated without variation on both sides of the
                    exterior. A nude Herakles leans over the charging lion, restraining it by
                    grasping the left rear paw with his right hand. The hero's sword can be seen on
                    the far side, as if projecting from his chest. The wrestlers are framed by a
                    symmetrical pair of crouching youths, each with a cloak draped over his left
                    arm. Both face to the right but look back left, so that only one observes the
                    wrestling match. <hi rend="bold">On side A</hi>, the artist has
                    placed the wrestling pair off center, leaving too little room for the youth at
                    left, who overlaps the handle. Hastily drawn trees and vines fill the
                    background, and from one hangs Herakles' garment. A leaping dolphin appears
                    under each handle. Though the draughtsmanship is rather careless and the
                    incision minimal, the vitality of the struggle is effectively captured.</p>
                <p>In the tondo, a satyr within a small reserved circle runs to the
                    right, looking back. He has a thick fillet hung from his right arm and carries a
                    large rhyton in his right hand. The vase did not fire properly in the tondo,
                    probably because several were stacked one upon the other in the kiln. Thus the
                    satyr appears dark red instead of black.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Brommer 1973, 135, A31</bibl>.
                        Leafless Group: <bibl>ABV, 632-53</bibl> and
                        <bibl>Para., 310-313</bibl>; for the Polmer
                        cup, Bothmer compares one on the Milan market (<bibl
                            >Para., 312, bottom</bibl>) and one at the University of
                        Illinois (<rs type="vase">Champaign CM 135</rs>).</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:New Orleans 16.39" type="vase">New Orleans
                        16.39</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Black-Figure Amphora</title>
                <rs type="collection">Collection of the New Orleans Museum of Art,
                    Gift of Alvin P. Howard (16.39, formerly 2035)</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Unattributed</rs>
                    <date>Ca. 520-500 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 28.6 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter: 17.5 cm.</measure> Side A: Herakles
                    battling Triton. Side B: Warrior and old men.</p>
                <p>Herakles' combat with the sea monster Triton (<hi rend="bold"
                    >side A</hi>) is a favorite subject on Attic vases of the second
                    half of the sixth century - this despite the fact that it is not one of the
                    twelve labors and is in fact an episode completely unknown to the literary
                    sources. Triton is mentioned by Hesiod (<bibl n="Hes. Th. 930-33"
                        >Hes. Th. 930-33</bibl>) as a son of Poseidon and Amphitrite,
                    though not as an opponent of Herakles.</p>
                <p>The scene should be distinguished from that of Herakles' struggle
                    with another sea creature, Nereus, from whom the hero learned the way to the
                    Garden of the Hesperides. That struggle is depicted on several early
                    black-figure vases: Herakles is unarmed and Nereus is recognized by his ability
                    to change his form into that of any animal or object and thus elude Herakles'
                    grasp. A lion's head growing from his back or snakes held in his hands allude to
                    the transformations. Nereus is a benign creature, the <hi rend="ital"
                        >Halios Geron</hi> (Old Man of the Sea), only reluctant to
                    divulge information. Triton is dangerous, and with him it is a fight to the
                    death.</p>
                <p>Herakles' battle with Triton replaces the struggle with Nereus on
                    Attic vases rather abruptly soon before the mid-sixth century and then remains
                    steadily popular until about 510. Triton's identity, in the absence of poetic
                    sources, is established by several inscribed vases. The scene is confined to
                    black-figure, apart from two red-figure exceptions.</p>
                <p>The New Orleans example is typical of many others. Herakles wears his
                    lion skin and carries a quiver over his shoulder, but his weapon is the sword.
                    Triton puts up little resistance to the hero's onslaught. The join between human
                    torso and fishy tail is at about the waist; the scales are small and the
                    underside of the tail is marked by a thick line of white. An old man, balding
                    and with white beard, watches from the left. This is probably none other than
                    Nereus, who, after losing his monstrous form and then giving way to Triton on
                    the vases, sometimes appears as an impartial witness to the combat.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">On side B</hi>, a fully armed warrior
                    sits on a low stool or bench. He wears a Corinthian helmet, and his sword is
                    visible behind the round shield whose device is a quiver. He is flanked by two
                    old men in <hi rend="ital">chiton</hi> and <hi rend="ital"
                        >himation,</hi> both with receding white hair and beard. The man
                    at left moves off with a long stride, gesturing farewell with a raised hand. The
                    other stays and faces the warrior, holding a staff. The scene is probably of
                    epic inspiration, but the figures cannot be identified.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Brommer 1973, 146, A18</bibl>.
                        On Triton: <bibl>Luce 1922, 174-92</bibl>; <bibl
                            >Glynn 1981, 121-32</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Mississippi 1977.3.61a and b" type="vase"
                        >Mississippi 1977.3.61a and b</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Black-Figure Neck-Amphora</title>
                <rs type="collection">Collection of The University Museums,
                    University of Mississippi Phase I Cultural Center (1977. 3.61 a-b)</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Near the Antimenes Painter [Robinson]</rs>
                    <date>530-520 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 41.6 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter: 27.7 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Height of lid: 8 cm.</measure> Side A: Herakles and
                    the Cretan Bull. Side B: Hermes, Dionysos and goddess.</p>
                <p>Herakles' later labors carried him to the ends of the earth and
                    beyond it to the land of the dead. By about the middle of the 6th century B.C.
                    vase-painters were illustrating these exotic adventures, of which the capture of
                    the Cretan Bull was one. King Minos of Crete, preparing to sacrifice to
                    Poseidon, found he had no suitable victim. He prayed to the god, who sent a
                    beautiful bull from the sea — so beautiful that Minos thought it too fine
                    to sacrifice and kept it for himself. (Poseidon's revenge for this insult was to
                    make Minos' wife fall in love with the bull; their son was the man-bull, the
                    Minotaur.) Herakles' seventh labor was to capture and bring back this bull for
                    his cowardly master Eurystheus. Unlike other animals Herakles encountered, the
                    bull seems to have no supernational qualities or other unusually dangerous
                    abilities, and he captures it, in vase-painting at least, with relatively little
                    difficulty. Here he has roped it around the horns and front legs, and it
                    collapses at his feet. Hermes waits at left to guide the far-wandering hero back
                    to Argos. This is not the most dramatic or fantastic of Herakles' adventures,
                    but it was a favorite with black-figure painters; more than 140 examples are
                    known.</p>
                <p>In the center of side B stands Dionysos, turning his head to look at
                    Hermes. At right stands a goddess holding on her shoulders two small children
                    drawn, as always in archaic art, as miniature adults. None of the figures is
                    named, but the two gods are recognizable because of the system of attributes
                    — clothing, objects, gestures — by which even foreigners and
                    illiterates could identify the personages depicted. Herakles' club, bow and
                    lionskin cloak, or any one or combination of them, is sufficient to identify
                    him. The same is true of Hermes' winged boots and herald's staff, or Dionysos'
                    wreath, grapevine and cup. The goddess is more difficult to identify, though her
                    general nature is clear: she is a <hi rend="ital"
                        >kourotrophos,</hi> a goddess of fertility (not necessarily a mother goddess as
                    such) who grants children to mankind, protects and nurtures them. The concept of
                    such a goddess was already ancient among the Greeks when this amphora was
                    painted, and it had become extremely complex and confused. In Athens and Attica
                    "Kourotrophos" was a cult title of several goddesses, from Ge the Earth-Mother
                    to virginal Artemis and Athena. Kourotrophos was also the name of a goddess or
                    goddesses worshiped independently in shrines of their own, and Kourotrophos was
                    honored by a preliminary sacrifice at major Athenian festivals. The goddess here
                    wears an ivy wreath like Dionysos', and it may be that she is his wife Ariadne
                    in the role of Kourotrophos, with their sons Staphylos and Oinopion. What it all
                    meant to the wealthy Etruscan who bought this amphora and took it to his grave
                    is impossible to guess.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Robinson 1956</bibl>; <bibl
                        >Brommer 1973, 195, A28</bibl>. For Herakles
                        and the Bull in archaic art: <bibl>Schefold
                            1978, 103-105</bibl>; for Kourotrophos: <bibl
                                >Hadzisteliou-Price 1978</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
                <byline>Lucy Turnbull</byline>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Richmond 60-11" type="vase">Richmond
                        60-11</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Black-Figure Neck-Amphora</title>
                <rs type="collection">Collection of the Virginia Museum of Fine
                    Arts, Richmond, The Williams Fund (60-11)</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Attributed to the Diosphos Painter</rs>
                    <date>Ca. 500-490 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 22.2 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter of base: 6.9 cm.</measure> Side A: Herakles'
                    combat with Kyknos. Side B: Athena and Ares.</p>
                <p>Herakles' combat with the Thessalian brigand Kyknos, a son of Ares,
                    was one of his <hi rend="ital">parerga,</hi> episodes that took
                    place in the course of the hero's travels when he performed the twelve labors.</p>
                <p>The story is not one of the more significant or colorful ones in
                    Herakles' long career, but it is one of the best known to us in its details,
                    thanks to a 480-line epic poem which survives, the Shield of Herakles <bibl
                        n="Hes. Sh.">Hes. Sh.</bibl>. Attributed in
                    antiquity to Hesiod, the poem is now thought to have been composed about a
                    century after Hesiod's time, in the early sixth century. At about the same time
                    the lyric poet Stesichoros wrote another version of the Kyknos story which is
                    now lost. Together these poems inspired a full series of Attic vase-paintings,
                    over one hundred of which are preserved, from the second quarter of the sixth
                    century to the first quarter of the fifth. The scene occurs occasionally in
                    sculpture as well, for example on one of the metopes of the Athenian Treasury at
                    Delphi.</p>
                <p>Painted depictions of the Kyknos story are always of one of two
                    types: a single combat, in which only the two protagonists are shown; or a
                    fuller version, in which Herakles is seconded by his patroness, Athena, and
                    Kyknos by his father, Ares, with Zeus sometimes appearing in the middle, either
                    to break up the fight or to show support for Herakles. The Virginia amphora is
                    very unusual in showing the full version, but with the participants divided
                    between the two sides of the vase.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">On side A</hi>, Herakles leaps over the
                    falling Kyknos. He wears his lion skin over a short <hi rend="ital"
                        >chiton,</hi> his sword hanging from a baldric, and wields a spear. Kyknos'
                    weapon is also a spear, and he wears a corselet and high crested Corinthian
                    helmet. His shield device is two balls on a light ground. Several nonsense
                    inscriptions appear in the field.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">On side B</hi>, Ares and Athena stand
                    back to back, their rear legs overlapping. Clearly we are meant to think of them
                    as moving in the direction of their respective protégés on Side A.
                    Ares wears hoplite armor, like his son, his shield device a winding serpent with
                    gaping jaws. Athena wears her aegis over her extended left arm, like a shield,
                    and a snake-like bracelet on her right wrist.</p>
                <p>This vase is attributed to the Diosphos Painter, one of the latest
                    black-figure artists, who began his career about 500 and may have continued well
                    into the Early Classical period. He was primarily a painter of lekythoi, but the
                    small neck-amphora with double-reeded handles and a special shape, sometimes
                    called a doubleen, is also characteristic of his work.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Para., 250</bibl>; <bibl
                        ><title>Ancient Art in the
                            Virginia Museum</title> (Richmond 1973) 86</bibl>. On Herakles and
                        Kyknos: <bibl>Vian 1945</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:San Antonio 75.59.15P" type="vase">San
                        Antonio 75.59.15P</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Black-Figure Amphora</title>
                <rs type="collection">Collection of the San Antonio Museum
                    Association (75.59.15P)</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Attributed to a painter of Group E [Bothmer]</rs>
                    <date>Ca. 540-530 B. C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 40 cm.</measure> Side A: Herakles rescuing
                    Deianeira from the Centaur Nessos. Side B: Wheeling chariot.</p>
                <p>One day when Herakles was out with his wife Deianeira, they came to
                    the River Evenos, in Aitolia, swollen with rain. The centaur Nessos offered to
                    carry Deianeira across, but as Herakles watched from the bank, Nessos tried to
                    take advantage of the woman in mid-stream. Herakles shot the centaur with an
                    arrow made more lethal by having been dipped in the blood of the Hydra. But
                    Nessos had his revenge, for with his dying words he persuaded Deianeira to save
                    the blood from his wound and use it as a love potion, should Herakles ever
                    wander in his affections. Years later, when Herakles brought home a concubine,
                    the princess Iole, his distraught wife spread the potion on a shirt, a gift for
                    Herakles, and thus unwittingly caused his agonizing death.</p>
                <p>The death of Nessos was one of the earliest myth scenes to appear in
                    Greek art, on a Proto-Attic amphora of the early seventh century, now in New
                    York, and remained a popular subject in Attic black-figure. But the painted
                    scenes seldom follow the canonical version of the story as recounted above,
                    which is best known to us from Sophocles' <hi rend="ital"
                        >Trachiniae</hi> (<bibl n="Soph. Trach.">Soph.
                            Trach.</bibl>). Instead, as on side A of this vase, Herakles' weapon is
                    usually a sword, instead of bow and arrow, and there is no indication that the
                    encounter takes places in or near a river. Herakles wears only a short <hi
                        rend="ital">chiton</hi> with a patterned hem; his scabbard
                    hangs from a baldric across his chest. He puts his arm around his wife's
                    shoulder, a protective gesture, as he advances toward the centaur.</p>
                <p>Deianeira wears a belted <hi rend="ital">peplos</hi> and
                    a short shawl-like mantle over it. Nessos looks back as he runs off to the
                    right, holding a stone in each hand. The centaurs live in the wild and regularly
                    fight with whatever weapons are ready to hand - tree branches and rocks.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">On side B</hi>, a four-horse chariot
                    wheels sharply around, the rear horses animatedly kicking their forelegs high in
                    the air. The chariot is driven by a bearded man in a pointed cap. He wears a
                    short-sleeved <hi rend="ital">chiton</hi> and over it a spotted
                    animal hide, a frequent attribute of charioteers in black-figure. Beside him in
                    the car stands a warrior in high crested Corinthian helmet, carrying a spear.
                    Such lively chariot scenes are an especially common motif in later black-figure
                    (compare <rs type="vase">Sarasota 1600.G4</rs>).</p>
                <p>The San Antonio amphora has been assigned by Dietrich von Bothmer to
                    Group E, a large but closely related group of black-figure painters of the third
                    quarter of the sixth century. The E refers to the great master Exekias, for, in
                    Beazley's words, this group is "the soil from which the art of Exekias rose, the
                    tradition which he absorbs and transcends" (<bibl
                        >Beazley 1951, 63</bibl>). This vase exemplifies the one-piece or
                    belly-amphora, with continuous curve from lip to foot. This type of amphora is
                    generally earlier than that with offset neck, or neck-amphora, especially
                    popular in later black figure (e.g. <rs type="vase">Sarasota
                        1600.G4</rs>, <rs type="vase">Richmond 60-11</rs>, <bibl
                            >Shapiro 1981a, no. 2</bibl>).</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Para., 56, 38 bis</bibl>; <bibl
                        >Cat. Sotheby 1974, Lot 227, ill</bibl>. On
                        Herakles and Nessos: <bibl>Fittschen
                            1970</bibl>. On the New York Nessos amphora: <bibl
                                >Schefold 1964, 36 and pl. 23</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Denman Collection (Shapiro No. 26)" type="vase"
                        >Denman Collection (Shapiro No. 26)</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Black-Figure Lekythos
                    (White-Ground)</title>
                <rs type="collection">Collection of Gilbert M. Denman, Jr., San
                    Antonio</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Attributed to the Edinburgh Painter [Cahn]</rs>
                    <date>Ca. 500 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 31.8 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter: 11.5 cm.</measure> Introduction of Herakles
                    to Olympos.</p>
                <p>After Herakles' death, caused by the poisoned shirt of Nessos (<rs
                    type="vase">San Antonio 75.59.15P</rs>, and his immolation on a
                    funeral pyre on Mount Oeta, he underwent an apotheosis, ascending to join the
                    company of gods on Mount Olympos. The scene occurs often in Attic black-figure,
                    starting in the second quarter of the sixth century, and continues, though less
                    popular, throughout red-figure. The scene is usually referred to as the
                    introduction, because Herakles is almost invariably accompanied by Athena, his
                    protectress, who is sometimes seen presenting him to her father Zeus and the
                    assembled gods and goddesses.</p>
                <p>The apotheosis, or introduction, is generally shown in one of two
                    ways: either Herakles is driven in a chariot by Athena; or, as here, they
                    approach on foot. Generally speaking the introduction on foot is popular in
                    earlier black-figure and is later replaced by the version with chariot, but the
                    former type does recur, and the procession of vertical figures is certainly more
                    appropriate for a narrow lekythos such as this example.</p>
                <p>The scene is framed by two slender Doric columns which mark the
                    entrance to Olympos. The group is led by Hermes, who gestures with upraised left
                    hand, as if signalling to the unseen gods Herakles' arrival. Hermes wears winged
                    boots and cap, <hi rend="ital">chlamys</hi> over a short <hi
                        rend="ital">chiton,</hi> and carries his <hi rend="ital"
                            >kerykeion.</hi> Next comes Athena, who looks back at Herakles,
                    her raised hand also indicating that they have reached their destination. Her
                    aegis, seen frontally, shows prominently the snaky fringe, and two snakes curl
                    up over the goddess' shoulders. She wears a high-crested Attic helmet and
                    carries a spear. Herakles wears only a short pleated <hi rend="ital"
                        >chiton</hi> with short sleeves and carries his club in his
                    right hand, a bow in his left. Behind him stands a bearded figure in a <hi
                        rend="ital">chiton</hi> and a tall pointed cap, holding two
                    spears. This might be Iolaos, Herakles' frequent companion on most of his
                    adventures <rs type="vase">Austin 1980.33</rs>, even though Iolaos
                    could not, of course, accompany the hero to Olympos.</p>
                <p>About 500 B.C. the Edinburgh Painter, to whom the Denman vase is
                    attributed, introduced the technique of decorating larger cylindrical lekythoi
                    with black figures on a white ground. It was only toward the middle of the fifth
                    century that white-ground lekythoi became associated exclusively with the
                    funerary cult (<bibl>Shapiro 1981a, nos.
                        42-45</bibl>. This painter is also recognized by his distinctive pattern of five
                    palmettes on the shoulder, the two outside ones facing the handle, and by use of
                    black paint for women's flesh, instead of the conventional white of standard
                    black-figure.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Cahn 1968, 18</bibl>. On the
                        introduction of Herakles: <bibl>Mingazzini
                            1925</bibl>. On the Edinburgh Painter: <bibl
                                >Kurtz 1975, 13-14</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:New Orleans 16.38" type="vase">New Orleans
                        16.38</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Black-Figure Amphora</title>
                <rs type="collection">Collection of the New Orleans Museum of Art,
                    Gift of Alvin P. Howard (16.38, formerly 2033)</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Attributed to the Bucci Painter (Name Vase)</rs>
                    <date>Ca. 530 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 34.9 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter: 23.3 cm.</measure> Side A: Herakles and
                    Hermes. Side B: Horseman and companions.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">On side A</hi>, Herakles and Hermes
                    stand on either side on a low rectangular altar. Herakles wears his lion skin
                    over a short <hi rend="ital">chiton.</hi> He customarily wears the
                    animal's head pulled over his own, as here, like a hood, and the forepaws tied
                    across his chest. A rear leg and the tail hang down low, below the hero's knees.
                    He carries his club and wears a sword in its scabbard, hanging from a baldric.
                    Hermes wears a striped <hi rend="ital">chlamys</hi> draped over his
                    left shoulder, winged shoes, and a cap, and carries the <hi rend="ital"
                        >kerykeion.</hi> Hero and god gesture to each other with
                    upraised left hand, probably a leave-taking, since Hermes moves off to the right
                    while looking back. Perhaps the two have just performed a sacrifice.</p>
                <p>The figures are framed by two slender Doric columns, reminiscent of
                    those seen on Panathenaic amphoras. On the left hand column perches a cock, as
                    on most Panathenaics, and on the right hand column an owl, which also occurs,
                    though rarely (compare the Panathaic amphora in Austin [<rs type="vase"
                        >Austin 1980.32</rs>], with owls on both columns). Nothing else
                    about the vase suggests a Panathenaic context, and another vase probably by the
                    same painter also has 'Panathenaic' columns; perhaps he simply borrowed them as
                    a decorative element.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">On side B</hi>, a horseman is mounted
                    between four standing male companions. The horse is seen frontally, a relatively
                    infrequent view, but with its head, as well as the rider's, in profile. The two
                    figures at the right are both bearded and carry spears; those at left are
                    beardless and unarmed, though one carries a staff. The scene probably shows a
                    young warrior setting out. It may be mythological - a Trojan hero, perhaps - but
                    need not be.</p>
                <p>This New Orleans amphora is the name vase of the Bucci painter, so
                    named by Dietrich von Bothmer for Donato Bucci of Civitavecchia, in whose
                    collection it once was. At least fifteen vases have been attributed to him, and
                    he is related in style both to the circle of the Antimenes Painter and to the
                    red-figure Andokides Painter.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>ABV, 315, 5</bibl>; <bibl
                        ><title>Annali dell'
                            Instituto di Corrispondenza Archaeologica</title> 1836, pl.F</bibl>;
                        <bibl>Gerhard 1843,pl. A, 19</bibl>; <bibl
                            >von Bothmer 1953a, ii 135 and pl. 47.
                            b-d</bibl>; <bibl>Schauenburg 1979, 69, fig.
                                18</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Dallas 1972.5" type="vase">Dallas
                        1972.5</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Black-Figure Eye-Cup</title>
                <rs type="collection">Collection of the Dallas Museum of Fine Arts,
                    Gift of Mr. and Mrs. Cecil H. Green (1972.5)</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Attributed to the Group of Walters 48.42</rs>
                    <date>520-510 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 12.3 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter (without handles): 31.7 cm.</measure>
                    Interior: Gorgoneion. Sides A and B: Herakles resting.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">On side A</hi>, Herakles reclines
                    against a rock, holding a footless bowl without handles, a phiale, in his left
                    hand. A soft cloak is casually draped over his left shoulder and arm. His
                    traditional lion skin hangs magically behind him from the vase rim. His weapons,
                    a sheathed sword with shoulder strap, bow, and arrow-filled quiver, also hang
                    above him. The hero has been distracted from his contemplative mood by something
                    behind him. While his powerful body remains in repose, his head snaps about in
                    the direction of the disturbance and his right hand instinctively grasps his
                    sword hilt. <hi rend="bold">On side B</hi> of the cup, the scene is
                    more tranquil. Herakles reclines once again on a rock, his weapons suspended
                    above him. Clad in an elegant mantle, or <hi rend="ital"
                        >himation,</hi> Herakles extends his high-handled wine cup, a kantharos, toward
                    an obliging satyr who obediently fills his vessel from a wine skin. The lack of
                    furniture and the rocky setting create an out-of-doors atmosphere to which the
                    satyr adds a fitting touch. Scenes of Herakles reclining, whether after one of
                    his labors or upon his arrival on Olympos, and attended by satyrs, appear on
                    Attic black-figure vases during the late sixth century B.C.</p>
                <p>Flanking each figured scene are large "female" eyes, almond-shaped
                    and lacking extended tear ducts, with eyebrows. These were thought to provide an
                    apotropaic service to the bearer. As John Boardman and others have noted, when
                    the cup was tipped to the lips the fertile imagination of one's drinking
                    companions saw a comical face with the cup handles serving as ears and the open,
                    hollow foot as a mouth (see illustration). In the handle zones are painted vines
                    and grape bunches which allude to the function of the cup as a container of
                    wine. The cup interior holds a gorgoneion encircled by a net pattern.</p>
                <p>The Dallas vase can be placed with a series of type A cups known as
                    the Group of Walters 48.42 from its name piece in Baltimore. The vase shape,
                    feminine eyes, grape vines in the handle zones, alternating outline and
                    silhouette rays from the foot, and the style of the gorgoneion are all
                    characteristics of vases in this group. The draftsmanship of the Dallas cup,
                    however, is far superior to most examples in the group and incorporates a number
                    of elements adopted from contemporary Attic red-figure painting, such as the
                    attempt at forshortening of Herakles' left foot on side A and the oblique angle
                    of his abdominal muscles, to create the impression of his twisting motion. The
                    undulating lines of his cloak on side A are a welcome change from the stiff
                    banded folds of earlier black-figure, while the sweeping curves of Herakles' <hi
                        rend="ital">himation</hi> on side B recall those of the
                    reclining Herakles' dress on the well known bilingual amphora in Munich by the
                    Andokides Painter (<bibl>ARV2, 4, 9</bibl>), himself
                    a contemporary red-figure artist.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p>Unpublished. On the Group of Walters 48.42: <bibl
                        >ABV, 205-207</bibl> and <bibl
                            >Para., 94-97</bibl>. On Herakles resting with satyrs: <bibl
                                >Brommer 1973, 191-192</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
                <byline>KARL KILINSKI II</byline>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Durham 1974.6" type="vase">Durham
                        1974.6</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Black-Figure Neck-Amphora</title>
                <rs type="collection">Collection of the Duke University Museum of
                    Art, Durham (1974.6)</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Leagros Group [D. K. Stanley]</rs>
                    <date>Late sixth century B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 29.8 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter: 19 cm.</measure> Side A: Peleus wrestling
                    Thetis. Side B: Theseus slaying the Minotaur.</p>
                <p>This typical late black-figure amphora, with its echinus mouth,
                    triple handles and torus foot, portrays two mythological scenes, both extremely
                    popular in Attic vase painting. While not specifically related, the scenes share
                    a similar compositional scheme: a pair of combatants in the center flanked by
                    two females.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Side A</hi> shows a half-draped young
                    man with long hair and sword at his waist embracing a woman. She wears a long
                    <hi rend="ital">chiton</hi> and is gesticulating wildly, as are
                    her two companions who flee from the scene. The one at the right holds a long
                    vine, and hence might be taken to be a maenad. However, such tendrils constitute
                    background filler on many late black-figure vases, and so are not relevant to an
                    interpretation of the scene. The manner in which the man embraces the woman, a
                    body hold, shows that they are wrestling, and so could be none other than Peleus
                    and his future bride, the sea nymph Thetis. The match is popular is Attic
                    vase-painting not only for its intrinsic dramatic appeal, but also because from
                    their union came the great hero Achilles.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Side B,</hi> distinguished from side A
                    by the up-and-down palmettes on the neck in place of the palmette-lotus chain,
                    shows a less friendly combat, a duel to the death. The youth in the short <hi
                        rend="ital">chiton</hi> is Theseus and his bull-headed opponent
                    is the Minotaur. The monster has fallen to his knee and attempts to defend
                    himself with the white rock clutched in his left hand. Theseus, however, has a
                    firm grasp on the Minotaur's left forearm and has plunged his sword into the
                    monster's chest. Red blood spurts from the wound. The pair are flanked by two
                    draped women; the one behind the hero encouraging him is perhaps Ariadne, the
                    other an anonymous Athenian maiden, part of the tribute to King Minos. In
                    addition to their compositional similarities, the two sides of this vase share
                    an amorous intent: young Greek heroes fighting for their future brides.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Christie's Sale Catalog 1974,
                        lot 112, p. 37 pl. 34</bibl>. On the wrestling match of Peleus and
                        Thetis: Brommer, <hi rend="ital">Vasenlisten</hi>, 3, 321-329.
                        On Theseus and the Minotaur: <bibl>Brommer 1973,
                            226-243</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
                <byline>Jenifer Neils</byline>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Diefenthal Collection (Shapiro No. 30)" type="vase"
                        >Diefenthal Collection (Shapiro No. 30)</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Red-Figure Bell-Krater</title>
                <rs type="collection">Collection of Mr. and Mrs. Edward L.
                    Diefenthal, Metairie, Louisiana</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Manner of the Dinos Painter [Bothmer]</rs>
                    <date>Ca. 425 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 29 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter: 31.4 cm.</measure> Side A: Theseus and the
                    Marathonian Bull. Side B: Three Draped Youths.</p>
                <p>Of the deeds of the hero Theseus, the most popular in Attic
                    vase-painting after the Minotauroctony is the capture of the wild bull ravaging
                    the plain of Marathon. It appears first on the early cups which depict the
                    youthful deeds of the hero in cyclical fashion, ca. 520-510 B.C., and endures
                    longer than any other new exploit, undergoing various transformations. The
                    earliest depictions, notably those on the late Archaic cycle cups, show Theseus
                    in the process of hobbling the bull. In the early Classical period the moment
                    changes, and we find the hero, club in hand, driving the restive beast to
                    Athens. By ca. 450 B.C., a third participant has been added to the scene, a
                    woman running before the bull and holding libation vessels. In no instance is
                    she labeled and there is some controversy over her identification.</p>
                <p>The Diefenthal krater clearly belongs to this third group, both in
                    date and iconography. Theseus, nude except for a <hi rend="ital"
                        >pilos</hi> or traveling cap, a cloak over his left arm, and a baldric
                    across his chest, is shown restraining the lunging bull by means of a club and a
                    rope attached to the animal's horns. Ahead of the bull runs a woman wearing a
                    belted <hi rend="ital">peplos,</hi> her hair tied up in a beaded
                    fillet. As she moves to the right, she looks back at Theseus, holding forth a
                    phiale in her out-stretched right hand. In her left she carries a trefoil-lipped
                    oinochoe viewed from the top. It has been argued by many that this woman is
                    either a local nymph running away in fright, or the female personification of
                    the locale, Marathon. However, just as Theseus is recognizable by his traveling
                    attire and club, so this woman should be identified by her attributes. We know
                    from mythological sources that the sorceress Medea attempted to poison the hero
                    upon his arrival in Athens before he was recognized by his father Aigeus. In the
                    extant accounts the timing of her attempt varies, either before or after the
                    bull episode. But, whenever it took place, it seems reasonable to regard this
                    woman with her offering vessels, who appears to be fleeing in fear of the
                    consequences of her foiled attempt on the hero's life, as Medea. This
                    identification is supported by other depictions of the scene which show a woman
                    in the same pose with the same attributes, but in oriental costume (i.e., a
                    sleeved outfit), an indisputable allusion to Medea's non-Greek origins.
                    Therefore, this vase-painting of Theseus depicts not one youthful agon, but two:
                    his conquest over the brute forces of nature exemplified by the bull, and his
                    victory over the forces of evil personified by Medea.</p>
                <p>The painting on the reverse is non-mythological and purely
                    conventional. Three youths, enveloped in their mantles, stand conversing. The
                    locale is the palaestra, as indicated by the objects hanging in the field: an
                    aryballos or ointment jar hanging between the first and second youths; a strigil
                    between the second and third.</p>
                <p>The bell krater is a popular shape in the Classical period, and this
                    scheme of decoration with a mythological scene on the front and secondary filler
                    on the back is very common. The vase is related to others done in the manner of
                    the Dinos Painter, an artist who specialized in larger pots, especially kraters.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p>Unpublished. On Theseus and the Marathonian bull: <bibl
                        >Brommer 1973, 252-257</bibl>; <bibl
                            >Shefton 1956, 159-163, pls. 60-61</bibl>. On
                        the Dinos Painter and his followers: <bibl>ARV2,
                            1151-1158</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
                <byline>Jenifer Neils</byline>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Mississippi 1977.3.97" type="vase"
                        >Mississippi 1977.3.97</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Red-Figure Neck Amphora</title>
                <rs type="collection">Collection of The University Museums,
                    University of Mississippi Phase I Cultural Center (1977.3.97)</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Attributed to the Group of Polygnotos</rs>
                    <date>440-430 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 42.2 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter: 24.1 cm.</measure> Side A: Theseus,
                    Peirithoos and Amazon. Side B: Three youths in mantles.</p>
                <p>The Amazon on side A holds her bow in the left hand and retreats to
                    the right, turning to strike with her battle-ax at Theseus, whose spear has
                    already penetrated her side. Only the distinctive ax marks her as an Amazon;
                    instead of the usual patterned tights she wears a Greek <hi rend="ital"
                        >peplos.</hi> Behind Theseus his friend Peirithoos prepares to
                    throw a stone. The figures are not named, but each is labeled "beautiful" —
                     <foreign xml:lang="greek">*K*A*L*O*S, *K*A*L*O*S,
                        *K*A*L*E</foreign>. This is one of six vases, all from the same circle of
                    painters and all with the same three-figure composition, differing slightly in
                    details of weaponry and costume, which probably go back to a common original. On
                    one of the other vases the central figure is labeled "Theseus," and the
                    identification should hold good for all six. Theseus is heroically nude except
                    for his helmet; the painter has given Peirithoos a shaggy pilos and an
                    animal-skin cloak, perhaps in reference to his rustic Thessalian homeland.</p>
                <p>The combats of Achilles and Herakles against Amazons appear in vase
                    painting after about 550 B.C., but Theseus' Amazonomachies begin in the last
                    quarter of the century, when the Athenians were attempting to raise their
                    national hero to equal status with Herakles. An epic poem, the <bibl n="Theseis"
                        >Theseis</bibl> was perhaps composed about 525,
                    and illustrations of episodes from the epic appear soon afterward. The theme of
                    Theseus' defeat of an Amazon army that invaded Attica to avenge his abduction of
                    their queen became especially popular after the Athenian repulse of the Persian
                    invasions of Attica in 490 and 480 B.C. Greek artists seldom represented
                    historical events directly, preferring to look to the legendary past for a
                    parallel event; thus for artists working in Athens, the Amazon invasion became a
                    visual metaphor for the Persian ones, and Amazonomachies were chosen as the
                    theme for decorating several public buildings. The common ancestor for the
                    examples of this three-figure composition could be either a wall painting or
                    another vase painting. Two large-scale Amazonomachies of Theseus were painted in
                    Athenian buildings in the generation after the Persian Wars, one by Mikon and
                    one by Polygnotos of Thasos (not the vase painter of the same name). No detailed
                    description of either painting survives, but 5th-century vase painters are
                    believed to have copied some of Polygnotos' innovations: many-figured
                    compositions, the placement of figures at different levels rather than on a
                    common ground line, and the use of trees and other landscape features. The
                    Theseus-Amazon pair from this vase also occur on at least four other vases, as
                    part of many-figured Amazonomachies with Polygnotan characteristics. Variations
                    on the Peirithoos figure also occur in these pictures, and it is likely that
                    this group was derived from a larger vase-painting that in turn was derived from
                    a wall painting.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Robinson 1956, 1-25, pl. 16,
                        71-2</bibl>; <bibl>ARV2, 1058</bibl>; <bibl
                            >von Bothmer 1957, 185-191; pl. 81, 4</bibl>;
                        For Theseus' significance in Attic art and politics: <bibl
                            >Ward 1970</bibl>; for relationships between wall painting
                        and vase painting: <bibl>Simon 1963,
                            43-62</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
                <byline>Lucy Turnbull</byline>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Richmond 79.100" type="vase">Richmond
                        79.100</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Red-Figure Ram's Head Rhyton</title>
                <rs type="collection">Collection of the Virginia Museum of Fine
                    Arts, Richmond, The Williams Fund, (79.100)</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Signed by Charinos as potter; attributed to the
                        Triptolemos Painter [Ohly-Dumm]</rs>
                    <date>480-470 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height (restored): 21.95 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Height of figured frieze: 6.35 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter of cup: 11.48 cm.</measure> Symposium of
                    Attic Kings.</p>
                <p>Five symposiasts recline around the cup attached to the top of this
                    magnificent molded ram's head. The four drinkers (1, 2, 4, 5) rest on striped
                    pillows, their legs to the left enveloped in their mantles, upper bodies frontal
                    and heads in profile. The middle man (3) is also semi-reclining, but has less
                    use for his pillow as he sits up to play his lyre; his left foot protrudes from
                    the drapery around his legs. Costume, attributes and age also vary among the
                    symposiasts. (1) is middle-aged, bearded, and his long black hair is rolled up
                    around a fillet. Under his mantle he wears a sleeveless <hi rend="ital"
                        >chiton,</hi> and he is distinguished from the other guests by
                    having two cups: a black-glazed kantharos resting in his left hand, and a kylix
                    with offset lip in his up-raised right hand. He holds one handle with his index
                    finger and is clearly about to toss the dregs in the popular Greek drinking game
                    known as <hi rend="ital">kottabos.</hi> Before aiming he looks back
                    at his nearest companion (2), an elderly white-haired gentleman, who is
                    similarly dressed and also holding a kantharos in his left hand. These two are
                    closely linked not only by position, but by gesture as well; the older man,
                    right hand raised, hails the younger. The third figure (3), a mature,
                    dark-haired man, lacks a <hi rend="ital">chiton</hi> under his
                    mantle, and, more significantly, a drinking cup. He appears to be tuning his <hi
                        rend="ital">barbiton</hi> or lyre, and remains a bit aloof from
                    the assembled company. The only youth on the vase (4) takes the fourth position;
                    beardless, he nonetheless has soft, downy sideburns on his cheeks, and wears his
                    hair in the ``severe" style, i.e., rolled up over a fillet with tight curls
                    encircling the face. He also lacks a <hi rend="ital">chiton,</hi>
                    but holds a black kantharos in his right hand. Like (1) he turns to look at the
                    figure directly behind, an older, white-haired man (5). Dressed like the other
                    elderly symposiast (2), this one is distinguished by his odd mug-like drinking
                    cup and by his gesture: he strokes his beard as he stares at the comely youth
                    before him. The festive setting is indicated not only by the presence of pillows
                    and drinking vessels, but by the musical instruments hanging on the wall behind,
                    two lyres and a <hi rend="ital">cithara</hi> decorated with
                    apotropaic eyes.</p>
                <p>While banqueting scenes and drinking parties are commonplace in Attic
                    vase-painting, especially in the Late Archaic period, this particular symposium
                    is unique among them. First, one is struck by the presence of kantharoi among
                    the drinking vessels. This cup with high-swung double handles is the specific
                    attribute of none other than the god of wine himself, Dionysos (see <bibl
                        >Shapiro 1981a, no. 12</bibl>). It is almost
                    never used by mortals, and only occasionally by heroes, usually Herakles at the
                    end of his labors when he assumes semi-divine status. But even more useful in
                    distinguishing these figures as heroes of legend are the inscriptions above
                    their heads. (1) is labeled KEKROPS, an early, legendary king of Athens, and (4)
                    is labeled THESEUS, the Attic hero <hi rend="ital">par
                        excellence,</hi> best known for his victory over the Cretan Minotaur, after
                    which, and following his father Aegeus' untimely death, he also became king of
                    Athens. These names suggest that we are dealing here with a royal gathering of
                    different generations. Who might the others be? Unfortunately, the inscribed
                    names are not completely preserved. (3) is partially labeled-UPOP-, but the
                    letters cannot be restored to correspond to the name of any Attic king or hero,
                    unless it proved to be a misspelling of the eponymous tribal hero Hippothoö
                    n. More likely, it is simply part of the name of a professional bard called
                    upon to entertain at this illustrious symposium. Finally, the remainder of a
                    name ending in the letters -ON is attached to the last figure (5). Given the
                    fact that he is depicted as two generations removed from Theseus, he might well
                    be identified as Pandion, the hero's grandfather and another king of Athens.
                    That leaves the second symposiast (2) yet to be identified. Possibilities among
                    Attic kings include: Erectheus, the father of Kekrops; Erichthonios, who is
                    often confused with the former as both were raised by Athena (see <bibl
                        >Shapiro 1981a, no. 4</bibl>); or Aigeus, the
                    father of Theseus. The age of the man argues for one of the first two; the space
                    limitations above his head perhaps for the third. However, if the same rules
                    regarding age relationships and juxtaposition of figures operate here as on the
                    other side, then the most likely identification of the two is father and son.
                    Also, Erectheus, as the prime Athenian ancestor, should not be missing from this
                    royal assembly.</p>
                <p>It remains to explain why these Attic kings should be depicted
                    together at all. It has been suggested, because of the date of the vase, that
                    they are celebrating the recent victory of the Greeks over the Persians.
                    However, given the prominence of the youngest hero on the cup, and the fact that
                    Greek vase-painting is more likely to deal with mythological than historical
                    events, it is perhaps more reasonable to assume that the Attic kings have
                    assembled to accept Theseus into their ranks, in which case the bard may well be
                    singing the hero's great feats either in Crete or on the Isthmian Road. While
                    there is no other depiction of Theseus directly comparable to that on the
                    Richmond rhyton, it is at precisely this time (ca. 480-460 B.C.) that interest
                    in the youth of the hero reaches its apogee among artists as well as poets. Not
                    only are there quantitatively more vase-paintings from this period, but the
                    range of subjects is considerably expanded; in particular, one finds a new
                    concern in establishing the hero's Athenian connections. All of this is not
                    surprising when one recalls that ca. 470 B.C. the Athenian naval commander Kimon
                    brought the bones of the hero back to the city and laid them in the Theseion, a
                    shrine dedicated to the hero. Such a magnificent piece of both modeling and
                    painting as this ram's head rhyton may well have served as a dedication in such
                    a shrine.</p>
                <p>The painting on the cup is attributed to the Triptolemos Painter, a
                    cup-painter of the Late Archaic period, who in his early phase owes much to
                    Douris. Later, and as this vase demonstrates, he is closer to the Brygos
                    Painter, who also painted symposia on the cups of rhyta. An anonymous,
                    presumably mortal symposium by the Triptolemos Painter appears on the exterior
                    of a cup in Berlin (<rs type="vase">Berlin F 2298</rs>: <bibl
                        >ARV2, 364, 52</bibl>), and provides a close
                    parallel for the Richmond vase.</p>
                <p>The rhyton is signed by the potter Charinos, previously known
                    exclusively as the maker of human-head kantharoi and oinochoai, on the majority
                    of which his name is incised on the handle. Here the potter's signature is
                    painted along the juncture of the two halves of the ram's face. Both the
                    modeling and painting of the ram's head are very expressive and naturalistic, in
                    contrast to the ornamental palmettes on the back. The foot is restored.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Neils 1980a, 221, 224-225, no.
                        37, ill. 151</bibl>. <bibl>Guy 1981,
                            2-15</bibl>. For Attic kings and eponymous heroes: <bibl
                                >Brommer 1957, 152-164, pls. 21-22</bibl>; <bibl
                                    >Kron 1976</bibl>; <bibl
                                        >Harrison 1979, 71-85</bibl>. On the Triptolemos Painter:
                        <bibl>ARV2, 360-367</bibl>. On Charinos:
                        <bibl>ARV2, 1531-1532</bibl>. On rhyta:
                        <bibl>Hoffmann 1962</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
                <byline>Jenifer Neils</byline>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Richmond 78.145" type="vase">Richmond
                        78.145</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic White-Ground Alabastron</title>
                <rs type="collection">Collection of the Virginia Museum of Fine
                    Arts, Richmond, The Williams Fund (78.145)</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Attributed to the Syriskos Painter [Cahn]</rs>
                    <date>470-460 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 15.2 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter: 5.4 cm.</measure> Side A: Amazon. Side B:
                    Palm tree and stool.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">On side A</hi>, an Amazon moves to the
                    right, but turns to look back. She is dressed in special oriental garb: a
                    cuirass over a short <hi rend="ital">chiton</hi> (only the hem of
                    which is shown, in dilute glaze) over black <hi rend="ital"
                        >anaxyrides</hi> (trousered and sleeved outfit) decorated with red dots and
                    stripes, with a long black <hi rend="ital">chlamys</hi> or cloak
                    worn shawl-like over both arms. The cuirass is decorated with dotted saltires on
                    the shoulder flaps and an abbreviated meander at the neck and waist. The female
                    warrior is armed with a <hi rend="ital">gorytos</hi> or quiver at
                    her waist, a battle axe in her right hand, and a <hi rend="ital"
                        >pelta</hi> or lunette shield in her left. <hi rend="bold">Side
                            B</hi> is considerably plainer, showing only a palm tree with twisted trunk,
                    and a simple stool or <hi rend="ital">diphros.</hi></p>
                <p>The white-ground alabastron, a perfume vase which imitates its
                    alabaster prototype both in shape and color, often bears exotic subject matter.
                    Those with Amazons, such as the Richmond example, are closely related
                    stylistically and iconographically to Beazley's "Group of the Negro Alabastra,"
                    where Negro warriors, similarly attired and posed, replace their female
                    counterparts. These foreign types have in common the fact that they both came to
                    the aid of Troy after the death of Hector, the Negroes under the Ethiopian
                    prince Memnon, and the Amazons following their queen, Penthesilea. Although
                    distinct racially and geographically, these foreigners share a common costume
                    and armament — both invented by the Attic vase-painters to connote a
                    "barbarian" or non-Greek. Likewise, the palm tree on the reverse indicates a
                    distant, alien land.</p>
                <p>This vase is attributed to the Syriskos Painter, an important
                    red-figure artist of the transitional period between late Archaic and early
                    Classic, whose workshop produced the majority of the Negro alabastra. Similar,
                    but slightly earlier "Amazon alabastra" by his hand are in the British Museum
                    (<rs type="vase">London B 673</rs>) and in the Badisches
                    Landesmuseum, Carlsruhe (<rs type="vase">Karlsruhe 69/34</rs>). The
                    Richmond Amazon, however, is distinguished from her sisters by her more
                    fashionable attire: black slippers, hoop earring, and curly hair tied up in
                    back. Both the classical features of this Amazon and the vase's place at the end
                    of the development of the type indicate a date in the second quarter of the
                    fifth century B.C.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Herbert A. Cahn, <title
                        >Classical Antiquity,</title> sale cat. (Zü
                        rich: André Emmerich Gallery Inc., 1976) no. 18</bibl>; <bibl
                            >Neils 1980b, 20, no. 62, pl. 7, 5-7</bibl>.
                        For Amazons on white-ground alabastra: <bibl
                            >Neils 1980b, 18-20, nos. 48-62</bibl>; <bibl
                                >von Bothmer 1957, 152, nos. 67-77</bibl>. On the Syriskos
                        Painter and his workshop: <bibl>ARV2,
                            256-270</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
                <byline>Jenifer Neils</byline>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Fayetteville 57-24-2" type="vase"
                        >Fayetteville 57-24-2</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Red-Figure Pelike</title>
                <rs type="collection">Collection of the University of Arkansas
                    Museum, Fayetteville (57-24-2)</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Attributed to the Biscoe Painter</rs>
                    <date>Ca. 450-440 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 24.5 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter: 19 cm.</measure> Side A: Two Amazons
                    mounted on horseback. Side B: Three youths.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">On side A</hi>, two armed warriors ride
                    to the right. Each wears a leather cuirass over a short linen <hi rend="ital"
                        >chiton</hi> and an Attic helmet with a crest which disappears
                    into the upper border. They wear shoes, but no greaves (shinguards). Each
                    carries two spears. The warriors might easily be taken for young, beardless
                    Athenian hoplites, but a comparison with similar scenes in Attic red-figure of
                    this period, some of which label the figures, shows that they are in fact
                    Amazons. In earlier vase-painting, Amazons are usually easily distinguished from
                    the Greek male hoplites with whom they fight, either by added white paint for
                    female flesh (in black-figure) or by their exotic dress and armor which recall
                    Thracians or Scythians. But by the mid-fifth century, their armor is often
                    indistinguishable from that of Greek hoplites, and they are increasingly shown
                    in quiet scenes, like this one, rather than in combat.</p>
                <p>The scene on this pelike may be one of many in this period that
                    reflect the influence of two famous but now lost Athenian wall paintings of the
                    Battle of Greeks and Amazons. One was in the Stoa Poikile, on the north side of
                    the Agora, the other in the Theseion, whose location is not known but may have
                    been on the lower north slope of the Acropolis. Both paintings were done about
                    460, the former by the great painter Mikon, the latter perhaps by the same
                    artist. One source specifically mentions that Mikon painted Amazons on horseback
                    (<bibl n="Aristoph. Lys. 678">Aristoph. Lys.
                        678-79</bibl>).</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Side B</hi> shows three beardless youths
                    engaged in conversation. All wear similar mantles, and the one at left carries a
                    staff. The draughtsmanship here is startlingly careless in comparison with the
                    fine style of Side A.</p>
                <p>The painter, who is named for a pelike now in Los Angeles (<bibl
                    >ARV2, 1063, top, 2</bibl>), was placed by
                    Beazley "on the outskirts of the Polygnotan Group," that is, somewhat distantly
                    related to one of the leading painters of larger pots in the mid-fifth century,
                    Polygnotos. Of the Amazons on this vase, however, Beazley wrote that the scene
                    is a very close imitation of the style of Polygnotos himself. Polygnotos in turn
                    came out of the school of the Niobid Painter, and both artists were profoundly
                    influenced by innovations in monumental painting of the Early Classical period.
                    Here is, then, one more reason to suspect that these Amazons find their ultimate
                    inspiration in a lost masterpiece of wall painting.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>ARV2, 1063, top, 1</bibl>;
                        <bibl>von Bothmer 1957, 199, no. 140 and pl.
                            83, 4</bibl>; <bibl>Maule 1971, 89-91 and
                                pl. 24, fig. 13-14</bibl>. On Amazons, and Amazonomachies in monumental
                        painting: <bibl>von Bothmer 1957, especially
                            163; 200</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Raleigh 74.1.6" type="vase">Raleigh
                        74.1.6</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Black-Figure Neck Amphora</title>
                <rs type="collection">Collection of the North Carolina Museum of
                    Art, Raleigh, (74.1.6)</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Leagros Group</rs>
                    <date>Ca. 500 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 34.3 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter: 21.9 cm.</measure> Side A: Ajax with the
                    body of Achilles. Side B: Fight.</p>
                <p>When Achilles was slain at Troy by Paris' arrow, it was Ajax who
                    rescued the body and carried it from the battlefield. Ironically, the rescued
                    armor would later prove to be the brave Ajax' undoing, when it was awarded to
                    Odysseus instead of to him. Ajax carrying Achilles' corpse first appears in
                    Attica on the François Vase of about 570, where the figures are labelled.
                    In several dozen later instances, such as the North Carolina example, the motif
                    of a warrior carrying the body of a dead comrade is usually assumed to refer to
                    the same heroic pair, even without inscriptions to assure their identity.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">On side A</hi>, Ajax walks slowly but in
                    long strides under his great burden, moving toward the left, as is usual in such
                    scenes. He wears a short belted <hi rend="ital">chiton,</hi>
                    greaves, scabbard suspended at the waist, and a low crested Corinthian helmet.
                    He carries two spears in his right hand and his shield on his left arm; the
                    device is a frontal lion or panther head. Achilles wears the same outfit, except
                    that his helmet has a tall crest and his shield device is a frontal satyr's
                    head. At the left a woman runs off, looking back, one hand raised in fright. She
                    may be identified as Thetis, Achilles' mother. She wears a sleeveless <hi
                        rend="ital">chiton</hi> and <hi rend="ital"
                            >himation,</hi> and a fillet in her hair.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">On side B</hi>, two warriors engage in
                    combat, as a third moves in from the right to support his falling comrade. All
                    three are fully armed in greaves, short pleated <hi rend="ital"
                        >chiton,</hi> corselet, and high crested Corinthian helmet. The falling
                    central warrior has as his shield device a tripod; his companion, three balls.
                    Their opponent's shield is seen from the inside, his left arm through the <hi
                        rend="ital">porpax,</hi> or strap. This is a type of shield
                    known as Boeotian, oval with two half-moon shaped cutouts. The other two are the
                    more standard round hoplite shields. All fight with spears and have sheathed
                    swords hanging from baldrics across their chests. One would like to connect this
                    scene with the Trojan subject on the other side, but in the absence of
                    inscriptions or other specific information the figures cannot be identified.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl><title
                        >Bulletin, North Carolina Museum of Art</title> 13, 1-2 (1976) no.
                        103 p. 39 (ill.)</bibl>; <hi rend="ital">ibid.</hi> 13, 3
                        (1976) 32-33 (ill.); <bibl><title
                            >Gazette des Beaux-Arts,</title> Paris (March, 1976)
                            no. 1286; p. 32, ill. 32</bibl>. On Ajax with the body of Achilles:
                        <bibl>Woodford &amp; Loudon 1980,
                            25-40</bibl>. (This vase should be added to Appendix I, p. 36, Group C).</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Mississippi 1977.3.99" type="vase"
                        >Mississippi 1977.3.99</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Red-Figure Pelike</title>
                <rs type="collection">Collection of The University Museums,
                    University of Mississippi Phase I Cultural Center (1977.3.99)</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Attributed to the Calliope Painter</rs>
                    <date>430-420 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 19.1 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter: 16.1 cm.</measure> Side A: Hector (?)
                    arming. Side B: Priam (?).</p>
                <p>A young man stands pulling off his cloak with his right hand while
                    with the left he takes the spear and helmet the woman holds for him. She carries
                    his shield, which bears a lion as its device, and gazes at him over its rim. On
                    the reverse, an older man stands holding a scepter and looking intently before
                    him. He must belong with the two figures on side A, in the traditional grouping
                    of a departing warrior between his parents. This was one of the longest-lived
                    themes in Greek vase-painting, as well as in Greek life. War was endemic in the
                    Greek world, with cities constantly quarreling among themselves, and every male
                    citizen could expect to be in battle many times in the course of his life. This
                    pelike was painted in the early years of the Peloponnesian War, when scenes like
                    this one were being enacted frequently in Athenian homes. No names are given
                    here; the young man looks like a contemporary Athenian whose wife or mother is
                    helping him with his weapons and shield, all of which are conventional
                    5th-century heavy infantry equipment. If this were meant to be a contemporary
                    scene, however, we would expect to see more armor; a breast-plate certainly, if
                    not also a pair of greaves. A young man who goes out to battle wearing only a
                    helmet and a sword belt is more likely to be a legendary hero, at least in
                    vase-painting. The bearded man on side B gives another clue to the warrior's
                    identity: from his wreath and scepter, he must be a king, and the hero leaving
                    home is his son. In all probability he is Priam, and the young man Hector, while
                    the woman may be his mother or his wife Andromache.</p>
                <p>The painter has set his figures well apart, and has made the helmet
                    the focal point of the picture by setting it at the crossing point of the
                    vertical line of the spear and the diagonal lines of the two arms. These
                    diagonals are extended and made more emphatic by the line of the cloak which
                    Hector pulls off with his right hand and by the body of the lion on the shield.
                    The helmet is held almost at eye level; are the figures looking at it or at each
                    other? Perhaps we have here an echo of the touching scene in the Iliad (<bibl
                        n="Hom. Il. 6.369-502">Hom. Il.
                        6.369-502</bibl>) of Hector's farewell to his wife Andromache, who begs him not
                    to go back to the battle, and to their baby son, who takes fright and begins to
                    cry at the sight of his father's helmet, with its crest "nodding terribly, as he
                    thought." The mood here is quiet and restrained, as in much of the art of the
                    period, but there is something of poignancy in the two faces regarding each
                    other over the crest of the helmet.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>ARV2, 1262, 60</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
                <byline>Lucy Turnbull</byline>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Richmond 57.9" type="vase">Richmond
                        57.9</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Black-Figure Neck Amphora</title>
                <rs type="collection">Collection of the Virginia Museum of Fine
                    Arts, Richmond, The Williams Fund (57.9)</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Attributed to the Antimenes Painter</rs>
                    <date>Ca. 520-510 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 34.4 cm.</measure> Side A: Judgment of Paris.
                    Side B: Recovery of Helen.</p>
                <p>Both scenes are part of the Trojan cycle, and there is a narrative
                    link between the two in the person of Helen. It was Paris' theft of Helen, the
                    wife of King Menelaos of Sparta, that precipitated the Trojan War, and it was
                    Aphrodite who promised Helen to Paris at the Judgment. Ten years later, the War
                    finally having ended with the Greek sack of Troy, Menelaos recovers his wayward
                    queen, to take her home to Sparta.</p>
                <p>The Judgment of Paris (<hi rend="bold">side A</hi>) was
                    a favorite subject in Greek art from the seventh century down to the end of the
                    Classical period. In later black-figure, as on this vase, Paris himself is often
                    not shown, and the scene must be understood as the three goddesses making their
                    way to Mount Ida, conducted there by Hermes. Of the three, Athena is usually
                    most easily recognized, by her helmet, and is most often in the middle. In
                    black-figure it is sometimes difficult to distinguish Hera and Aphrodite. The
                    standard order is for Hera to lead the group, with Aphrodite bringing up the
                    rear; that is probably the case here, since the staff carried by the front
                    figure could be interpreted as Hera's sceptre. Otherwise the two goddesses look
                    remarkably similar and even make the same gesture, sniffing a flower. Hermes
                    wears traditional travelling attire: winged boot, short <hi rend="ital"
                        >chiton</hi> and <hi rend="ital">chlamys,</hi> and
                    he holds the <hi rend="ital">kerykeion.</hi></p>
                <p>The Recovery of Helen (<hi rend="bold">side B</hi>) also
                    has a long pedigree in Greek art, going back to the seventh century, and this
                    Richmond vase shows the most canonical version of the myth as represented in
                    Attic black-figure. Menelaos rather brusquely grasps his wife's hand,
                    threatening her with his sword and glaring back at her as he starts to walk off
                    to the right. Helen hesitates, standing stiffly, her mantle pulled down over her
                    head like a veil. As if Menelaos' drawn sword were not persuasive enough, a
                    second Greek sword behind Helen encourages her to move along. This may belong to
                    Odysseus, who accompanied Menelaos during the last night at Troy. Both warriors
                    are dressed alike in greaves, short pleated <hi rend="ital"
                        >chiton,</hi> corselet, and Corinthian helmet, Menelaos' with a tall crest,
                    Odysseus' with a low one. Two draped figures, apparently male, overlapping the
                    handle palmettes, symmetrically frame the scene, but seem to be meant only as
                    filler, rather than as integral parts of the narrative.</p>
                <p>The vase is attributed to the Antimenes Painter, one of the major
                    black-figure artists of the first generation after the invention of red-figure,
                    who is fond of Trojan subjects and painted several other versions of each of
                    these scenes.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>ABV, 271, 78 and 691, 78
                        bis</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 118,78</bibl>; <bibl
                            >Gerhard 1840-1858, pl. 72</bibl>; <bibl
                                ><title>Ancient Art in the
                                    Virginia Museum</title> (Richmond 1973) 96-97</bibl>. On the
                        Judgment of Paris: <bibl>Clairmont 1951</bibl>;
                        <bibl>Raab 1972</bibl>. On the Recovery of
                        Helen: <bibl>Ghali-Kahil 1955</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Richmond 62.1" type="vase">Richmond
                        62.1</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Red-Figure Hydria</title>
                    <rs type="collection">Collection of the Virginia Museum of Fine
                        Arts, Richmond, The Williams Fund (62.1.1)</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Attributed to the Nausicaa Painter</rs>
                    <date>Ca. 450 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 45.5 cm.</measure> Perseus beheading Medusa</p>
                <p>The myth of Perseus beheading the Gorgon Medusa was especially
                    popular in Proto-Attic and early Attic black-figure, a century and more before
                    the period of this vase. After that the scene recurs only sporadically, and this
                    version is one of the latest known. In Archaic art, the moment in the story most
                    often depicted is the chase after the beheading, when Perseus flees with the
                    severed head, pursued by Medusa's sisters. In only a few red-figure scenes of
                    the mid-fifth century, including this one, do we see the hero sneaking up on his
                    victim as she sleeps.</p>
                <p>Medusa is very much the center of attention in the composition, the
                    focus of all eyes. She sleeps peacefully against the trunk of a tree, her left
                    wing apparently hidden by the rising ground. The frontal face is a relatively
                    rare occurrance in Attic vase-painting and is generally restricted to a few
                    specific purposes, including the depiction of sleeping figures. Medusa wears a
                    short pleated <hi rend="ital">chiton</hi> with short sleeves. In
                    the course of the fifth century she gradually loses the monstrous features that
                    had characterized her since her first appearances in Greek art in the seventh
                    century. Eventually she will emerge as a beautiful young woman, as on a famous
                    pelike in New York (<bibl>ARV2, 1032,55</bibl>). On
                    the Richmond vase the transformation is not complete, as indicated by the broad
                    nose and huge gaping mouth, with protruding tongue.</p>
                <p>Perseus approaches stealthily from the right, holding in his left
                    hand the <hi rend="ital">kibisis,</hi> or leather pouch in which he
                    will carry the head, and in his right a sickle (<hi rend="ital"
                        >harpe</hi>). Behind him stands his guide, Hermes, identified by his
                    traveller's hat (<hi rend="ital">petasos</hi>) and <hi rend="ital"
                        >kerykeion.</hi> Perseus seems unaware of the power of Medusa's
                    gaze to turn men to stone, for he does not, as on most vases, avert his eyes.</p>
                <p>Athena stands opposite Perseus and reaches out her right hand, as if
                    cautioning the hero against making noise and awakening the Gorgon. She wears a
                    large Corinthian helmet and carries a spear. Her aegis, which will later carry
                    the Gorgon's head as an apotropaic device, is not seen. Behind Athena sits a
                    stately bearded figure, wearing a fillet in his hair and holding a curved stick.
                    In his full publication of the vase, K. Schauenburg suggested that he is Atlas,
                    who in some versions of the myth was a victim of the Gorgon's gaze and thus gave
                    his name to a mountain. Here he would be a kind of local divinity or
                    personification, of a type that occurs in later red-figure - usually seated and
                    off to one side - alluding to the mountain setting.</p>
                <p>The Nausicaa Painter is one of Beazley's "Later Mannerists." His real
                    name is given by a signature on an amphora in London (<bibl
                        >ARV2, 1107,7</bibl>), Polygnotos, but since the name is
                    shared by two other vase-painters, as well as the famous wall painter, the
                    nickname taken from his painting of Odysseus and Nausicaa (<bibl
                        >ARV2, 1107,2</bibl>) has been retained.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>ARV2, 1683, 48 bis</bibl>;
                        <bibl>Para., 452</bibl>; <bibl
                            >C. Alexander, in <title>Art News</title>
                            61 (1962) 29</bibl>; <hi rend="ital">ibid.,</hi> in <bibl
                                ><title>Arts in
                                    Virginia</title> 2 (1962) 9</bibl>; <bibl>K.
                                        Schauenburg, ``Zu einer Hydria des Nausikaa-Malers in Richmond," <title
                                            >Kunst in Hessen und am Mittelrhein</title> 3 (1963)
                                        3-15</bibl>; <bibl><title
                                            >Ancient Art in the Virginia Museum</title> (Richmond 1973)
                                            95</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Durham 1972.1" type="vase">Durham
                        1972.1</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Red-Figure Column-Krater</title>
                <rs type="collection">Collection of the Duke University Museum of
                    Art, Durham (1972.1)</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Attributed to a Follower of the Pan Painter
                        [Cahn]</rs>
                    <date>Ca. 470 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 30 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter: 28 cm.</measure> Side A: Youth making a
                    sacrifice. Side B: Youth with two spits.</p>
                <p>The front of this vase (<hi rend="bold">side A</hi>),
                    recognizable not only by the more elaborate picture but by the lotus bud chain
                    on the neck, shows a youth in a sanctuary in the process of making a sacrifice.
                    All the elements of a Greek outdoor religious shrine are here: a plain
                    rectangular altar festooned with a garland; a <hi rend="ital"
                        >pinax</hi> or votive plaque hanging above; and a three-legged table with claw
                    feet bearing sacrificial food (cakes or meat). In addition, the youth has a <hi
                        rend="ital">liknon</hi> or openwork basket cradled in his left
                    arm; with his right hand, he seems to be reaching for something to place on the
                    altar toward which he looks. The reverse (<hi rend="bold">side
                        B</hi>) has a single figure, another youth, standing in profile to the right so
                    that he is facing the altar and the youth on the other side. He holds two long
                    spits, used in roasting meat. The one held horizontally in his right hand
                    already has meat adhering to the end; the one held upright in his left appears
                    to be empty.</p>
                <p>Not only the mannerist style but the subject matter and many of the
                    details of the Duke krater owe much to paintings by the Pan Painter. His most
                    famous scene of sacrifice is the Busiris pelike in Athens (<bibl
                        >ARV2, 554, 82</bibl>) where Herakles has turned the tables on
                    his Egyptian adversaries. One of the fleeing priests on the reverse carries a
                    table and bundle of spits. Even more pertinent, however, is the Pan Painter's
                    column-krater in Naples (<bibl>ARV2, 551, 15</bibl>)
                    which depicts a shrine of Hermes. Here one youth is already roasting meat over a
                    flaming altar, while another, half-draped like the youths on the Duke krater,
                    looks on holding a <hi rend="ital">liknon.</hi> Although the vase
                    in Durham is much simpler in composition, it nonetheless conveys the essential
                    aspects of a religious scene.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl><title>Attische
                        Rotfigurige Vasen,</title> Sonderliste N</bibl>; <bibl
                            >Münzen, May 1971, no. 8, pp. 10ff</bibl>. On meat
                        roasting in religious scenes: <bibl>Rizza
                            1959-1960, 321-345</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
                <byline>Jenifer Neils</byline>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Austin 1980.32" type="vase">Austin
                        1980.32</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Black-Figure Neck Amphora of
                    Panathenaic Shape</title>
                    <rs type="collection">Collection of the Archer M. Huntington Art
                        Gallery, the University of Texas, Austin, James R. Dougherty, Jr. Foundation
                        and Archer M. Huntington Museum Fund Purchase (1980.32)</rs>
                    <date>Ca. 540 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 27.5 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter: 17.2 cm.</measure> Side A: Athena. Side B:
                    Flute player between two judges.</p>
                <p>The vase is of the same shape as those given to victors in the
                    Panathenaic Games, and the pose of Athena on <hi rend="bold">side
                        A</hi> is similar to that on prize amphoras. But this is not a prize vase, for
                    it is too small and lacks the inscription <foreign xml:lang="greek"
                        >*T*O*N *A*Q*E*N*E*Q*E*N *A*Q*L*O*N</foreign> ("From the
                    Games at Athens") running alongside one of the columns that flank Athena.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">On side A</hi>, Athena stands in the
                    pose of the <hi rend="ital">promachos</hi> ("who fights in the
                    forefront"), fully armed; she held a spear in her upraised left hand. She wears
                    an Attic helmet, with a high crest projecting from a simple cap, a necklet, long
                    belted peplos, and her aegis slung crosswise so that three snake heads are
                    visible behind. Her shield, with a wide rim painted in red, has as a device
                    three large white balls. She stands between two slender Doric columns, on top of
                    which perch owls, in place of the cocks which regularly stand atop the columns
                    on Panathenaic prize amphoras. The owl is Athena's (hence Athens') bird.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">On side B</hi>, a young flutist <hi
                    rend="ital">(auletes)</hi> stands on a three-stepped podium <hi
                        rend="ital">(bema)</hi> and plays, while two seated figures
                    listen. The <hi rend="ital">auletes</hi> wears a loose fitting
                    chiton, a fillet around his head, and a <hi rend="ital"
                        >phorbeia,</hi> or leather mouthpiece which helps hold the flutes in place. One
                    of the listeners is beardless, the other bearded; both sit on folding stools and
                    wear a striped <hi rend="ital">himation</hi> over a <hi rend="ital"
                        >chiton.</hi></p>
                <p>Because of the Panathenaic context - the vase's shape and the Athena
                    of Side A - it seems likely that the seated listeners are judges and that the
                    scene refers to musical competitions which took place at the Greater Panathenaea
                    in Athens every four years. Literary and epigraphical sources do not confirm the
                    existence of such musical contests before the fourth century, but this vase and
                    several others suggest that in the sixth and early fifth centuries there may
                    have been as many as four musical events: flute-playing and lyre-playing, either
                    alone or accompanying a singer (a lyre player could accompany himself). These
                    musical competitions, along with contests for rhapsodes, who recited passages
                    from Homer, may have all been introduced with the major reorganization of the
                    Panathenaea in 566 B.C. The earliest of the vases, about 560, is an amphora of
                    Panathenaic shape in London (<rs type="vase">London B 141</rs>), on
                    which a flute-player and a bearded man stand facing each other on a low
                    platform, between a young athlete and a seated judge. Perhaps this scene
                    represents the contest for <hi rend="ital">aulodia,</hi> singing to
                    the flute, while ours shows <hi rend="ital">auletria,</hi> or
                    unaccompanied flute-playing.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>CVA, Castle Ashby (Great
                        Britain 15) 8-9 and pl. 15, 5-6</bibl>; <bibl
                            >Christie's Sale Catalog 1980, lot. 89, pp. 142-143,
                            ill</bibl>; <bibl>E. Gerhard, in <title
                                >Archaeologische Zeitung</title> 1846, 340, no.
                                2</bibl>; <bibl>A. Furtwängler, <title
                                    >ibid.</title> 1881, 303</bibl>; <bibl
                                        >H. Philippart, in <title
                                            >L'Antiquité Classique</title> 4 (1935) 212</bibl>. On
                        musical contests at the Panathenaia: <bibl>J. A.
                            Davison, in <title>Journal of Hellenic Studies</title>
                            78 (1958) 36-42</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Tulane Collection (Shapiro No. 41)" type="vase"
                        >Tulane Collection (Shapiro No. 41)</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Black-Figure Lekythos</title>
                    <rs type="collection">Collection of Tulane University, Gift of
                        Alvin P. Howard, New Orleans</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Attributed to the Gela Painter [Bothmer]</rs>
                    <date>Ca. 500 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 29.9 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter: 12.8 cm.</measure> Bull being led to
                    sacrifice.</p>
                <p>Four men accompany a sacrificial bull, forming a small procession.
                    Alongside the animal stands a man holding a vine in his left hand. He wears a
                    fillet, and the border of his <hi rend="ital">himation</hi> is
                    decorated with white balls. Perhaps these trappings indicate that he is a
                    priest. Just behind the bull walks a flute-player; next comes a man holding
                    vines who wears a wreath of incised leaves; and finally another man holding
                    vines. All four are bearded and wear <hi rend="ital">himatia</hi>
                    draped over the left shoulder.</p>
                <p>The bull was always a favorite sacrificial victim, from Homeric times
                    to the historic period of the sixth and fifth centuries. Like other forms of
                    religious ritual, a sacrifice was often performed to musical accompaniment. Such
                    processions leading sacrificial animals were, for example, a conspicuous part of
                    the Panathenaic festival in Athens, to judge from the depiction of such a
                    procession on the Parthenon frieze.</p>
                <p>The Gela Painter, to whom this vase is attributed, was a prolific
                    artist who began his career at the end of the sixth century and decorated nearly
                    two hundred lekythoi which survive. He is known for his originality of subject
                    matter, and this lively version of a subject not often represented in
                    vase-painting is a good example of his work.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p>Unpublished. The Gela Painter: <bibl
                        >Haspels 1936, 78-86; 205-215</bibl>; <bibl
                            >ABV, 473-75</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Private Collection (Shapiro No. 42)" type="vase"
                        >Private Collection (Shapiro No. 42)</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic White-Ground Lekythos</title>
                    <rs type="collection">Private Collection, New Orleans</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Attributed to the Thanatos Painter [Bothmer]</rs>
                    <date>Ca. 460-450 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 26.1 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter: 8.5 cm.</measure> Two women mourning at a
                    tomb.</p>
                <p>The scene shows a visit to the tomb of a loved one, the most popular
                    subject on white-ground funerary lekythoi. In the center, the stele, crowned by
                    a low pediment, stands on a broad two-stepped platform. Two sashes are tied
                    around the stele, one pulled tight near the top, the other hanging loosely near
                    the bottom. The women on either side of the stele are, unlike some in such
                    scenes, openly mourning. The figure at left raises both hands slightly over her
                    head. She wears a long <hi rend="ital">chiton</hi> and a
                    loose-fitting red <hi rend="ital">himation.</hi> The other woman,
                    whose hair is very closely cropped (probably in mourning), kneels beside the
                    tomb and with both hands takes hold of the upper step. She looks down at the
                    stone with intent but calm gaze. She too wears a <hi rend="ital"
                        >chiton</hi> and red <hi rend="ital">himation,</hi> the latter
                    having fallen off her shoulder to her waist.</p>
                <p>White-ground lekythoi were first produced in the late sixth century
                    <bibl>Shapiro 1981a, no. 26</bibl>, and for
                    several generations they were decorated with a wide variety of subjects and were
                    presumably used, in the home and elsewhere, like black-or red-figure lekythoi,
                    as oil containers. In the Early Classical period, white lekythoi began to assume
                    a specialized function as offerings for the dead, placed on or in the tomb. The
                    delicate nature of the white paint and the fugitive colors that were often
                    applied made these vases somewhat impractical for everyday use and perhaps
                    helped suggest this ritual purpose.</p>
                <p>This vase, like the two which follow, is the work of the Thanatos
                    Painter, one of the small number of fine painters who decorated exclusively
                    white lekythoi in the middle years of the fifth century. He was strongly
                    influenced by the Achilles Painter, the greatest vase-painter of the day, but,
                    unlike him, did not, as far as we know, also work in red-figure. He is also one
                    of the first painters whose white lekythoi are, to judge from the iconography,
                    entirely funerary. Nearly fifty white lekythoi are attributed to the Thanatos
                    Painter, who is named for a rare representation of Thanatos and Hypnos (Death
                    and Sleep) on a lekythos in London (<bibl>ARV2,
                        1228, 12</bibl>).</p>
                <p>The shoulders of Classical white lekythoi are regularly decorated
                    with a pattern of three palmettes linked by spiralling tendrils. Within this
                    scheme many subtle variations can be detected from painter to painter; the
                    Thanatos Painter generally favors a simple pattern which is uncluttered by many
                    extra tendrils and lotus buds. On most of his lekythoi, the figures are outlined
                    in dilute glaze of lustrous golden brown or yellow, but in a few of his later
                    works, including these three, he adopts the new technique of outline in matte
                    paint, red or black, or a mixture of the two. The figures on this vase are more
                    slender than most by the Thanatos painter, and Beazley was uncertain whether
                    this might be the work of a pupil.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p>Unpublished. <bibl>ARV2,
                        1230,46</bibl>. On the Thanatos Painter: <bibl
                            >Kurtz 1975, 38-41</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Private Collection (Shapiro No. 43)" type="vase"
                        >Private Collection (Shapiro No. 43)</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic White-Ground Lekythos</title>
                    <rs type="collection">Private Collection, New Orleans</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Attributed to the Thanatos Painter [Bothmer]</rs>
                    <date>Ca. 460-450 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 25.8 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter: 8.5 cm.</measure> Woman and little girl at
                    a tomb.</p>
                <p>In the center, the plain shaft of the stele stands on a tall, wide
                    base. Sashes hang loosely near the top. A young girl approaches the tomb from
                    the left, holding out a doll in both hands. She has curly hair and wears a very
                    thin, transparent <hi rend="ital">chiton.</hi> Her features are
                    those of an adult, but her stature - more than a head shorter than the woman
                    opposite - indicates that she is meant to be a child. As on the preceding vase,
                    the scene is a visit to the tomb of a family member, and the doll is a gift for
                    the deceased, a token of remembrance. Curiously, the doll bears a strong
                    resemblance to the girl who carries it. Perhaps the tomb is a child's, as is
                    certainly the case on the lekythos which follows.</p>
                <p>The woman at the right stands frontally, her head in profile looking
                    toward the tomb. With her right hand she gestures toward the stele, or past it
                    to the girl, and in her left she holds a basket which probably contains sashes,
                    like the chest on <bibl>Shapiro 1981a, no.
                        44</bibl>. Behind the girl is a conical object with zig-zag decoration and two
                    long strings, suspended from the upper border of the picture field. It is a <hi
                        rend="ital">sakkos,</hi> or snood, a kind of hairnet often worm
                    by women or seen hanging on the wall in domestic scenes.</p>
                <p>This lekythos and two others from the same collection are all
                    attributed to the Thanatos Painter (see <bibl
                        >Shapiro 1981a, no. 43</bibl>).</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p>Unpublished. <bibl>ARV2, 1230,
                        45</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Private Collection (Shapiro No. 44)" type="vase"
                        >Private Collection (Shapiro No. 44)</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic White-Ground Lekythos</title>
                    <rs type="collection">Private Collection, New Orleans</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Attributed to the Thanatos Painter [Bothmer]</rs>
                    <date>Ca. 460-450 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 25.7 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter: 8.3 cm.</measure> Woman and maid at a
                    child's tomb.</p>
                <p>The tomb consists of a short, nearly square stele on top of a high
                    four-stepped podium. Several red sashes are tied around the stele and others
                    trail down the steps. Atop the stele sits a pudgy little boy, scarcely more than
                    a baby, with tousled curly hair. This has been called a statue of the dead
                    child, though it is extremely lifelike. It could represent an image of the
                    deceased as in life, just as on later white lekythoi a dead warrior is sometimes
                    seen sitting on the steps of his own tomb <bibl
                        >Shapiro 1981a, no. 45</bibl>.</p>
                <p>A servant girl, with close-cropped hair, snub nose, full lips, and
                    prominent chin, approaches from the right, holding out an alabastron in her left
                    hand. Clearly she is meant to be a Negro. On her head she carries a long, low
                    basket of sashes like those already decorating the tomb. At the left stands a
                    woman closely wrapped in a dark red cloak, perhaps the mother of the dead child.
                    Behind her hangs a <hi rend="ital">sakkos</hi> (see <bibl
                        >Shapiro 1981a, no. 43</bibl>).</p>
                <p>The vase is by the Thanatos Painter, to whom the previous two
                    lekythoi from the same collection are also attributed <bibl
                        >Shapiro 1981a, nos.42, 43</bibl>.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p>Unpublished. <bibl>ARV2,
                        1230,44</bibl>; for the Negro maid, compare a lekythos by the Bosanquet
                        Painter, <rs type="vase">Berlin inv. 3291</rs>; <bibl
                            >ARV2, 1227,9</bibl>; <bibl
                                >Snowden 1970, fig. 25</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Davis Collection (Shapiro No. 45)" type="vase"
                        >Davis Collection (Shapiro No. 45)</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic White-Ground Lekythos</title>
                    <rs type="collection">Collection of Mr. and Mrs. Arthur Q. Davis,
                        New Orleans</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Unattributed</rs>
                    <date>Ca. 430-420 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 40 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter: 10.9 cm.</measure> Warrior and woman at
                    tomb.</p>
                <p>In the center stands a tall stele on a low two-stepped base. Two dark
                    blue ribbons are hung around it, and it is crowned by sketchy floral ornaments.
                    At the right sits a young beardless warrior. He wears a short belted tunic which
                    is fastened at the left shoulder and a dark blue <hi rend="ital"
                        >chlamys.</hi> The latter is fastened by a brooch over his chest and flows
                    down his back, so that he sits on the lower part of it. He also appears to have
                    a hat resting on the nape of the neck, perhaps a <hi rend="ital"
                        >petasos,</hi> and he holds two spears in his raised left hand.</p>
                <p>From the left side approaches a woman in a thin, frilly <hi
                    rend="ital">chiton.</hi> She holds a small basket by its
                    arching handle in her left hand and a phiale in her right.</p>
                <p>The motif of a dead young warrior sitting on or beside his own tomb
                    occurs on white lekythoi of the last third of the fifth century. One
                    particularly well known example, belonging to Group R, is in the National
                    Museum, Athens (<bibl>ARV2, 1383, 11</bibl>). Many
                    of these must have been made for the families of those who fell in the
                    Peloponnesian War. The woman bringing offerings to the grave could be the
                    deceased young man's mother, sister, or wife.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>New Orleans Museum of Art,
                        <title>New Orleans Collects,</title> 1971, no.
                        287</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Austin 1980.37" type="vase">Austin
                        1980.37</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Early Corinthian Aryballos</title>
                    <rs type="collection">Collection of the Archer M. Huntington Art
                        Gallery, the University of Texas, Austin, James R. Dougherty, Jr. Foundation
                        and Archer M. Huntington Museum Fund Purchase (1980.37)</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Warrior Group</rs>
                    <date>Ca. 600 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 6.2 cm.</measure> Duel of warriors flanked by
                    riders.</p>
                <p>The incision and attention to detail are particularly careful on this
                    miniature Corinthian perfume bottle. The two warriors on foot are heraldically
                    posed, and the two squires who wait behind them are also perfectly symmetrical.
                    Only the contrast between the two shields which occupy the center of the
                    composition, one seen from the outside, the other from the inside, mitigates the
                    rigid symmetry.</p>
                <p>The combatants are dressed alike in low crested Corinthian helmets,
                    short tunics with decorated border at top and bottom, and greaves. Subtle
                    variations in the incised decoration of the helmet crests and the borders of the
                    garments also enliven the composition. They fight with spears, though the right
                    hand warrior's weapon is mostly obscured behind his body and shield. The other
                    warrior's spear crosses behind his head, an impossible position, in order not to
                    block our view of his profile. The one shield device we can see is a splendid
                    frontal bull's head which fills the surface and even overlaps the rim. The
                    horsemen also wear tunics, though undecorated, and fillets in their long flowing
                    hair.</p>
                <p>The rest of the vase's surface is almost covered with filling
                    ornament, mostly plain blobs and rosettes whose incision is not always as
                    careful as that of the figures. In addition there is a pattern of tongues on the
                    shoulder and the lip, and an incised double palmette on the handle.</p>
                <p>The footless round aryballos became a very popular shape rather
                    suddenly in the Early Corinthian period, at the end of the seventh century,
                    perhaps due to contact with the Near East, where the shape had long been known.
                    By about 600, the animal style that had dominated earlier Corinthian
                    vase-painting was starting to die out, and a figured style, favoring soldiers,
                    horsemen, and padded dancers, was increasingly popular. The warrior Group
                    comprises several dozen aryballoi of Payne's shape B1. Although the Austin vase
                    is unattributed, according to D. A. Amyx the style recalls the Heraldic Riders
                    Painter.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Amyx 1988, 309, 11 bis</bibl>;
                        <bibl>CVA, Castle Ashby (Great Britain 15)
                            19 and pl. 30, 4-6</bibl>; <bibl>Christie's
                                Sale Catalogue 1980, London, July 2, 1980, lot. 54ii, p. 95, ill</bibl>.
                        On the Warrior Group: <bibl>Payne 1931,
                            288</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Raleigh G.79.11.5" type="vase">Raleigh
                        G.79.11.5</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Red-Figure Oinochoe</title>
                    <rs type="collection">Collection of the North Carolina Museum of
                        Art, Raleigh (G.79.11.5)</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Attributed to the Painter of the Brussels
                        Oinochoai</rs>
                    <date>Ca. 470-460 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 24.5 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter: 15.25 cm.</measure> Two warriors.</p>
                <p>Lacking all subsidiary ornament, this sleek, black-glazed oinochoe
                    highlights two confronted warriors. The one to the left is older, bearded, and
                    ready for battle. He is dressed in a short <hi rend="ital"
                        >chiton,</hi> cuirass and Corinthian helmet, and armed with a spear and large
                    circular shield, the device of which is a writhing black snake. Standing
                    frontally, he gazes to his left at the youth on the other side of the vase. This
                    warrior is less well equipped. Despite a cloth headband, his long hair lies in
                    ringlets over his shoulders. His nude body is draped with a long <hi rend="ital"
                        >chlamys</hi> or cloak. He holds a spear and a plain black
                    shield in his left hand, and holds forth a crested Corinthian helmet in his
                    right.</p>
                <p>The two warriors are certainly related in some way. Not only do they
                    stare at each other, but on similarly shaped vases the two sides are usually
                    connected. It has been suggested that the younger warrior is receiving arms from
                    the older in preparation for the Persian Wars which ended in 480/479 B.C.
                    However, arming scenes are ubiquitous in Attic vase-painting, and this
                    particular one is likely to be simply genre.</p>
                <p>On the other hand, the shape of this footless oinochoe is very rare
                    in Attica, although popular with the Etruscans. Hence, it and the others by the
                    Painter of the Brussels Oinochoai may well have been made for export.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>North Carolina Museum of Art,
                        <title>Calendar</title> (January, 1980)</bibl>. For
                        other spouted oinochoai: <bibl>Schauenburg 1975,
                            97-102</bibl>. On oinochoai: <bibl>Green
                                1972, 1 - 16</bibl>. On the Painter of the Brussels Oinochoai: <bibl
                                    >ARV2, 775</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
                <byline>Jenifer Neils</byline>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Sarasota 1600.G4" type="vase">Sarasota
                        1600.G4</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Black-Figure Neck-Amphora</title>
                    <rs type="collection">Collection of the John and Mable Ringling
                        Museum of Art, Sarasota, Gift of Mr. Manuel Ortiz, Jr., (1600.G4)</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Attributed to the Edinburgh Painter [Bothmer]</rs>
                    <date>Ca. 500-480 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 26.9 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter: 16.9 cm.</measure> Side A: Goddess and
                    warrior in a wheeling chariot. Side B: Two warriors leaving home.</p>
                <p>A four-horse chariot wheeling round is a favorite subject on late
                    black-figure vases, mainly neck-amphoras. <hi rend="bold">On side
                        A</hi>, the two horses on the far side raise their forelegs high in the air,
                    creating a whirl of movement, and each horse's head is seen from a different
                    angle, the middle two meeting or overlapping. In the car stand a female figure,
                    holding the reins, and beside her a warrior in a high crested helmet, holding a
                    spear. Often when the driver of a chariot is female, she is Athena, recognizable
                    by her helmet. Without the helmet, we must assume she is another goddess, but
                    cannot say which one (compare the neck-amphora in the Agora: <bibl
                        >Para., 302</bibl>).</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">On side B</hi>, two young, fully-armed
                    warriors prepare to depart for battle. They wear greaves and Corinthian helmets,
                    one with a low crest, the other a high one. They stand in profile to left so
                    that their shield devices are visible: a facing bull's head and two balls (a
                    third ball is presumably hidden behind the other shield). One warrior carries a
                    spear and a second cuts diagonally across the pair. The warriors stand between
                    an older man and a woman: perhaps two brothers taking leave of their parents.
                    The old man is bearded and balding, though his hair is long in back. He wears a
                    <hi rend="ital">chiton</hi> and <hi rend="ital"
                        >himation</hi> and leans on a staff. The woman wears a fillet, and her <hi
                            rend="ital">chiton</hi> is decorated at the neck and the hem.</p>
                <p>The Edinburgh Painter, perhaps best known for his innovation in the
                    use of white-ground (<bibl>Shapiro 1981a, no.
                        26</bibl>), also decorated many small neck-amphoras in the conventional
                    black-figure technique.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p>Unpublished. For similar neck-amphoras by the Edinburgh Painter:
                        <bibl>ABV, 478 (iii)</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
                <milestone n="122" unit="page"/>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Durham 1969.3" type="vase">Durham
                        1969.3</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Black-Figure Kyathos</title>
                    <rs type="collection">Collection of the Duke University Museum of
                        Art, Durham (1969.3).</rs>
                    <date>Ca. 510-500 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 17 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter: 16 cm.</measure> Fight with Chariots</p>
                <p>The composition forms a continuous frieze around the outer surface of
                    the vase. At the center, where a large portion is unfortunately missing, two
                    heavily armed warriors (hoplites) do battle. The figure moving toward the right
                    has the upper hand, a convention in Greek art, as his opponent sinks to his
                    knees. The inside of the victor's shield is seen, his left arm holding it
                    through a strap <hi rend="ital">(porpax).</hi> Behind each warrior
                    is his four-horse chariot; in the car stands the charioteer wearing the
                    traditional long white chiton. The scene is flanked by two onlookers, one on
                    either side of the handle: an armed hoplite and a nude figure with a cloak
                    draped over one arm.</p>
                <p>Chariots were not used in Greek warfare in the historical period.
                    Homeric heroes do, however, regularly ride to the field of battle in a chariot,
                    often accompanied by a charioteer, then dismount to fight in single combat. Thus
                    this scene was probably inspired by epic poetry, though without other clues it
                    is impossible to try to name the combatants.</p>
                <p>The kyathos is a small dipper with a single high-swung handle, used
                    for ladling wine out of a krater. The shape is an adaptation of an Etruscan
                    vessel which had been made in Italy as early as the seventh century. Its
                    manufacture began in Athens about 535 B.C. and continued for only a half
                    century, apparently intended exclusively for export to Etruria.</p>
                <p>Most of the roughly 450 extant kyathoi seem to have been produced by
                    one large workshop in the Athenian potters' quarter, that of Nikosthenes, which
                    also manufactured other shapes for export to Etruria. The majority of kyathoi
                    are decorated with Dionysiac subjects, a reference to the vessel's association
                    with wine. Scenes of combat are relatively rare: four kyathoi by the Philon
                    Painter depict fight scenes (<bibl>ABV,
                        516-517</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 255</bibl>), including
                    horsemen, but none other has chariots.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl><title>Hesperia
                        Art Bulletin</title> 45/46 (January, 1969) A15</bibl>. On kyathoi:
                        <bibl>Eisman 1975, 76-83</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="50" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Chapel Hill 71.8.1" type="vase">Chapel Hill
                        71.8.1</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Red-Figure Squat Lekythos</title>
                    <rs type="collection">Collection of Ackland Art Museum, University
                        of North Carolina, Chapel Hill (71.8.1)</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Manner of the Eretria Painter [A. Lezzi-Hafter]</rs>
                    <date>Ca. 430-420 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 21.3 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter: 14.6 cm.</measure> Women at their toilette.</p>
                <p>Seventeen women sit or stand in a variety of poses, in two registers,
                    each holding an attribute which figured in the daily life of Athenian matrons
                    and their maid-servants.</p>
                <p>The figures are grouped in pairs, each consisting of a mistress and
                    maid, with the exception of one threesome in the upper register: a seated
                    mistress attended by two standing maids (<bibl
                        >Shapiro 1981a, drawing, pps. 130-131, nos. 3, 4, 5</bibl>). Many poses are
                    similar, but none exactly duplicates another, and variations in dress, coiffure,
                    and attributes also help avoid monotony.</p>
                <p>The most frequent attribute is a small chest or box, held by six of
                    the figures (<bibl>Shapiro 1981a, drawing, pps.
                        130-131, nos. 2, 5, 7, 10, 12, 15</bibl>). Most of these chests are made of
                    wicker and could have contained jewelry, toiletries, wool, articles of clothing,
                    or other objects. They vary in size and shape: three have legs (ibid. nos. 5, 7,
                    12) and of these one has animal feet (ibid., no. 12). Some are richly patterned
                    on the outside (ibid., nos. 2, 10), others plain. On one can be seen two round
                    knobs (ibid. no. 5), which look like drawer pulls, but are probably for tying on
                    the lid. Other attributes are a wicker wool basket (ibid., no. 9), a ball of
                    wool (ibid. no. 11), mirrors (ibid. nos. 4, 13, 17), an alabastron for precious
                    oil or perfume (ibid., no. 8), leafy sprigs (ibid. nos. 1, 14), and an
                    embroidered headband with tasseled fringe (ibid., no. 16). In addition two
                    objects are suspended from the wall behind: a headband (ibid., between 9 and 10)
                    and an alabastron (ibid., between 3 and 4). This bottle, like the one held by a
                    seated mistress (ibid., no. 8), is made of glass, decorated with a multi-colored
                    zig-zag pattern, a type which has survived in several examples.</p>
                <p>Four of the women sit on <hi rend="ital">klismoi,</hi>
                    backed chairs with curving legs (ibid., nos.4, 6, 11, 14; compare the Chapel
                    Hill lekythos, <rs type="vase">Chapel Hill 78.15.1</rs>). One sits
                    on a four-legged stool, a <hi rend="ital">diphros</hi> (ibid.,
                    no.8). Most of the maids wear only a thin, crinkly linen garment, the <hi
                        rend="ital">chiton</hi> (e.g. ibid., no. 5), while several of
                    the matrons wear a heavy woolen peplos (ibid., no.2, 16). Some wear both a <hi
                        rend="ital">chiton</hi> and, over it, a <hi rend="ital"
                            >himation</hi> (e.g.ibid., no. 4). Most of the women wear their
                    hair up and bound with a headband, or <hi rend="ital">mitra,</hi>
                    which may be patterned (ibid., nos. 5, 12). Only one mistress' hair hangs down
                    in loose wavy tresses (ibid., no. 6); perhaps she will use the contents of the
                    chest being handed to her to tie it up.</p>
                <p>Squat lekythoi were first manufactured in Athens earlier in the fifth
                    century and were especially popular during the period of this vase. They were
                    used to contain oil and were primarily for use at home by women like those
                    depicted on this example.</p>
                <p>In style the vase is closely related to the work of the Eretria
                    Painter, the greatest miniaturist of his generation. The disposition of the
                    figures in superposed registers is unusual and is paralleled by only two other
                    squat lekythoi, one by the Eretria Painter (<bibl
                        >ARV2, 1248, 9</bibl>), the other by an imitator (<bibl
                            >ARV2, 1257, middle, 1</bibl>). Originally attributed to the
                    painter himself, the Chapel Hill vase is now considered to be more likely by an
                    imitator closely associated with his workshop.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>R. Sutton 1972</bibl>; <bibl
                        >Mack 1974, 22-23</bibl>. On the Eretria
                        Painter: <bibl>Isler-Kerényi 1972,
                            30-31</bibl>. Attribution: A. Lezzi-Hafter, letter to R. F. Sutton, 1/28/74,
                        and letter from R. F. Sutton to the writer, 2/25/81.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="51" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Houston 80.95" type="vase">Houston
                        80.95</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Red-Figure Hydria</title>
                    <rs type="collection">Collection of The Museum of Fine Arts,
                        Houston, Museum Purchase with funds donated by General and Mrs. Maurice
                        Hirsch (80.95)</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Attributed to the Painter of the Yale Oinochoe</rs>
                    <date>Ca. 470-460 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 34.8 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter: 33.3 cm.</measure> Women working wool.</p>
                <p>The scene is a charming and authentic image of Athenian domestic
                    life, showing three young women and a pet heron. In the center, a woman stands
                    over a <hi rend="ital">kalathos,</hi> a wicker wool basket, about
                    to place in it (or take from it) a large bundle of wool. (Compare the woman
                    drawing skeins of wool from a <hi rend="ital">kalathos</hi> on the
                    Chapel Hill lekythos <rs type="vase">Chapel Hill 78.15.1</rs>). At
                    the left a woman holds an alabastron, an unguent bottle, in one hand, and in the
                    other reaches out a similar bottle over the stooping figure, toward a third
                    woman at the right. The women at left and right wear plain <hi rend="ital"
                        >chiton</hi> and <hi rend="ital">himation,</hi>
                    while the central figure's garment is gaily decorated with an all-over pattern
                    and fringed hem. All three wear a fillet, and their hair is tied in a knot at
                    the back.</p>
                <p>A heron, standing on long spindly legs, faces and watches intently
                    the woman in the center. The heron was sacred to Aphrodite and was a favorite
                    pet of Athenian matrons. Hence it is seen not infrequently in domestic settings
                    such as this one.</p>
                <p>Scenes of women working wool, as well as other domestic occupations,
                    become increasingly popular in Attic red-figure after about 500 B.C. Of six
                    hydrias attributed to the Painter of the Yale Oinochoe, five, including this
                    one, show women's scenes with common elements. A hydria in Copenhagen (<bibl
                        >ARV2, 503, 24</bibl>) portrays another aspect of
                    wool working, a woman holding spindle and distaff. Two others, in London (<bibl
                        >ARV2, 503, 23</bibl>) and at Harvard (<bibl
                            >ARV2, 503, 22</bibl>), include herons, one being
                    fed by its mistress. On the Harvard vase, a <hi rend="ital"
                        >kalathos</hi> hangs upside down on the wall. A hydria at San Simeon (<bibl
                            >ARV2, 503, 21</bibl>) shows a rare scene of
                    women working out of doors, picking apples. The painter also decorated many
                    other shapes, but his drawing is seldom as fine as it is here.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p>Unpublished. On the Painter of the Yale Oinochoe: <bibl
                        >ARV2, 501-503</bibl>; <bibl
                            >H. M. Fracchia, in <title>California
                                Studies in Classical Antiquity</title> 5 (1972) 103-111</bibl>. On
                        herons: <bibl>Beazley 1920, 60-61</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="52" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Chapel Hill 78.15.1" type="vase">Chapel
                        Hill 78.15.1</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Red-Figure Lekythos</title>
                    <rs type="collection">Collection of the Ackland Art Museum,
                        University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill (78.15.1)</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Attributed to the Bowdoin Painter</rs>
                    <date>Ca. 470-450 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 27.8 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter: 9.5 cm.</measure> Woman at a wool basket.</p>
                <p>A favorite subject of the Bowdoin Painter is a domestic scene of a
                    woman, wearing a thin <hi rend="ital">chiton,</hi> seated or, as
                    here, standing near a wool basket <hi rend="ital">(kalathos)</hi>
                    from which she draws skeins of wool. The scene is, in Miss Richter's words, ``a
                    simple Greek version of the later Dutch interiors representing women at work"
                    (<bibl>Richter 1958, 75</bibl>).</p>
                <p>This vase includes more details of the indoor setting than most.
                    Beside the woman is an unusually large high-backed chair, a <hi rend="ital"
                        >klismos,</hi> with a cover spread over the seat. Two black
                    squares mark the points at which the frame-pieces are mortised into the legs.
                    The chair, however, is peculiarly tall and out of proportion, the back-board so
                    high that it would function rather as a headrest. Behind the <hi rend="ital"
                        >klismos</hi> a garment is suspended from the wall, and at the
                    right hangs a footed basket for flowers or fruit. The tall <hi rend="ital"
                        >kalathos</hi> is probably made of wicker.</p>
                <p>The Bowdoin Painter was a prolific, though generally uninspired
                    artist to whom over 200 lekythoi are attributed, as well as a small number of
                    vases of other shapes. He had a long career, beginning at the very end of the
                    Archaic period and extending down to at least 450.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p>Unpublished. <bibl>ARV2,
                        681,82</bibl>. On <hi rend="ital">klismoi:</hi>
                        <bibl>Richter 1926b, 45-53</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="53" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Diefenthal Collection (Shapiro No. 53)" type="vase"
                        >Diefenthal Collection (Shapiro No. 53)</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Black-Figure Little Master Cup</title>
                    <rs type="collection">Collection of Mr. and Mrs. Edward L.
                        Diefenthal, Metairie, Louisiana</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Attributed to the Centaur Painter [Cahn]</rs>
                    <date>Ca. 540 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 9.7 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter (without handles): 13.7 cm.</measure> Sides
                    A and B: Hare hunt.</p>
                <p>The same scene is repeated without variation on both sides of the
                    exterior of this charming small cup. A youth strides to the left, preparing to
                    throw a stone at a large rabbit. The youth is nude but for a <hi rend="ital"
                        >chlamys</hi> which is draped over his outstretched left arm and
                    is decorated with a border of white dots. The rabbit is some distance away and
                    seems as yet unaware of the danger as he hops along briskly. The rabbit's neck
                    and flank, the youth's hair, and his <hi rend="ital">chlamys</hi>
                    are all painted in added red.</p>
                <p>Rabbits were favorite pets of Athenian boys, to judge from their
                    popularity on vases as gifts from an older man to his beloved. In addition, the
                    hunting of wild rabbits, as here, was a popular sport among boys and young men.</p>
                <p>The Diefenthal cup is one of a large group of small black-figure
                    cups, decorated in miniature style, of the second and third quarters of the
                    sixth century, named by Beazley Little Master Cups. This one is a band cup, so
                    named from the reserved band at handle level within which the figured scene is
                    placed. The Centaur Painter, who decorated at least twenty-five small cups and
                    no other shapes, favored centaurs, either alone or in combat or, once, throwing
                    a stone at a fawn (<bibl>Para., 78, 3bis</bibl>), a
                    scene not unlike this one.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Münzen, 1977 (Antike
                        Vasen) no. 23, ill</bibl>. On the Centaur Painter: <bibl
                            >ABV, 189-90</bibl>; <bibl
                                >Para., 78-79</bibl>; <bibl>Villard 1953, 65
                                    - 69</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="54" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Mississippi 1977.3.74" type="vase"
                        >Mississippi 1977.3.74</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Black-Figure "Sprinkler"
                    (Klepsydra?)</title>
                    <rs type="collection">Collection of The University Museums,
                        University of Mississippi, Phase I Cultural Center (77.3.74)</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Unattributed</rs>
                    <date>Ca. 500 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 17.3 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter: 12.2 cm.</measure> Side A: Boy in tree;
                    youth and man dancing. Side B: The like.</p>
                <p>The general meaning of the scene repeated on both sides of this
                    unusual vessel is clear: the trees are fruit trees, which the boys have climbed
                    to pick or shake down the fruit, while youths and men dance under the trees. It
                    is harder to say what kind of fruit is meant; the shape and foliage of the trees
                    are entirely conventional, and the painter did not bother to distinguish leaves
                    from fruit. Dancers are common in scenes of the grape harvest, but these are
                    clearly trees, not vines. The most probable answer is olive trees, since the
                    olive was the fruit most highly valued by the Greeks, both as food and for its
                    oil. The older dancers wear wreaths of leaves on their heads; the younger ones
                    have red garlands or fillets around their heads and necks. This must be a
                    harvest or first-fruits festival, one of those rustic, cheerful jollifications
                    that were celebrated in villages all over the Greek-speaking world, rather than
                    a more formal city ceremony. The dancers have slung their cloaks over their
                    outstretched left arms, to free their legs for more energetic movement as the
                    line of dancers goes stamping, kicking and spinning through the olive grove in
                    one of the vigorous dances that Greek villagers enjoy to this day.</p>
                <p>The shape of the vase is unusual and raises questions about its use.
                    It is derived from the mastos, a cup in the shape of a human breast. The body is
                    a sphere, topped by a clay nipple painted red. The base is pierced with some 60
                    small holes, and the hollow handle opens at each end into the body. In the top
                    of the handle is a single hole; when the vessel has been filled by plunging it
                    into a liquid, the user's thumb over the hole prevents the liquid from running
                    out until desired. This could have been used as a sprinkler for ritual
                    lustrations and purifications or to lift wine from a large container without
                    disturbing the lees or bringing with it any foreign matter that might be
                    present; it holds enough to fill a medium-sized kylix, or two small ones. If the
                    shape has any significance for the use, it would suit both purposes: the breast
                    has connotations of fertility for a harvest festival, or eroticism for a
                    drinking party. The type of vessel is rare but not unique; some 5th-century
                    examples are copied from animal-head rhyta, drinking vessels which may have a
                    small hole in the bottom. Such rhyta may have been used to aerate wine by
                    releasing it in a thin stream into a cup, and this may be the purpose of our
                    "sprinkler" as well. Indeed, it would be more efficient than a rhyton, releasing
                    the wine in 60 thin streams instead of just one.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>CVA, Robinson Collection 3, pl.
                        3, 1</bibl>. For rhyta as aerators of wine: <bibl
                            >Hoffmann 1961, 21-26</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
                <byline>Lucy Turnbull</byline>
            </div>
            <div n="55" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Schimmel Collection (Shapiro No. 55)" type="vase"
                        >Schimmel Collection (Shapiro No. 55)</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Boeotian Black-Figure Tripod-Kothon</title>
                    <rs type="collection">Collection of Norbert Schimmel, courtesy of
                        the Dallas Museum of Fine Arts</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Attributed to the Boeotian Dancers Group</rs>
                    <date>570-560 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 13.6 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Width: 18.4 cm.</measure> Komasts, athletes, and
                    animals.</p>
                <p>Six nude male figures are disposed in pairs on the three leg panels.
                    The first set is engaged in a heated dance. These frolicking acrobats are
                    komasts, comic dancers whose activities incline toward mischief-making at every
                    opportunity. The two bearded dancers here confront each other in their
                    jubilation. Each dancer has an incised line across the left bicep, creating the
                    impression of a short-sleeved garment. This is a sure indication that members of
                    this tribe of revelers were once clad, as indeed they were in earlier scenes on
                    Attic and Corinthian komos vases from which the Boeotian komasts derive. The
                    heavier komast gingerly raises an inviting hand to the chin of his companion in
                    hopes of obtaining even a more intimate response. Homosexual activity is
                    frequently depicted in scenes on Greek vases (<rs type="vase"
                        >Mississippi 1977.3.72</rs>, <rs type="vase">Jacksonville
                            AP.66.28</rs>) and especially among the ranks of komasts. Moving
                    counter-clockwise around the vase the next pair of komasts is actively engaged
                    in another favorite pastime, the consumption of wine. The eager drinker on the
                    right raises a wine pitcher, an oinochoe, directly to his lips. Sparing no time
                    for the formalities of proper table manners he steadies the hefty pitcher with
                    both hands while draining its contents. The disapproving expression on his
                    partner's face and the anticipative air in his pose indicate his dismay, since
                    the high-handled wine cup, a kantharos, he extends toward the pitcher may well
                    be dry. The third leg panel displays not komasts, but athletes. In this scene a
                    vigorous boxing match is in progress between a paunchy, bearded male figure on
                    the left and a somewhat slimmer youth, or beardless athlete, on the right.
                    Immediately behind the boxers stands a tripod, the contested prize and no doubt
                    an inspiration to the contenders' enthusiasm. The tripod recalls the vessel on
                    which it is actually painted; however, the example depicted in the scene has
                    tall, slender legs, large ring handles, and is meant to be constructed of
                    bronze.</p>
                <p>The six creatures on the tubular body of the vase are likewise
                    depicted in pairs and in heraldic fashion. Two frontal-faced panthers crane
                    their necks over a palmette. Two sirens are separated by a lotus bud on a tall
                    stem, while a pair of does inspect one another or graze placidly together. Each
                    pair of creatures is oblivious to the others and, likewise, follows the isolated
                    pattern established by the human figures on the separate leg panels. In contrast
                    to the animated humans the six creatures appear lifeless, serving merely as
                    decorative objects, and provide us with a clear indication as to where the
                    painter's interests lie.</p>
                <p>The Schimmel vase belongs to a series of vessels (many of them
                    tripod-kothons) known as the Boeotian Dancers Group. Choice of figural subjects,
                    especially the frolicking komasts, field ornaments, vase shape and most
                    importantly the painted style indicate a common workshop for vases in the Group.
                    Prevailing evidence suggests that the workshop was located in or near Tanagra in
                    southeast Boeotia. This site was along a main road from Athens, and it was under
                    Athenian influence, by way of the Attic Komast Group, that the workshop of the
                    Boeotian Dancers Group created much of its art. The parading animals, field
                    ornaments, and even the komasts themselves on these vases all derive from
                    Corinthian workshops; however, these elements entered the Boeotian repertoire
                    via Attic vases and/or vase-painters.</p>
                <p>The shape of the tripod-kothon is designed for maximum stability. Its
                    relatively small size indicates that it contained scented oils, a substance too
                    precious to be lost by tipping over a vase. A lid, now lost, would have
                    curtailed evaporation. The central spike under the bowl and the struts attached
                    to the back of the legs are ceramic but reflect the construction of metal
                    prototypes.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Muscarella 1974, no. 53</bibl>.
                        On the Boeotian Dancers Group: <bibl>K.
                            Kilinski, <title>American Journal of Archaeology</title>
                            82 (1978) 173-191</bibl>. On komasts: <bibl
                                >Greifenhagen 1929</bibl>; <bibl>Seeberg
                                    1971</bibl>. On homosexuality in Greece: <bibl
                                        >Dover 1978</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
                <byline>Karl Kilinski II</byline>
            </div>
            <div n="56" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Diefenthal Collection (Shapiro No. 56)" type="vase"
                        >Diefenthal Collection (Shapiro No. 56)</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Black-Figure Kalpis</title>
                    <rs type="collection">Collection of Mr. and Mrs. Edward L.
                        Diefenthal, Metairie, Louisiana</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Unattributed</rs>
                    <date>Ca. 500-490 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 32.7 cm.</measure> Quadriga.</p>
                <p>A four-horse chariot stands ready to depart, as one of the horses
                    looks down and impatiently paws the ground. A dog stands before the horses,
                    facing them but looking around at his tail. The tail is swung in a high arc, and
                    a little glaze has accidentally dripped from it. In the car of the chariot
                    stands a tall bearded driver wearing a long white <hi rend="ital"
                        >chiton,</hi> holding the reins, and carrying in his right hand a goad (<hi
                            rend="ital">kentron</hi>). Since no warrior is present, perhaps
                    the chariot is bound not for the battlefield, but rather for a competition at
                    the games or a festival.</p>
                <p>The kalpis is a variety of hydria in which the neck, shoulder, and
                    body form a continuous curve. It is primarily a red-figure shape and was first
                    introduced about 520, but there are many examples in later black-figure. The
                    figured scene may be confined to a panel on the shoulder, as here, or extend
                    over the bulge and onto the body, as often in red-figure. On the Diefenthal
                    kalpis, the picture is framed below by two bands of ivy leaves without berries
                    and on the other three sides by a double net pattern. The standing quadriga is
                    not an uncommon subject; according to Dietrich von Bothmer, the closest parallel
                    is on a vase in Hamburg (<rs type="vase">Hamburg 1908.253</rs>;
                    <bibl>CVA, pl. 27</bibl>).</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p>Unpublished.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="57" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Richmond 63.11" type="vase">Richmond
                        63.11</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Red-Figure Cup</title>
                    <rs type="collection">Collection of the Virginia Museum of Fine
                        Arts, Richmond (63.11)</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Attributed to the Antiphon Painter</rs>
                    <date>490-480 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 9.4 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter (without handles): 23 cm.</measure>
                    Interior: Young athlete with strigil. Sides A and B: Athletes.</p>
                <p>All three scenes show young athletes in the palestra. In the tondo, a
                    nude youth stands frontally, looking to his right. He holds a strigil, the
                    curved metal instrument used by athletes to scrape dust, sweat, and oil off
                    their bodies. The boy is scraping off his right wrist. In the background hangs a
                    sponge, used by athletes in bathing.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">On side A</hi>, two more youths scrape
                    themselves with strigils. A third figure has the conventional attribute and
                    dress of the <hi rend="ital">paidotribes</hi>, or trainer: a
                    voluminous cloak draped over one shoulder and a knotty stick. Usually, however,
                    the <hi rend="ital">paidotribes</hi> is a mature bearded man, the
                    proprietor of the palestra (cf.<rs type="vase">New Orleans
                        16.11</rs>); this trainer is a beardless boy who appears no older than the
                    athletes.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">On side B</hi>, four nude youths stand
                    or turn in a variety of poses. One holds a large diskos in his left hand and
                    strides to the left, as if about to release it. One holds a strigil, apparently
                    trying to scrape his back, while another comes up, perhaps to lend a hand. The
                    fourth stands off to the left by himself.</p>
                <p>Athletic subjects gave Late Archaic red-figure vase-painters an
                    opportunity to experiment in rendering the nude male body in many different
                    poses. Here we have a range of poses, from frontal to several varieties of
                    three-quarter view, to a slightly awkward back view.</p>
                <p>The Antiphon Painter was a specialist in cups, and one of his
                    favorite subjects was athletes. His figures are usually quite lively, though not
                    as finely drawn as those of his contemporaries, Onesimos and the Panaitian
                    Group. He reached his mature style at the very end of the Archaic period, in the
                    480's.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>ARV2, 1646, 13 bis</bibl>;
                        <bibl>Para., 521</bibl>; <bibl
                            ><title>Ancient Art in the Virginia
                                Museum</title> (Richmond 1973) 105</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="58" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Durham 1969.4" type="vase">Durham
                        1969.4</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Black-Figure Oinochoe
                    (White-Ground)</title>
                    <rs type="collection">Collection of the Duke University Museum of
                        Art, Durham (1969.4)</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Workshop of the Athena Painter [A. Clark]</rs>
                    <date>Ca. 500 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 22 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter: 17 cm.</measure> Athlete and trainer.</p>
                <p>The scene is set in the palestra, despite the vines in the
                    background, which are only a filling ornament typical of this period, rather
                    than an indication of locale. In the center, a well developed young athlete
                    prepares to practice a jump. He holds a pair of bronze jumping weights (<hi
                        rend="ital">halteres</hi>). Facing him stands a young man in a
                    tightly wrapped <hi rend="ital">himation,</hi> who is probably the
                    trainer who coaches the young jumper. At the left stands a young boy,
                    considerably smaller than the other two. He holds a variety of accoutrements
                    regularly used in the palestra: a strigil, or scraper, a round oil bottle, and a
                    large spotted (hide?) bag for holding equipment. These are all tied to the
                    knotty staff which the boy holds in his right hand. The staff should belong to
                    the trainer and the other equipment to the jumper. Perhaps the boy is a young
                    slave who looks after the paraphernalia of athletes and trainers.</p>
                <p>The Duke vase is one of many late black-figure oinochoai produced by
                    the Athena Painter's workshop. A number of these, though by no means all, were
                    decorated in the white-ground technique (compare <rs type="vase"
                        >Sarasota 1600.G5</rs>). Among the oinochoai of this workshop Beazley
                    distinguished several classes according to variations in shape. The Duke
                    example, with its short neck and no collar, spreading mouth, round handle, and
                    the figured scene occupying the whole surface, rather than framed in a panel,
                    belongs to the Sèvres Class.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl><title>Hesperia
                        Art Bulletin</title> 45/46 (January, 1969) no. A 17</bibl>; <bibl
                            >Mertens 1977, 73, no. 68</bibl>.
                        Sèvres Class: <bibl>ABV,
                            524-25</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="59" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Chapel Hill 66.27.4" type="vase">Chapel
                        Hill 66.27.4</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Red-Figure Cup</title>
                    <rs type="collection">Collection of the Ackland Art Museum,
                        University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill, Ackland Fund (66.27.4)</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Workshop of the Codrus Painter</rs>
                    <date>Ca. 430 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 10 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter: 28.3 cm.</measure> Interior: Archer. Sides
                    A and B: Athletes.</p>
                <p>This cup illustrates life in the Greek palestra, a favorite theme
                    throughout Attic red-figure vase-painting. Like many cups by the Codrus Painter
                    and his followers, this one depicts various forms of athletic training. All the
                    participants are male, short-haired, well built and nude. In the center of <hi
                        rend="bold">side A</hi> are two confronted wrestlers: one, bent
                    over at the waist, is helpless, while the other grips him in a body hold in
                    preparation for giving him ``the heave." The contestants are flanked by a pair
                    of bystanders who gesture toward the wrestlers as if giving advice. <hi
                        rend="bold">On side B</hi> a jumper takes center stage. With
                    both arms and left leg extended, he is shown in the take-off position for the
                    running broad jump. He is likewise framed by two fellow athletes; the one at the
                    left with a stick is perhaps a trainer.</p>
                <p>The subject of the tondo, an archer testing his bow, is an unusual
                    one. Archers normally appear in military scenes where they are characterized by
                    their non-Greek garb as foreigners, usually Scythians. This nude athlete, on the
                    other hand, is clearly Greek, and the setting is the palestra, as indicated by
                    the pillar or goal post at the left. This cup then documents the practice of
                    archery as part of the athletic training of Athenian youths. While before the
                    Persian Wars the bow had little status among the Greeks, its worth was proven at
                    the Battle of Salamis, and by 450 B.C., the Athenian military had a trained
                    corps of archers, who were used effectively during the Peloponnesian War. Thus,
                    this cup, which dates to the time of the latter war, illustrates not only the
                    athletic training of Athenian youth but their military preparation for the great
                    conflict with Sparta.</p>
                <p>If not by the Codrus Painter himself, this cup can be assigned to his
                    workshop, one which favored athletic scenes. The heavy physique of the athletes,
                    the proclivity for faces in three-quarter view, and the palmette complexes under
                    the handles are all characteristic of this artist.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p>On Greek athletics: <bibl>Gardiner
                        1930</bibl>; <bibl>Harris 1972</bibl>. On
                        archery: <bibl>Snodgrass 1967, esp.
                            98-99</bibl>. A late archaic cup (<rs type="vase">Boston
                                10.207</rs>) by Onesimos shows Greek archers in the tondo and athletes on
                        the exterior; for a discussion of the archers: <bibl
                            >Caskey &amp; Beazley, 27-28</bibl>. On the Codrus
                        Painter: <bibl>ARV2, 1268-1275</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
                <byline>Jenifer Neils</byline>
            </div>
            <div n="60" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:New Orleans 16.11" type="vase">New Orleans
                        16.11</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Red-Figure Oinochoe</title>
                    <rs type="collection">Collection of the New Orleans Museum of Art,
                        Gift of Alvin P. Howard (16.11)</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Manner of the Nikias Painter</rs>
                    <date>Ca. 400 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 18 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter: 14 cm.</measure> Athletes and trainer.</p>
                <p>Two young nude athletes practise jumping under the watchful eye of a
                    <hi rend="ital">paidotribes,</hi> or trainer. The boy in the
                    center, in mid-jump, holds the bronze jumping weights <hi rend="ital"
                        >(halteres)</hi> used to give added momentum. Behind him a youth
                    waits his turn, resting one hand on his hip and with the other gesturing toward
                    the jumper. On the ground beside the jumper is a low stone slab on a flat base,
                    perhaps a distance marker for measuring the jump.</p>
                <p>The bearded <hi rend="ital">paidotribes</hi> holds a
                    long staff, hooked at the top. His ornate <hi rend="ital"
                        >himation,</hi> a mass of delicately swirling folds, and especially the wreath
                    he wears suggest he is not an ordinary trainer in a palestra. Rather, he could
                    be an official or judge at a festival or athletic games.</p>
                <p>In the field are two round objects, one behind the trainer, the other
                    between the two athletes, each with a dotted circle within a reserved blob. They
                    might be diskoi, hung on the wall, or aryballoi, small round oil bottles,
                    suspended so that we see the mouth facing out.</p>
                <p>The vase can be dated the the very end of the fifth century and is
                    closely related in style to the Nikias Painter, who worked mostly on larger
                    shapes, kraters and hydrias.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p>Unpublished. Nikias Painter: <bibl
                        >ARV2, 1333-35</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="61" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:New Orleans 16.15" type="vase">New Orleans
                        16.15</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Red-Figure Pelike</title>
                    <rs type="collection">Collection of the New Orleans Museum of Art,
                        Gift of Alvin P. Howard (16.15)</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Attributed to the Painter of London E 395</rs>
                    <date>Ca. 430-420 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 11.9 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter: 11 cm.</measure> Side A: Athlete with
                    jumping weights and youth. Side B: Woman.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">On side A</hi>, a nude youth with curly
                    hair holds a pair of <hi rend="ital">halteres,</hi> or metal
                    jumping weights. He strides to the right, as if preparing to make a practice
                    jump. A second youth, clad in a long thin mantle, extends his right hand toward
                    the first. Perhaps he is a trainer giving advice to a novice on the use of the
                    <hi rend="ital">halteres.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">On side B</hi>, a woman stands closely
                    wrapped in a <hi rend="ital">himation.</hi> She is stylish, with
                    her hair bound by a fillet and a long loop earring. She has no apparent
                    connection with the athletes on the other side, but is a standard figure on the
                    reverses of smaller vases of this period.</p>
                <p>The vase was attributed by Beazley to a minor follower of the Washing
                    Painter, who decorated many small and usually undistinguished pelikai in the
                    years around 425 (<rs type="vase">Mississippi 1977.3.196</rs>). He
                    takes his name from his fondness for scenes of women bathing.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>ARV2, 1140, 3</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="62" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Mississippi 1977.3.72" type="vase"
                        >Mississippi 1977.3.72</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic (?) Black-Figure Tripod Pyxis</title>
                    <rs type="collection">Collection of The University Museums,
                        University of Mississippi, Phase I Cultural Center (77.3.72)</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Unattributed</rs>
                    <date>550-540 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 5.5 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter: 8.5 cm.</measure> Side A: Bride (?) and men
                    conversing. Side B: Men and women conversing. Side C: Courtship of men and boys</p>
                <p>The significance, if any, of the groups on sides A and B is
                    uncertain. Only the gesture of the woman holding her veil before her face hints
                    that she may be a bride; the painter probably intended no more than to provide
                    an atmosphere of fashionable gaiety surrounding the principal scene on side C.
                    This shows three stages of courtship between men and adolescent boys. Two
                    couples are making love; in each pair the older lover <hi rend="ital"
                        >(erastes)</hi> stands with his knees bent, clasping his beloved
                    <hi rend="ital">(eromenos)</hi> around the waist and resting
                    his head on the boy's shoulder. The third couple is at an earlier stage of
                    courtship; the man reaches toward the boy's chin with one hand and toward his
                    genitals with the other, while the boy tries with both hands to fend him off
                    (compare <rs type="vase">Jacksonville AP.66.28</rs>). At the far
                    right a man approaches holding a gamecock, a standard gift from a wooer to the
                    boy he was courting. Perhaps this one is intended for the unattached youth who
                    seems to be dancing at the far left.</p>
                <p>This is an early example of a theme that appeared often in vase
                    painting between about 560 and 470 B.C. Though later painters might treat such
                    themes with more psychological subtlety, scenes of actual lovemaking are
                    presented seriously, never becoming much more undignified or explicit than this.
                    Scenes of heterosexual lovemaking on the other hand, may be far more explicit,
                    often with heavy emphasis on the grotesque and comic aspects of sex. The reason
                    for this difference lies in Athenian social customs. Women played no part in
                    Athenian public life. Women of good family seldom went out in public and had few
                    opportunities to meet men socially who were not their own relatives. Marriage
                    was a practical arrangement, undertaken to perpetuate the family and its
                    property, and the couple might never have met before the wedding. The women who
                    appear in scenes of drinking and lovemaking are not wives but hired entertainers
                    and prostitutes, many of them slaves, with whom a serious love relationship
                    would be impossible. For an Athenian man of the upper classes, the only real
                    chance for an emotionally satisfying love affair with a social equal was with a
                    boy or youth of his own class. In Athens and most other Greek cities such
                    relationships were not only permitted but approved and praised as the source of
                    one of life's greatest joys. For the boy, such a relationship was considered
                    beneficial and educational, giving him a recognized place in the male society in
                    which he would spend most of his adult life.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Robinson 1956, 1-25, pl. 1,
                        5-7</bibl>. For courtship scenes in general: <bibl
                            >J. D. Beazley, "Some Attic Vases in the Cyprus Museum,"
                            <title>Proceedings of the British Academy</title> 33
                            (1947), 3-31</bibl>. For the place of such relationships in Athenian
                        society: <bibl>Shapiro 1981b,
                            133-143</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
                <byline>Lucy Turnbull</byline>
            </div>
            <div n="63" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Denman Collection (Shapiro No. 63)" type="vase"
                        >Denman Collection (Shapiro No. 63)</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Red-Figure Oinochoe</title>
                    <rs type="collection">Collection of Gilbert M. Denman, Jr., San
                        Antonio</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Attributed to the Berlin Painter</rs>
                    <date>Ca. 490-480 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 29.2 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter: 12.7 cm.</measure> Youth and seated woman</p>
                <p>This elegant oinochoe, with its trefoil lip and high-swung handle
                    terminating in a painted palmette, illustrates a tryst between a young man and a
                    woman. The locale is clearly the <hi rend="ital">gynaikeion</hi> or
                    women's quarters; the woman is seated as if at home, and a mirror is hanging on
                    the wall above her head. Her seat is a <hi rend="ital">klismos</hi>
                    or high-backed chair equipped with a dotted cushion. Her appearance is rather
                    prim and matronly, despite her prominent breasts. She is garbed in a <hi
                        rend="ital">chiton</hi> and <hi rend="ital"
                            >himation,</hi> and her curly hair is tied up in a fillet. Her finery
                    includes a pendant necklace and at least one spiral bracelet in added red.
                    Leaning towards her on his staff is a mantle-clad youth wearing a wreath in his
                    short hair. He is a visitor and his mission is made explicit by the object
                    clutched in his left hand, a coin purse. While some scholars have taken such
                    scenes to represent a husband bringing home his pay, others interpret it not as
                    a conjugal encounter but as a commercial venture, that is, a man negotiating for
                    the favors of a <hi rend="ital">hetaira</hi> (courtesan). That the
                    latter interpretation is correct is here verified by the sexual implications of
                    the other attributes. The youth is handing the woman a flower, while she appears
                    to be tickling him with a long tendril. The fact that the picture appears on a
                    wine jug used by men at their drinking parties perhaps also supports this view.</p>
                <p>This vase is considered by Beazley to be an early work of the Berlin
                    Painter, one of the most prolific late archaic pot-painters in the Athenian
                    Kerameikos. While he generally preferred amorous pursuits, this scene of quiet
                    dalliance is admirably suited to the shape of the oinochoe.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Para., 345, 184 ter.</bibl>. On
                        scenes of youths and <hi rend="ital">hetairai:</hi>
                        <bibl>Rodenwaldt 1932, 7-21</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
                <byline>Jenifer Neils</byline>
            </div>
            <div n="64" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Jacksonville AP.66.28" type="vase"
                        >Jacksonville AP.66.28</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Black-Figure Eye Cup</title>
                    <rs type="collection">Collection of the Cummer Gallery of Art,
                        Jacksonville (AP.66.28)</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Group of Courting Cups [Shapiro]</rs>
                    <date>Ca. 520-500 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 10 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter: 21.25 cm.</measure> Side A: Man courting a
                    boy. Side B: Youth riding a hippalektryon.</p>
                <p>Scenes of homosexual courting between men and boys first appear on
                    Attic black-figure vases soon before the middle of the sixth century. In the
                    third and especially the last quarter of the century this becomes one of the
                    often repeated genre scenes in vase-painting. After 500 the scene's popularity
                    falls off sharply, and after about 475 it disappears entirely. Well over 100
                    representations are known in all.</p>
                <p>Sir John Beazley distinguished three stages in the courtship, and all
                    painted scenes illustrate one of the three: an initial encounter (type alpha);
                    the giving of gifts by the older man to the youth (type beta); and the
                    consummation, in which the pair are intertwined (type gamma; cf. <rs type="vase"
                        >Mississippi 1977.3.72</rs>). Type alpha is depicted most often,
                    and the Jacksonville vase is a typical example.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">On side A</hi>, the older lover (<hi
                    rend="ital">erastes</hi>) stands at the left and reaches out
                    both hands to his beloved (<hi rend="ital">eromenos</hi>). With his
                    left hand he chucks the boy's chin, as if to distract him while the lowered
                    right hand moves in on its target. The boy reaches out with his left, perhaps a
                    gesture of diffidence. Both are entirely nude, as is the rule in black-figure;
                    in red-figure versions one or both will often be at least partly draped. The
                    boy's hair is long and flows freely in the back, while the man's is bound by a
                    fillet. The wooer's knees are usually bent to compensate for his greater
                    stature.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">On side B</hi>, a youth rides a
                    hippalektryon, a mythical creature, half horse and half cock. It is one of many
                    hybrids - fantastic beasts composed of elements of two or more animals or, like
                    the centaur and the siren, part animal, part human - who populate Archaic Greek
                    vase-painting and sculpture. Most hybrids seem to have come into Greece from the
                    East, but there is no prototype of the hippalektryon in Egyptian or Near Eastern
                    Art. Nevertheless it appears regularly on Attic vases (and only Attic) from the
                    second quarter of the sixth century down to the end of the century or a little
                    later. The rider is usually, as here, an unarmed youth. The hippalektryon has no
                    mythology and is in fact scarcely mentioned by Greek writers: once in a lost
                    play of Aeschylus, as a device painted on a ship, and once by Aristophanes, who
                    implies that by his time (late fifth century) the average Athenian had never
                    heard of it. But the vase-painters are consistent in portraying it with the hind
                    legs of a cock and the forelegs of a horse, though attached to a cock's breast.</p>
                <p>This cup may be assigned to a group of nearly thirty vases assembled
                    by Beazley in <hi rend="ital">Paralipomena</hi> as the Group of
                    Courting Cups. They are eye cups (see <bibl>Shapiro
                        1981a, no. 13</bibl>) of Type A (a shallow bowl, plain lip, short, splaying
                    foot with a moulding separating it from the bowl). The whites of the eyes are
                    filled in with white paint, unlike those of earlier eye cups, which are mostly
                    left in outline. All but a few of the Courting Cups have a man and boy on one
                    side, and many repeat the motif on both sides. One has a youth on a
                    hippalektryon on both sides (<bibl>Para.,
                        83,22</bibl>). The choice of the courtship to decorate drinking cups that would
                    be used at all-male symposia is not surprising; the monotonous repetition of the
                    same formula and the hasty draughtsmanship show that the motif is nearing the
                    end of its artistic life.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p>Unpublished. On courtship scenes: <bibl
                        >J. D. Beazley, <title>Some Attic Vases in
                            the Cyprus Museum</title> (London 1948) 6-31</bibl>; <bibl
                                >Shapiro 1981b, 133-43</bibl>. On the
                        hippalektryon: <bibl>D. von Bothmer, in <title
                            >Bulletin of the Metropolitan Museum of Art</title>
                            11 (1953) 132-36</bibl>. Group of Courting Cups: <bibl
                                >Para., 82-83</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="65" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Fayetteville 56-25-28" type="vase"
                        >Fayetteville 56-25-28</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Red-Figure Lekythos</title>
                    <rs type="collection">Collection of the University of Arkansas
                        Museum, Fayetteville (57-27-42)</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Attributed to the Painter of London E 342</rs>
                    <date>Ca. 460 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 29.6 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter: 9.9 cm.</measure> Youth and Girl.</p>
                <p>A youth stands in profile to the right, stretching out both hands to
                    a young woman, who stands frontally but looks sideways at him. He is dressed in
                    a <hi rend="ital">himation;</hi> she wears a <hi rend="ital"
                        >peplos</hi> and a thin wrap, one end of it hanging from her
                    left arm, the other end held in her right hand. In her other hand she holds a
                    tall upright staff. The boy offers her an object, sizeable and slightly oblong:
                    perhaps a pomegranate, or else another fruit or a ball of wool. Two strokes in
                    added red projecting from the top could represent the stem of a fruit.</p>
                <p>Pomegranates were always a symbol of fertility in Greece, owing to
                    the profusion of juicy seeds. Several myths allude to the erotic associations of
                    the fruit, most notably the story of Persephone, who was raped by the god Hades,
                    then was obliged to remain half the year with her new husband in the Underworld
                    after she had eaten of a pomegranate. Hence the pomegranate appears occasionally
                    in vase-paintings as a love gift from a young man to his intended, or from
                    husband to wife, as on a pyxis in Athens (<bibl
                        >Para., 391, 88 bis</bibl>). Various other fruits and balls of wool serve
                    the same purpose on red-figure vases, as romantic love tokens between the sexes.
                    For the object on the Fayetteville lekythos, R. F. Sutton compares that on a
                    contemporary lekythos in Cassel (<bibl>Para., 402,
                        Nikon Painter, 33 bis</bibl>).</p>
                <p>The staff which the woman holds, normally an attribute only of
                    goddesses and queens, suggests that the painter may have intended to create a
                    heroized version of a popular romantic genre scene.</p>
                <p>The vase was assigned by Beazley to an artist of the Early Classical
                    period who painted many small neck amphoras, but also lekythoi and other small
                    vase shapes. Many of his scenes show a young man and woman, sometimes together
                    but more often on either side of the same vase. In four instances, other types
                    of gifts are exchanged (<bibl>ARV2, 668, 29-31 and
                        33</bibl>).</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>ARV2, 669, 45</bibl>; <bibl
                        >Maule 1971, 87-88 and pl. 21, 6</bibl>. On
                        love gifts of fruit and wool: <bibl>Sutton 1981,
                            320-26</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="66" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Fayetteville 56.25.15" type="vase"
                        >Fayetteville 56.25.15</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Red-Figure Kylix</title>
                    <rs type="collection">Collection of the University of Arkansas
                        Museum, Fayetteville (56.25.15)</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Attributed to Oltos [Hecht]</rs>
                    <date>Ca. 510 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 6.7 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter: 18.6 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter with handles: 24.5 cm.</measure> Interior:
                    Woman with krotala.</p>
                <p>This simple cup, undecorated on the exterior, has a single figure
                    within a reserved circle on the interior. She is a buxom woman, dressed in a
                    long pleated <hi rend="ital">chiton</hi> with an ample overfold at
                    the waist. Her curly, black hair is tied with a long red fillet and she sports a
                    round, black earring. She is moving to the left, perhaps dancing, as she holds a
                    pair of <hi rend="ital">krotala</hi> or castanets in her hands.</p>
                <p>The woman with her pinched nose, frowning mouth and excessively long
                    feet is typically Oltan. Oltos, whose name is known from two signed cups, was a
                    prolific cup-painter in the early years of red-figure (ca. 525-500 B.C.). He
                    depicted many such music-making women whose identification is determined by
                    their context. When accompanied by satyrs, they are clearly maenads; when nude
                    or at a symposium, obviously <hi rend="ital">hetairai</hi> or
                    prostitutes. Since neither this singleton nor her "sister" on a similar cup at
                    Mount Holyoke College (<bibl>Para., 328, 127
                        ter.</bibl>) has a clear-cut context, they remain simply dancing women.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl><title>Vente
                        Publique X</title> 22-23 June 1951 (Bale: Monnaies et
                        Médailles) pl. 20, no. 413</bibl>; <bibl
                            >ARV2, 66, 130</bibl>; <bibl
                                >Maule 1971, 86-87, pl. 21, figs. 1-2</bibl>. On Oltos: <bibl
                                    >Bruhn 1943</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
                <byline>Jenifer Neils</byline>
            </div>
            <div n="67" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Sarasota 1600.G3" type="vase">Sarasota
                        1600.G3</rs>
                </head>
                <p><title>Attic Red-Figure Cup</title>
                    <rs type="collection">Collection of the John and Mable Ringling
                        Museum of Art, Sarasota (1600. G3)</rs>
                    <rs type="painter">Unattributed</rs>
                    <date>500-475 B.C.</date>
                    <measure>Height: 12.7 cm.</measure>
                    <measure>Diameter (with handles): 36.56 cm.</measure>
                    Interior: Youth reclining at a symposium</p>
                <p>The exterior of the cup is undecorated. In the tondo, a beardless
                    youth reclines on a <hi rend="ital">kline,</hi> or couch, and leans
                    against a thick cushion with striped cover. His legs are enveloped in a heavy
                    cloak, one end of which is draped over his left arm, leaving his chest bare. He
                    also wears a fillet in his short, cap-like hair, decorated with leaves. In each
                    outstretched hand the youth holds a skyphos, a type of drinking vessel (cf.
                    <bibl>Shapiro 1981, no. 15</bibl>) with a
                    considerably larger capacity than a typical cup such as this one. In the
                    background hangs an object of spotted animal hide, probably a flute case.</p>
                <p>The scene is clearly meant to be understood as an excerpt from a
                    gathering of several drinkers. The youth sits up and twists his head, as if to
                    look back at a companion on the next <hi rend="ital">kline,</hi>
                    and one of the two skyphoi must be intended for a fellow symposiast. The flute
                    case alludes to the musical entertainment popular at such parties.</p>
                <p>Along the upper border of the scene is the inscription <foreign
                    xml:lang="greek">[epig-rough]*O *P*A*I*S</foreign> completed
                    by the word <foreign xml:lang="greek">*K*A*L*O*S</foreign> in the
                    exergue beneath the <hi rend="ital">kline</hi>: <hi rend="ital"
                        >Ho pais kalos</hi> ("the boy is beautiful"). This is typical of
                    the many inscriptions on Attic vases praising the beauty of a boy, often naming
                    him (cf. <rs type="vase">Mississippi 1977.3.103</rs>), but just as
                    often limited to the simple formula as we have it here. The formula may even be
                    added to scenes in which, unlike this one, there is no one to whom it may
                    plausibly refer.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p>Unpublished. On kalos inscriptions: <bibl
                        >Robinson &amp; Fluck</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
