<?xml version="1.0"?>





<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
	<title>Phintias and Euthymides</title>
	<author>Jenifer Neils</author>
	<sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor><principal>Gregory Crane</principal><respStmt><resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp><name>Lisa Cerrato</name></respStmt>
	&fund.NEA;
      </titleStmt>
	<publicationStmt><publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher><pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace><authority>Perseus Project</authority></publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
	<note anchored="true">Jenifer Neils, Case Western Reserve University</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
	<p>Created in electronic form.
      </p></sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>

    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl>
	<refState unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
	<language ident="en">English
	</language><language ident="greek">Greek
	</language><language ident="xgreek">Transliterated Greek
      </language></langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
    
    <revisionDesc><!--
      <change><date>24 September 1999</date>
	<respStmt><name>DAS</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>
	$Log: vp.pe.xml,v $
	Revision 1.1  2009-12-09 18:06:56  rsingh04
	moved more xml files around based on copyright status

	Revision 1.3  2009/03/04 21:44:15  lcerrato
	fixing bad bibls

	Revision 1.2  2005/08/18 13:56:34  packel
	fixed item tags

	Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 15:06:18  packel
	Converted to XML
	
Revision 1.8  2003/07/01 22:18:53  yorkc
Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)

Revision 1.7  2000/06/19 21:39:29  dasmith
Make all FIGURES REND="float".

Revision 1.6  2000/03/04 20:35:23  dasmith
Added separate funder entity to TEI header.

Revision 1.5  1999/09/24 22:19:50  dasmith
Converted to TEI2 tagging.


</item></change>
    --> <change when="2014-11-13" who="Stella Dee">edited markup and assigned CTS URN</change></revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
<text><body>
<div type="section" n="1"><head>Introduction</head>

<p>On a red-figure hydria now in Munich (<rs key="Perseus:object:Munich 2421" type="vase">Munich 2421</rs>; <bibl>FR, pl. 71, 1</bibl>) <note anchored="true" n="1"><p>Munich, Antikensammlungen 2421; <bibl>ARV2, 23, 7 and 1620</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 323</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 155</bibl>.</p></note> we see one of the first depictions of a subject which subsequently becomes more popular in Attic vase-painting, the music lesson. This one is typical in showing a seated youth, plektron in hand, strumming his lyre. Before him an older man, sitting on a <foreign xml:lang="xgreek">klismos</foreign> (chair) instead of a <foreign xml:lang="xgreek">diphros</foreign> (stool), holds the strings of his instrument still. Two onlookers, a draped youth, enveloped in his himation, and an older man leaning on his walking stick stand nearby. What makes this scene unusual is that its painter, Phintias, has labeled the music student Euthymides, the name of his younger colleague in the ceramics business. Such camaraderie is characteristic of the group of vase-painters whom Beazley dubbed the "Pioneers" because they were the first to realize the potential of the new red-figure technique invented ca. 530-520 B.C. They appear to have been a close-knit group, naming each other on their vases and rivaling one another in their attempts to depict naturalistic bodies in challenging poses.</p>

<p>If we glance up to the shoulder of this vase (<figure n="1990.34.0362" rend="float"></figure>), we see two half-draped hetairai, lounging on striped pillows and playing the drinking game kottabos, in which they flip the dregs of their wine toward an invisible target at the left. Out of the lips of the first hetaira, who turns around to address her comrade, comes a salute to Euthymides by means of the letters placed near her mouth: <foreign xml:lang="greek">*S*O*I*T*E*N*D*I *E*U*Q*U*M*I*D*E*I</foreign>. The implication of this remark is probably that she desires to be loved by the handsome youth. The somewhat awkward depiction of the breasts of the two women (<figure n="1990.34.0363" rend="float"></figure>, <figure n="1990.34.0364" rend="float"></figure>) shows how Phintias was struggling with the problem of foreshortening. In this particular detail, however, he was more successful than his fellow-Pioneer Euphronios who painted a similar scene on a psykter now in St. Petersburg (<rs key="Perseus:object:St. Petersburg B. 1650" type="vase">St. Petersburg B. 1650</rs>).</p>

<milestone ed="MD" unit="card"/>

<p>The Munich hydria belongs to the developed stage of Phintias' career as a vase-painter (ca. 510 B.C.), along with a similar vase in London signed by the artist (<rs key="Perseus:object:London E 159" type="vase">London E 159</rs>; <figure n="1990.14.0188" rend="float"></figure>).<note anchored="true" n="2"><p><bibl>ARV2, 24, 9 and 1620</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 155</bibl>.</p></note>  Both vases group four figures on the central panel, three facing to the right, one left, and two reclining half-draped figures on the shoulder. On the shoulder of the London hydria, we find two male symposiasts, also lying against striped pillows (<figure n="1990.14.0189" rend="float"></figure>), the older holding two kylixes, the younger a lyre. Below on the body panel are three nude boys hastening with their hydriai to the fountain house indicated by the lion-head waterspout at the far right, while an elder, draped man looks on. Scenes of water fetching are especially appropriate for water vessels, but as with the female revelers on the Munich hydria, Phintias has here reversed the traditional sex roles, for women are normally engaged in this activity. At this time (ca. 520-510 B.C.) there appeared a large number of late black-figure hydriai which show women at the fountain house, but this is one of the rare examples of males fetching water. <note anchored="true" n="3"><p>For a list of such fountain-house scenes in Attic black-figure, see <bibl>Dunkley 1935-36</bibl>, 152 ff.; <bibl>Diehl 1964, 230-231</bibl>. It should be noted that four youths are carrying hydriai on the Parthenon frieze, and that metal hydriai were the prize for the winners in the torchrace at the Panathenaia.</p></note>  With their head wreaths, curly hair, long fingers and feet, they closely resemble the music student on the Munich vase. Likewise the framing ornament of black-figure dotted palmettes below and simple meander above is the same on both vases. However, note the more advanced red-figure palmettes at the sides of the London vase, indicating that it is marginally later than the Munich hydria. During this experimental phase, artists who were no doubt trained in the earlier technique, only gradually abandoned black-figure conventions in favor of red-figure.</p></div>
 
<div type="section" n="2"><head>Mythological Scenes</head>
 
<p>While these two hydriai are devoted to scenes of daily life, at the beginning of his career Phintias expressed an interest in mythology. His earliest extant vase, a kylix in Munich signed by the potter Deiniades and dated to ca. 520 B.C. (<rs key="Perseus:object:Munich 2590" type="vase">Munich 2590</rs>)<note anchored="true" n="4"><p><bibl>ARV2, 24, 12</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 323</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 155</bibl>.</p></note> has a running satyr with a drinking horn in the tondo (<figure n="1993.01.0227" rend="float"></figure>). If we compare him to the satyr with two kantharoi in the tondo of one of his latest cups (<rs key="Perseus:object:Malibu 80.AE.31" type="vase">Malibu 80.AE.31</rs>; <figure n="1990.05.0467" rend="float"></figure>),<note anchored="true" n="5"><p><bibl>ARV2, 1620, 20 bis</bibl>. See <bibl>J. Frel, "A View into Phintias' Private Life," <title>Studies in Honor of Leo Mildenberg</title> (Wetteren 1984) 57-60, pls. 8-9</bibl>; <bibl>C. Weiss, "Phintias in Malibu und Karlsruhe," <title>Greek Vases in the J. Paul Getty Museum</title> 4, 1989, 83-94</bibl>.</p></note> we can see how far the artist has progressed in representing a figure in motion; note for instance the frontal chest of the early satyr and the attempted profile chest of the later one. The earlier satyr is posed much like running figures in the tondos of black-figure cups, and does not yet take advantage of the new technique which allows for overlapping of forms.</p>
 
<p>On the exterior of the Munich cup, Phintias has depicted two exploits of the hero Herakles: his attack on the sleeping giant Alkyoneus (<figure n="1990.34.0275" rend="float"></figure>), and his struggle with Apollo for the tripod (<figure n="1990.34.0277" rend="float"></figure>). Both compositions are carefully balanced with Herakles and Hermes on A and Herakles and Apollo on B mirror images of each other. Beazley called this cup "from the painter's nonage" and one can see clear signs of the influence of earlier artists such as Psiax and the Andokides Painter. For instance, the closed eye of Alkyoneus has lashes painted above and below just like the eye of Herakles' lionskin on the Andokides Painter's amphora in Boston (<rs key="Perseus:object:Boston 99.538" type="vase">Boston 99.538</rs>; <bibl>CB No. 115</bibl>; <figure n="1990.24.0385" rend="float"></figure>).</p>

<milestone ed="MD" unit="card"/>

<p>The struggle for the tripod is represented in a unique fashion on this cup: it resembles a wrestling match with Herakles and Apollo confronted, and the hero's quiver hanging in the background as if on the palaestra wall. In his later version of this scene, on a signed amphora (Type A) in Tarquinia (<rs key="Perseus:object:Tarquinia RC 6843" type="vase">Tarquinia RC 6843</rs>; <figure n="1993.01.0480" rend="float"></figure>),<note anchored="true" n="6"><p><bibl>ARV2, 23, 2 and 1620</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 323</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 155</bibl>.</p></note> Phintias adopts the traditional format: Herakles dashing off with Apollo in close pursuit.<note anchored="true" n="7"><p>On the struggle for the tripod in Greek art, see <bibl>D. von Bothmer in <title>Festschrift fur Frank Brommer</title> (Mainz 1977) 51-63</bibl>.</p></note>  But unlike the Andokides Painter (<rs key="Perseus:object:New York 63.11.6" type="vase">New York 63.11.6</rs>) and others who also favored this scene, Phintias leaves out the attendant goddesses and monumentalizes the antagonists, displaying their developed musculature in adventurous poses. Note the frontal legs and foreshortened feet, so typical of the Pioneers. Herakles, normally a bearded man, is here shown as a handsome youth with beautifully coiffed curls rendered in relief, downy sideburns executed with dilute glaze, and carefully drawn eyelashes. This composition was copied by a fellow Pioneer on an unattributed amphora in Boston (<rs key="Perseus:object:Boston 63.1515" type="vase">Boston 63.1515</rs>; <figure n="1990.24.0471" rend="float"></figure>),<note anchored="true" n="8"><p><bibl>ARV2, 1705</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 324, 7 bis</bibl>.</p></note> but this lesser artist felt the necessity of placing a palm tree between the protagonists, and depicted Herakles in the traditional fashion with a beard (<figure n="1990.24.0472" rend="float"></figure>).</p>
 
<p>The reverses of both amphoras show Dionysiac revelers. On the Boston vase (<figure n="1990.24.0473" rend="float"></figure>) there is a somewhat tame maenad with two vines in the center, flanked by two excited satyrs (<figure n="1990.24.0474" rend="float"></figure>). The scene on the vase by Phintias in Tarquinia is much more ambitious with five figures overflowing the panel. Dressed in a long chiton and himation, a stately Dionysos stands in the center, holding a grape-laden vine and his common attribute, the kantharos. A maenad armed with a thyrsos and embraced by a satyr cavorts on either side. Phintias here shows off his skills as a mature red- figure painter; from eyelashes and fingernails to complex groupings of overlapping satyr, panther and maenad, the vase is a tour de force. Telltale signs of his hand are the neck of the chiton rendered with three parallel lines, and the U) anklebone, and the wrinkled frontal face of the satyr at the left.</p>
 
<p>Another early vase illustrates Phintias' initial interest in myth and his preferred composition for panels of large vases: three figures moving to right, and a fourth acting as a caesura by facing left. In the case of his amphora in Paris (<rs key="Perseus:object:Louvre G 42" type="vase">Louvre G 42</rs>; <figure n="1992.06.0413" rend="float"></figure>),<note anchored="true" n="9"><p><bibl>ARV2, 23, 1 and 1620</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 323</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 154</bibl>.</p></note> the figures are Apollo coming to the rescue of his mother Leto who is being abducted by Tityos, while Artemis, bow in hand, looks on from the right on the obverse. On the reverse is a trainer with three athletes (<figure n="1992.06.0417" rend="float"></figure>). This vase can be placed after the Tarquinia amphora because on the obverse the border ornament is three-quarters red-figure (but still three-quarters black-figure on the reverse: <figure n="1992.06.0415" rend="float"></figure>), and the intricate detailing has subsided. However, Phintias still shows his fondness for "buckellöchen" or small glazed dots in relief used to indicate curly hair (<figure n="1992.06.0430" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1992.06.0424" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1992.06.0439" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1992.06.0448" rend="float"></figure>), an early Pioneer trait. Also early is the continued used of incision, as on the hair of Apollo (<figure n="1992.06.0423" rend="float"></figure>) and Artemis (<figure n="1992.06.0434" rend="float"></figure>). Like incision, added red is characteristic of black-figure, and one sees its continued use in early red-figure, especially for wreaths (<figure n="1992.06.0439" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1992.06.0444" rend="float"></figure>).</p></div>
 
<div type="section" n="3"><head>The Gymnasium</head>

<p>Along with the schoolroom and the dining room, the gymnasium was a part of every young male Athenian's life, and so is a common theme in Attic vase-painting. It was particularly favored by the Pioneers since athletic scenes allowed them to depict the nude body in a variety of positions. Such poses were also a preoccupation of contemporary sculptors, as evidenced by the marble kouros base in Athens (<rs key="Perseus:object:Athens, NM 3476" type="sculpture">Athens, NM 3476</rs>) which is decorated with athletes in relief against a red background. It is constructive to compare the pose of the frontal acontist testing the bindings of his javelin on the reverse of the Paris amphora (<figure n="1992.06.0446" rend="float"></figure>) with that of the ballplayer on the relief. Both attempt to depict a frontal leg and twisting abdomen as realistically as possible. If one turns to a later vase by Phintias, the psykter in Boston (<rs key="Perseus:object:Boston 01.8019" type="vase">Boston 01.8019</rs>; <bibl>CB No. 67</bibl>; <figure n="1990.24.0468" rend="float"></figure>),<note anchored="true" n="10"><p><bibl>ARV2, 24, 11 and 1620</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 155</bibl>.</p></note> one can find an even closer parallel for the relief base; the acontist is in the exact same pose as his counterpart on the relief.</p>
 
<p>All twelve individuals on the Boston psykter are named. The acontist instructing his companion (<figure n="1990.24.0470" rend="float"></figure>) at the far left bears the name <foreign xml:lang="greek">*F*A*U*L*O[*S]</foreign>. Phayllos was a pentathlete from Croton famous for winning three victories at the Pythian Games at Delphi and for commanding the only West Greek ship at the battle of Salamis. The name appears on three other Pioneer vases: an amphora in Munich where he is about to throw the discus (<rs key="Perseus:object:Munich 2308" type="vase">Munich 2308</rs>; <figure n="1990.34.0260" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1990.34.0271" rend="float"></figure>),<note anchored="true" n="11"><p><bibl>ARV2, 26, 2 and 1620</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 156</bibl>.</p></note> on a neck-amphora in Malibu where he is in the process of hurling the discus (<rs key="Perseus:object:Malibu 84.AE.63" type="vase">Malibu 84.AE.63</rs>; <figure n="1990.05.0254" rend="float"></figure>);<note anchored="true" n="12"><p><bibl><title>Getty Museum Journal</title> 13, 1985, 168, 17</bibl>; J. Paul Getty Museum, <title>Handbook of the Collection</title> (1986) 48.</p></note> and another psykter in Turin where he is using a strigil.<note anchored="true" n="13"><p><rs key="Perseus:object:Turin 4123" type="vase">Turin 4123</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 28, 11 and 1620</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 156</bibl>.</p></note> The first and third of these vases are signed by the painter Euthymides son of Pollias, whom Phintias named twice on his hydria in Munich discussed earlier, and the second is attributed to him. The use of this name demonstrates another connection between the two artists. They also share the kalos-name Megakles, which could be a reference to a contemporary Athenian, a member of the prominent Alkmaionid family, who was ostracized in 487 B.C.<note anchored="true" n="14"><p><foreign xml:lang="xgreek">Megakles kalos</foreign> appears on the hydria in London (<rs key="Perseus:object:London E 159" type="vase">London E 159</rs>) by Phintias and a hydria in Bonn (<bibl>ARV2, 28, 12</bibl>) signed by Euthymides as painter.</p></note> The name of Megakles was also once painted on a large terracotta polychrome plaque decorated with a warrior found on the Athenian Acropolis (<rs key="Perseus:object:Athens, Acr. 1037" type="sculpture">Athens, Acr. 1037</rs>), but was partially erased in favor of another name, perhaps after Megakles' ostracism. Another Acropolis plaque, this decorated with a black-figure Athena (<rs key="Perseus:object:Athens, Acr. 2590" type="scuplture">Athens, Acr. 2590</rs>; Graef/Langlotz pl. 109), was dedicated by Pollias, undoubtedly the vase-painter's father and the sculptor who signed several statue bases found on the Acropolis. Since the painting on the first of these two plaques is related to the style of Euthymides, it seems likely that they came from his workshop, suggesting that vase-painters might have been monumental painters as well.<note anchored="true" n="15"><p>See <bibl>J. Boardman, JHS 76, 1956, 20-22</bibl>.</p></note></p></div>

<div type="section" n="4"><head>"As never Euphronios"</head>
 
<p>Euthymides' most famous inscription appears on an amphora in Munich (<rs key="Perseus:object:Munich 2307" type="vase">Munich 2307</rs>; <figure n="1990.33.0508.lg" rend="float"></figure>):<note anchored="true" n="16"><p><bibl>ARV2, 26, 1 and 1620</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 323</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 155-156</bibl>.</p></note> it reads <foreign xml:lang="greek">&epig-rough;*O*S*O*U*D*E*P*O*T*E*E*U*F*R*O*N*I*O*N</foreign>. Beazley took this "as never Euphronios" to be a light-hearted challenge to a comrade, while others saw it as a cry of senile jealousy. More recently it has been suggested that the words mean something like "Euphronios never revelled like us", since the three figures on this side of the vases are komasts.<note anchored="true" n="17"><p>See <bibl>G. Neumann, "Zu einige Beischriften auf Münchner Vasen," <title>AA</title> 1977, 38-43</bibl>; <bibl>H. Engelmann, " 'Wie nie Euphronios'," <title>ZPE</title> 68, 1987, 129-133</bibl>.</p></note> Whether the words indicate occupational rivalry or a humorous taunt, they demonstrate again the close personal and professional interrelationships of the Pioneer vase-painters.</p></div>
 
<div type="section" n="5"><head>Composition and Style</head>

<p>As one can see on this amphora and others (for instance, <figure n="1990.34.0260" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1990.34.0261" rend="float"></figure>), Euthymides' preferred composition is three figures to a panel (in contrast to Phintias' four) with those at the sides acting as parentheses for the central figure, a tradition carried on by the Kleophrades Painter. This reduction allows the artist leeway for bigger, beefier figures who contort their bodies as they revel, so that the viewer is given profile, back and frontal views of the male anatomy. The simple arming scene on the obverse is repeated on another amphora in Munich (<rs key="Perseus:object:Munich 2308" type="vase">Munich 2308</rs>; <figure n="1990.34.0261" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1990.34.0262" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1993.01.0441" rend="float"></figure>).<note anchored="true" n="18"><p><bibl>ARV2, 26-27, 2 and 1620</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 156</bibl>.</p></note> Although the two youthful warriors are identical, on the first vase he is labeled Hektor and is accompanied by his parents, King Priam and Hecuba, while on the second he is named Thorykion and is flanked by archers in Scythian garb (<figure n="1990.34.0267" rend="float"></figure>). Thorykion is otherwise unknown but since the word means "wearer of a breastplate", the name is certainly apt. He and Hektor both bend their heads downwards (<figure n="1990.34.0265" rend="float"></figure>), in a pose favored by Euthymides, while they concentrate on fastening their cuirasses.</p>
 
<p>On an amphora attributed to Euthymides in the Louvre (<rs key="Perseus:object:Louvre G 44" type="vase">Louvre G 44</rs>),<note anchored="true" n="19"><p><bibl>ARV2, 27, 3</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 156</bibl></p></note> one sees many of the characteristics of the artist's hand: the bowed head (<figure n="1992.06.1472" rend="float"></figure>); the long, flat space between thumb and fingers (<figure n="1992.06.1475" rend="float"></figure>), the evenly stacked drapery folds (<figure n="1992.06.1478" rend="float"></figure>), and the palmette ornament with upward curling tendrils (<figure n="1992.06.1473" rend="float"></figure>).</p>
 
<milestone ed="MD" unit="card"/>

<p>Euthymides' most successful composition is Theseus' abduction of Helen which covers both sides of an amphora in Munich (<rs key="Perseus:object:Munich 2309" type="vase">Munich 2309</rs>; <figure n="1993.01.0229" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1993.01.0228" rend="float"></figure>)<note anchored="true" n="20"><p><bibl>ARV2, 27, 4 and 1620</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 323</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 156</bibl>.</p></note>. Theseus' hold on the young girl resembles a wrestling pose as he lifts her off the ground.  Behind him another girl named Korone (the girls' names are actually interchanged) attempts to free Helen, while the fourth figure, Theseus' comrade Peirithoos, looks behind, presumably at the two girls racing along on the other side of the vase. Behind them is the only motionless figure, an older man, who, in Pioneer fashion, speaks the words: <foreign xml:lang="greek">*X*A*I*R*E*X*Q*E*S*E*U*S</foreign>, "Greetings Theseus."</p>
 
<p>Euthymides' asymmetrical composition, wide-striding poses, flowing drapery, and backward glances contribute to the drama of the narrative, and the human element is conveyed by the tender touch of Helen's hand to her abductor's hair.  It is tempting to compare this abduction with the earlier one by Phintias (<rs key="Perseus:object:Louvre G 42" type="vase">Louvre G 42</rs>; <figure n="1992.06.0413" rend="float"></figure>). Beazley assessed the latter as follows: "how fussy and petty, for all its scrupulous virtuosity, when it is placed beside the grandeur of Theseus and his bride."</p></div>

<div type="section" n="6"><head>Conclusion</head>

<p>Thus, in the end Euthymides outdistanced his colleague Phintias, but throughout their careers they shared many qualities. As we have seen, their figures are lively, not only physically but also verbally. They, more than their successors the Berlin and Kleophrades Painters, decorated large as well as small vases. They both signed many of their works as painter, and in a few instances as potter.<note anchored="true" n="21"><p>Phintias' signature as potter is preserved on a cup in Athens (<rs key="Perseus:object:Athens, NM 1628" type="vase">Athens, NM 1628</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 25, 1</bibl>) and two cockle-shell aryballoi (<bibl>ARV2, 25, 2-3</bibl>). Euthymides' incised signature as potter is preserved on an oinochoe in New York (<rs key="Perseus:object:New York 1981.11.9" type="vase">New York 1981.11.9</rs>;<bibl> Beazley Addenda 2, 404-405</bibl>) and on a stand in the Agora (<bibl>ARV2, 28, 17</bibl>). See <bibl>H. Immerwahr,<title>Attic Script: A Survey</title> (Oxford 1990) 72</bibl>.</p></note> demonstrating that they, like Euphronios, were skilled in both techniques or owned pottery establishments. A cup now in Baltimore (<rs key="Perseus:object:Baltimore, Hopkins AIA B4" type="vase">Baltimore, Hopkins AIA B4</rs>; <figure n="1990.06.0094" rend="float"></figure>) <note anchored="true" n="22"><p><bibl>ARV2, 24, 14</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 323</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 155</bibl>.</p></note> may have served as an advertisement for such an establishment. Decorated in the tondo only, it shows a youth, money sack in hand (<figure n="1990.06.0098" rend="float"></figure>), bending over to inspect a group of pots: a skyphos, a neck-amphora in a stand, and a kylix (<figure n="1990.06.0099" rend="float"></figure>). It is tempting to think that these are the wares of Phintias who signed the vase as painter, or his friend Euthymides, and that the scene alludes to their success as ceramicists in late-sixth century Athens.</p>
</div>
</body></text></TEI>
