<?xml version="1.0"?>





<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Archaeological Collection of the Johns Hopkins University
                    (Selections)</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Ellen Reeder Williams</author>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <idno type="ISBN">0801830508</idno>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState n="chunk" unit="entry"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    	<revisionDesc><!--
    		<change><date>5/27/09</date><respStmt><name>RS</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt>
    			<item>  
    				$Log: rw.xml,v $
    				Revision 1.1  2009-10-08 19:10:56  rsingh04
    				began reorganizing texts module by collection.  created separate work directory in texts module to keep hopper files separate from in progress files

    				Revision 1.6  2009/06/19 19:02:01  lcerrato
    				fixed bad bibls

    				Revision 1.5  2009/05/27 15:55:16  rsingh04
    				added cvs log keyword

    			</item>
    		</change>
    	--> <change when="2014-11-13" who="Stella Dee">edited markup and assigned CTS URN</change></revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div n="98" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Baltimore, Hopkins K116" type="vase"
                        >Baltimore, Hopkins K116</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>Boeotian Trefoil Oinochoe</title>
                    <date>750-720 B.C.</date>
                </p>
                <p>K 116. Kemper Simpson Collection. Ht, 22.5 cm; diam foot, 9.6 cm; max
                    diam mouth, 8.2 cm. Intact.</p>
                <p>Glaze orange-brown. Solid glazed neck. Principal zone of decoration
                    in panel opposite handle on shoulder, bounded beneath by three horizontal lines.
                    Long-legged bird stands in right profile beneath a zigzag. In front of him is
                    four-spoked wheel with short strokes radiating outward from circumference and
                    with circle enclosing dot between each spoke. Beneath this panel are six
                    vertical lines, alternately wavy and straight. Each side of body occupied by
                    seven concentric circles. Strap handle has wavy line down center and a line down
                    each side continuing across its base above long-legged bird in right profile.
                    Horizontal band encircles foot of vase.</p>
                <p>This jug exemplifies the heavily Atticizing character of late
                    geometric Boeotian vasepainting.<note n="1" place="unspecified" anchored="true"
                       >
                        <p><bibl>Coldstream 1968,
                            196-211</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> The class to which our vase belongs was produced in the Oinochoe
                    Workshop in Thebes<note n="2" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Ruckert 1976, 17, 41-44,
                                59-60</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> and was inspired by Attic oinochoai of the Concentric Circle group,
                    which are dated by Coldstream between 750 and 720 B.C.<note n="3"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Coldstream 1968, 74-76,
                                330-31, LG Ib 750-735 and LG IIa 735-720</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> The Attic vases have been found only in Attica and bear motifs
                    associated with contests, such as tripods, double axes, and horses; for this
                    reason it is suggested that these Attic oinochoai served primarily as
                        prizes.<note n="4" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Karageorghis 1975,
                            172</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> In contrast, we can conclude that the Boeotian oinochoai were primarily
                    funerary because the wavy bands on the handles surely echo the plastic snakes on
                    Boeotian vessels that were destined for burial.<note n="5" place="unspecified"
                        anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Coldstream 1977,
                            201</bibl>.</p>
                    </note></p>
                <p>The Boeotian oinochoai reflect their Attic prototypes both in the
                    shape and in the technique, whereby brown paint is applied directly to the
                    surface without slip.<note n="6" place="unspecified" anchored="true"
                       >
                        <p><bibl>Ruckert 1976, 17,
                            59</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> Most of the decorative scheme is also similar: the solid glazed neck,
                    the concentric circles on each side of the body, and the horizontal band around
                    the foot. In the panel scene on the shoulder, however, the Boeotian artist
                    introduces horizontal zigzags and crosshatched triangles, which are often
                    detached on other Boeotian examples of this same class.<note n="7"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Coldstream 1968,
                            210</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> And, in contrast to the striding Attic birds, the Boeotian counterparts
                    are stationary and long-legged.<note n="8" place="unspecified" anchored="true"
                       >
                        <p><bibl>Ruckert 1976,
                        43</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> On the Attic vases, beneath the panel there is a series of horizontal
                    lines, but on the Boeotian jugs they are replaced by straight or wavy vertical
                    lines, which are possibly derived from Corinthian vasepainting.<note n="9"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>F. Canciani, <title
                                   >JdI</title> 80 (1965):68</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> On the basis of the profiles and the painted snakes on the handles, the
                    Boeotian oinochoai are thought to be contemporary with their Attic counterparts
                    and thus also to date to the period 750 to 720 B.C.<note n="10"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Ruckert 1976, 17, 41,
                                43-44, I 750-735 and II 735-720</bibl>.</p>
                    </note></p>
                <p>The ultimate origin of the shape and the concentric circles lies in
                    Cypriot Ware, Bichrome IV,<note n="11" place="unspecified" anchored="true"
                       >
                        <p><bibl>Karageorghis 1975,
                            172</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> and possibly in Mycenaean pottery. Perhaps also of Cypriot inspiration
                    are the double axes that appear on the Attic examples.<note n="12"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Karageorghis 1975,
                            172-73</bibl>.</p>
                    </note></p>
                <milestone n="133" unit="page"/>
            </div>
            <div n="99" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Baltimore, Hopkins BMA 60.55.2" type="vase"
                        >Baltimore, Hopkins BMA 60.55.2</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>Black-Figure Amphora with Herakles and Amazons</title>
                    <date>550-500 B.C.</date>
                </p>
                <p>60.55.2. Baltimore Museum of Art, formerly Robinson Collection, from
                    Barden Collection of Hamburg. "Gela." Ht, 54.2 cm; diam mouth, 34.4 cm; diam
                    foot, 20.8 cm. Dull black glaze, chipped. Intact.</p>
                <p>Upper surface of rim reserved. Reserved ring molding between body and
                    foot. Neck glazed inside to depth of 3.6 cm.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="ital">Side A</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Figures stand on glazed groundline. Herakles moves to his left, with
                    left leg upraised. He wears chiton beneath lionskin, with scalp brought up over
                    head, paws tied at neck, tail flying out behind. Bowcase over shoulder, scabbard
                    at waist. His right hand holds a dagger, which he is about to thrust at his
                    opponent, while his left hand is hidden by her shield. She is moving away from
                    Herakles, with her legs in right profile, her left leg advanced. She turns back
                    to Herakles, her right arm uplifted with a spear, her head and crested helmet in
                    left profile, and over her left arm a shield with emblem of serpent and ball.
                    She wears a chiton beneath a muscle cuirass, which is shown frontally, and an
                    animal skin. On either side of the pair are two Amazons, each in crested helmet,
                    short chiton, and cloak, with shield and spear. Devices on shields are, from
                    left: pellets, bull's head (?), disc, tripod.</p>
                <p>Added red: eyes, cloaks, shield rims of all Amazons. 1 and 2: skirt,
                    3: lion-skin, 4: skirt, 5: plume of helmet, 6: panels in skirt.</p>
                <milestone n="134" unit="page"/>
                <p>Added white: flesh of Amazons, devices of shields, dots in borders
                    below helmet plumes, lion tusks, Herakles' baldric, sections of plumes on
                    helmets of 2 and 5.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="ital">Side B</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Figures stand on glazed groundline. Dionysos, in center in right
                    profile, wears a himation and ivy wreath and carries kantharos in uplifted left
                    hand. Four vine branches wind away from shoulder. Flanking him on each side is
                    maenad with long hair and wreath, wearing a long chiton with incised crosses at
                    waist and incised dotted border at neckline. Maenad facing Dionysos wears short
                    jacket. Nude satyr seen in profile at each side of scene.</p>
                <p>Added red: panels in skirts, dots at waist, centers of eyes, curls of
                    maenads, leaves of ivy wreaths. Added white: flesh of maenads.</p>
                <p>Lotus and palmette above picture on side A. Chain of lotus buds above
                    picture on side B. Rays around base. Two red lines around neck and two more
                    below each picture (one line above rays, one around foot).</p>
                <p>The uninterrupted profile of neck and shoulder classifies the form of
                    this amphora as Type B, examples of which are commonly found among black-figure
                    vases of the second half of the sixth century. The amphorae are usually
                    ornamented with a ray pattern around the foot and ivy or lotus patterns above
                    the pictures, which commonly portray mythological battles or Dionysiac revelry.</p>
                <p>The obverse of our amphora illustrates a popular myth, the
                    representations of which have been thoroughly examined by von Bothmer. Our
                    composition belongs within Bothmer's category C. examples of which first
                    appeared after 550 B.C. and depict an unassisted Herakles in combat with three
                    or more Amazons.<note n="1" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>von Bothmer 1957,
                            30</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> Our scene belongs in subsection gamma,<note n="2" place="unspecified"
                        anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>von Bothmer 1957,
                            56</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> because the retreating Amazon directly behind Herakles is dressed as a
                    hoplite and glances behind her as she flees. Our representation is also related
                    to compositions of subsection alpha,<note n="3" place="unspecified"
                        anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>von Bothmer 1957,
                            53</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> where there is only a single Amazon behind Herakles, but one with the
                    pose and gesture of the Amazon who stands at the viewer's far left side of our
                    panel.</p>
                <p>Typical of representations of Herakles and the Amazons after 550 are
                    Herakles' choice of club or sword rather than spear,<note n="4"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>von Bothmer 1957,
                            31</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> and the use of the Attic helmet with oblong or L-shaped
                        cheekpieces.<note n="5" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>von Bothmer 1957, 33,
                            59</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> Both the position of Herakles' left arm behind the shield<note n="6"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>von Bothmer 1957, pls. 30.1
                                and 39.1</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> and the gesture of the right sword arm<note n="7" place="unspecified"
                        anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>von Bothmer 1957, pl.
                            41.4</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> are paralleled in other representatives of this conflict.</p>
                <milestone n="136" unit="page"/>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>CVA, USA fasc. 4, Robinson
                            fasc. 1, 43-44, pls. XXV.2, XXVI, XXVII</bibl>; <bibl
                           >von Bothmer 1957, 57, no. 183, pl. 45.3</bibl>; <bibl
                           >Brommer 1973, 13, no. 17</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="100" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Baltimore, Hopkins AIA B64" type="vase"
                        >Baltimore, Hopkins AIA B64</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>Nikosthenic Amphora</title>
                    <date>540-530 B.C.</date>
                </p>
                <p>B 64. Baltimore Society AIA, formerly Helbig Collection. Ht, 30 cm;
                    max w across handles, 20.9 cm; diam at rim, 11.3 cm; diam of foot, 10.1 cm.
                    Mended from several pieces, with part of lip and neck restored.</p>
                <p>Ray pattern around rim. Inside neck are three glazed bands of varying
                    heights separated by reserved strips. Strap handles have central vertical line
                    flanked by bands of rays. On each side of neck is a combat between two pairs of
                    boxers shown in profile. Added red on hair. Beneath foot of boxers on side A is
                    signature: <foreign xml:lang="greek"
                        >*N*I*K*O*S*Q[*E]*N*E*S*M*E*P*O*I*E*S*E*N</foreign>.</p>
                <p>Beneath neck, principal zone of decoration lies between two raised
                    ridges around center of body and consists of double row of ivy leaves. Above is
                    band of tongues above rightward key pattern. Beneath are bands of: tongue, rays,
                    reserved zigzag upon a glazed background, and rays. Between body and foot is
                    glazed ridge with incised groove on either side. Foot has echinus shape, with
                    vertical side reserved.</p>
                <p>Soon after 550 B.C., the Attic potter Nikosthenes<note n="1"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p>For Nikosthenes, <bibl>ABV,
                                216-23</bibl> and <bibl>Para.,
                            108-9</bibl>; <bibl>Boardman 1974,
                            64</bibl>; <bibl>M. Eisman, <title
                                   >GettyMusJ</title> 1 (1974):43-54</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> created a distinctive Attic version of a type of Etruscan bucchero
                    amphora that originated in Caere (see <bibl>E.R.
                        Williams 1984, no. 125</bibl>). He retained the wide lip, strap handles, and
                    ridges around the body, but he substituted black-figure decoration for the
                    relief ornament on the Etruscan prototype. All of the one hundred or more
                    surviving Nikosthenic amphorae that have a provenance are said to come from
                    Caere; therefore, it appears that the Attic version was made specifically for
                    the city where the prototype originated.</p>
                <p>Most of the Nikosthenic amphorae are signed by Nikosthenes as potter
                    or shopowner, but none bears the signature of a painter. Beazley believed that
                    all the amphorae were painted by a single hand, whom he called Painter N. More
                    recently it has been proposed that we broaden this designation to the Group of
                    Nikosthenes, since it is plausible that several artists, including apprentices,
                    participated in the decoration of the vases.<note n="2" place="unspecified"
                        anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Eisman, <title
                                   >GettyMusJ</title> 1 (1974):48</bibl>.</p>
                    </note></p>
                <p>The Hopkins vase is typical of Nikosthenic amphorae both in the
                    patterns and the representations of boxers.<note n="3" place="unspecified"
                        anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Ibid., 45. Our vase is no.
                                2 in the list of boxing scenes in footnote 18</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> The shape, with the pronounced spherical body, is somewhat unusual,
                    although Beazley noted that the echinus foot appears in the "B"
                        Torlonia<milestone n="137" unit="page"/> group assigned
                    to the early years of Nikosthenes' career, about 550 B.C.<note n="4"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>ABV, 220</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> It does indeed seem that the Hopkins example belongs among the early or
                    middle phases, since the later amphorae, made around 520 B.C., have a more
                    elongated neck and tapering body, and a greater simplicity of ornament that
                    compares closely with decorative patterns employed on other black-figure vases
                    of the last third of the sixth century.<note n="5" place="unspecified"
                        anchored="true">
                        <p>Eisman [<bibl><title
                                   >GettyMusJ</title> 1 (1974):52 no. 48</bibl>]
                            believes that the latest amphorae date from about 515. Boardman [<bibl
                               >Boardman 1974, 64</bibl>] thinks that
                            the workshop was active to about 510 B.C.</p>
                    </note></p>
                <p>The workshop of the potter Nikosthenes was certainly one of the
                    larger and more innovative Attic studios between 550 and 510 B.C. The Six
                    technique may have originated here, as may have the practice of applying a
                    white-ground background to black-figure ware. The shop certainly introduced the
                    kyathos, which was inspired by an Etruscan shape. Prominent painters, such as
                    Oltos, Psiax, Epiktetos, and the Theseus Painter, are thought to have been
                    associated with this establishment.<note n="6" place="unspecified"
                        anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Boardman 1974, 64</bibl>;
                                <bibl>Eisman, <title
                                    >GettyMusJ</title> 1 (1974):48-49</bibl>.</p>
                    </note></p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>FR, 252, no. 2</bibl>; <bibl
                           >D. M. Robinson, <title
                            >AJA</title> 26 (1922):54-58</bibl>; <bibl
                            >Hoppin 1924, 179</bibl>; <bibl>CVA, USA
                            fasc. 4 Robinson fasc. 1, 43, pls. XXIV.2, XXV.1</bibl>; <bibl
                           >ABV, 220, no. 336</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="101" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Baltimore, Hopkins AIA B1" type="vase"
                        >Baltimore, Hopkins AIA B1</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>Fragment from Kylix by Oltos</title>
                    <date>ca. 520 B.C.</date>
                </p>
                <p>B 1. Baltimore Society AIA, formerly Hartwig Collection. Max ht, 5
                    cm; max 1, 7.7 cm. Part of exterior decoration of kylix with upper edge
                    belonging to original rim.</p>
                <p>Maenad moves to her right; torso frontal, head in left profile. She
                    wears chiton, himation fastened over right shoulder, and panther skin knotted at
                    throat. Her left elbow is bent, with a pine branch in left hand. Her hair is
                    drawn behind the ears, bent up at nape, and fastened to back of head with
                    fillet. Disc earrings, bracelet on left wrist. Behind her are the extended
                    fingers of a right hand.</p>
                <p>Relief contour throughout. Dilute glaze for mouth and inner line of
                    ear. Added purple for fillet, leaves, bracelet. Hairline incised.</p>
                <p>This fragment arrived at the university as part of the restored
                    sections of the kylix by the Pistoxenos Painter (<rs type="vase"
                        >Baltimore, Hopkins AIA B12</rs>). Subsequently, Beazley recognized the
                    Hopkins piece to be part of the exterior of a kylix to which fragments in
                    Florence, Heidelberg, Braunschweig, Bowdoin, and the Villa Giulia also belong
                    (see <hi rend="ital">above,</hi> Beazley pl. X; and <rs type="vase"
                       >Bowdoin 1913.14</rs>).<note n="1" place="unspecified"
                        anchored="true">
                        <p>For Oltos, see <bibl>J. D.
                                Beazley, <title>JHS</title> 58 (1938):267</bibl>;
                                <bibl>Boardman 1975, 56-57</bibl>; <bibl
                               >ARV2, 53-67</bibl>; <bibl
                               >Para., 326-28</bibl>; <bibl
                               >Beazley Addenda 2, 1933, 7, pls. I.21, 23</bibl>; X.
                            The Bowdoin fragment appears in <bibl
                                >Buitron 1972, 69, no. 30</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> The maenad on our segment formed part of a procession of satyrs and
                    maenads whose counterparts on the opposite side are a fleeing girl and two men.
                    In the tondo was a representation of Pegasus, together with the signature of
                    Kachrylion, the prominent Attic potter for whom Phintias (see <rs type="vase"
                       >Baltimore, Hopkins AIA B4</rs>) and the Kiss Painter (see <rs
                        type="vase">Baltimore, Hopkins AIA B5</rs>) may also have
                        worked.<note n="2" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Bloesch 1940,
                        45-50</bibl>.</p>
                    </note></p>
                <p>Oltos was one of the most skilled early artists of red-figure
                        vasepainting.<note n="3" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>E. Finkenstaedt, <title
                                   >AJA</title> 72 (1968): 383, pl. 129</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> He signed two cups and is accredited with over one hundred fifty vessels
                    in all. Although he primarily painted kylixes, he also worked on amphorae,
                    psykters, stamnoi, and a kyathos. He was employed by the best potters of his
                    age, including Kachrylion, Nikosthenes, Pamphaios, and Hischylos.<note n="4"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Bloesch 1940, 31, 33,
                                45-50, 64</bibl>; <bibl>ARV2,
                        53</bibl>.</p>
                    </note></p>
                <p>The artist's distinctive style can be recognized in the stumpy bodies
                    and the square heads with long noses and narrow, elongated eyes. Also
                    characteristic is the patterning of the extended figures. Oltos's use of relief
                    line was extensive and particularly skilled.</p>
                <milestone n="138" unit="page"/>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Philippart 1928, 50</bibl>;
                            <bibl>D. M. Robinson, <title
                                >AJA</title> 21 (1917): 167, fig. 7</bibl>; <bibl
                           >Beazley 1918, 7, 12, no. 51</bibl>; <bibl
                           >Hoppin 1919, vol. II, 261, no. 47c</bibl>; <bibl
                           >Beazley 1925, 17, no. 70</bibl>; <bibl
                           >Beazley 1933a, pl. X</bibl>; <bibl
                           >CVA, USA fasc. 6, Robinson fasc. 2, 11, pl.
                            I.1</bibl>; <bibl>ARV2, 59, no.
                    55</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="102" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Baltimore, Hopkins AIA B4" type="vase"
                        >Baltimore, Hopkins AIA B4</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>Kylix by Phintias</title>
                    <date>520-510 B.C.</date>
                </p>
                <p>B 4. Baltimore Society AIA, formerly Hartwig Collection. Ht, 7 cm;
                    diam with handles, 25 cm; diam rim, 18.5 cm; diam foot, 7.4 cm. Mended from many
                    pieces.</p>
                <p>Tondo is bordered by narrow reserved band. Youth stands in right
                    profile, a mantle thrown over his left shoulder, exposing only right shoulder
                    and breast. Vine wreath in hair. He has just arisen from a stool and leans
                    forward with both arms outstretched, money bag in left hand, fingers of right
                    hand extended, staff leaning against left shoulder. In front of him are a
                    skyphos, amphora set in a stand, and a kylix resting in rim of amphora.
                    Inscribed in field:</p>
                <p><foreign xml:lang="greek">*F*I*N[*T*I]*A*S
                        *E*G*R*A*F*S*E*N *X*A*I*R*I*A*S *K*A*L*O*S</foreign>.</p>
                <p>Relief contour throughout, except at hairline. Dilute glaze for inner
                    markings and for fuzz on cheeks. Added red for wreath, cord on money bag,
                    lettering. Incised hairline.</p>
                <p>Phintias belonged to the Pioneer group of red-figure painters, who
                    began work in the time of the Andokides Painter and continued into the late
                    sixth century. About seventeen vases of a variety of shapes have been attributed
                    to Phintias, seven of which, including this one, he signed as painter.<note
                        n="1" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>ARV2, 22-26</bibl>; <bibl
                               >Para., 323, 507, 509</bibl>; <bibl
                               >Boardman 1975, 30-32</bibl>.</p>
                    </note></p>
                <p>Phintias betrays his heritage from black figure in his use of
                    incision rather than reserve line to delineate the hairline. Also typical of
                    early red figure is Phintias's reliance on relief line, rather than dilute
                    glaze, for interior markings, and his penchant for the stacked pleats and
                    swallowtails seen in contemporary sculpture. Figures painted by Phintias can be
                    recognized by the length and pronounced curve of the eye, and by the almost
                    concave profile of the nose. Other characteristic features are the animated
                    contour of the hair and the long fingers and feet.<note n="2"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p>Simon, 97, pls. 98-101; G. Pinney, <hi rend="ital"
                               >AJA</hi> 85 (1981): 151; C. M. Cardon, <hi rend="ital"
                               >AJA</hi> 83 (1979): 172.</p>
                    </note></p>
                <p>Bloesch suggested that many of the vases that Phintias painted were
                    supplied by the prominent potter Kachrylion, who also fashioned pieces for the
                    Kiss Painter.<note n="3" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Simon &amp; Hirmer
                                1976, 97-98, pls. 98-101</bibl>; <bibl
                                >ARV2, 25, nos. 1-3</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> Our kylix would indeed seem to be associated with Kachrylion, since the
                    bulge above the foot recalls Kachrylion's distinctive treatment of Type-C cups
                    having a plain lip.<note n="4" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Bloesch 1940, 119-22 and
                                120, nos. 1-4</bibl>. Type-C kylixes are characterized by a flat
                            plate foot and a bulge in the stem. Occasionally the lip is offset.</p>
                    </note> The tall, slender stem and shallow bowl indicate that our cup is later
                    than an example in Boston that is signed by Kachrylion.<note n="5"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><rs type="vase">Boston 95.33</rs>. <bibl
                               >Bloesch 1940, 119, no. 1</bibl>. I owe
                            this comparison to Sally Roberts.</p>
                    </note></p>
                <milestone n="140" unit="page"/>
                <p>Besides being a painter, Phintias was also a potter. He signed as
                    potter one cup of Type-B shape and two aryballoi,<note n="6" place="unspecified"
                        anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>ARV2, 25</bibl>. Cup is <rs
                                type="vase">Athens 1628</rs>. <bibl
                               >Bloesch 1940, 61</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> and several more cups have been attributed to him.<note n="7"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>ARV2, 178, nos. 1-6</bibl>;
                                <bibl>G. Pinney, <title
                                    >AJA</title> 85 (1981):155, 157</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> Recent study of the style of the painting and the profiles of the vases
                    attributed to Phintias has determined that Phintias worked in the same studio
                    with Euthymides and the Dikaios Painter, and that he trained several prominent
                    artists, including Kleophrades and the Berlin Painter, for whom Phintias may
                    have fashioned several cups.<note n="8" place="unspecified" anchored="true"
                       >
                        <p><bibl>M. Robertson [<title
                                   >AJA</title> 62 (1958): 57, 62,
                            64]</bibl>attributes Athens 1628 to the Berlin Painter. <bibl
                               >G. Pinney [<title
                                >AJA</title> 85 (1981): 146, 155-58]</bibl> discusses the
                            relationship between the Berlin Painter and Hermokrates, whom she
                            believes to be identical with the Salting Painter.</p>
                    </note></p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Hartwig, <title
                                >RömMitt</title> 2 (1887):169, no. VIII</bibl>; <bibl
                           >Wernicke 1889, 54, no. 2</bibl>; <bibl
                           >H. S. Jones, <title
                            >JHS</title> 12 (1891):372-73</bibl>; <bibl
                            >Hartwig 1893, 172, pl. XVII.1</bibl>; <bibl
                            >Harrison &amp; MacColl 1894, 18</bibl>; <bibl
                           >FR, 251-52, no. 1</bibl>; <bibl
                           >Pottier 1909, fig. 5</bibl>; <bibl
                           >G. Perrot, <title>Histoire de l'art dans
                                l'antiquité</title> (1882-1914), vol. 10, 464, fig.
                        265</bibl>; <bibl>Hoppin 1917, 99-102</bibl>;
                            <bibl>Beazley 1918, 28</bibl>; <bibl
                           >Hoppin 1919, vol. II, 355, no. 2</bibl>;
                            <bibl>Pfuhl 1923, <milestone n="139"
                                unit="page"/> vol. 1, 441, and vol. 3, 119, fig.
                            384</bibl>; <bibl>Richter 1923, 81-82, no.
                            5, fig. 85</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley 1925, 57,
                            no. 2</bibl>; <bibl>Philippart 1928,
                        50</bibl>; <bibl>P. Cloche, <title
                               >Les classes, les métiers, le trafic</title>
                            (Paris, 1931), 51, pl. XXXII</bibl>; <bibl
                            >CVA, USA fasc. 6, Robinson fasc. 2, 12-13, pls. II.1, III.2</bibl>;
                            <bibl>Schnitzler 1948, pl. 39</bibl>; <bibl
                           >Sparkes &amp; Talcott 1958, fig.
                        12</bibl>; <bibl>Bernhard 1966, fig. 86</bibl>;
                            <bibl>ARV2, 24, no. 14</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="103" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Baltimore, Hopkins AIA B3" type="vase"
                        >Baltimore, Hopkins AIA B3</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>Kylix by Epiktetos</title>
                    <date>520-510 B.C.</date>
                </p>
                <p>B 3. Baltimore Society AIA, formerly Hartwig Collection. "Chiusi."
                    Ht, 14.1 cm; diam rim, 32.8 cm; diam foot, 12.7 cm. Mended from many pieces.
                    Foot is ancient but does not belong. A few parts along rim restored (before
                    acquisition) with segments of another ancient kylix.</p>
                <p>Tondo is bordered by narrow reserved band. Wreathed satyr reclines on
                    a couch, which is indicated by narrow reserved band (fragments imprecisely
                    assembled give inaccurate effect of bent line). His back is supported by a
                    pillow decorated with three black bands crossed by two close-set lines. His legs
                    are bent and upraised, with feet pressed against edge of tondo. With both hands
                    and upraised right knee he raises pointed amphora to his lips. Inscribed beneath
                    couch and in field above satyr's head: <foreign xml:lang="greek"
                        >*E*P*I*K*T*E*T*O*S *E*G*R*A*F*S*E*N</foreign>.</p>
                <p>Relief contour throughout except for reserved contour of beard.
                    Dilute glaze for inner markings. Added red for tail, wreath, lettering. Incised
                    contour of hair at crown and nape.</p>
                <p>Epiktetos was a prominent early red-figure painter who specialized in
                        cups.<note n="1" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>ARV2, 70-79</bibl>; <bibl
                               >Para., 328-29</bibl>; <bibl
                               >Boardman 1975, 57-59</bibl>; <bibl
                               >J. D. Beazley, <title>JHS</title> 58
                                (1938):267</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> He signed his name on forty vases and is accredited with sixty more,
                    many of which are signed only with <hi rend="ital"
                    >"egraphsen."</hi> Epiktetos also worked as a potter. He signed one vase as both
                    potter and painter,<note n="2" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>ARV2, 78 no. 102</bibl>
                                (<rs type="vase">Athens, Acr. 6</rs>, a plate).</p>
                    </note> and he wrote only <hi rend="ital">"epoiesen"</hi> on other
                    vases that we know he both potted and painted.<note n="3" place="unspecified"
                        anchored="true">
                        <p>He also signed one vase, which he both potted and painted,
                            with the word <hi rend="ital">"egraphsen"</hi> (<bibl
                               >ARV2, 76, no. 78</bibl>). Another bears
                            the words <hi rend="ital">"egraphsen"</hi> and <hi
                                rend="ital">"epoiesen"</hi> (<bibl
                               >ARV2, 73, no. 31</bibl>).</p>
                    </note></p>
                <p>Epiktetos worked for a number of potters, including Andocides,
                    Nikosthenes, and Hischylos, for whom he painted bilingual cups. In his later
                    years, Epiktetos painted for Pistoxenos, Pamphaios, and Python, and he
                    undoubtedly came into contact with artists of the early fifth century, such as
                    Douris (see <rs type="vase">Baltimore, Hopkins AIA B8</rs>, <rs
                        type="vase">Baltimore, Hopkins AIA B9</rs>) and Makron (see <rs
                        type="vase">Baltimore, Hopkins AIA B10</rs>).<note n="4"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>ARV2, 70</bibl>; <bibl
                               >M. Robertson, <title
                                >JHS</title> 85 (1965):100</bibl>; <bibl
                                >Boardman 1975, 59</bibl>.</p>
                    </note></p>
                <p>Epiktetos displays influence from black-figure vase-painting in his
                    use of incision along the contour of the hair, but, in contrast to Phintias and
                    other painters of<milestone n="142 " unit="page"/> the
                    Pioneer Group, Epiktetos prefers the newer dilute glaze, rather than relief
                    line, for the interiors of his figures. He is especially admired for the
                    excellence of his tondo compositions, of which our example is a good
                    illustration. The scene displays a sensitive balance of light and dark and an
                    admirable skill in the handling of the satyr, who, as the cup is rotated,
                    appears to stand and lean over the amphora.<note n="5" place="unspecified"
                        anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Beazley [<title
                                   >JHS</title> 58 (1938):267]</bibl>notes that the
                            vertical axis of a tondo composition is rarely at right angles with the
                            handles.</p>
                    </note> Also noteworthy is the skillful draughtsmanship of the face.</p>
                <p>Our cup is probably an early work, since the proportions of the satyr
                    are slender,<note n="6" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Buitron 1972,
                        72</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> the use of red is generous,<note n="7" place="unspecified"
                        anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Simon &amp; Hirmer
                                1976, 96, pls. 96-97</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> and the profile of bowl and stem can be compared with those on cups by
                    the potter Hischylos,<note n="8" place="unspecified" anchored="true"
                       >
                        <p><bibl>Bloesch 1940, 31-35</bibl>;
                            see also <bibl>M. Robertson, <title
                                   >JHS</title> 85 (1965):99-100</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> with whom Epiktetos was associated early in his career. A later version
                    of the same scene appeared on a kylix once in Rome; that cup was said by Beazley
                    to be in the manner of Epiktetos and possibly by the artist himself.<note n="9"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>ARV2, 80, no.
                        15</bibl>.</p>
                    </note></p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>P. Hartwig, <title
                               >RömMitt</title> 2 (1887):167, no. 1</bibl>;
                            <bibl>P. Hartwig, <title
                            >Jdl</title> 6 (1891):250-57, pl. V</bibl>; <bibl
                           >P. Hartwig, <title>Jdl</title> 7 (1892):
                            118</bibl>; <bibl>Harrison &amp; MacColl
                            1894, pl. IX.1</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley 1918,
                            14-16, fig. 7</bibl>; <bibl>Hoppin 1919,
                            vol. I, 301, no. 2</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley
                            1925, 26, no. 20</bibl>; <bibl>Philippart
                            1928, 50</bibl>; <bibl>W. Kraiker, <title
                               >JdI</title> 44 (1929):177, no. 33</bibl>; <bibl
                           >CVA, USA fasc. 6, Robinson fasc. 2, 11-12,
                            pls. I.3, II.3</bibl>; <bibl>D. K. Hill,
                                <title>JWalt</title> 1 (1938):29, fig. 6</bibl>;
                            <bibl>Buschor 1943, fig. 42</bibl>; <bibl
                           >ARV2, 75, no. 56</bibl>.<milestone n="141"
                            unit="page"/></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="104" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Baltimore, Hopkins AIA B2" type="vase"
                        >Baltimore, Hopkins AIA B2</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>Kylix Fragment by Epiktetos</title>
                    <date>ca. 500 B.C.</date>
                </p>
                <p>B 2. Baltimore Society AIA, formerly Hartwig Collection. "Chiusi."
                    Greatest dimension, 15.5 cm; diam tondo, 9.5 cm. Broken all around. Includes
                    part of stem. Surface worn.</p>
                <p>Tondo is bordered by narrow reserved band. Beardless youth wearing
                    red wreath strides forward in right profile, his knees bent, his right leg
                    advanced. His outstretched right hand grasps a wineskin; his left hand supports
                    a staff over his left shoulder, from the end of which hangs his cloak. Inscribed
                    in red lettering in field: <foreign xml:lang="greek"
                        >*E*P*O*I*E*S*E*N</foreign>.</p>
                <p>Relief contour throughout. Incised hairline.</p>
                <p>This fragment bears the word "<hi rend="ital"
                    >epoiesen,</hi>" which we know Epiktetos inscribed on vases that he both potted
                    and painted.<note n="1" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>ARV2, 70</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> Typical of later archaic painting are the greater slimness and
                    elasticity of the thighs, the attempt at a three-quarter view with the left
                    shoulder advanced, and the refined profile of the face. Characteristic of
                    Epiktetos are the skillful composition, with the pose and scale of the youth
                    perfectly adjusted to the field and with the animation of the stride in harmony
                    with the curving frame. The incised hairline contrasts with the reserved line in
                    use among contemporary artists.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>P. Hartwig, <title
                               >RömMitt</title> 2 (1887):169, no. X</bibl>;
                            <bibl>P. Hartwig, <title
                            >JHS</title> 12 (1891): 347, fig c</bibl>; <bibl
                           >A. E. Pottier, <title>MonPiot</title> 20
                            (1913):144, fig. 18</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley
                            1918, 19</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley, <title
                               >BSR</title> 11 (1929):16 n. 3</bibl>; <bibl
                           >W. Kraiker, <title
                            >Jdl</title> 44 (1919):194, no. 2</bibl>; <bibl
                           >CVA, USA fasc. 6, Robinson fasc. 2, 11, pl. I</bibl>;
                            <bibl>ARV2, 76, no. 75</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="105" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Baltimore, Hopkins AIA B5" type="vase"
                        >Baltimore, Hopkins AIA B5</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>Kylix by the Kiss Painter</title>
                    <date>ca. 500 B.C.</date>
                </p>
                <p>B 5. Baltimore Society AIA, formerly Hartwig Collection. "Chiusi."
                    Ht, 11 cm; diam with handles, 38.7 cm; diam rim, 30.7 cm; diam foot, 11.1 cm.
                    Mended from many pieces.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="ital">Interior</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Standing on exergue is bearded male facing front. His weight is on
                    his right leg; his left knee is bent with foot behind him. He wears a mantle
                    brought over his left shoulder, exposing right shoulder and chest. Right hand on
                    hip; left arm extended, with hand holding end of staff. His head, seen in right
                    profile, wears an ivy wreath. Facing him is a nude youth wearing a laurel
                    wreath, legs in left profile, torso three-quarters turned to front. He stands on
                    a two-stepped starting block and holds an aryballos and sponge in left hand. In
                    field are aryballos and sponge suspended from nail. An upended pick is set in
                    ground in front of base. Inscribed in field, second word retrograde: <foreign
                        xml:lang="greek">*L*E*A*G*R*O*S *K*A*L*O*S</foreign> (Leagros
                    is beautiful).</p>
                <p>Tondo is bordered by reserved band. <hi rend="ital"
                        >Exterior, Side A</hi></p>
                <p>Striding youth with mantle draped over shoulders carries skyphos in
                    left hand and staff supporting oinochoe in right. Inscribed in field above tip
                    of staff: <foreign xml:lang="greek">*E</foreign>. Youth approaches
                    a large-column krater, on the other side of which is a nude youth with himation
                    over shoulders. Inscribed in field beneath figures: <foreign xml:lang="greek"
                       >*K*A*L*O*S</foreign> (beautiful).</p>
                <p>Rest of scene consists of one striding nude youth and another in
                    draped himation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="ital">Exterior, Side B</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Standing bearded male extends left hand to approaching youth, who
                    carries skyphos in extended right hand, staff in left. Both figures are nude,
                    with mantles draped over shoulders. Remainder of scene consists of beardless
                    youth in right profile, nude except for mantle over shoulders, playing flutes.
                    In front of him is maiden, of<milestone n="144" unit="page"
                    /> whom only a part of pleated chiton and mantle survives. Inscribed in field
                    above all four figures: <foreign xml:lang="greek"
                        >*E*P]*I*D*R*O*M*O*S [*K]*A*L*O*S</foreign>.</p>
                <p>Relief contour throughout interior and exterior, except for some feet
                    on exterior. Hairline reserved at forehead and nape and incised at crown. Dilute
                    glaze for inner markings. Added red: interior—wreath, javelin loop,
                    string and wristband of aryballoi, nail securing one aryballos, lettering;
                    exterior—lettering. Graffito on underside of foot.</p>
                <p>The Kiss Painter is known from only five cups. He takes his name from
                    the affectionate scenes on the tondos of kylixes in Berlin and New York.<note
                        n="1" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>ARV2, 177-78 (no. 1 [177]
                                is in Berlin, no. 2 [177] is in New York)</bibl>; <bibl
                               >Para., 339</bibl>; <bibl
                                >J. Beazley, <title>JHS</title> 58
                            (1938):267</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> All but one of the cups has a komos scene on the exterior. The Baltimore
                    vase is the only inscribed example and bears within the tondo the well-known
                    love name Leagros, which appears on a number of black-figure vases of about this
                        date.<note n="2" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Boardman 1974,
                        110</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> The inscription on the exterior, <hi rend="ital">epidromos
                        kalos,</hi> praises the delights of athletic pursuits.</p>
                <p>The profile of the vase resembles those of kylixes by the potter
                    Kachrylion, to whom this cup has been attributed.<note n="3" place="unspecified"
                        anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>G. Nicole, RA 5, 3-4
                                (1916): 396</bibl>; <bibl>Hoppin 1919,
                                vol. 1, 176, no. 20</bibl>; see also <bibl
                               >Bloesch 1940, 45-50</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> Kachrylion also fashioned the kylix to which our fragment by Oltos (<rs
                        type="vase">Baltimore, Hopkins AIA B1</rs>) belonged, and
                    possibly made the cup that was decorated by Phintias (<rs type="vase"
                       >Baltimore, Hopkins AIA B4</rs>).</p>
                <p>The scene in the tondo takes place in a palaestra, where youths
                    trained in the various sports whose equipment is depicted here: the casting of
                    the javelin, the broad jump (for which a pick was used to measure distances),
                    and the foot race, which made use of a starting gate, a block of which is
                    probably shown here.<note n="4" place="unspecified" anchored="true"
                       >
                        <p><bibl>Harris 1972, 27-29</bibl>.
                            Alternate interpretation proposed by <bibl
                                >A. E. Raubitschek [<title>Hesperia</title> 8
                                (1939):161-63]</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> The aryballos contained the olive oil that athletes applied with a
                    sponge before exercising.</p>
                <p>The advances made by vasepainters of about 500 B.C. can be seen in
                    the foreshortened frontal leg of the trainer in the tondo and the three-quarter
                    positions of the youthful torsos on the tondo and exterior. Also typical of
                    vasepainting from the end of the sixth century is the use of dilute glaze for
                    interior markings.</p>
                <milestone n="146" unit="page"/>
                <p>The large bodies with protruding buttocks and the expanses of flesh
                    and drapery uninterrupted by detail recall the similar broad style of the
                    contemporary Euthymides.<note n="5" place="unspecified" anchored="true"
                       >
                        <p><bibl>Simon &amp; Hirmer
                                1976, 101, pls. 112-15</bibl>.</p>
                    </note></p>
                <p>The graffito on the underside of the foot is one of several examples
                    that are found on many vases dating between ca. 550 and 500 B.C. These markings
                    are believed to have been applied to vases intended for export, especially to
                    Etruria, and to signify prices and other commercial information relating to the
                    sale of the vessels.<note n="6" place="unspecified" anchored="true"
                       >
                        <p><bibl>Boardman 1974,
                            202-3</bibl>; <bibl>Johnston 1979, 6-8,
                            12</bibl>.</p>
                    </note></p>
                <milestone n="147" unit="page"/>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>K. Wernicke, AZ 43 (1885):255,
                            no. 16, pl. 19.2</bibl>; <bibl>P. Hartwig,
                                <title>RömMitt</title> 2 (1887):167, no.
                        2</bibl>; <bibl>Wernicke 1889, 41, no.
                        20</bibl>; <bibl>Hartwig 1893, 39-43, figs.
                        5a-b</bibl>; <bibl>Klein 1898, 75, no. 20, fig.
                            15</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley 1918, 22</bibl>;
                            <bibl>Hoppin 1919, vol. I, 176, no.
                        20</bibl>; <bibl>K. Elderkin, HSCP 35
                            (1924):119, no. 2</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley
                            1925, 54, no. 3</bibl>; <bibl>A.
                            Raubitschek, <title>Hesperia</title> 8
                        (1939):162</bibl>; <bibl>M. Guarducci, <title
                               >Annuario,</title> NS 3-4 (1941-42), 132</bibl>;
                            <bibl>CVA, USA fasc. 6, Robinson fasc. 2,
                            13-14, pls. V, VI.1</bibl>; <bibl>ARV2, 177,
                            no. 3</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="106" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Baltimore, Hopkins 9022" type="vase"
                        >Baltimore, Hopkins 9022</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>Lekythos in Six Technique</title>
                    <date>ca. 500 B.C.</date>
                </p>
                <p>9022. Ht, 18.9 cm; diam mouth, 4 cm; diam foot, 5 cm. Mended from
                    many pieces, with parts of handle and rim restored.</p>
                <p>Rim and inside of neck glazed. Glazed handle, with underside
                    reserved. On shoulder is chain of lotus buds, with stalks linking every three
                    buds; band of tongues above.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="ital">Body:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Satyr strides in right profile, left leg advanced. Right outstretched
                    hand grasps right wrist of a maenad, while left arm is outstretched toward her
                    genitals. Maenad advances in left profile, left leg advanced and both arms
                    outstretched. Contour and interior markings of satyr incised. Delicate incisions
                    for maenad's eye, brow, hairline, arms, back left leg, and back of right thigh.
                    Interior of maenad was painted white.</p>
                <p>Two red lines above scene; one red line beneath figures as
                    groundline. Foot in two degrees, glazed except for reserved side of top step and
                    underside.</p>
                <p>In Six technique the background is in black glaze, like the
                    background in red-figure vasepainting, but the artist works the figures either
                    by incising their contours through the black glaze or by applying white, red, or
                    brown paint on top of the glaze before the vase is fired.<note n="1"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Boardman 1974, 178</bibl>;
                                <bibl>J. Six, <title
                                    >Gazette Archéologique</title> 13 (1888): 193-294</bibl>;
                                <bibl>Haspels 1936, 106ff.</bibl>; <bibl
                               >P. E. Corbett, <title
                                    >JHS</title> 85 (1965):24</bibl>; <bibl
                               >Kurtz 1975, 116-19</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> The painter may, as in the case with our maenad, render a figure
                    entirely or mostly in color, using incision only for details. Alternately, he
                    may work a figure like our satyr in "outline Six," wherein all of the figure is
                    incised and no color is added.<note n="2" place="unspecified" anchored="true"
                       >
                        <p><bibl>Kurtz 1975, 116,
                            119</bibl>.</p>
                    </note></p>
                <p>The Six technique originated during the first half of the sixth
                    century, but at first was employed only for parts of figures. Not until around
                    530 B.C., in the experimental atmosphere that stimulated the introduction of
                    red-figure vasepainting, did Nikosthenes and Psiax first work entire vases in
                    Six technique.<note n="3" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Boardman 1974,
                        178</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> In the later sixth century the technique was most popular in the
                    workshops of the Sappho<note n="4" place="unspecified" anchored="true"
                       >
                        <p><bibl>ABV, 507-8</bibl>; <bibl
                               >Haspels 1936, 94-130, 227-28</bibl>;
                                <bibl>Para., 246-48</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> and Diosphos Painters,<note n="5" place="unspecified" anchored="true"
                       >
                        <p><bibl>ABV, 508-11</bibl>; <bibl
                               >Haspels 1936, 94-130, 235-36</bibl>;
                                <bibl>Para., 248-50</bibl>. To the
                            examples listed by Beazley, add: <bibl
                                >Hornbostel 1977, 298, no. 258</bibl>; <bibl
                               >Kurtz 1975, pl. 6.4</bibl> in Columbia, Missouri.
                            Another, surely by one of these two painters, is discussed by D. von
                            Bothmer in <bibl>Brommer Festschrift, 61,
                                pl. 19</bibl> (<rs type="vase">New York
                        67.11.22</rs>).</p>
                    </note> artists who were influenced, and perhaps trained, by the Edinburgh
                    Painter. The Sappho and Diosphos Painters were primarily black-figure artists
                    who painted a variety of shapes but specialized in lekythoi, which they executed
                    in Six technique as well as in black-figure and white-ground. The Diosphos
                    Painter is credited with over thirty-six lekythoi; the Sappho Painter is
                    assigned only eleven lekythoi and one hydria.</p>
                <p>Our vase is best paralleled by work of the Sappho Painter. Although
                    both the Sappho and the Diosphos Painters used lekythoi of the DL type, those of
                    the Sappho Painter have the shallow mouths and squat, full bodies with tapering
                    profiles of the Hopkins vase, in contrast to the deeper mouths and
                    straight-sided cylinders preferred by the Diosphos Painter.<note n="6"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Kurtz 1975, 80</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> The stalks in the bud patterns of the Sappho Painter generally skip two
                    buds, as on our example, while those of the Diosphos Painter usually skip only
                    one, but<milestone n="148" unit="page"/> occasionally two,
                    and sometimes add white dots between the buds.<note n="7" place="unspecified"
                        anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Haspels 1936,
                        94</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> The Six lekythoi of both painters have a red line beneath the scene, but
                    the Sappho Painter almost always applies two red lines above, as on our vessel,
                    while the Diosphos Painter may employ a checker or key pattern.<note n="8"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Haspels 1936,
                        95</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> While the Diosphos Painter often relies upon incision alone, the Sappho
                    Painter also executes elements of his representation in added white.<note n="9"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Kurtz 1975, 119</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> Our vase is especially similar to a lekythos by the Sappho Painter in
                    New York on which a satyr, worked entirely by incision, crouches amid an
                    amphora, serpent, and rocks, all of which are rendered in white.<note n="10"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Haspels 1936, 228, no.
                            43</bibl>, which is the same as <bibl><title
                                   >Bulletin of the Metropolitan Museum of
                                Art</title> (1930):136, fig. 4</bibl>. (17.8 cm; <rs type="vase"
                               >New York 23.160.87</rs>).</p>
                    </note></p>
                <p>On the Hopkins vase the incisions for the maenad are so much lighter
                    and more delicate than those for the satyr that they could not have been
                    intended to be seen through the white paint and thus must be preliminary
                    incisions intended as guidelines for the artist. On this lekythos the artist
                    carefully respected these sketches in his final application of color, but on
                    other Six vases the preliminary incisions are often disregarded.<note n="11"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>P. Corbett, <title
                                   >JHS</title> 85 (1965):16-28, especially
                            24-25</bibl>.</p>
                    </note></p>
                <p>The Sappho Painter used Six technique early in his career, and
                    certainly the heavy thighs and strict profile of the satyr support a date for
                    our vase of ca. 500 B.C.</p>
                <milestone n="149" unit="page"/>
            </div>
            <div n="107" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Baltimore, Hopkins 9260" type="vase"
                        >Baltimore, Hopkins 9260</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>Black-Figure Neck Amphora by the Michigan Painter</title>
                    <date>ca. 500 B.C.</date>
                </p>
                <p>9260. Ht, 21.5 cm; diam rim, 11.4 cm; diam body, 14.2 cm; diam foot,
                    7.5 cm. Mended from many pieces.</p>
                <p>Upper surface of rim reserved; neck glazed inside. Glazed triple
                    handles with undersides reserved. Profiled ridge separating neck from body; ring
                    molding between body and foot. Both ridge and molding are painted red.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="ital">Side A</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Glazed groundline. A bull in left profile collapses beneath the
                    attack of two lions. In field above is inscription <hi rend="ital"
                        >ISIS.</hi> Added red for dots in lions' manes and for streams of blood
                    under mouth and claws.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="ital">Side B</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Two bulls drink from vessel between them. Vines above their heads
                    wind from base of handles.</p>
                <p>Framed by a line above and a line beneath are three palmettes. The
                    central seven-petal palmette is upright, the flanking five-petal palmettes are
                    suspended. Two dots flank the middle leaf of the central palmette and two more
                    dots lie on the inner sides of the middle leaves of the side palmettes.</p>
                <p>Band of black tongues above picture. Beneath picture is a line, then
                    two staggered rows of dots, double lines, rays. Foot glazed except for bottom of
                    sides and underside. Below handles are volutes terminating in triple lotuses.
                    Beneath foot is dipinto.</p>
                <p>This vase is the work of the Michigan Painter, whom Beazley later
                    recognized to be identical with the Painter of Brussels R 312, an artist of the
                    Dot-Band Class who was active in the late sixth century.<note n="1"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p>The Michigan Painter is discussed in <bibl
                               >ABV, 343-44</bibl>. For the Dot-Band class,
                            recognized by the dot band beneath the scene and by the ornament on the
                            neck, see <bibl>ABV, 483</bibl>, and <bibl
                               >Para., 220-21</bibl>. The Painter of
                            Brussels R 312 is discussed in <bibl>ABV,
                                483</bibl>. The artists are identified in <bibl
                               >Para., 221</bibl>, with other additions on 157. See
                            also <bibl>Philippaki 1967, 22</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> The painter principally worked on small neck amphorae, but he also
                    painted larger neck amphorae, Panathenaic amphorae, stamnoi, and at least one
                    oinochoe.</p>
                <p>On the necks of the small amphorae we find two<milestone n="151"
                        unit="page"/> distinct palmette patterns. In the scheme
                    on our example and on those vases originally attributed to the Painter of
                    Brussels R 312, the central seven-petal palmette is upright and enclosed by four
                    dots, while the flanking palmettes are suspended and have five petals each.
                    These later palmettes can also be seen in the ornament under the handles of
                    Brussels R 312. On amphorae formerly assigned to the Michigan Painter, the
                    central seven-petal palmette is suspended and there are no dots, while the
                    flanking upright palmettes have five or seven petals.</p>
                <p>On his small neck amphorae, the Michigan Painter favors the heroic
                    themes popular in the late sixth century, such as the Labors of Herakles (on
                    examples in London<note n="2" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><rs type="vase">London B 277</rs> (Herakles and
                            the Bull), <bibl>ABV, 343, no. 8</bibl>,
                            which is the same as <bibl>CVA, GB fasc. 5,
                                BM fasc. 4, pl. 70</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> and Maplewood<note n="3" place="unspecified" anchored="true"
                       >
                        <p>Maplewood (Herakles and Antaeus) is the same as <bibl
                               >Para., 157, no. 9 quarter</bibl>.</p>
                    </note>, of Ajax and Achilles (on vases in Brussels<note n="4"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><rs type="vase">Brussels R 312</rs>, <bibl
                               >ABV, 483, no. 1</bibl>, is the same as
                                <bibl>Para., 157, no. 9 bis</bibl>,
                            which is the same as <bibl>CVA, Belgium
                                fasc. 1, Brussels fasc. 1, 3, pl. 9.1</bibl>. See <bibl
                               >S. Woodford, <title>AJA</title> 84
                                (1980):37, no. G.1</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> and Lucerne<note n="5" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p>Lucerne, art market, which is the same as <bibl
                               >Para., 157, no. 9 ter</bibl>. See <bibl
                               >S. Woodford, <title>AJA</title> 84
                                (1980): 37, no. G.3</bibl>.</p>
                    </note>), and of Peleus and Thetis (on an amphora in Boulogne<note n="6"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p>Musée des beaux-arts et d'archéologie, Inv. no.
                            85-B, <bibl>ABV, 483, no. 3</bibl> is the
                            same as <bibl>Para., 157, no. 9,
                        6</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> [<rs type="vase">Boulogne no. 85</rs>]). He is also fond of
                    Hermes, whom we find on another example in Boulogne<note n="7"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><rs type="vase">Boulogne, 13-A</rs>, <bibl
                               >ABV, 483, no. 4</bibl> is the same as
                                <bibl>Para., 157, no. 9</bibl>7.</p>
                    </note> (<rs type="vase">Boulogne no. 13</rs>), and of komos or
                    Dionysiac figures, who appear on amphorae in Michigan<note n="8"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><rs type="vase">Ann Arbor 2599</rs>, <bibl
                               >ABV, 344, no. 9</bibl> is the same as
                                <bibl>CVA, USA fasc. 3, Michigan fasc.
                                1, 30, pl. XIV.3</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> and Chicago<note n="9" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><rs type="vase">Chicago 1889.97</rs>, <bibl
                               >ABV, 483, no. 2</bibl> is the same as
                                <bibl>Para., 157, no. 9, 5</bibl>.</p>
                    </note>.</p>
                <p>The Michigan Painter was content with a limited repertory of motifs.
                    The bull on the Hopkins vase is almost identical with the one defeated by
                    Herakles on the amphora in London and is clearly inspired by black-figure
                    representations of the Cretan bull in combat with Herakles.<note n="10"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p>See <bibl>Shapiro 1981a, 64, no.
                                23</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> The reverses are particularly redundant, and usually feature dancing
                    figures. The two women on the reverse of the Michigan amphora are almost
                    identical with those on the reverses of the vases in Boulogne (<rs type="vase"
                       >Boulogne 85</rs>) and London, except for their gestures and
                    details like the addition of castanets. The two youths flanking the woman on the
                    obverse of the Michigan vase are replaced by satyrs on the reverse of the
                    amphora in Chicago and by women on the reverse of the example in Boulogne.</p>
                <p>The signature characteristics of the painter were pointed out by
                        Philippaki:<note n="11" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Philippaki 1967,
                        22</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> the stacked arcs for the knees, the emphatic engraved arcs delineating
                    the upper contour of the beard, and the description of the eye by means of a
                    circle set between short horizontal lines. Typical of his treatment of animals
                    are the four gashes for the ribs, the preponderance of wrinkles under the neck
                    and behind the forelegs, and the presence of one or two arcs on the shoulder
                    [e.g., on our bull, on the bull on the amphora in London, and on the horse on
                    the reverse of the vase in Maplewood]. On his human figures we often find two
                    horizontal lines for the mouth, a large shock of hair above the forehead, and an
                    emphatically beaked nose. The collarbone is described by a long incision
                    terminating in<milestone n="153" unit="page"/> an arc, and
                    the ribs are delineated by a cluster of lines.</p>
                <p>To the vases assembled by Beazley we can add a further example that
                    was recently on the art market in Freiburg.<note n="12" place="unspecified"
                        anchored="true">
                        <p>Galerie Günter Puhze, Stadtstrasse 28, D-7800
                        Freiburg.</p>
                    </note> The neck pattern on that amphora is identical to the one on the Hopkins
                    vase. On the obverse we find Herakles fighting Nereus, a subject compatible with
                    this artist's known affinity for that hero. The composition and much of the
                    detail in the scene compare closely with the representation of Peleus and Thetis
                    on the amphora, <rs type="vase">Boulogne 85</rs>. On the reverse of
                    the Freiburg vase, the woman flanked by two armed warriors can be compared with
                    the scene on the reverse of the Brussels amphora, where two warriors are shown
                    in combat. Finally, the Freiburg figures exhibit the jutting chin, nose, and
                    back of the head familiar in other works from the hand of this artist.</p>
                <p>The scene on the observe of the Hopkins vase is a familiar one in
                    Attic sculpture of the last half of the sixth century. Pedimental groups
                    representing one or two lions in triumph over a fallen bull have been assigned
                    to the Hekatompedon and to the Peisistratid temple on the Acropolis. Another
                    pedimental group was found in the Agora.<note n="13" place="unspecified"
                        anchored="true">
                        <p>For the Hekatompedon, see <bibl
                                >Ridgway 1977, 199</bibl>. The Peisistratid temple is discussed on
                            205-8, and the Agora pediment on 210. Still another group is divided
                            between Athens and New York (210).</p>
                    </note></p>
                <p>The dipinto on the underside of the foot is of the type classified by
                    Johnston as 32Av. The same mark appears on two oinochoai in Boston by the
                    Chicago Painter. Those vases are said to come from Gela, a provenance that
                    supports Johnston's contention that dipinti bore commercial information relevant
                    to the export of the vessels.<note n="14" place="unspecified" anchored="true"
                       >
                        <p><bibl>Johnston 1979,
                            85-86</bibl>; <bibl>D. von Bothmer, review
                                of Johnston in <title>AJA</title> 85 (1981):
                            353</bibl>.</p>
                    </note></p>
                <milestone n="154" unit="page"/>
            </div>
            <div n="108" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Baltimore, Hopkins AIA B8" type="vase"
                        >Baltimore, Hopkins AIA B8</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>Kylix by Douris</title>
                    <date>500-490 B.C.</date>
                </p>
                <p>B 8. Baltimore Society AIA, formerly Hartwig Collection. "Chiusi."
                    Ht, 9.5 cm; diam with handles, 30.4 cm; diam of rim, 23.2 cm; diam foot, 9.6 cm.
                    Mended.</p>
                <p>Two warriors in left profile step on left leg, right leg extended,
                    right arm upraised with spear. Male in foreground wears chiton, cuirass with
                    star on shoulder lappet, greaves, and crested Corinthian helmet with upraised
                    cheekpieces and dot band at base of crest. Over his left arm is shield with
                    dotted rim and emblem consisting of left profile of lion head. Scythian
                    companion wears tight-fitting, long-sleeved, long-legged garment alternating
                    black and reserved bands; on top is sleeveless pleated tunic. He wears a
                    Phrygian cap with two lappets by left ear; open gorytos hangs at left side. Both
                    warriors are barefoot. Inscribed in field: <foreign xml:lang="greek"
                       >*X*A*I*R*E*S*T*R*A*T*O*S *K*A*L*O*S</foreign>.</p>
                <p>Relief contour throughout, except for underside of toes of left feet
                    and reserved outline of Scythian's hair. Dilute glaze for folds of Scythian's
                    tunic. Added purple for pads under greaves and lettering. Border consists of
                    rightward meander.</p>
                <p>Douris, one of the most prominent of all red-figure painters, was
                    active during the first three decades of the fifth century.<note n="1"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>ARV2, 425-51</bibl>; <bibl
                               >J. D. Beazley, <title
                                    >JHS</title> 58 (1938):267</bibl>; <bibl
                               >Para., 374-76</bibl>; <bibl
                               >Muscarella 1974, no. 59, potting attributed to
                                Euphronios</bibl>; <bibl>Dörig
                                1975, no. 205</bibl>; <bibl>Boardman
                                1975, 137-39</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> He signed forty vases and has been assigned about two hundred fifty
                    more. Most of these pieces are cups, but Douris worked on other shapes as well,
                    both in white ground and red figure. He was also a competent potter and signed
                    one kantharos in Brussels as both potter and painter.<note n="2"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>ARV2, 425, and 445, no.
                            256</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> Despite his familiarity with the potter's wheel, Douris preferred to
                    paint vessels fashioned by Python,<note n="3" place="unspecified" anchored="true"
                       >
                        <p><bibl>ARV2, 426-27</bibl>; <bibl
                               >Bloesch 1940, 96-101</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> and, as a young artist, by Euphronios, for whom Onesimos also
                        worked.<note n="4" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Bloesch 1940,
                        70</bibl>.</p>
                    </note></p>
                <p>Beazley divided the painting career of Douris into four periods and
                    assigned our cup to the first phase, dating about 500-490 B.C..<note n="5"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>ARV2, 425-26</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> In these years Douris's style was still in a formative stage, and his
                        admiration<milestone n="159" unit="page"/> for
                    Chairestratos, as demonstrated by the inscriptions, steadfast.</p>
                <p>The picture in the tondo shows a hoplite accompanied by a member of
                    the Scythian tribe, which lived to the north of Greece. Scythians served as
                    archers in the Athenian army from about 530 B.C. to the end of the sixth
                    century, but after this date the Persians, who had by now acquired control of
                    Scythia, curtailed emigration to Athens,<note n="6" place="unspecified"
                        anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Vos 1963, 60, 68,
                            87</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> and the few Scythians who did settle in Athens were primarily employed
                    as policemen. For this reason representations of Scythian warriors after 500
                    B.C. were based on memory rather than observation, and, not surprisingly, the
                    depictions are often inaccurate. For example, the striped garment our Scythian
                    wears appeared on representations of Scythians from about 510 B.C. and thus is
                    probably a reliable rendition of the actual dress,<note n="7"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Vos 1963, 12, 40, 51,
                            81</bibl>; <bibl>Schauenburg 1975, 90
                                (1975): 107, 111</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> but the chiton and spear are surely artistic license. On the other hand,
                    Douris has correctly coupled the Scythian with a hoplite; we know that hoplites
                    traditionally advanced under cover of Scythian arrows.<note n="8"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Vos 1963, 72-73</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> Douris portrayed Scythians on three later vases of his third and fourth
                    periods, and these depictions are, not unexpectedly, even less accurate.<note
                        n="9" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>ARV2, 432, no. 55, and 433,
                                no. 63, from period 3</bibl>. No. 130 (p. 438) is from period 4. For
                            this last, see <bibl>Schauenburg 1975,
                            111</bibl>.</p>
                    </note></p>
                <p>The lion head on the hoplite's shield is a common image in
                    Achaemenian art, especially among gold appliqués, or bracteae.<note
                        n="10" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Ghirshman 1964, 380-81,
                                439, nos. 553-55</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> The motif first appears in Attic vasepainting at the end of the sixth
                    century, undoubtedly as a result of increased contact with the Persian world,
                    which erupted in the invasions of 490 and 480 B.C.<note n="11"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p>See a lion head as shield device on kylix by the Foundry
                            Painter (ca. 495 B.C.) in <bibl>Mü
                                nzen, vol. 13 (1961):84, no. 159, pl. 51</bibl>.</p>
                    </note></p>
                <milestone n="160" unit="page"/>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>P. Hartwig, <title
                               >RömMitt</title> 2 (1887):168, no. 5</bibl>;
                            <bibl>Hartwig 1893, 212, pl. 22.2</bibl>;
                            <bibl>Klein 1898, 99, no. 10</bibl>; <bibl
                           >FR, 251-52, no. 1</bibl>; <bibl
                           >Beazley 1918, 97, no. 7</bibl>; <bibl
                           >Hoppin 1919, vol. I, 277, no. 45</bibl>; <bibl
                           >Beazley 1925, 200, no. 14</bibl>; <bibl
                           >Philippart 1928, 50</bibl>; <bibl
                           >CVA, USA fasc. 6, Robinson fasc. 2, 15-16,
                            pl. XI</bibl>; <bibl>ARV2, 442, no.
                        215</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="109" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Baltimore, Hopkins BMA 60.55.1" type="vase"
                        >Baltimore, Hopkins BMA 60.55.1</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>Lekythos by the Athena Painter</title>
                    <date>ca. 490 B.C.</date>
                </p>
                <p>60.55.1 Baltimore Museum of Art from Robinson Collection. "Gela." Ht,
                    31.8 cm; diam, 12.6 cm; diam foot, 8.5 cm. Crack across lower part of body.
                    Surface chipped.</p>
                <p>Neck glazed inside. On shoulder is band of five nine-petal palmettes
                    with central one inverted, others upright and angled toward handle. Dots flank
                    base and topmost petal of each palmette. Above is band of tongues beneath red
                    line. Glazed handle with underside reserved.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="ital">Body</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Youth in right profile astride a dolphin extends right arm with
                    phiale toward a satyr who crouches on a rock, right knee drawn up, right arm
                    extended with oinochoe in right hand. Vine tendrils grow from rock. Behind satyr
                    are another youth and dolphin seen in right profile. Added white for bellies of
                    dolphins, lines on rock, flowers on satyr's oinochoe.</p>
                <p>Above picture is band of zigzag between two pairs of bounding lines.
                    Red line beneath scene and another between body and foot.</p>
                <p>The Athena Painter<note n="1" place="unspecified" anchored="true"
                       >
                        <p><bibl>ABV, 522-25</bibl>; <bibl
                               >Para., 260-62</bibl>; <bibl
                               >Haspels 1936, 147-65, 254-58</bibl>; <bibl
                               >Kurtz 1975, 14-16</bibl>; <bibl
                               >Boardman 1974, 148</bibl>. To these add
                                <bibl>Hornsbostel, 292, no. 254</bibl>,
                            and <bibl>Dörig 1975, nos.
                            210-11</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> was one of a number of artists who continued to work in black figure
                    long after many of his contemporaries had taken up the new red-figure technique.
                    The artist was trained in the workshop of the Edinburgh Painter, together with a
                    colleague of similar style, the Theseus Painter. The Athena Painter began work
                    around 490 B.C. and devoted himself primarily to oinochoai and lekythoi. His
                    lekythoi resemble those of the Edinburgh Painter in their standard shape, with
                    straight outline and torus foot, and in the shoulder pattern, which consists of
                    five palmettes amid dots. Our lekythos dates from the early years of the
                    artist's career, before he painted the neck black, enclosed his row of bars
                    within black lines, and added a tendril with bud to the palmettes on either side
                    of the handle. Still later lekythoi are often in white ground.</p>
                <p>The Athena Painter treated a variety of subjects, usually active
                    scenes, and on his early vases he often depicted riders, satyrs, and
                        silens.<note n="2" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Haspels 1936,
                            254-55</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> His figures do not stand upon a groundline, in the traditional manner,
                    but instead upon two red lines directly beneath the scene or upon the black
                        field.<note n="3" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Haspels 1936,
                        148</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> Characteristic features of the artist's work are the oval heads, the
                    incised outline at the top of the beard and hair, and the reverse E pattern for
                    the kneecap.<note n="4" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Haspels 1936,
                            148-49</bibl>; <bibl>Boardman 1974,
                            48</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> Typical of the date at which the painter was working is the inaccurate
                    depiction of the dolphin's flukes, which are here set vertically instead of
                        horizontally.<note n="5" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Stebbins 1919, 6, 9,
                            16</bibl>.</p>
                    </note></p>
                <p>The subject of our vase has been variously described as Arion.<note
                        n="6" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>CVA, USA fasc. 6, Robinson
                                fasc. 2, 27</bibl>. See <bibl>J. D.
                                Beazley, <title>JHS</title> 58
                        (1938):268</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> Taras,<note n="7" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p>See <bibl>J. D. Beazley, <title
                                   >JHS</title> 54 (1934):90</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> or Theseus.<note n="8" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p>See <bibl>Haspels 1936,
                            151</bibl>, and <bibl>CVA, USA fasc. 6,
                                Robinson fasc. 2, 27</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> The last identification is especially appealing since both Bacchylides
                        (<bibl n="Bacchyl. Dith. 16.97">Bacchyl.
                    16.97-100</bibl>) and Hyginus (<bibl n="Poet. Astr. II.5"
                       >Poet. Astr. II.5</bibl>) tell us that Theseus rode a dolphin
                    on his visit to<milestone n="161" unit="page"/> the Nereids
                    or to Amphitrite. Beazley believed that the second rider was merely one of the
                    repeat figures that characterize late black-figure lekythoi, and he suggested
                    that the satyr, with whom Theseus is occasionally shown, was derived from a
                    satyr play.<note n="9" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>J. D. Beazley, <title
                                   >JHS</title> 58 (1938):268 and <hi rend="ital"
                                   >JHS</hi> 54 (1934):90</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> The satyr's presence in this scene would not be inappropriate, since
                    there was a traditional connection between wine and the sea, and consequently
                    between dolphins and Dionysiac figures, such as satyrs.<note n="10"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>M. Davies 1978,
                            72-81</bibl>. Our vase is discussed on 78.</p>
                    </note></p>
                <p>Haspels, followed by Beazley, tentatively suggested that the Athena
                    Painter was identical with a red-figure artist, the Bowdoin Painter.<note n="11"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Haspels 1936, 157</bibl>;
                                <bibl>ARV2, 677</bibl>; <bibl
                               >Kurtz 1975, 16</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> The lekythoi attributed to the latter artist are similar in shape to
                    those of the Athena Painter (BL) and exhibit the Athena Painter's distinctive
                    innovations, which consist of the black neck, outlined bars, and black-figure
                    palmettes with added tendril and bud. Should the identification be correct, the
                    career of this artist extended into the second half of the fifth
                        century.<milestone n="162" unit="page"/></p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Haspels 1936, 255, no.
                        14</bibl>; <bibl>CVA, USA fasc. 4, Robinson
                            fasc. 1, 51, pl. XXXVII</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="110" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Baltimore, Hopkins AIA B6" type="vase"
                        >Baltimore, Hopkins AIA B6</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>Kylix of the Proto-Panaetian Group</title>
                    <date>ca. 490 B.C.</date>
                </p>
                <p>B 6. Baltimore Society AIA, formerly Hartwig Collection. "Chiusi."
                    Ht, 8 cm; diam with handles, 26.6 cm; diam rim, 20 cm; diam foot, 7.8 cm. Mended
                    from many pieces.</p>
                <p>Tondo is bordered by narrow reserved band. Satyr seated to his left
                    on wineskin, torso three-quarters frontal. Left knee is raised, with lower leg
                    extended; right knee is bent, with lower leg drawn back. Elbow bent with left
                    hand uplifted over head. Right hand in front of chest; fingers of both hands
                    outstretched. Head is turned back in left profile and wears fillet with long
                    ends hanging down over torso. Inscribed in field: <foreign xml:lang="greek"
                       >*P*A*N*A*I*T*I*O*S *K*A[*L]*O*S</foreign>; inscribed on
                    wineskin: <foreign xml:lang="greek">*K[*A]*L*O*S</foreign>.</p>
                <p>Relief contour throughout, except for reserved outline of beard and
                    incised contour of back of head. Dilute glaze for interior markings. Added red
                    for fillet and lettering.</p>
                <p>It was Furtwängler who first suggested that the Panaitios
                    Painter was really the youthful Onesimos.<note n="1" place="unspecified"
                        anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>FR, 134</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> This identification was endorsed by Beazley in his revised edition of
                        <hi rend="ital">ARV2,</hi> where the vases previously assigned
                    to the two artists were grouped as the work of the single painter Onesimos.<note
                        n="2" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>ARV2, 313-31</bibl>; <bibl
                               >Para., 358-61</bibl>; <bibl
                               >Boardman 1975, 133-34</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> Beazley listed our vase as one of nine cups that he believed were
                    "specially akin" to the early work of Onesimos and perhaps<milestone n="163"
                        unit="page"/> from his own hand.<note n="3"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>ARV2, 314-16</bibl>. Add:
                                <bibl>Hornbostel 1977, 307, no. 263, and
                                310, no. 264</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> Hence Beazley termed this group "Proto-Panaetian."</p>
                <p>Onesimos was a prolific and skilled painter who specialized in cups,
                    which were often supplied to him by the renowned potter and painter Euphronios.
                    Onesimos's style is distinguished by the overall mastery of draughtsmanship, and
                    particularly by his elegant patterns of elongated fingers and tails.<note n="4"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>S. Buluc, <title
                                   >AJA</title> 70 (1966):369-70</bibl>.</p>
                    </note></p>
                <p>The motif of the satyr astride a wineskin appears frequently in Attic
                    vasepainting, as does the similar image of a satyr riding a dolphin. Davies
                    reminds us of the traditional association of wine and the sea,<note n="5"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>M. Davies 1978,
                        79</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> and certainly this animated figure would have bobbed in a lively manner
                    once this cup was filled with wine and jostled by an eager symposiast.</p>
                <milestone n="164" unit="page"/>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Klein 1886, 278</bibl>; <bibl
                           >P. Hartwig, <title>Rö
                                mMitt</title> 2 (1887):167, no. 3</bibl>; <bibl
                           >Hartwig 1893, 448, pl. 44.1</bibl>; <bibl
                           >Klein 1898, 107, no. 4</bibl>; <bibl
                           >FR, 251-52, no. 1</bibl>; <bibl
                           >D. M. Robinson, <title>AJA</title> 21
                            (1917):87</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley 1918,
                        87</bibl>; <bibl>Hoppin 1919, vol. I, 421, no.
                            36</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley 1925, 167, no.
                        14</bibl>; <bibl>Philippart 1928, 50</bibl>;
                            <bibl>CVA, USA fasc. 6, Robinson fasc. 2,
                            14, pl. VII</bibl>; <bibl>ARV2, 316, no.
                        7</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="111" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Baltimore, Hopkins AIA B11" type="vase"
                        >Baltimore, Hopkins AIA B11</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>Kylix by the Antiphon Painter</title>
                    <date>490-480 B.C.</date>
                </p>
                <p>B 11. Baltimore Society AIA, formerly Hartwig Collection. "Cervetri."
                    Ht, 9.3 cm; diam with handles, 30.7 cm; diam rim, 24 cm; diam foot, 8 cm. Mended
                    from many pieces. Foot is ancient but may not belong. (Top of foot and base of
                    stem were filed for close fit.)</p>
                <p><hi rend="ital">Interior</hi>: </p>
                <p>Standing youth in left profile wears fillet and mantle, which expose
                    only top of head and face. Left arm at hip; right arm raised to chest. In field
                    before him are a sponge, strigil, aryballos. Inscribed in field on either side
                    of youth: <foreign xml:lang="greek">[epig-rough]*O *P*A*I*S
                        *K*A*L*O[*S]</foreign>. (The boy is beautiful.)</p>
                <p>Tondo is bordered by leftward meander between reserved bands.</p>
                <p><hi rend="ital">Exterior, Side A</hi>: </p>
                <p>Pankration scene. Standing at left is youth in right profile wearing
                    a mantle that exposes only top of head and eyes.</p>
                <p>Right hand beneath folds is uplifted to conceal most of face. Fillet
                    indicated by reserved band between relief lines. Hanging in field in front of
                    youth are weights and bag. Suspended nearby are strigil, sponge, and bag. In
                    center are two wrestling youths, the victor crouching with left knee drawn up,
                    torso frontal, right arm upraised. Left hand is placed over mouth of opponent,
                    who lies on his back, left hand extended over head, right forearm uplifted, legs
                    in air. Approaching them is a trainer wearing mantle over left shoulder and
                    holding staff in outstretched right hand. Head in left profile wearing taenia.</p>
                <p>Relief contour throughout, except beneath feet and incised hairlines.
                    Dilute glaze for inner markings and lettering. Added purple for fillets of youth
                    on tondo and of two figures with staffs on A and B. Vertical edge of foot
                    reserved with black line around lower edge.</p>
                <p><hi rend="ital">Exterior, Side B</hi>: </p>
                <p>Palaestra scene. Standing in right profile is trainer wearing fillet
                    and mantle draped over left shoulder, exposing right shoulder and arm. Staff in
                    left hand; right arm with rod in hand is extended to pair of wrestlers, one
                        of<milestone n="165" unit="page"/> whom is almost
                    entirely missing except for right foot. Opponent is shown in left profile, with
                    back in three-quarter view, elbows bent with hands extended.</p>
                <p>The Antiphon Painter is credited with almost one hundred cups, most
                    of which have exterior as well as tondo decoration.<note n="1"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>ARV2, 335-41</bibl>; <bibl
                               >Beazley, <title
                                >JHS</title> 58 (1938):267</bibl>; <bibl
                                >Para., 361-62</bibl>; <bibl>Boardman
                                1975, 135</bibl>; <bibl>Hornbostel 1977,
                                312, no. 266</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> The painter prefers genre scenes, either very active ones involving
                    athletes and hunters, or quiet figures like the youth in our tondo. His
                    inscriptions are general words of praise (e.g., "the boy is beautiful," as on
                    our own vase), or refer to specific individuals, such as Antiphon, for whom the
                    painter is<milestone n="166" unit="page"/> named.<note n="2"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>ARV2, 335, no.
                        1</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> Other youths who are complimented include Lysis,<note n="3"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>ARV2, 336, no. 10; 338, no.
                                39; 339, nos. 52, 60</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> Aristarchos,<note n="4" place="unspecified" anchored="true"
                       >
                        <p><bibl>ARV2, 336, no. 16</bibl>,
                            which is the same as <bibl>D. K. Hill,
                                    <title>JWalt</title> 23 (1960):16, 24</bibl>.
                            See also <bibl>Para., 362</bibl>, in
                            Schimmel Collection.</p>
                    </note> and Nikostratos.<note n="5" place="unspecified" anchored="true"
                       >
                        <p><bibl>ARV2, 337, no.
                        26</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> The Antiphon Painter worked for several potters, especially Euphronios,
                    who provided vases for Onesimos and Douris.<note n="6" place="unspecified"
                        anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>ARV2, 336, nos. 10, 14, 18;
                                337, no. 25; 339, no. 57; 340, nos. 63, 73; 341, nos. 77, 88</bibl>.
                                <bibl>Bloesch 1940, 71, 79,
                        80</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> Our artist also decorated vases for the potter Python, for whom
                    Epiktetos and Douris also worked.<note n="7" place="unspecified" anchored="true"
                       >
                        <p><bibl>ARV2, 340, no. 71</bibl>.
                            See also <bibl>ARV2, 1646</bibl> and <bibl
                               >Para., 361</bibl>.</p>
                    </note></p>
                <p>The style of the Antiphon Painter is representative of early
                    fifth-century vasepainting in the rounded, prominent jaws, the garments, which
                    fall with few folds, and the three-quarter and back views, which are not always
                    completely successful. The painter's style is close to that of the early or
                    proto-Panaetian phase of Onesimos and can be recognized by the even, almost
                    monotonous spacing of the folds, the drapery pulled tightly over the arms and
                    grasped by the fists, and the black borders just above the hems of the garments.</p>
                <p>On our cup, the scenes in the tondo and on the exterior represent a
                    palaestra where youths trained in wrestling and in the pankration.<note n="8"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Harris 1964,
                        105-9</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> Side A illustrates the beginning of the encounter, which continues on
                    side B, where the trainer gesticulates at the contestants. The sponges, strigil,
                    and aryballos were used for applying oil before exercising and for removing it
                    afterward.</p>
                <milestone n="167" unit="page"/>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>P. Hartwig, <title
                               >RömMitt</title> 2 (1887):168, no. VI</bibl>;
                            <bibl>Hartwig 1893, 575ff, pl. 64</bibl>;
                            <bibl>FR, 251-52, no. 1</bibl>; <bibl
                           >Gardiner 1910, 437</bibl>; <bibl
                           >Perrot &amp; Chipiez, vol. 10, 629, fig.
                            350</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley 1918, 111</bibl>;
                            <bibl>Hoppin 1919, vol. II, 166, no.
                        1</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley 1925, 232, no.
                        26</bibl>; <bibl>Philippart 1928, 51</bibl>;
                            <bibl>Gardiner 1930, 214, fig. 189</bibl>;
                            <bibl>CVA, USA fasc. 6, Robinson fasc. 2,
                            18-19, pls. XVII, XVIII.1</bibl>; <bibl
                            >Buschor 1940, 153, fig. 172</bibl>; <bibl
                            >ARV2, 340, no. 65</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="112" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Baltimore, Hopkins AIA B10" type="vase"
                        >Baltimore, Hopkins AIA B10</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>Kylix by Makron with Dionysiac Scene</title>
                    <date>490-480 B.C.</date>
                </p>
                <p>B 10. Baltimore Society AIA, formerly Hartwig Collection. "Caere."
                    Ht, 12.5 cm; diam with handles, 39 cm; diam rim, 29 cm; diam foot, 11.1 cm.
                    Mended from many pieces. Surface abraded.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="ital">Interior</hi>
                </p>
                <p>On exergue, dancing to their right, are two maenads in girded chitons
                    with overfolds, necklaces, bare feet. Maiden in advance stands with weight on
                    frontal left leg, right leg bent and in left profile, thyrsos in right hand. She
                    glances back at her companion, with her head in right profile, long hair bound
                    in fillet and knotted at tip. Her companion steps forth with right leg extended,
                    left knee bent, torso frontal. Upraised right hand holds small branch. Left hand
                    at hip holds end of thyrsos. Head in left profile, with hair gathered up at nape
                    and bound in fillet. Tondo is bordered by leftward meander.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="ital">Side A</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Goat beneath handle follows maenad standing in right profile holding
                    torches. In front of her is another maenad, also in right profile, carrying
                    kithara. Approaching them is Dionysos, who is standing in left profile and is
                    wearing ivy wreath and chiton beneath mantle draped over left shoulder and
                    around waist. He carries a kantharos in upraised right hand, a vine with two
                    grape bunches in left. Behind him are a maenad with castanets, another in right
                    profile blowing double flute, and a final frontal maenad with castanets. All
                    maenads wear chitons and mantles except for end maenad with castanets, who wears
                    chiton only. Sketch lines visible beside head of maenad blowing flute.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="ital">Side B</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Beneath handle is lotus and palmette scheme. Four pairs of satyrs and
                    maenads clad only in chitons and wreaths or fillets: satyr carrying maenad;
                    maenad with thyrsos repelling satyr in fawnskin, maenad resisting satyr with
                    thyrsos; dancing satyr and maenads.</p>
                <milestone n="168" unit="page"/>
                <p>Relief contour throughout, except for reserved hairline. Added red
                    for vine leaves and some wreaths. Reserved line beneath scene; reserved line
                    above scene except at handles.</p>
                <p>Makron was a prolific painter; almost three hundred fifty vases are
                    attributed to him.<note n="1" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>ARV2, 458-81</bibl>; <bibl
                               >J. D. Beazley, <title
                                    >JHS</title> 58 (1938):267</bibl>; <bibl
                               >Para., 377-79</bibl>; <bibl
                               >Boardman 1975, 140</bibl>. Add: <bibl
                               >A. Ashmead and K. Phillips, <title
                                    >AJA</title> 70 (1966):366-68</bibl>; <bibl
                               >CVA, USA fasc. 17, Toledo fasc. 1, 34, pls.
                            53-54</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> He primarily painted cups, but he also worked on skyphoi, plates,
                    aryballoi, askoi, and at least one pyxis. He signed only one vase, a skyphos in
                    Boston that also bears the signature of Hieron the potter.<note n="2"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>ARV2, 458, no. 1, and
                                perhaps 479, no. 336</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> We know that Hieron and Makron had a particularly close association,
                    since thirty-one vases that bear the signature of Hieron have been attributed to
                    Makron; occasionally, however, Hieron fashioned vases for other artists.<note
                        n="3" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Bloesch 1940, 91-96</bibl>;
                                <bibl>ARV2, 481-82</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> Our cup has the unusual shape of Type C, which is characterized by an
                    offset lip, a bulge in the stem, and a flat, platelike foot.<note n="4"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Bloesch 1940, 111, and 132,
                                nos. 17-19</bibl>.</p>
                    </note></p>
                <p>Makron has a penchant for komos scenes involving numerous animated
                    figures with objects in uplifted hands. The maenads usually wear closely pleated
                    chitons with billowing overfolds and carry thyrsoi. The ornamental motifs under
                    the handles vary greatly.<note n="5" place="unspecified" anchored="true"
                       >
                        <p><bibl>Ashmead and Phillips,
                                    <title>AJA</title> 70 (1966):366-68</bibl>. Ours
                            is especially close to <bibl>Simon &amp;
                                Hirmer 1976, pl. 169</bibl>, which is the same as <bibl
                               >ARV2, 462, no. 48</bibl>.</p>
                    </note></p>
                <p>Makron did not rely heavily on his sketch lines, but often
                    disregarded those delineating the drapery or the head, as can be seen in the
                    figure of the maenad in the middle of side A.<note n="6" place="unspecified"
                        anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>R. DePuma, <title
                                   >AJA</title> 72 (1968):152-54</bibl>.</p>
                    </note></p>
                <milestone n="171" unit="page"/>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>P. Hartwig, <title
                               >RömMitt</title> 2 (1887):168, no. VII</bibl>;
                            <bibl>Hartwig 1893, 289-94, pls. 30.3 and
                        31</bibl>; <bibl>FR, 251-52, no. 1</bibl>; <bibl
                           >FR, 237</bibl>; <bibl
                           >Beazley 1918, 101, 103, no. 28</bibl>; <bibl
                           >Hoppin 1919, vol. II, 96, no. 43</bibl>; <bibl
                           >Beazley 1925, 214, no. 35</bibl>; <bibl
                           >Jacobsthal 1927, 132</bibl>; <bibl
                           >L. Lawler, <title
                            >MAAR</title> 6 (1927), pls. XIX.1, XX.4</bibl>; <bibl
                           >Philippart 1928, 50-51</bibl>; <bibl
                           >CVA, USA fasc. 6, Robinson fasc. 2, 17-18, pls. XV,
                        XVI.1</bibl>; <bibl>ARV2, 463, no.
                    51</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="113" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Baltimore, Hopkins AIA B13" type="vase"
                        >Baltimore, Hopkins AIA B13</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>Neck Amphora by the Harrow Painter</title>
                    <date>ca. 480 B.C.</date>
                </p>
                <p>B 13. Baltimore Society AIA, formerly Hartwig Collection. "Tarentum."
                    Ht, 39 cm; diam mouth, 16.1 cm; diam foot, 11 cm. Mended from many pieces, with
                    handles and most of rim restored in plaster. Foot is ancient but may not belong.
                    Alien lid with which vase was first published is now at the University of
                    Mississippi.</p>
                <p>Scenes on both sides are unframed, with figures standing on narrow
                    bands as groundlines.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="ital">Side A</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Silenos strides forward in right profile, hands bound behind back.
                    Following him is a bearded hunter who looks back, head in left profile. Hunter
                    wears boots, short chiton that has a black border at neckline and hem, and
                    petasos hanging behind neck. Right hand holds two spears; left hand hold ends of
                    the thongs that wrap Silenos's wrists. To the hunter's left is hunting dog.</p>
                <p>Relief contour line throughout. Relief line for drapery detail, top
                    of boots, thongs. Hair outlined in reserve. Dilute glaze for inner details of
                    body, neck and sleeve of chiton. Added purple for petasos cord, thongs of
                    Silenos.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="ital">Side B</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Bearded Midas stands three-quarters left, face in left profile. He
                    wears a pleated chiton beneath himation, carries staff in upraised right hand.
                    Some relief contours. Hair and beard outlined in reserve. Dilute glaze for inner
                    details of chiton.</p>
                <p>Tongues above each picture, terminating beneath handles. Graffito on
                    shoulder.</p>
                <p>When Dionysos was passing through Asia Minor, Silenos, a human-equine
                    member of the entourage, wandered away and was captured by a hunter who brought
                    the captive to King Midas.<note n="1" place="unspecified" anchored="true"
                       >
                        <p><bibl n="Hdt. 8.138">Hdt.
                            8.138</bibl>; <bibl n="Xen. Anab. 1.2.13"
                                >Xen. Anab. 1.2.13</bibl>. See <bibl
                                >Brommer 1941, 36</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> The king returned Silenos to Dionysos, and the grateful deity agreed as
                    a reward to grant Midas's wish that everything he touched be turned to gold.
                    Midas soon discovered, however, that all food and drink became golden, too, and
                    thus he appealed to Dionysos to<milestone n="172" unit="page"
                       /> remove the magic touch. The god instructed Midas to
                    wash in the river Pactolus, which henceforth became renowned for its
                    gold-bearing sands.</p>
                <p>This adventure of Midas was first seen on Chiote and Spartan vases of
                    the mid-sixth century.<note n="2" place="unspecified" anchored="true"
                       >
                        <p><bibl>F. Brommer, <title
                                   >AntK Beiheft</title> 7 (1970):55-57</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> Around the year 500 B.C. the subject appeared in Attic vase-painting,
                    where it remained popular for the next one hundred fifty years.<note n="3"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Brommer 1941,
                        43</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> Artists depicted several different moments in the tale, including the
                    capture of Silenos in Midas's garden, his abduction to King Midas, and his
                    presentation before the king. Not before the fifth century do we find Midas
                    depicted in oriental dress,<note n="4" place="unspecified" anchored="true"
                       >
                        <p><bibl>F. Brommer, <title
                                   >AntK Beiheft</title> 7 (1970): 56</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> and after 450 B.C. he wears the ass ears that he acquired by unwisely
                    voting against Apollo in a musical competition.<note n="5" place="unspecified"
                        anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Ibid., 56</bibl>; <bibl
                               >Brommer 1941, 43</bibl>; <bibl
                                n="Ovid Met. 11.153">Ovid Met.
                                11.153ff.</bibl>; <bibl n="Hyginus Fab. 191.1"
                               >Hyginus Fab. 191.1</bibl>.</p>
                    </note></p>
                <p>The Harrow Painter is known for almost one hundred large vases, of
                    which half are amphorae and column kraters.<note n="6" place="unspecified"
                        anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>ARV2, 272-77</bibl>; <bibl
                               >Para., 353-54</bibl>, with note on alien
                            lid, which is in Mississippi, not Cambridge. <bibl
                               >J. D. Beazley, <title>JHS</title> 58
                                (1938):267-68</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> The profile of the body of the Baltimore example compares most closely
                    with those of the artist's neck amphorae with twisted handles, and for this
                    reason twisted handles have been restored on our vessel.<note n="7"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p>Our vase is especially similar to <bibl
                               >ARV2, 272, no. 6</bibl>, upon which the restoration
                            of our vase is based. I thank very much D. von Bothmer, who provided
                            photographs and advice. Through no fault of his, the handles of our
                            restoration are not quite correctly proportioned.</p>
                    </note></p>
                <p>The Harrow Painter was most comfortable with genre subjects, but on
                    his amphorae he occasionally turned to mythological and especially Dionysiac
                    themes. His style was inspired primarily by that of the Berlin Painter, whose
                    influence is apparent in the use of one or two quietly standing figures on each
                    side of the amphora, and in the tendency to distribute figures from a single
                    scene on both sides of the vase. The Harrow Painter falls short of the Berlin
                    Painter, however, both in draughtsmanship and in the ability to endow a scene
                    with emotional content. Our painter also has a tendency to repeat his figures,
                    especially the older man draped in a mantle.<note n="8" place="unspecified"
                        anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>ARV2, 272, no. 8</bibl>,
                            which is the same as <bibl>Münzen, 40
                                (December 13, 1969): 60, no. 100, pl. 41</bibl>. <bibl
                               >ARV2, 273, no. 19 bis</bibl>, is the same as <bibl
                               >Münzen, 13 (May 1961): 89, no.
                                165, pl. 55</bibl>.</p>
                    </note></p>
                <p>The graffito on the shoulder of the vessel was applied after the vase
                    was fired. Although most graffiti are thought to carry a commercial meaning, the
                    unusual position of this mark may denote ownership or dedication.<note n="9"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Boardman 1974, 202</bibl>;
                                <bibl>Johnston 1979, 5, 6, 8</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> The lettering is Etruscan or possibly Oscan.<note n="10"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p>I owe this suggestion to A. Johnston.</p>
                    </note></p>
                <milestone n="174" unit="page"/>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>FR, 252, no. 3</bibl>; <bibl
                           >J. D. Beazley, <title
                            >JHS</title> 36 (1916):133, no. 30</bibl>; <bibl
                           >Beazley 1918, 56</bibl>; <bibl
                           >Hoppin 1919, vol. II, 3, no. 3</bibl>; <bibl
                           >Beazley 1925, 120, no. 40</bibl>; <bibl
                           >CVA, USA fasc. 6, Robinson fasc. 2, 25, pls. XXIX,
                        XXX</bibl>; <bibl>Brommer 1941, 40, no. 4, and
                            44, fig. 6</bibl>; <bibl><title
                               >Ancient Art in American Private Collections</title>
                            (Cambridge, 1954), no. 278, pl. LXXXIII</bibl>; <bibl
                           >ARV2, 73, no. 22</bibl>; <bibl
                           >Brommer 1973, 535, no. B4</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="114" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Baltimore, Hopkins AIA B9" type="vase"
                        >Baltimore, Hopkins AIA B9</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>Kylix by Douris</title>
                    <date>480-470 B.C.</date>
                </p>
                <p>B 9. Baltimore Society AIA, formerly Hartwig Collection. "Chiusi."
                    Ht, 9.5 cm; diam with handles, 30 cm; diam rim, 22.5 cm; diam foot, 8.7 cm.
                    Mended.</p>
                <p>Standing on exergue is a bearded male bending over a whip top, his
                    supporting right leg frontal, his left leg in left profile. In the hand of his
                    upraised right arm is a stick, on which there are three strings. His left hand
                    rests on his left knee. His torso is largely concealed by his chlamys, which is
                    fastened on his right shoulder. His head is in right profile and he wears a
                    petasos. In field below his right elbow is a floral motif. On other side of top
                    is youth whose torso faces three-quarters front, legs in left profile, right arm
                    extended, left hand on hip. Mantle draped over body and back of head, exposing
                    only right shoulder and arm. Fillet. In field above his head is a floral motif.
                    Inscribed in field: <foreign xml:lang="greek">*K*A*L*O*S
                    *X*H</foreign>.</p>
                <p>Relief contour throughout, except for reserved hairline. Dilute glaze
                    for some inner markings. Added red for strings of stick and lettering. Border
                    consists of rightward meander.</p>
                <p>The petasos and chlamys suggest that the top-spinner is Hermes, and
                    this identification is confirmed by vases in Florence<note n="1"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>CVA, Italy fasc. 38,
                                Florence fasc. 4, 6-7, pl. 124.2</bibl>, which is the same as <bibl
                               >ARV2, no. 113, p. 377</bibl>. Also <bibl
                               >J. D. Beazley, <title
                                    >JHS</title> 58 (1938):267</bibl>. For Hermes in traveler's
                            attire, see <bibl>Zanker 1965,
                            115-116</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> and Tübingen<note n="2" place="unspecified" anchored="true"
                       >
                        <p><bibl>Watzinger 1924, 44, no.
                                E78, pl. 25</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> on which Hermes, outfitted with kerykeion and winged sandals, is engaged
                    in spinning a top. Beazley<note n="3" place="unspecified" anchored="true"
                       >
                        <p><bibl>Beazley, <title
                                   >JHS</title> 58 (1938): 267</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> suggests that, after receiving the whip from Apollo (<bibl
                        n="HH Herm. 497">HH Herm. 497</bibl>), Hermes
                    invented the whip top, although other types of tops subsequently evolved.<note
                        n="4" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>D. Gould, <title
                                   >Expedition</title> 22 (1980):43-47</bibl>. Our
                            vase is on p. 44, fig. 4.</p>
                    </note> We are perhaps to imagine that the god is in the palaestra, an area
                        sacred<milestone n="175" unit="page"/> to Hermes and an
                    association that accounts for the deity's special rapport with youth.<note n="5"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Zanker 1965, 94,
                        99</bibl>.</p>
                    </note></p>
                <p>This cup belongs to Douris's late period,<note n="6"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>ARV2, 425-27</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> when the stopt meander was common, the drawing was delicate, and the
                    small figures were well contained within the circular field. At this time Douris
                    was working primarily for the potter Python.</p>
                <milestone n="176" unit="page"/>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>P. Hartwig, <title
                               >RömMitt</title> 2 (1887):169, no. 9</bibl>;
                            <bibl>Hartwig 1893, 657-59, pl. 72.2</bibl>;
                            <bibl>FR, 251-52, no. 1</bibl>; <bibl
                           >P. Wolters, <title
                            >MJb</title> 8 (1913):89, fig. 7</bibl>; <bibl
                           >Beazley 1918, 97</bibl>; <bibl
                           >Hoppin 1919, vol. I, 277, no. 46</bibl>; <bibl
                           >Beazley 1925, 208, no. 119</bibl>; <bibl
                           >Philippart 1928, 50</bibl>; <bibl
                           >CVA, USA fasc. 6, Robinson fasc. 2, 16, pl.
                            XII</bibl>; <bibl>Zschietzschmann 1959, pl.
                            181.2</bibl>; <bibl>ARV2, 445, no.
                        251</bibl>; <bibl>D. Gould, <title
                               >Expedition</title> 22 (1980):44, fig. 4</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="115" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Baltimore, Hopkins AIA B12" type="vase"
                        >Baltimore, Hopkins AIA B12</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>Kylix in the Manner of the Pistoxenus Painter</title>
                    <date>ca. 460 B.C.</date>
                </p>
                <p>B 12. Baltimore Society AIA, formerly Hartwig Collection. Max
                    dimension, 24 cm; diam tondo, 14.3 cm. Mended from a number of pieces, with
                    large sections and stem missing.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="ital">Interior</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Bearded satyr dances in left profile, weight on left leg, with right
                    leg raised. Right arm extended. Left hand holds a panther skin behind back; feet
                    of skin brought forward over shoulder. Drinking horn in field before left foot.
                    Tondo is bordered by leftward meander between reserved bands.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="ital">Side A</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Maenad dressed in chiton with overfold and sakkos reclines to her
                    left against a rock, with legs drawn up and thyrsos resting against left
                    shoulder. She looks to her left at an approaching bearded satyr, shown in left
                    profile with arms outstretched. Drinking horn in field between figures. Behind
                    maenad is another bearded satyr standing frontally with right knee bent, left
                    leg extended out behind him. Right hand grasps phallus, left arm extended toward
                    maenad. Drinking horn in field behind him. Relief contour. Dilute glaze for
                    hair, beard, some drapery folds.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="ital">Side B</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Left leg of satyr running toward maenad, of whom only the lower part
                    draped in chiton survives. To her left is hand or tail or another satyr. Dilute
                    glaze for chiton. Ivy leaf under handles.</p>
                <p>Beazley determined that fragments in Florence belong to side B, which
                    also depicts a Dionysiac scene<note n="1" place="unspecified" anchored="true"
                       >
                        <p><bibl>ARV2, 865, no. 2</bibl>;
                                <bibl>Beazley 1933a, 16, no.
                        42</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> in which a maenad is turning toward a satyr approaching from her right;
                    behind her is another satyr who runs away.</p>
                <p>The Pistoxenus Painter is accredited with over thirty vases, most of
                    which are cups.<note n="2" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>ARV2, 859-63</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> His best work is in white ground, of which only a handful of examples
                    are known. Both Pistoxenus and Euphronios are known to have supplied pots for
                    him.</p>
                <p>This vase was acquired in a restored state that incorporated the
                    fragment by Oltos (no. 101).</p>
                <milestone n="177" unit="page"/>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>D. M. Robinson, <title
                               >AJA</title> 21 (1917):160-68</bibl>; <bibl
                           >Beazley 1933a, no. 42, pl. 16</bibl>; <bibl
                           >CVA, USA fasc. 6, Robinson fasc. 2, 20, pl.
                            XXI.1</bibl>; <bibl>ARV2, 865, no.
                    2</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="116" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Baltimore, Hopkins BMA 51.486" type="vase"
                        >Baltimore, Hopkins BMA 51.486</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>Bell Krater by the Christie Painter</title>
                    <date>ca. 440 B.C.</date>
                </p>
                <p>51.486. Baltimore Museum of Art, from collection of Saidie May,
                    purchased from J. Brummer. "Attica." Ht, 37 cm; diam rim, 32.5 cm; diam foot,
                    17.8 cm. Intact.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="ital">Side A</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Striding winged Eos in right profile, left leg advanced, arms
                    extended. She wears chiton with belted overfold; hair gathered at nape and
                    surmounted by diadem with ornament executed in pellets of clay. In front of her
                    and moving away is Kephalos, left leg advanced, head turned back in left
                    profile. He wears chlamys fastened on right shoulder, laurel wreath, petasos
                    hanging behind neck, and laced sandals. He carries two spears in his right hand.
                    Behind Eos and moving away from her is similarly attired youth, grazing back at
                    Eos, with his head in right profile. Inscribed in field above hand of Eos:
                        <foreign xml:lang="greek">*K]*A*L*E</foreign>.</p>
                <p>Relief contour for face, back of neck, edge of wings of Eos, faces,
                    and spears of youths. Relief line for drapery folds. Dilute glaze for ends of
                    hair, borders of garments, thongs of boots, details on wings. Added white for
                    ornament on diadem, laurel wreath, lettering. Reserved hairline.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="ital">Side B</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Standing youth seen in right profile leans on staff and faces two
                    other youths standing in left profile. All are draped in himatia and wear
                    fillets; central youth also leans on staff. In field are halteres and bag. Added
                    white for cords of bag and fillets. Reserved hairlines.</p>
                <p>Beneath pictures is band of meander alternating with dotted
                    cross-square; reserved band beneath. Leftward laurel wreath between reserved
                    bands encircles vase above pictures. Band of tongues around base of handles.
                    Reserved groove at juncture of body and foot.</p>
                <p>About fifty vases have been attributed to the Christie Painter, of
                    which twenty-five are bell kraters, the rest being calyx kraters, stamnoi,
                    pelikai, and hydriai.<note n="1" place="unspecified" anchored="true"
                       >
                        <p><bibl>ARV2, 1046-49</bibl>; <bibl
                               >Para., 444, 517</bibl>; <bibl
                               >J. D. Beazley, <title
                                    >JHS</title> 58 (1938):268</bibl>; Hornbostel, 335, no. 286.</p>
                    </note> Common to many of these vases are a meander and saltire border and a
                    representation of three standing youths on the reverse.<note n="2"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Buitron 1972, 128, no.
                            71</bibl>, which is the same as ARV2, 1047, no. 20; <bibl
                               >Hornbostel 1977, 335, no. 286</bibl>.</p>
                    </note></p>
                <p>The Christie Painter favors Dionysiac themes and lively mythological
                    scenes, such as Amazonomachies. On our vase, Eos, the goddess of dawn, is
                        eagerly<milestone n="178" unit="page"/> pursuing the
                    Attic hunter Kephalos; according to some traditions, the offspring of that union
                    will be Phaethon.<note n="3" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>S. Kaempf-Dimitriadou,
                                    <title>AntK Beiheft</title> 11 (1979):17, 61 n.
                                94</bibl>; <bibl n="Hes. Th. 986ff."
                                >Hes. Th. 986ff.</bibl>; <bibl n="Paus. 1.3.1"
                               >Paus. 1.3.1</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> The Christie Painter took up the subject a second time on a bell krater
                    (now in Genoa) on which Eos again advances to her left, but now hastens to
                    embrace a youth with a lyre.<note n="4" place="unspecified" anchored="true"
                       >
                        <p><bibl>ARV2, 1048, no. 28</bibl>,
                            which is the same as <rs type="vase">Genoa 1216</rs>; <bibl
                               >CVA, Italy fasc. 19, Genoa fasc. 1, 6,
                                pl. 9</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> That figure is Tithonos, who requested from the deity eternal life but
                    forgot to ask for eternal youth. As Tithonos grew older and less attractive, Eos
                    enclosed him in a chamber, where according to some traditions he was transformed
                    into a cicada.<note n="5" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl n="Hom. Od. 5.1">Hom. Od.
                                5.1</bibl>; <bibl n="HH 5.218">HH
                            5.218</bibl>; <bibl n="Hellanikos frag. 140 Jacoby"
                               >Hellanikos frag. 140 Jacoby</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> Behind Eos is a youth identical to the figure retreating from Eos on the
                    Hopkins vase. The youth on the Genoa krater has been identified as Kephalos and
                    the scene has been described as a conflation of the two romantic episodes.<note
                        n="6" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>CVA, Genoa fasc. 1, 6, pl.
                                9</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> On the Hopkins vase, the retreating hunter is probably only a nameless,
                    decorative pendant to Kephalos and typical of the unrelated bystanders who often
                    appear in contemporary representations of the myth.<note n="7"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Kaempf-Dimitriadou, <title
                                   >AntK Beiheft</title> 11 (1979):18</bibl>.</p>
                    </note></p>
                <p>The subjects of Eos and Tithonos and of Eos and Kephalos were very
                    popular in late sixth- and early fifth-century vasepainting. The striking
                    similarities between the representations suggest that the vasepaintings were
                    inspired by a single pictorial prototype.<note n="8" place="unspecified"
                        anchored="true">
                        <p>See late archaic metope from Selinus [<bibl
                               >Holloway 1975, 19, 22</bibl>]. <bibl
                               >Kaempf-Dimitriadou, <title>AntK
                                    Beiheft</title> 11 (1979):16-21</bibl>; <bibl
                               >Trendall 1967, 16</bibl>.</p>
                    </note></p>
                <p>The Christie Painter exercised a tremendous influence on a
                    contemporary early Lucanian painter, the Pisticci Painter, who imitated the
                    ornament and style of the Attic artist and even depicted the myth of Eos and
                    Tithonos on at least three vases. The similarities between the two painters are
                    so extensive that it is possible that the Pisticci Painter was trained in Athens
                    and was even Greek.<note n="9" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Trendall 1967, 9</bibl>;
                                <bibl>Trendall 1966, 16</bibl>; <bibl
                               >B. MacDonald, <title
                                >AJA</title> 85 (1981): 160</bibl>.</p>
                    </note></p>
                <milestone n="179" unit="page"/>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>CVA, USA fasc. 6, Robinson
                            fasc. 2, 32-33, pl. XLV</bibl>; <bibl>ARV2,
                            1048, no. 27</bibl>; <bibl>S.
                            Kaempf-Dimitriadou, <title>AntK Beiheft</title> 11
                            (1979):85, no. 110</bibl>; <bibl>Brommer
                            1980, 24, no. 49</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="117" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Baltimore, Hopkins BMA 41.134" type="vase"
                        >Baltimore, Hopkins BMA 41.134</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>White-Ground Lekythos</title>
                    <date>440-420 B.C.</date>
                </p>
                <p>41.134. (P.4015 on underside of foot.) Baltimore Museum of Art, gift
                    of Blanche Adler, purchased in 1926 from Joseph Brummer. Ht, 24.6 cm; diam
                    mouth, 4.6 cm; diam foot, 4.8 cm. Handle is probably not original.</p>
                <p>Color of figure scene and ornament fired red. Maiden in right profile
                    holds object (now missing) in both hands. The color of her garment has faded,
                    leaving only her nude body. She stands before a grave stele wrapped with taenia
                    and surmounting stepped base. On other side of stele is youth, standing
                    frontally, head in left profile. He wears a himation, which is draped over his
                    body, exposing his right shoulder and breast.</p>
                <p>Upper surface of lip reserved. On neck is tongue pattern between
                    single lines. On shoulder is scheme of three five-petal palmettes entwined in
                    volutes. Central palmette is inverted, other two are turned toward handle. Above
                    picture is meander in groups of three, alternately leftward and rightward,
                    separated by saltire squares. Two lines above and beneath. Single line under
                    picture.</p>
                <p>The white-ground technique developed in Athens at the end of the
                    sixth century B.C. The artist outlined his figures upon a field of white slip
                    before firing the vase. After the vessel was removed from the kiln, matte colors
                    were applied, but because this paint was not baked onto the vase, the colors
                    have often faded or vanished.<note n="1" place="unspecified" anchored="true"
                       >
                        <p><bibl>Kurtz 1975, XX</bibl>.</p>
                    </note></p>
                <p>From its early years, the technique was applied to lekythoi, but it
                    was only in the second quarter of the fifth century that white-ground lekythoi
                    regularly depicted funerary subjects and became primarily associated with the
                        grave.<note n="2" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Kurtz 1975, XIX</bibl>;
                                <bibl>Kurtz &amp; Boardman 1971,
                                102-5</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> The vessels were used to hold libations of olive oil and were placed as
                    offerings at the base of the grave stele or were buried with the deceased.<note
                        n="3" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Kurtz 1975, XIX</bibl>;
                                <bibl>Beazley 1938, 5</bibl>.</p>
                    </note></p>
                <p>In the middle of the fifth century the Achilles Painter dispensed
                    with the relief line heretofore used for outlining the figures and introduced
                    the softer matte paint that would become almost canonical on later lekythoi like
                    ours. Our vase is surely the product of the Bird Group, a large workshop that
                    was active in the 430's and 420's under the leadership of the Bird Painter,<note
                        n="4" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>ARV2, 1231-235;
                            1687-688</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 467</bibl>;
                                <bibl>Kurtz 1975, 52-55</bibl>. His
                            palmettes are IIa.</p>
                    </note> and in which the Painter of Munich 2335 may also have worked. The
                    palmette ornament on the neck of our lekythos is characteristic of vases by this
                    latter artist, as is the emotional note conveyed by the sharply downturned head
                    of the maiden.<note n="5" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>ARV2, 1168-169, 1685, 1703,
                                1707</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 458-59</bibl>;
                                <bibl>Kurtz 1975, 55-56</bibl>. His
                            palmettes are also IIa. See also <bibl>F.
                                Felton, <title>AthMitt</title> 91 (1976):94, no. 28,
                                pl. 29 and 94, no. 29, pl. 30</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> We might also compare examples by the Bird Painter<note n="6"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>ARV2, 1232, no. 10</bibl>.
                            I owe this and the following comparison to D. Kurtz.</p>
                    </note> and by another colleague, the Carlsberg Painter.<note n="7"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>ARV2, 1235, no.
                        10</bibl>.</p>
                    </note></p>
                <milestone n="180" unit="page"/>
            </div>
            <div n="118" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Baltimore, Hopkins BMA 41.133" type="vase"
                        >Baltimore, Hopkins BMA 41.133</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>White-Ground Lekythos</title>
                    <date>440-420 B.C.</date>
                </p>
                <p>41.133. (P.2468 on underside of foot.) Baltimore Museum of Art, gift
                    of Blanche Adler. Ht, 28.7 cm; diam mouth, 5.8 cm; diam foot, 5.2 cm. Chipped
                    all over.</p>
                <p>Color of figure scene and ornament fired red. Nude maiden, seen in
                    right profile, carries a duck in her extended hands and approaches a grave stele
                    on stepped base. On other side of stele is youth in left profile with right arm
                    extended. He is draped in a red cloak.</p>
                <p>Upper surface of lip reserved. On shoulder beneath single line is
                    palmette scheme of three five-petal palmettes entwined in volutes. Central
                    palmette inverted, other two turned toward handle. Upper border of picture
                    consists of meander grouped in threes, alternately leftward and rightward,
                    separated by saltire squares. Two lines above and beneath. Single line under
                    picture.</p>
                <p>Like the previous example, this lekythos can also be attributed to an
                    artist of the Bird Group, a workshop headed by the Bird Painter, whose work this
                    vessel particularly recalls, both in the configuration of the palmette pattern
                    and in the less emphatic poignancy of the representation.<note n="1"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>ARV2, 1231-235</bibl>;
                                <bibl>Para., 467</bibl>; <bibl
                               >Kurtz 1975, 52-55</bibl>. Compare <bibl
                               >ARV2, 1233, no. 23</bibl>, a comparison
                            I owe to D. Kurtz.</p>
                    </note> In contrast to the maiden on the preceding vase, the figure on our
                    example has more delicate features, with a shorter face and a more subtly
                    rounded profile of the nose.<note n="2" place="unspecified" anchored="true"
                       >
                        <p>See <bibl>ARV2, 1687-688</bibl>,
                            and <bibl>Para., 467</bibl>, for his late
                            and fine style. See also <bibl>F. Felton,
                                    <title>AthMitt</title> 91
                        (1976):99-100</bibl>.</p>
                    </note></p>
                <milestone n="182" unit="page"/>
            </div>
            <div n="119" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Baltimore, Hopkins 9286" type="vase"
                        >Baltimore, Hopkins 9286</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>Bell Krater by Hoppin Painter</title>
                    <date>ca. 380-350 B.C.</date>
                </p>
                <p>9286. Robinson Collection. "Tarentum." Ht, 34.8 cm; diam rim, 38 cm;
                    diam foot, 19 cm. Intact.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="ital">Side A</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Three figures run in left profile. In front is bearded nude male with
                    pail in left hand, torch in uplifted right hand, and cloak over shoulders. In
                    center is woman dressed in chiton with overfold, her right hand uplifted, her
                    left hand holding a tympanum. Behind her is nude youth carrying jug in right
                    hand. His mantle is flung over the left arm and hand, in which he holds a spear.
                    Relief contour for some details. Band of wave pattern above figures.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="ital">Side B</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Bearded youth with short, curly hair stands in right profile and
                    addresses two youths who turn toward him. All figures are enveloped in long
                    mantles to ankles. Youth in center holds staff in right hand; in field behind
                    his head is reserved disc.</p>
                <p>Figures on both sides stand on narrow reserved band above band of
                    leftward meander that terminates below handles in dotted cross-square, from
                    which rises a scroll motif. Above pictures is leftward laurel band between
                    reserved bands. Zone of tongues around roots of handles.</p>
                <p>This krater is one of eleven vases attributed to the Hoppin Painter,
                    who with five colleagues formed the Hoppin Group, painting in the Plain Apulian
                        style.<note n="1" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Trendall 1966, 20</bibl>;
                                <bibl>Cambitoglou &amp; Trendall
                                1961, 55-56</bibl>. Our vase is p. 56, no. 2.</p>
                    </note> The workshop was located in Tarentum and was active between about 380
                    and 350 B.C. The Hoppin Painter was probably trained by artists of the school of
                    the Tarporley Painter (400-380 B.C.), a disciple of the Sisyphos Painter, who
                    originated both the Plain and the Ornate Styles.</p>
                <p>The Hoppin Painter worked mostly on bell kraters, although he also
                    painted one pelike and one calyx krater. His vases are recognized by their tall,
                    slim figures with flying drapery, the wrapped heads of the women, and the youths
                    with white fillets and himatia draped over their arms.<note n="2"
                        place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Cambitoglou &amp;
                                Trendall 1961, 55</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> The three figures on the reverse of our vase also appear on vases by the
                    artist in Lecce<note n="3" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Cambitoglou &amp;
                                Trendall 1961, 56, no. 3</bibl>, and <rs type="vase"
                                >Lecce 620</rs>, <bibl>CVA, Italy fasc.
                                6, Lecce fasc. 2, pl. 12</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> and Cambridge.<note n="4" place="unspecified" anchored="true"
                       >
                        <p><bibl>Cambitoglou &amp;
                                Trendall 1961, 56, no. 1</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> The style of the Hoppin Painter is especially close to that of the Lecce
                        Painter,<note n="5" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Cambitoglou &amp;
                                Trendall 1961, 62</bibl>.</p>
                    </note> who was active at about the same time, the second quarter of the fourth
                    century.</p>
                <milestone n="185" unit="page"/>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>FR, 252, no. 4</bibl>; <bibl
                           >CVA, USA fasc. 7, Robinson fasc. 3, 27, pl.
                            XIX</bibl>; <bibl>Trendall 1938, 26 n.
                        41</bibl>; <bibl>Cambitoglou &amp; Trendall
                            1961, 56, no. 2</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="120" type="entry" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                <head>
                    <rs key="Perseus:object:Baltimore, Hopkins 42.70" type="vase"
                        >Baltimore, Hopkins 42.70</rs>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <title>South Italian Squat Lekythos</title>
                    <date>ca. 350-325 B.C.</date>
                </p>
                <p>42.70. Brooklyn Museum Gift. "Apulia, near Capua." Ht, 31.7 cm; diam
                    rim, 9.2 cm; diam foot, 13.1 cm. Mended and restored. Deposit over surface.</p>
                <p>Youth seated in left profile turns his head to gaze behind him. He is
                    nude except for mantle draped across waist and legs. He holds a staff in his
                    outstretched right hand. Behind him is draped standing maiden, turning to her
                    left. In front of her is Dionysos, seated three-quarters to his right with nude
                    torso, mantle draped over legs. In his right hand he holds a thyrsos. He turns
                    his head to glance back at a standing female in left profile who holds a thyrsos
                    in her right hand. Extensive use of added white.</p>
                <p>Tongues around lower half of neck; band of wave pattern on shoulder
                    above reserved band. Figures stand on white band enclosed by black bounding
                    lines. Beneath is band of wave pattern beneath dotted white line, then white and
                    black bands. At back is seventeen-petal palmette amid scrolls.</p>
                <p>This vase was identified by Trendall as a product of the LNO Painter,
                    who worked in the Cumaean shop of the CA Painter during the third quarter of the
                    fourth century.<note n="1" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <p><bibl>Trendall 1967</bibl>. Our
                            vase is 480, no. 282, pl. 185. See discussion on 479-83.</p>
                    </note> Trendall points out that the LNA Painter was influenced by the Orvieto
                    and CC Sub-groups (Cumae A) within the CA workshop, as well as by another
                    subgroup, the Apulianizing Group (340-320 B.C.), best represented by the Ivy
                    Leaf Painter (Cumae A II).</p>
                <p>The Hopkins vase is characteristic of Cumaean painting in its
                    generous use of white, yellow, and red paint, and its spiky stephanai.
                    Distinctive of the LNO Painter are the tall headdresses on the women and the
                    quiet groupings of standing and seated figures with multiple attributes.</p>
                <div type="bibl" org="uniform" sample="complete">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <p><bibl>Trendall 1967, 480, no. 282,
                            pl. 185</bibl>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
