<?xml version="1.0"?>





<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
	<title>The Achilles Painter</title>
	<author>John H. Oakley</author>
	<sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor><principal>Gregory Crane</principal><respStmt><resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp><name>Lisa Cerrato</name></respStmt>
	&fund.NEA;
      </titleStmt>
	<publicationStmt><publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher><pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace><authority>Perseus Project</authority></publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
	<note anchored="true">John H. Oakley, The College of William and Mary in Virginia
      </note></notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
	<p>Created in electronic form.
      </p></sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>

    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl>
	<refState unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
	<language ident="en">English
	</language><language ident="xgreek">Transliterated Greek
      </language></langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
    
    <revisionDesc><!--
      <change><date>24 September 1999</date>
	<respStmt><name>DAS</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>
	$Log: vp.ach.xml,v $
	Revision 1.1  2009-12-09 18:06:56  rsingh04
	moved more xml files around based on copyright status

	Revision 1.3  2009/03/04 21:44:16  lcerrato
	fixing bad bibls

	Revision 1.2  2005/08/18 13:56:33  packel
	fixed item tags

	Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 15:06:06  packel
	Converted to XML
	
Revision 1.5  2003/07/01 22:18:53  yorkc
Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)

Revision 1.4  2000/06/19 21:39:28  dasmith
Make all FIGURES REND="float".

Revision 1.3  2000/03/04 20:35:23  dasmith
Added separate funder entity to TEI header.

Revision 1.2  1999/09/24 22:19:50  dasmith
Converted to TEI2 tagging.


</item></change>
    --> <change when="2014-11-13" who="Stella Dee">edited markup and assigned CTS URN</change></revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
<text><body>
<div type="section" n="1"><head>Introduction</head>

<p>A large belly amphora in the Vatican displays the figure of a warrior labelled Achilles on the front (<rs key="Perseus:object:Vatican 16571" type="vase">Vatican 16571</rs>; <bibl>FR, pl. 167,2</bibl>).<note anchored="true" n="1"><p><bibl>ARV2, 987, 1 and 1676</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 437</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 311</bibl>.</p></note> Dressed in a diaphanous chitoniskos beneath an elaborately decorated cuirass, he stands in a contrapposto position looking off pensively to the right. In his left hand he holds a long spear over his shoulder; his right hand is propped on his hip. A cloak is draped over his left arm, and a sword in scabbard hangs from a baldric that crosses his chest and rests at his side. The beauty of this exquisitely drawn figure, which has often been compared to the Doryphoros of Polykleitos, inspired Sir John Beazley to name its anonymous draftsman the 'Achilles Painter,' an artist who is now known to have decorated more than three hundred vases in three techniques,<note anchored="true" n="2"><p><bibl>ARV2, 987-1004, 1677, and 1708</bibl>; <bibl>ABV, 408-9 and 696</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 177, 345, 437-439, and 516</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 106 and 311-13</bibl>; <bibl>J. H. Oakley, <title>The Achilles Painter</title>, forthcoming</bibl>.</p></note> black-figure, red-figure, and white-ground.</p>
<p>The Vatican amphora is Type B, a variety rare around 450-445 B.C., the date of this vase. On the reverse a female figure wearing a peplos and sakkos holds the vessels for a libation, a phiale and an oinochoe, by her waist. She faces the left, so that when one goes around the vase, it is easy to imagine direct eye contact between the two figures on the vase. This is part of the reason why she has been plausibly identified as Briseis, the young woman given to Achilles as war booty, but later taken from him by Agamemnon.</p>
<p>The vase is decorated in the red-figure technique and is one of a number of masterpieces produced by the Achilles Painter during the Middle phase of his career. Special details of drawing here include the shading between some of the folds of his cloak, the fine dilute glaze used for drawing the scales on the side of the cuirass, and the elaborate rendition of the profile eye, complete with eye lashes.</p></div>

<div type="section" n="2"><head>The Achilles Painter and the Berlin Painter</head>

<p>A solitary figure against a black background is a composition the Achilles Painter derived from his teacher, the Berlin Painter,<note anchored="true" n="3"><p>See most recently <bibl>C. M. Cardon, <title>The Berlin Painter and his School</title>, diss. New York University 1977</bibl>; <bibl>Kurtz 1983</bibl>; <bibl>Robertson 1992, 66-83 and 198</bibl>.</p></note> as is the pattern used in the band underneath Achilles. Beazley referred to it as ULFA, short for "upper, lower, facing alternately," that is, stopt meanders facing alternately right and left, divided by saltire squares attached alternately to the upper and lower border. The Achilles Painter favored it, as did other artists working in the Berlin Painter's tradition, including those in the Achilles Painter's workshop. The use of this motif helps one trace the Berlin Painter's workshop and his tradition during its seventy-five year history (ca. 500-425 B.C.).</p></div>

<div type="section" n="3"><head>Red-Figure Vases</head>

<p>The earliest vases by the Achilles Painter are red-figure and date to the 460s. Both the style of drawing, compositions and figural types are clearly derived from the work of the Berlin Painter. Compare, for example, the woman running right (perhaps Aegina) and looking back toward her pursuer Zeus on a lekythos in Hamburg (<rs key="Perseus:object:Hamburg 1983.278" type="vase">Hamburg 1983.278</rs>),<note anchored="true" n="4"><p><bibl>Hornbostel 1977, 320-1, no. 273</bibl>.</p></note> with the woman on a lekythos in Cambridge by the Berlin Painter (<rs key="Perseus:object:Cambridge, Fitzwilliam Museum 37.28" type="vase">Cambridge, Fitzwilliam Museum 37.28</rs>).<note anchored="true" n="5"><p><bibl>ARV2, 211, 205</bibl>; <bibl>CVA, Fitzwilliam 2 (Great Britain 11) RS pl. 13, 2</bibl>.</p></note> Not only are their poses the same, but the lines for the folds of their short mantles are almost identical. There are, however, slight differences that allow one to distinguish between the artists, particularly the short, curving lines in the gaps between the sets of long parallel lines for the folds of the lower chiton on the Achilles Painter's vase. But given the close resemblances, there is no doubt the Achilles Painter learned his craft from the Berlin Painter.</p></div>

<div type="section" n="4"><head>Red-Figure: Early Phase</head>

<p>In his Early phase (460s-450 B.C.) the Achilles Painter preferred to decorate Nolan amphorai and lekythoi, the shapes the Berlin Painter favored late in his career. Some of the vases from this Early phase were originally assigned by Beazley to an artist he called the Meletos Painter, but later he saw they were his earliest works.<note anchored="true" n="6"><p>First combined in <bibl>Richter &amp; Hall 1936, 152, n. 7</bibl>.</p></note> At this time most of the Achilles Painter's red-figure vases have pursuit scenes, and these remain the stock theme in red-figure throughout his career. Normally the composition is limited to two figures; later he sometimes expanded it on larger vases. A dinos in Würzburg provides a good example (<rs key="Perseus:object:Wrzburg L 540" type="vase">Würzburg L 540</rs>; <figure n="1992.09.0199" rend="float"></figure>).<note anchored="true" n="7"><p><bibl>ARV2, 992, 69</bibl>.</p></note> The main protagonists, Peleus and Thetis, struggle in the middle of the frieze going around the vessel (<figure n="1992.09.0204" rend="float"></figure>). In this case the pursuer has already closed with his prey, although she is still in flight. Relatives surround her, namely her sister Nereids (<figure n="1992.09.0200" rend="float"></figure>, <figure n="1992.09.0209" rend="float"></figure>, and <figure n="1992.09.0217" rend="float"></figure>) and their father Nereus (<figure n="1992.09.0210" rend="float"></figure>), who alternately run to and from the pair. The painter has not dryly repeated the figures, but has varied the poses and dress of the women. Peploi and a long mantle are now regularly used in place of the chiton and short mantle which are normally found on the earlier vases, and the women's hair styles are different. A comparison of Kymathoe, the sister to the left of Peleus and Thetis (<figure n="1992.09.0201" rend="float"></figure>), with the fleeing woman on the Hamburg lekythos leaves no doubt that this is the same artist.</p>

<milestone ed="JG" unit="card"/>

<p>In addition to pursuits many other scenes on Early and Middle vases derive from the Berlin Painter. The youthful horserider on a lekythos in Philadelphia (<rs key="Perseus:object:Philadelphia 30-51-2" type="vase">Philadelphia 30-51-2</rs>; <figure n="1991.07.0096" rend="float"></figure>)<note anchored="true" n="8"><p><bibl>ARV2, 993, 95</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 437</bibl>.</p></note> is similar to one by the Berlin Painter on a lekythos in a Swiss private collection,<note anchored="true" n="9"><p>Private; <bibl><title>Das Tier in der Antike</title> (Zurich 1974) pl. 43.253</bibl>.</p></note> but there are differences, such as the chitoniskos worn by the Berlin Painter's figure. The three black palmettes on the reserve shoulder of the vessel (<figure n="1991.07.0103" rend="float"></figure>) are an invention of the Achilles Painter and become one of the hallmarks of red-figure lekythoi from his workshop.<note anchored="true" n="10"><p><bibl>Kurtz 1975, 43-4</bibl>.</p></note> A comparison of the head of the rider (<figure n="1991.07.0101" rend="float"></figure>) with that of Achilles on the namepiece in the Vatican illustrates how the same details are drawn more elaborately on the painter's finest vases.</p></div>

<div type="section" n="5"><head>Red Figure: Middle Phase</head>

<p>The majority of the red-figure masterpieces come from the beginning of the Middle phase (450-445 B.C.) and are found on large shapes, particularly calyx-kraters. A recently published calyx-krater in the J. Paul Getty Museum (<rs key="Perseus:object:Malibu 77.AE.44.1" type="vase">Malibu 77.AE.44.1</rs>)<note anchored="true" n="11"><p><bibl><title>GVGetMus</title> 2 (1985) 213-15, figs. 35a-c</bibl>.</p></note> is perhaps the finest, although its fragmentary state detracts from one's first impression of it. As on many of his most exquisite vases, the subject matter is unique. Athena is shown in the center of the obverse giving Herakles' arms to Philoktetes on the left, while Herakles looks on from the right. Breathtaking in execution are the details, such as Athena's griffin diadem and earring, and the figures' hands. Compare Athena's eye and ear to Achilles on the namepiece in the Vatican. The individual delineation of some of the strands of her hair and the added clay bits for part of Herakles' hair are details found on other of the painter's masterpieces.</p>

<milestone ed="JG" unit="card"/>

<p>During his Middle phase (450-435 B.C.) the Achilles Painter started to develop several new stock themes that he continued to use into his Late phase (435-420s B.C.). One of his favorites is Oedipus's confrontation with the Sphinx. On the obverse of a Nolan amphora in Boston (<rs key="Perseus:object:Boston 06.2447" type="vase">Boston 06.2447</rs>; <figure n="1992.11.0105" rend="float"></figure>; <bibl>CB no. 51</bibl>)<note anchored="true" n="12"><p><bibl>ARV2, 989, 26</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 311</bibl>; <bibl>Caskey &amp; Beazley, I, pl. 23 and Suppl. pl. 2, 33.</bibl></p></note> the Sphinx sits atop a column at the left looking at Oedipus whose hand gesture indicates he is in the process of solving the riddle. Dressed as a youthful traveller, he wears a chlamys over a chitoniskos, holds a spear in his left hand, and has a petasos hanging from his neck and a sword in scabbard at his side. Simple, balanced, two-figure compositions like this are the hallmark of the later Achilles Painter and one of the reasons he is considered the most "classical" of all vase-painters.</p>
<p>The mantled youth holding a staff on the reverse of this Nolan amphora is a stock figure that is repeated with variations on many of the reverses of the painter's vases. Because these figures were quickly drawn and used repeatedly by painters, they are one of the most useful details for attributing vases to an artist.<note anchored="true" n="13"><p><bibl>J. D. Beazley, "The Master of the Achilles Amphora in the Vatican," <title>JHS</title> 34 (1914) 184-5, fig. 5</bibl>.</p></note> Compare this figure to the ones on the back of a Nolan amphora in Japan<note anchored="true" n="14"><p><bibl>E. Simon, <title>The Kurashiki Ninagawa Museum. Greek, Etruscan and Roman Antiquities</title> (Mainz 1982) 99-101</bibl>.</p></note> and a pelike in London (<rs key="Perseus:object:London E 385" type="vase">London E 385</rs>).<note anchored="true" n="15"><p><bibl>ARV2, 990, 50 and 1676</bibl>.</p></note> A bearded man is shown instead of a youth on the latter, but this is just one of several variations to the stock type. The pose of the figures and delineation of the mantle — note particularly the manner of rendering the overfold — are identical. These figures are so repetitious that it is easy to see why fragments, such as one in North Carolina,<note anchored="true" n="16"><p><rs key="Perseus:object:Chapel Hill, William Hayes Ackland Memorial Art Center 77.6.8" type="vase">Chapel Hill, William Hayes Ackland Memorial Art Center 77.6.8</rs> [H. Immerwahr].</p></note> can be securely attributed to the artist.</p></div>

<div type="section" n="6"><head>Red-Figure: Late Phase</head>

<p>The latest red-figure vases date ca. 430 B.C., and in his Late phase the artist decorated only smaller shapes, such as Nolan amphorai and lekythoi. Many of his most trivial works, small squat lekythoi with busts of figures, come from around this time. One in Oxford<note anchored="true" n="17"><p><rs key="Perseus:object:Oxford 1957.30" type="vase">Oxford 1957.30</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 994, 109</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 438</bibl>.</p></note> with the bust of Artemis is a typical example. Many others were produced by other painters in his workshop, all anonymous except for several by the Phiale Painter, his student.</p></div>

<div type="section" n="7"><head>White-Ground Vases</head>

<p>So far we have only considered the red-figure vases by the artist, but he is best known for his white-ground lekythoi which comprise about half his oeuvre. They start a little later than the red-figure vases, the earliest coming from the decade 460-450 B.C., but last longer, continuing into the early 420s. At first Beazley and others did not see the connection of the earliest with the artist, since among other things the figures are stiff and second white is used for the flesh.<note anchored="true" n="18"><p><bibl>Luce 1919, 19-32</bibl> was the first to see that they were by the Achilles Painter. Beazley in <title>VP</title> 49-50 and 80 in 1928 accepted his conclusions.</p></note> Almost all the Achilles Painter's Early white-ground lekythoi have a scene with two women, termed by Beazley 'mistress and maid.' A recent attempt to see all of them as connected with bridal preparations is unconvincing,<note anchored="true" n="19"><p><bibl>J. R. Reilly, "Many Brides: "Mistress and Maid" on Athenian Lekythoi," <title>Hesperia</title> 58 (1989) 411-44</bibl>.</p></note> since the circumstances for the setting and the identities of the two women vary, and some are clearly connected with funerary rites.</p></div>

<div type="section" n="8"><head>White Ground: Early Phase</head>

<p>On an Early lekythos in Berlin (<rs key="Perseus:object:Berlin F 2443" type="vase">Berlin F 2443</rs>; <figure n="1992.07.0410" rend="float"></figure>) the composition is expanded.<note anchored="true" n="20"><p><bibl>ARV2, 995, 118</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 438</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 312</bibl>.</p></note> A woman on the left in a sleeveless chiton (<figure n="1992.07.0413" rend="float"></figure>) hands over a child to a woman in chiton and mantle seated in a klismos at the right (<figure n="1992.07.0416" rend="float"></figure>), who raises her hands to receive the baby. At the left a sakkos hangs on the wall behind the first woman (<figure n="1992.07.0412" rend="float"></figure>), and a mirror, an oinochoe, and part of a kantharos hang above the seated woman (<figure n="1992.07.0418" rend="float"></figure>). Second white is used for the flesh of all three, and the baby wears a band of amulets across his chest. The color for the chitons is lost, but the black for the seated figure's mantle is preserved. The painter's color palette changed during the course of his career, and later he normally colored the mantle red. The outlines at this time are painted in brown, and the palmettes on the shoulder and the ornament are often in black. The scheme of palmettes on this lekythos (<figure n="1992.07.0419" rend="float"></figure>) are similar to that on the painter's red-figure lekythoi.</p>
<p>Between the figures is an inscription that reads: "Dromippos, son of Dromokleidos is fair." This type of inscription, referred to as a 'kalos name,' is normally found on the artist's Early and Middle white-ground lekythoi. The names he favored on Early white-ground besides Dromippos include Diphilos the son of Melanopos and Lichas the son of Samieus, and on Middle, Hygiaion and Axiopeithes the son of Alkimachos. None appears on his Late work. Lichas and Kleinias also appear on his Early red-figure work and Axiopeithes on his Middle. Several other names appear once on vases in either technique. These names help to define the stages of the painter's career, and there is a greater variety of 'kalos names' on the Achilles Painter's works than on any other ancient vase-painter's.</p>
<p>It is interesting that all the white-ground inscriptions are stoichedon and in tabella form, a by now old-fashioned format for those on stone. Several other vase painters used it occasionally, but more than three-quarters of the known examples are by the Achilles Painter, so he clearly set the standard. Their use may reflect the political climate which led to the passing of Perikles' citizenship law.<note anchored="true" n="21"><p>So <bibl>H. A. Shapiro, "Kalos Inscriptions with Patronymic," <title>ZPE</title> 68 (1987) 107-18</bibl>; but see also <bibl>F. Lissarrague, "La stèle avant la lettre," <title>AnnArchStorAnt</title> 10 (1988) 97-105</bibl>.</p></note></p></div>

<div type="section" n="9"><head>White Ground: Middle Phase</head>

<p>Two lekythoi, one in Philadelphia (<rs key="Perseus:object:Philadelphia MS5463" type="vase">Philadelphia MS5463</rs>),<note anchored="true" n="22"><p><bibl>ARV2, 996, 143</bibl>.</p></note> the other in Worcester (<rs key="Perseus:object:Worcester 1900.65" type="vase">Worcester 1900.65</rs>),<note anchored="true" n="23"><p><bibl>ARV2, 997, 151</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 312</bibl>.</p></note> illustrate the changes that occurred during the beginning of his Middle phase, a time of great transition in respect to technique (450-445 B.C.). 'Mistress and maid' scenes are still the norm, as illustrated by both vases, and the types of objects shown hanging in the background are the same. Two standing figures, as on the Worcester lekythos (<figure n="1990.29.0041" rend="float"></figure>), or one standing and the other sitting, as on the Philadelphia lekythos (<figure n="1991.07.0947" rend="float"></figure>), are still the most popular arrangements. The use of second white, however, disappears, and although it is still used for the figures on the Philadelphia lekythos (<figure n="1991.07.0949" rend="float"></figure> and <figure n="1991.07.0954" rend="float"></figure>), it only colors the ribbons in the basket held by the left-hand woman on the Worcester vase (<figure n="1990.29.0048" rend="float"></figure>). Note also the change in tone of the white background, from a creamy off-white to a chalky, brighter hue. Both lekythoi display the painter's new use of dilute, golden glaze. The hair of the figures on the Philadelphia lekythos is brown (<figure n="1991.07.0952" rend="float"></figure> and <figure n="1991.07.0958" rend="float"></figure>), not black as earlier (<figure n="1992.07.0414" rend="float"></figure> and <figure n="1992.07.0417" rend="float"></figure>), and the color of the ornamental band has changed (<figure n="1991.07.0957" rend="float"></figure>). The palmettes on the shoulder of the Worcester lekythos illustrate the painter's canonical form, with five major leaves for each of the three palmettes and cross-over tendrils originating from the volutes of the central one (<figure n="1990.29.0054" rend="float"></figure>). Often additional leaves are added in matt red. The arrangement on the Early lekythoi has more leaves (<figure n="1992.07.0419" rend="float"></figure>) and often resembles that found on many of the painter's red-figure lekythoi (<figure n="1991.07.0103" rend="float"></figure>).<note anchored="true" n="24"><p>The shoulder ornament on the lekythos in Philadelphia shows a rare early use of matt paint (<figure n="1991.07.0959" rend="float"></figure>).</p></note></p>

<milestone ed="BZ" unit="page"/>
<milestone ed="JG" unit="card"/>

<p>The figural types and compositions on the painter's lekythoi vary little, although the quality of the drawing ranges from good to superb. A typical example from his ripe Middle period (445-435 B.C.) is a lekythos in the Arthur M. Sackler Museum in Cambridge (<rs key="Perseus:object:Harvard 1972.43" type="vase">Harvard 1972.43</rs>; <figure n="1990.01.0674" rend="float"></figure>).<note anchored="true" n="25"><p><bibl>ARV2, 1000, 186</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 313</bibl>.</p></note> The poses of the figures are very close to those on the Worcester lekythos, with the exception of the plemochoe which the right-hand woman holds up in her left hand (<figure n="1990.01.0676" rend="float"></figure> and <figure n="1990.01.0684" rend="float"></figure>). The mirror hanging in the background is similar to those found earlier (<figure n="1990.01.0685" rend="float"></figure>; compare <figure n="1992.07.0418" rend="float"></figure> and <figure n="1991.07.0953" rend="float"></figure>). Golden dilute glaze is used for all the outlines and ornament (<figure n="1990.01.0683" rend="float"></figure> and <figure n="1990.01.0688" rend="float"></figure>), and traces of red for the mantles are preserved (<figure n="1990.01.0684" rend="float"></figure>) — in contrast to the black mantle often used in the Early period.</p>
<p>During the Middle period scenes at graves make their appearance. They never became as popular as the two figured 'mistress and maid' composition, which now instead of only two women, sometimes have a male and a female, as on a lekythos in London with a woman and a warrior (<rs key="Perseus:object:London D 51" type="vase">London D 51</rs>; <figure n="1990.14.0160" rend="float"></figure>),<note anchored="true" n="26"><p><bibl>ARV2, 1000, 201 and 1677</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 313</bibl>.</p></note> or two males. One of the finer grave scenes in New York shows a youth to either side of an elaborate tombstone decorated with wreaths and fillets.<note anchored="true" n="27"><p>Metropolitan Museum of Art, <rs key="Perseus:object:New York 1989.281.72" type="vase">New York 1989.281.72</rs>; <bibl>Muscarella 1974, no. 63</bibl>.</p></note> The tiny <foreign xml:lang="xgreek">eidolon</foreign> flying over the younger youth on the right suggests that he is the deceased, who is here represented as if living in the flesh, while the other youth is a visitor to his grave. It is never precisely clear whether the deceased is one of the two figures shown in these scenes, and a matter of debate for many years. On some lekythoi there is little doubt that he is shown, on others it is clear that he is not; the majority fall in between.</p>
<milestone ed="BZ" unit="page"/>
<milestone ed="JG" unit="card"/>
<p>One of the painter's masterpieces, and one of the finest of all Greek vases, is a lekythos in Munich from his Middle period (<rs key="Perseus:object:Munich Shoen 80" type="vase">Munich Shoen 80</rs>; <figure n="1990.34.0001" rend="float"></figure>).<note anchored="true" n="28"><p><bibl>ARV2, 997, 155</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 438</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 312</bibl>.</p></note> Again two women are shown, but the one on the right plays a lyre and sits upon a rock labelled Helicon, the home of the Muses (<figure n="1990.34.0005" rend="float"></figure>). In depicting Muses, the artist has elevated his figures to a higher level. The Muse standing at the left (<figure n="1990.34.0004" rend="float"></figure>) gestures with her right hand, as if keeping time to the music, while a bird is perched on the rock between them, an effective device for recalling the song that often accompanies instrumental music (<figure n="1990.34.0003" rend="float"></figure>). The colors are very well preserved, and make one realize just how beautiful these vases were; unfortunately on most white-ground lekythoi all or part of the color is lost, and primarily the outlines remain.</p></div>

<div type="section" n="10"><head>White Ground: Late Phase</head>

<p>During the painter's Late period (435-430/25 B.C.) he moves to using matt paint exclusively, but the same compositions and figural types are depicted. Often the drawing is not as careful, and his line not as steady. A lekythos in Basel<note anchored="true" n="29"><p><rs key="Perseus:object:Basel, Antikenmuseum und Sammlung Ludwig BS 443" type="vase">Basel, Antikenmuseum und Sammlung Ludwig BS 443</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 1001, 208</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 438</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 313</bibl>.</p></note> with a 'mistress and maid' is a good example. The figures are dryly drawn, the proportions not as well defined, and the figures stiffer, clear signs that the artist has aged.</p></div>

<div type="section" n="11"><head>Black-Figure Vases</head>

<p>The Achilles Painter also worked in a third technique, black-figure. Several prize Panathenaic amphorai, all from his later career, have been attributed to him. The Athena on the front of them seems to derive from those on the Berlin Painter's Panathenaics, particularly the Gorgoneion shield device which is a hallmark of this workshop. The athletic scenes on the reverses show variety, and include both long-distance runners, sprinters, and discus-throwers. The runners, in particular, owe something to the Berlin Painter's.<note anchored="true" n="30"><p>See most recently, <bibl>R. Lindner, "Waffenläufer auf Panathenäischen Preisamphoren," <title>Kotinos. Festschrift für Erika Simon</title> (Mainz 1992) 146-50</bibl>.</p></note> On several vases new iconographical schemata are introduced by the Achilles Painter. For example, he is the first to combine a scene of the proclamation of the victor with the event,<note anchored="true" n="31"><p><bibl>P. Valavanis, "La proclamation des vainqueurs aux Panathénées," <title>BCH</title> 114 (1990) 346-50</bibl>.</p></note> as illustrated by a Panathenaic amphora in Bologna.<note anchored="true" n="32"><p><rs key="Perseus:object:Bologna, Museo Civico 18039" type="vase">Bologna, Museo Civico 18039</rs>; <bibl>ABV, 409, 1</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 177</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 106</bibl>.</p></note></p></div>

<div type="section" n="12"><head>The Workshop of the Achilles Painter</head>

<p>The Achilles Painter took over the Berlin Painter's workshop ca. 460 B.C. and was joined ca. 450 B.C. by his most prolific student, the Phiale Painter, who is named after a vase of this shape in Boston (<rs key="Perseus:object:Boston 97.371" type="vase">Boston 97.371</rs>; <bibl>CB no. 62</bibl>; <figure n="1992.11.0127" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1992.11.0128" rend="float"></figure>) These two major painters were the key artists in one of the two most important classical workshops. They preferred to produce small and mid-sized vases, such as Nolan amphorai and lekythoi; the other, the Polygnotan, favored large vases such as stamnoi and kraters. Several minor artists also worked for a time in the Achilles Painter-Phiale Painter's workshop, including the Westreenen Painter, the Dwarf Painter, the Persephone Painter, the Clio Painter, and the Loeb Painter, as did several other major painters for parts of their career, such as the Sabouroff Painter, the Painter of Munich 2335, and the Kleophon Painter.<note anchored="true" n="33"><p><bibl>Oakley 1990, 47-57</bibl> for an outline of the workshop. It will be more fully reconstructed in Oakley (supra n. 1).</p></note></p>

<milestone ed="JG" unit="card"/>

<p>The Phiale Painter<note anchored="true" n="34"><p>See Oakley (supra n. 32) for the painter.</p></note> derived several of his scenes from the Achilles Painter and depicted a fair number of pursuit scenes, the staple product of their tradition. A good example is a Nolan amphora at Yale with a youth pursuing a woman (<rs key="Perseus:object:Yale 1913.134" type="vase">Yale 1913.134</rs>; <figure n="1990.02.0256" rend="float"></figure>, <figure n="1990.02.0264" rend="float"></figure>).<note anchored="true" n="35"><p><bibl>ARV2, 1015, 13</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 315</bibl>.</p></note> But the Phiale Painter was very much his own man, and developed his own specialties, such as scenes of dancing girls with their mistress, as on a lekythos in Bowdoin College (<rs key="Perseus:object:Bowdoin 1913.11" type="vase">Bowdoin 1913.11</rs>).<note anchored="true" n="36"><p><bibl>ARV2, 1021, 118</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 441</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 316</bibl>.</p></note> Still most of his vases are connected by both shape and ornament to the workshop. Note the ULFA pattern on the Nolan amphora at Yale, for example.</p>
<p>Other painters in the workshop, including the Westreenen Painter, were greatly influenced by the Achilles Painter. Compare the rider on his pelike in Tampa (<rs key="Perseus:object:Tampa 86.64" type="vase">Tampa 86.64</rs>; <figure n="1991.08.0688" rend="float"></figure>)<note anchored="true" n="37"><p><bibl>ARV2, 1006, 2</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 439</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 314</bibl>.</p></note> with the one on the earlier lekythos by the Achilles Painter in Philadelphia (<figure n="1991.07.0096" rend="float"></figure>) that we looked at before. Still other vases which clearly were made in the workshop either imitate or are influenced by the style of the Achilles Painter. A good example of the latter is a lekythos in Kansas City with Eos pursuing a boy with a lyre, who is usually identified as Tithonos (<rs key="Perseus:object:Kansas City 33.3/2" type="vase">Kansas City 33.3/2</rs>; <figure n="1990.18.0383" rend="float"></figure>, <figure n="1990.18.0384" rend="float"></figure>, <figure n="1990.18.0385" rend="float"></figure>). Although one of the Achilles Painter's favorite scenes, the style of drawing — note the details of the face, drapery, etc. — is not that of the Achilles Painter. The shape and shoulder ornament, however, are Achillean.</p></div>

<div type="section" n="13"><head>Conclusion</head>

<p>As we have seen, the Achilles Painter had a long career, spanning more than thirty years (470/60-430/25 B.C.). On his early work his style is slow to develop, and especially the red-figure reveals his dependence on his teacher, the Berlin Painter. The peak in quality and originality of his red-figure work takes place during the early part of his Middle phase (450-445 B.C.) when he produced some of the masterpieces of Greek vase-painting. Later, although he developed several new scenes, the quality is not as uniformly high. It is his white-ground lekythoi, however, which were the standard to which all other painters looked and for which the Achilles Painter is most famous. On many vases in both techniques the static poses of his figures and the complex yet natural rendering of drapery in simple, yet moving scenes on many vases in both techniques reflect the style and mood of the Parthenon sculptures, which is why the Achilles Painter is considered the most classical of all Greek vase-painters.</p></div>
</body></text></TEI>
