<?xml version="1.0"?>





<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
	<title>The Harrow Painter, with a Note on the Geras Painter</title>
	<author>Michael Padgett</author>
	<sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor><principal>Gregory Crane</principal><respStmt><resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp><name>Lisa Cerrato</name></respStmt>
	&fund.NEA;
      </titleStmt>
	<publicationStmt><publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher><pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace><authority>Perseus Project</authority></publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
	<note anchored="true">Michael Padgett, Princeton University</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
	<p>Created in electronic form.
      </p></sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>

    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl>
	<refState unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
	<language ident="en">English
	</language><language ident="xgreek">Transliterated Greek
      </language></langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
    
    <revisionDesc><!--
      <change><date>24 September 1999</date>
	<respStmt><name>DAS</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>
	$Log: vp.harrow.xml,v $
	Revision 1.1  2009-12-09 18:06:56  rsingh04
	moved more xml files around based on copyright status

	Revision 1.3  2009/06/12 21:05:34  lcerrato
	fixed bad bibls

	Revision 1.2  2005/08/18 13:56:33  packel
	fixed item tags

	Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 15:06:12  packel
	Converted to XML
	
Revision 1.5  2003/07/01 22:18:53  yorkc
Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)

Revision 1.4  2000/06/19 21:39:29  dasmith
Make all FIGURES REND="float".

Revision 1.3  2000/03/04 20:35:23  dasmith
Added separate funder entity to TEI header.

Revision 1.2  1999/09/24 22:19:50  dasmith
Converted to TEI2 tagging.


</item></change>
    --> <change when="2014-11-13" who="Stella Dee">edited markup and assigned CTS URN</change></revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
<text><body>
<div type="section" n="1"><head>Introduction</head>

<p>The Harrow Painter was named by J. D. Beazley after an oinochoe at Harrow school with a picture of a handsome boy holding a hoop.<note anchored="true" n="1"><p><bibl>ARV2, 276, 76</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 103</bibl>.</p></note> Along with the Kleophrades Painter, the artist was the subject of one of Beazley's earliest articles,<note anchored="true" n="2"><p><bibl>J. D. Beazley, "Two Vases in Harrow," <title>JHS</title> 36 (1916) 38-47</bibl>.</p></note> in which he attributed 39 vases to this "minor" pot-painter, whom he later called "a poorly-equipped painter whose ordinary employment was daubing cheap neck-amphorae and column-kraters with dull and ill-drawn forms."<note anchored="true" n="3"><p><bibl>Beazley 1918, 56</bibl>.</p></note> These are harsh words, though not wholly inaccurate, for although he has been justly called "more than ordinarily competent,"<note anchored="true" n="4"><p><bibl>Boardman 1975, 112</bibl>.</p></note> the Harrow Painter was indeed a minor talent, not withstanding the undeniable charm of some of his works. If, however, one looks beyond the quality of his line and his relatively low standing in the artistic pantheon, one discovers in him many elements of interest and more than a few delightful pictures.</p></div>

<div type="section" n="2"><head>Works</head>

<p>The Harrow Painter had a relatively long career, beginning not long before 480 and extending well into the 460s, from the end of the Late Archaic period into the Early Classical. The current list of works attributed to his hand stands at about 112, with another dozen or so probably by him or very close in style.<note anchored="true" n="5"><p>Beazley attributed 97 vases and fragments to the Harrow Painter, but at least 15 more have been added since <title>Paralipomena</title>; see the list in <bibl>Padgett 1989, 160-205</bibl>, to which may be added: (1) a fragment (oinochoe?) with a youth wearing a Thracian cap; <bibl>M. Marti, in <title>Die Sammlung Collisani</title> (Zürich 1990) 131, no. 189</bibl>; (2) a neck-amphora with twisted handles in the Patricia Kluge collection, Charlottesville, Virginia; <bibl><title>One Thousand Years of Ancient Greek Vases</title>, Royal-Athena Galleries (New York 1990) no. 64</bibl>; A, seated youth with lyre, and man; B, draped youth; (3) column-krater <rs key="Perseus:object:Kiel B 547" type="vase">Kiel B 547</rs> (<bibl>CVA, Kiel 1, pls. 31, 1-2 and 32, 1-5; A, Herakles and Pholos; B, two komasts</bibl>), which B. Freyer-Schauenburg compares to the Harrow Painter and which is certainly from his hand. Among attributions to the painter which should be excluded from the list are: (1) kalpis formerly in the London market; Sotheby's, London, 13-14 July 1981, no. 266; E. Böhr, <bibl>CVA, Tübingen 4, p. 2</bibl>; (2) column-krater <rs key="Perseus:object:Kassel T.716" type="vase">Kassel T.716</rs> (<bibl>CVA, 1, 54, pl. 33</bibl>), which is surely by the Boreas Painter; (3) column-krater in the Fondazione Mormino, Palermo, which has more in common with the Leningrad Painter and his associates in the Early Mannerist Group; <bibl>V. Tusa, <title>Odeon</title> (Palermo 1971) 430, pl. 57 a-b</bibl>; (4) psykter in the Villa Giulia (<rs key="Perseus:object:Villa Giulia 3577" type="vase">Villa Giulia 3577</rs>; <figure n="1993.01.0129" rend="float"></figure>), which Robertson believes is an attempt by the painter to copy a wall-painting, but which seems to me neither by nor in the manner of the Harrow Painter; <bibl>Robertson 1992, 134</bibl>; <bibl>FR, pl. 15</bibl>.</p></note></p>

<p>Among his early works are large neck-amphorai with twisted handles and slender oinochoai with graceful figures isolated against a black background. In style these works show the strong influence of another, greater artist, the Berlin Painter. This influence, often noted by Beazley and others, is manifested in several ways, from the stances of individual figures and the patterns of drapery folds, to a consistent concern for drawing certain muscles with golden dilute glaze. Beazley thought the figures on a pair of oinochoai formerly in the Noble collection, now in the Tampa Museum of Art, were direct copies of the Berlin Painter (<rs key="Perseus:object:Tampa 86.72" type="vase">Tampa 86.72</rs>; <figure n="1991.08.0715" rend="float"></figure> and <rs key="Perseus:object:Tampa 86.73" type="vase">Tampa 86.73</rs>; <figure n="1991.08.0709" rend="float"></figure>).<note anchored="true" n="6"><p><bibl>ARV2, 1635-36, 13 bis and 13 ter, and 1705, 78 bis and 78 ter</bibl>. See also <bibl>Robertson 1992, 127-28, fig. 131</bibl>.</p></note> In each case, a nude slave boy is running along with provisions for a symposium; one carries a ladle and jug and the other balances a tray of food while rolling a hoop, a childish distraction that emphasizes his youth. Although, as Beazley said, these pictures have the grace, the <foreign xml:lang="xgreek">charis</foreign>, of the Berlin Painter, the Harrow Painter's distinctive style is also clearly discernible.</p> 

<milestone ed="BZ" unit="page"/>
<milestone ed="JG" unit="Card"/>

<p>The influence of the Berlin Painter on the Harrow Painter's work is undeniable, and one could point to other parallels besides the oinochoai in Tampa.<note anchored="true" n="7"><p>For example, cf. the Athena on the oinochoe <rs key="Perseus:object:Copenhagen, Thorvaldsen Museum 94" type="vase">Copenhagen, Thorvaldsen Museum 94</rs> (<bibl>ARV2, 276, 78</bibl>), the Harrow Painter, with the goddess on the oinochoe <rs key="Perseus:object:Leiden PC 74" type="vase">Leiden PC 74</rs> (<bibl>ARV2, 198, 25</bibl>), by the Berlin Painter. It is possible that larger compositions, such as the Heraclean Amazonomachy on the column-krater <rs key="Perseus:object:Rome, Palazzo dei Conservatori 185" type="vase">Rome, Palazzo dei Conservatori 185</rs> (<bibl>ARV2, 274, 41</bibl>), may have been copied from or inspired by the Berlin Painter, whose own grander depiction of the subject on the amphora <rs key="Perseus:object:Basel BS 453" type="vase">Basel BS 453</rs> (<bibl>CVA, pl. 45</bibl>) may in turn have been based on a work of Euphronios, such as his volute-krater in Arezzo (<rs key="Perseus:object:Arezzo 1465" type="vase">Arezzo 1465</rs>; <figure n="1993.01.0355" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1993.01.0356" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1993.01.0357" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1993.01.0363" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1993.01.0361" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1993.01.0360" rend="float"></figure>; <bibl>ARV2, 15, 6</bibl>). Some imitations of the Berlin Painter are so skilled that it is difficult to say who was responsible; e.g. <rs key="Perseus:object:Louvre G 178" type="vase">Louvre G 178</rs> (<bibl>ARV2, 218, 2</bibl>), in which Beazley saw details recalling the Harrow Painter.</p></note> However, Robertson is surely correct that the Harrow Painter was neither a pupil of the Berlin Painter nor a member of his workshop.<note anchored="true" n="8"><p><bibl>M. Robertson, "Beazley and After," <title>MJb</title> 27 (1976) 29-46</bibl>; <bibl>Robertson 1992, 134</bibl>.</p></note> This is supported by a comparison of similar vase shapes, such as neck-amphorae, which were clearly produced by different potters, and by the fact that each artist eschewed some shapes favored by the other. Rather, the Harrow Painter seems to have admired the Berlin Painter from a distance, perhaps, as Robertson has suggested, as the principal painter in an independent workshop.<note anchored="true" n="9"><p><bibl>Robertson 1992, 127</bibl>.</p></note> He did not try to mimic the master's narrative style or transfer whole multi-figure compositions to his own works, but was impressed by individual figures and intimate groups. It is perhaps this influence which accounts for a certain affinity with another artist related to the Berlin Painter, the Tithonos Painter, some of whose works are quite close in style to the Harrow Painter.<note anchored="true" n="10"><p>E.g. <rs key="Perseus:object:Naples 3182" type="vase">Naples 3182</rs> and <rs key="Perseus:object:Hamburg 1893.100" type="vase">Hamburg 1893.100</rs> (<bibl>ARV2, 309, 5 and 9</bibl>).</p></note> The Syriskos Painter, another artist influenced by the Berlin Painter, also occasionally worked in a vein reminiscent of the Harrow Painter, although he was a better draughtsman and a more flattering imitator of the master.<note anchored="true" n="11"><p>Some of his satyrs are especially close; e.g. <rs key="Perseus:object:Frankfurt, Liebieghaus L 116" type="vase">Frankfurt, Liebieghaus L 116</rs> and <rs key="Perseus:object:Heidelberg 125" type="vase">Heidelberg 125</rs> (<bibl>ARV2, 260, 3 and 262, 36</bibl>). Cf. the himation folds on <rs key="Perseus:object:Munich 2407" type="vase">Munich 2407</rs> and <rs key="Perseus:object:Frankfurt St. V 3" type="vase">Frankfurt St. V 3</rs>, by the Harrow Painter (<bibl>ARV2, 274, 35 and 37</bibl>), to those on <rs key="Perseus:object:London E 161" type="vase">London E 161</rs>, by the Syriskos Painter (<bibl>ARV2, 262, 41</bibl>).</p></note></p></div>

<div type="section" n="3"><head>Stock Figures and "Back Men"</head>

<p>Gempeler saw the Berlin Painter's influence continuing throughout the 470s, when both he and the Harrow Painter largely abandoned the use of relief-line contours.<note anchored="true" n="12"><p><bibl>Gempeler 1969, 20</bibl>.</p></note> The truth of this is difficult to gauge, for the Harrow Painter's drawing can be much freer and broader than the Berlin Painter's. On the backs of his pots he often abandoned any attempt at refinement, settling for a stock figure of a youth or man (or both) wearing a himation. In speaking of the Pan Painter, Beazley referred to "his back-men, his mantle-figures," and certainly the mantled figures of the Harrow Painter are among his hallmarks.<note anchored="true" n="13"><p><bibl>Beazley 1974a, 5</bibl>.</p></note> The pair on the reverse of the column-krater <rs key="Perseus:object:Harvard 1925.30.33" type="vase">Harvard 1925.30.33</rs> (<bibl>ARV2, 275, 53</bibl>) are typical, particularly the youth at the left, with both arms covered by his himation, the latter pushed out before his chest like a ledge (<figure n="1991.06.0030" rend="float"></figure>); the same figure, sometimes facing left, appears on the reverses of several other vases.<note anchored="true" n="14"><p>E.g. <rs key="Perseus:object:Naples 86304" type="vase">Naples 86304</rs> (<bibl>ARV2, 275, 65</bibl>).</p></note> The bearded man facing the youth and leaning on a knotty staff (<figure n="1991.06.0026" rend="float"></figure>) is identical to the man on the obverse (<figure n="1991.06.0017" rend="float"></figure>), who faces a seated boy holding a lyre (<figure n="1991.06.0010" rend="float"></figure>). The boy has the same type of "ledge" himation as the youth on the reverse, and except for being seated, he differs otherwise only in having a slight fringe on his hair, a minor concession to the normal practice of imparting more detail to the obverse figures. The youth standing behind the boy and holding a staff is another of the painter's stock characters (<figure n="1991.06.0021" rend="float"></figure>); he too appears as a "back-man" on some vases.<note anchored="true" n="15"><p>E.g. <rs key="Perseus:object:Florence 4024" type="vase">Florence 4024</rs> (<bibl>ARV2, 275, 63</bibl>).</p></note> This figure was omitted when the other two — the seated boy with a lyre and the man leaning on his staff — were repeated in identical fashion on a neck-amphora with twisted handles, now in a private collection.<note anchored="true" n="16"><p>Patricia Kluge collection, Charlottesville (described in a previous note, supra). The sponge and strigil hanging on the wall in the Harvard painting are also depicted on the Kluge amphora, with the addition of an aryballos.</p></note></p>

<milestone ed="JG" unit="Card"/>

<p>This economy of figural types was not unique to the Harrow Painter, and he could escape its limitations by adapting a stock type to fit the purposes of a particular theme or story. The man on the reverse of the neck-amphora <rs key="Perseus:object:Baltimore, Hopkins AIA B13" type="vase">Baltimore, Hopkins AIA B13</rs>(<figure n="1990.06.0400" rend="float"></figure>), for example, wears a himation and holds a staff, but the staff is unusually tall, resembling the scepters that identify kings in many paintings. Because the scene on the obverse shows the captured satyr Marsyas being led into captivity by a henchman of the Phrygian king Midas, we may wonder if the man on the reverse is Midas himself, waiting for the captive to be brought before him.<note anchored="true" n="17"><p><bibl>ARV2, 273, 22</bibl>. Cf. the mantled figure of Zeus on the neck-amphora <rs key="Perseus:object:Naples 126062" type="vase">Naples 126062</rs> (<bibl>ARV2, 273, 16</bibl>), who holds a thunderbolt as well as a scepter, setting him apart from mortal kings. For Midas, see <bibl>L. Roller, "The Legend of Midas," <title>Classical Antiquity</title> 2 (1983) 299-313</bibl> and <bibl>M.C. Miller, "Midas as the Great King in Attic Fifth-Century Vase-Painting," <title>AntK</title> 31 (1988) 79-88</bibl>.</p></note></p></div>

<div type="section" n="4"><head>Later Works</head>

<p>As previously mentioned, the neck-amphorae with twisted handles should date to around 480, when the Berlin Painter produced his; the amphora with the capture of Silenus, just described, has a restored foot and handles but was probably of this type. The neck-amphorae with triple handles date mostly to the 470s, while those with ridged handles were produced in the late 470s and 460s. The painter's late works exhibit some of the characteristics of the Early Classical style, with broad, flowing drapery, fewer relief lines, less fastidious detail, and more cursory execution of ornament; e.g. the column-krater <rs key="Perseus:object:Philadelphia MS2464" type="vase">Philadelphia MS2464</rs>; <figure n="1991.07.0028" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1991.07.0032" rend="float"></figure> (<bibl>ARV2, 278, 2</bibl>).<note anchored="true" n="18"><p>Beazley hesitated over the attribution of the Philadelphia krater, but there is no doubt that it is by the Harrow Painter. Beazley also considered the column-krater <rs key="Perseus:object:Palermo V 792" type="vase">Palermo V 792</rs> (<bibl>ARV2, 275, 58</bibl>) a late work; cf. another late column-krater, formerly in the London art market: Christie's, December 10, 1986, no. 220; <bibl>Padgett 1989 (supra) 185, no. H.58A</bibl>.</p></note> The Philadelphia vase is decorated with a symposium scene, and some other column-kraters with this subject are also late in style, especially those with ivy on the neck.<note anchored="true" n="19"><p>E.g. <rs key="Perseus:object:Florence 3999" type="vase">Florence 3999</rs> and <rs key="Perseus:object:Montaubon MI.87.4.14" type="vase">Montaubon MI.87.4.14</rs> (<bibl>ARV2, 275, 47-48</bibl>).</p></note> These and other late works have a mass-produced look that is only occasionally alleviated by a sudden outbreak of charm, such as the satyr and fawn on a late oinochoe in Schwerin.<note anchored="true" n="20"><p><rs key="Perseus:object:Schwerin 1293" type="vase">Schwerin 1293</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 273, 19</bibl>.</p></note></p></div>

<div type="section" n="5"><head>Stylistic Characteristics</head>

<p>Some of the characteristics of the Harrow Painter's drawing have already been mentioned. Clavicles are often hooked and sometimes pointed; occasionally they are not hooked at all. Eyes are formed of shallow, opposing curves, open at the inner corner, with a black pupil (<figure n="1991.06.0023" rend="float"></figure> and <figure n="1991.06.0020" rend="float"></figure>). In a few cases, the relief lines contouring the eyes are edged with dilute glaze.<note anchored="true" n="21"><p>E.g. the obverse figures on <rs key="Perseus:object:Leipzig T 3890" type="vase">Leipzig T 3890</rs> (<bibl>ARV2, 273, 21</bibl>).</p></note> Ears may be scroll-shaped (<figure n="1990.06.0361" rend="float"></figure>), but often are simply outlined by the line of the hair (<figure n="1990.06.0358" rend="float"></figure> and <figure n="1991.06.0032" rend="float"></figure>). Male figures may have rounded pectorals with a triangle below the midline, or right-angle midlines and no triangle. Men's beards are normally pointed and, on obverse figures at least, fringed (<figure n="1990.01.1571" rend="float"></figure>, <figure n="1991.07.0044" rend="float"></figure>, and <figure n="1991.06.0020" rend="float"></figure>). Satyrs have shorter beards, but with extra-long fringes for an appropriately wild look. The hair of males and satyrs often lies quite low over the forehead, like a cap (<figure n="1991.06.0032" rend="float"></figure> and <figure n="1991.07.0052" rend="float"></figure>), and various shades of dilute glaze are used for different textures of hair, such as the wispy sideburns of the young Theseus or the balding pate of Nereus, both on the column-krater <rs key="Perseus:object:Harvard 1960.339" type="vase">Harvard 1960.339</rs>, discussed below (<figure n="1990.01.1576" rend="float"></figure>; <figure n="1990.01.1567" rend="float"></figure>). At least two figures have hair rendered with relief dots.<note anchored="true" n="22"><p>The woman on <rs key="Perseus:object:Leipzig T 3890" type="vase">Leipzig T 3890</rs> (see previous note, supra), and the Herakles on <rs key="Perseus:object:Munich 2407" type="vase">Munich 2407</rs> (<bibl>ARV2, 274, 35</bibl>).</p></note></p>

<milestone ed="BZ" unit="page"/>
<milestone ed="JG" unit="Card"/>

<p>Nude males are frequently shown infibulated: not only athletes and komasts, but also Herakles.<note anchored="true" n="23"><p><rs key="Perseus:object:Munich 2407" type="vase">Munich 2407</rs> (<bibl>ARV2, 274, 35</bibl>).</p></note> On most nudes, the minor muscles and those of the abdomen are drawn with dilute glaze (<figure n="1991.08.0717" rend="float"></figure>). This in itself is unremarkable, but on the painter's figures the abdominal muscles are often quite noticeable, set off within a prominent oval, as on the boy on <rs key="Perseus:object:Tampa 86.73" type="vase">Tampa 86.73</rs> (<figure n="1991.08.0712" rend="float"></figure>). Sometimes these muscles are tapered or foreshortened in an unsuccessful attempt to represent the twisting transition to a frontal chest; compare the boy on the other Tampa oinochoe (<rs key="Perseus:object:Tampa 86.72" type="vase">Tampa 86.72</rs>; <figure n="1991.08.0717" rend="float"></figure>). Ankles are normally indicated by a short, vertical line (<figure n="1991.06.0019" rend="float"></figure>), sometimes with a slight hook at the bottom (<figure n="1991.08.0719" rend="float"></figure> and <figure n="1990.01.1578" rend="float"></figure>). Many women wear sakkoi, sometimes with a short flap covering the nape; e.g. the Nereid on <rs key="Perseus:object:Harvard 1960.339" type="vase">Harvard 1960.339</rs> (<figure n="1990.01.1562" rend="float"></figure>) and the seated woman on the hydria <rs key="Perseus:object:Tampa 76.70" type="vase">Tampa 76.70</rs> (ARV2, 276, 70; <figure n="1991.08.0919" rend="float"></figure>). Several male gods wear embroidered chitons, while the folds of women's chitons range from the monotonous to the decorative; for the latter, note the combination of relief lines, dilute lines, embroidered dots, and dilute wash on the chiton of the Nereid on <rs key="Perseus:object:Harvard 1960.339" type="vase">Harvard 1960.339</rs> (<figure n="1990.01.1561" rend="float"></figure>).</p></div>

<div type="section" n="6"><head>Shapes: Amphorae</head>

<p>The Harrow Painter was exclusively a pot-painter; no cups of any kind have been attributed to him. His favorite shapes were neck-amphorae and column-kraters, but he also painted stamnoi, hydriai, pelikai, and oinochoai. Single fragments expand the range to include plates and calyx-kraters. A variety of amphorae are represented, including a small amphora of Panathenaic shape and a fragmentary belly-amphora.<note anchored="true" n="24"><p><rs key="Perseus:object:Berlin F 2162" type="vase">Berlin F 2162</rs> and <rs key="Perseus:object:Florence 8 B 21" type="vase">Florence 8 B 21</rs> (<bibl>ARV2, 273, 25-26</bibl>).</p></note> The various types of neck-amphorae and their chronology are discussed above. Most have disk or torus feet, the latter often in two degrees; occasionally the foot is ogival. Ornament is limited to a band of tongues below the neck, although this too is often omitted. Some with twisted handles have a mouth in two degrees; two with such handles have tall, tapering bodies akin to examples by the Kleophrades and Berlin Painters.<note anchored="true" n="25"><p><rs key="Perseus:object:Villa Giulia 50471" type="vase">Villa Giulia 50471</rs> and <rs key="Perseus:object:Mississippi 1977.3.87" type="vase">Mississippi 1977.3.87</rs>; <figure n="1991.01.0441" rend="float"></figure> (<bibl>ARV2, 272, 1-2</bibl>).</p></note> None of these can properly be called Nolan amphorae, and both this, and the fact that the Harrow Painter apparently decorated no lekythoi, are additional factors distancing him from the workshop of the Berlin Painter.</p></div>

<div type="section" n="7"><head>Shapes: Pelikai and Kalpides</head>

<p>Of the painter's pelikai and kalpides, several are unpublished and others are too fragmentary for meaningful analysis. Some of the pelikai have framed pictures, others are unframed.<note anchored="true" n="26"><p>Becker classifies only one framed pelike (<rs key="Perseus:object:Tarquinia RC 973" type="vase">Tarquinia RC 973</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 273, 27</bibl>). Of those without frames, the best preserved, <rs key="Perseus:object:Louvre C 10789" type="vase">Louvre C 10789</rs> (<bibl>ARV2, 274, 32</bibl>), is assigned to a subgroup dominated by the Syleus Painter. See <bibl>Becker 1977, 40-41, no. 116, and 71, no. 208</bibl>.</p></note> One hydria, <rs key="Perseus:object:Tampa 86.70" type="vase">Tampa 86.70</rs>  (<bibl>ARV2, 276, 70</bibl>; <figure n="1991.08.0915" rend="float"></figure>), is of black-figure shape. The five stamnoi are also a problem to classify, as one is lost and two are fragmentary. The Munich stamnos <rs key="Perseus:object:Munich 2407" type="vase">Munich 2407</rs> lacks both neck and rim, but is classed by Philippaki with early stamnoi by the Berlin Painter.<note anchored="true" n="27"><p><bibl>ARV2, 274, 35</bibl>; <bibl>Philippaki 1967, 34</bibl>. The stamnos <rs key="Perseus:object:Frankfurt, Liebieghaus St. V.3" type="vase">Frankfurt, Liebieghaus St. V.3</rs> (<bibl>ARV2, 274, 37</bibl>), which Philippaki (pp. 64 and 68) assigns to the Class of the Copenhagen Painter's stamnoi, differs significantly from the Munich vase, with flat handles, ovoid body, and broad neck. The eggs around the rim and the tongues below the neck are standard on stamnoi of the period.</p></note></p></div>

<div type="section" n="8"><head>Shapes: Kraters</head>

<p>Column-kraters account for nearly 40% of the Harrow Painter's known production. Those with framed pictures (over half) have the standardized ornament, with frames of ivy and tongues, rays above the foot, and ivy around the outer rim. Most of these have a wide band of lotus buds on the obverse neck, sometimes replaced with ivy.<note anchored="true" n="28"><p><rs key="Perseus:object:Florence 3999" type="vase">Florence 3999</rs> and <rs key="Perseus:object:Montaubon MI.87.4.14" type="vase">Montaubon MI.87.4.14</rs> (<bibl>ARV2, 275, 47-48</bibl>).</p></note> Only a few follow the common scheme of having lotus buds and palmettes on top of the mouth; e.g. <rs key="Perseus:object:Harvard 1960.339" type="vase">Harvard 1960.339</rs> (<figure n="1990.01.1552" rend="float"></figure>). Most of the kraters with unframed pictures have rays above the foot and lotus buds on the obverse neck; when the buds are replaced by ivy, laurel, or palmettes, the rays are omitted.<note anchored="true" n="29"><p>Ivy: once London art market; Sotheby's, December 14-15, 1981, no. 274. Laurel: <rs key="Perseus:object:Malibu 81.AE.37" type="vase">Malibu 81.AE.37</rs> (<bibl>Para., 354, 64 ter</bibl>). Palmettes: Munich private collection; <bibl><title>JdI</title> 94 (1979) 103, fig. 36</bibl>; <bibl>Padgett 1989, (supra) 191-92, fig. 115, no. H.65A</bibl>; and another once in the New York art market; Sotheby's, May 20, 1982, no. 100; <bibl>Padgett 1989 (supra) 192, no. H.65B</bibl>.</p></note> Frames were preferred for the more ambitious, mythological subjects, such as <rs key="Perseus:object:Harvard 1960.339" type="vase">Harvard 1960.339</rs> (<figure n="1990.01.1544" rend="float"></figure>), with the meeting of Theseus and Poseidon. Unframed subjects tend to be single individuals or tightly grouped pairs, such as Thetis and Achilles, or Zeus grappling with Ganymede.<note anchored="true" n="30"><p><rs key="Perseus:object:Berlin F 3163" type="vase">Berlin F 3163</rs> and <rs key="Perseus:object:Naples 3152" type="vase">Naples 3152</rs> (<bibl>ARV2, 275, 59-60</bibl>).</p></note></p></div>

<div type="section" n="9"><head>Shapes: Oinochoai</head>

<p>The painter's oinochoai are few but varied. Those of shape 1, like the name-vase at Harrow, are nearly identical, with an ogival foot, constricted trefoil mouth, and high, sharply-ridged handle. Similar but not identical oinochoai were painted by the Berlin Painter, whose influence is also evident in the graceful figures on these jugs. We have already noted the influence of the Berlin Painter on the two oinochoai in Tampa, but they are of shape 2, with squatter proportions and broad disk feet; the Berlin Painter seems not to have decorated any oinochoai of this type, another point of difference between him and the Harrow Painter.<note anchored="true" n="31"><p>Even less common are the other two oinochoai by the Harrow Painter: one of shape 5A, the other of shape 5B; <rs key="Perseus:object:Basel 1921.363" type="vase">Basel 1921.363</rs> and <rs key="Perseus:object:New York 12.229.13" type="vase">New York 12.229.13</rs> (<bibl>ARV2, 276, 79-80</bibl>).</p></note></p></div>

<div type="section" n="10"><head>Provenances</head>

<p>Almost half of the vases by the Harrow Painter have known provenances, and of these fully half come from Italy. It is not surprising that many have been found in Etruria, at such sites as Caere, Tarquinia, Vulci, Spina, Bologna, and Falerii. What is interesting is that South Italian and Sicilian sites — Naples, Nola, Taras, Ruvo, Gela, Selinus, Akragas — have produced even more. The sample is large enough that one is perhaps justified in relating the difference to a slow decline in the importance of the Etruscan market in the years after the Persian Wars. The Harrow Painter did not work exclusively for the Italian market, however, as fragments of twelve of his vases were found on the Athenian Acropolis, a relatively high number by an individual pot-painter. A single piece from Kerch, in the Crimea, shows that his wares traveled east as well as west.<note anchored="true" n="32"><p>For a distribution chart of provenances, not including new attributions, see <bibl>F. Giudice, <title>Vasi e frammenti "Beazley" da Locri Epizifiri</title> (Catania 1989) pl. 21, 1</bibl>.</p></note></p></div>

<div type="section" n="11"><head>Subject Matter: Courtship</head>

<p>In his choice of subject matter, the Harrow Painter was not particularly imaginative; we have already commented on his repetitive "back-men" and mantled figures. Sometimes one or two komasts occupy the reverse, but only once does a woman appear there unescorted.<note anchored="true" n="33"><p><rs key="Perseus:object:St. Petersburg 1555" type="vase">St. Petersburg 1555</rs> (<bibl>ARV2, 272, 10</bibl>).</p></note> Many obverses, too, are devoted to nothing more than a man leaning on his staff before a boy. Sometimes there are several courting males, a mix of <foreign xml:lang="xgreek">erastai</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="xgreek">eromenoi</foreign> passing time in the palaestra, the setting suggested by the ubiquitous sponge, strigil, and aryballos hanging in the background (<figure n="1991.08.0926" rend="float"></figure>). Such depictions are common in this period, and there is little doubt that even seemingly innocent scenes of youths standing in conversation contain undercurrents of the male courtship and homosexuality condoned and even encouraged in some circles of Athenian society, including the aristocracy.<note anchored="true" n="34"><p>For homosexuality in ancient Greece, see <bibl>Dover 1978</bibl>.</p></note> Both of the scenes on <rs key="Perseus:object:Harvard 1925.30.33" type="vase">Harvard 1925.30.33</rs> (<bibl>ARV2, 275, 53</bibl>), and the reverse of <rs key="Perseus:object:Philadelphia MS2464" type="vase">Philadelphia MS2464</rs> (<bibl>ARV2, 278, 2</bibl>)<figure n="1991.07.0046" rend="float"></figure> are of this type, and many more examples can be found within the painter's oeuvre. The lyre held by the youth on the Harvard vase does not mean this is a music lesson, but rather is an indication of age: he is still a schoolboy. On another of the painter's column-kraters, a boy with a lyre is offered a purse, another common subject of the time.<note anchored="true" n="35"><p><rs key="Perseus:object:Agrigento C.2033" type="vase">Agrigento C.2033</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 275, 52</bibl>. For this subject, see <bibl>M. Meyer, "Männer mit Geld: zu einer rotfigurigen Vase mit 'Altagszene'," <title>JdI</title> 108 (1988) 87-125</bibl>. It is debated whether the purses constitute a bribe, a payment for sexual favors, or a simple love-gift. Gloria Pinney (<bibl><title>AJA</title> 90 (1986) 218</bibl>) thinks the purses contained not money, but trivial love-gifts such as astragaloi; she makes no attempt, however, to distinguish them from purses in scenes of everyday commerce, where they clearly contain money. Lyres, too, are sometimes offered as love gifts; e.g. <rs key="Perseus:object:Athens 1176" type="vase">Athens 1176</rs>, by the Geras Painter (<bibl>ARV2, 287, 31</bibl>). For the broader subject of love-gifts, particularly animals such as hares and cocks, see <bibl>Koch-Harnack 1983</bibl>.</p></note> Not even the running boys on the two Tampa oinochoai are exempt, for they are probably slaves running to render service at a symposium, where they may become the objects of amorous attention.<note anchored="true" n="36"><p>Cf. the boy with jug and ladle on <rs key="Perseus:object:Tampa 86.72" type="vase">Tampa 86.72</rs> (<figure n="1991.08.0717" rend="float"></figure>), with his counterpart serving the banqueters on <rs key="Perseus:object:Florence 3999" type="vase">Florence 3999</rs> (see earlier note, supra).</p></note> Even male gods have their heads turned by handsome boys: the Harrow Painter twice represented Zeus panting after Ganymede, as well as the pursuit of the young Pelops by Poseidon.<note anchored="true" n="37"><p><rs key="Perseus:object:St. Petersburg 607" type="vase">St. Petersburg 607</rs> (<bibl>ARV2, 272, 10</bibl>) and <rs key="Perseus:object:Naples 3152" type="vase">Naples 3152</rs> (<bibl>ARV2, 275, 60</bibl>).</p></note></p></div> 

<div type="section" n="12"><head>Hetairai and Love-Making</head>

<p>The number of his pederastic scenes might lead one to think this was a personal preoccupation of the Harrow Painter, but heterosexual love was another of his themes. Here too there are divine correspondents, with Dionysos pursuing Ariadne on two early neck-amphorae.<note anchored="true" n="38"><p><rs key="Perseus:object:Villa Giulia 50471" type="vase">Villa Giulia 50471</rs> and <rs key="Perseus:object:Mississippi 1977.3.87" type="vase">Mississippi 1977.3.87</rs>; <figure n="1991.01.0449" rend="float"></figure> (<bibl>ARV2, 272, 1-2</bibl>).</p></note> In the mortal sphere, the sexual undercurrents in pictures of men and women standing together might be overlooked or undervalued were it not that the man is occasionally shown groping the woman or offering her a purse.<note anchored="true" n="39"><p>Groping: <rs key="Perseus:object:Tarquinia RC 7455" type="vase">Tarquinia RC 7455</rs> (<bibl>ARV2, 272, 3</bibl>). Offering a purse: <rs key="Perseus:object:St. Petersburg 605" type="vase">St. Petersburg 605</rs> (<bibl>ARV2, 272, 12</bibl>) and <rs key="Perseus:object:Villa Giulia 1054" type="vase">Villa Giulia 1054</rs> (<bibl>ARV2, 275, 50</bibl>).</p></note> In one of the painter's most intriguing paintings, on the hydria <rs key="Perseus:object:Tampa 76.70" type="vase">Tampa 76.70</rs> (<bibl>ARV2, 276, 70</bibl>), a man bearing a purse and accompanied by a youth has come calling on a woman, who is seated within a room with a Doric frieze and an Aeolic column. The man leans on his staff facing the woman, but it is not clear that she can see him. She sits on a stool, holding a mirror in her left hand and conversing with a small boy. The domestic setting recalls the so-called "spinning hetairai," who sit working wool while waiting for their next customer.<note anchored="true" n="40"><p>For "spinning hetairai," see <bibl>Rodenwaldt 1932, 7-21</bibl>; and <bibl>Keuls 1983, 225-29</bibl>. Cf. the scene on <rs key="Perseus:object:Palermo 2047" type="vase">Palermo 2047</rs>, by the Harrow Painter (<bibl>ARV2, 275, 58</bibl>), where a man leaning on a staff and accompanied by a youth is offered a wreath by a woman seated next to a column.</p></note> Is this a husband returning home, a visit to a hetaira, or a more innocent commercial transaction? This is the ambiguity that underlies many such scenes, exacerbated in this instance by the presence of the boy and the distance between the man and woman. This scene has usually been interpreted as a visit to a hetaira; if this is correct, the boy may have been sent in to negotiate with the woman, or perhaps he has been brought here by his <foreign xml:lang="xgreek">erastes</foreign> for some sexual education.<note anchored="true" n="41"><p><bibl>Meyer 1988</bibl> agrees it is a hetaira, but believes the offering of a purse has a larger, symbolic meaning unknown to us. Eva Keuls interprets the scene as entirely respectable, with the boy being the woman's son and the man a "hen-pecked husband trying to appease his wife with money"; see <bibl>Keuls 1985, 260</bibl>.</p></note></p></div>

<div type="section" n="13"><head>Other Subjects</head>

<p>The Harrow Painter's other subjects range from the commonplace to the unusual. There is the usual complement of pictures featuring Dionysos or Herakles, the latter in such stock situations as wrestling the Nemean Lion, battling Amazons, and stealing up on the sleeping Alkyoneus.<note anchored="true" n="42"><p>Nemean Lion: stamnos, <rs key="Perseus:object:Munich 2407" type="vase">Munich 2407</rs> (<bibl>ARV2, 274, 35</bibl>). Amazons: column-krater, <rs key="Perseus:object:Rome, Palazzo dei Conservatori 185" type="vase">Rome, Palazzo dei Conservatori 185</rs> (<bibl>ARV2, 274, 41</bibl>). Pholos: column-krater, <rs key="Perseus:object:Kiel B 547" type="vase">Kiel B 547</rs> (<bibl>CVA, Kiel 1, pls. 31, 1-2 and 32, 1-5</bibl> (see list of new attributions, supra)). Alkyoneus: column-krater, <rs key="Perseus:object:Palermo, Fondazione Mormino" type="vase">Palermo, Fondazione Mormino</rs>; <bibl>V. Tusa, <title>Odeon</title> (Palermo 1971), 429, pl. 55a-c</bibl> (where incorrectly attributed to the Geras Painter); <bibl>Padgett 1989, 182-83, fig. 114, no. H.50B</bibl>.</p></note> Other relatively common subjects include athletes, musicians, warriors arming, symposiasts, and komasts, one of the latter being of "Anacreontic" type, with sakkos and parasol<note anchored="true" n="43"><p><rs key="Perseus:object:Munich 2326" type="vase">Munich 2326</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 273, 18</bibl>.</p></note> His portrayal of Zeus Keraunios, charging with eagle and thunderbolt, on a column-krater in a private collection, is one of the best of its kind.<note anchored="true" n="44"><p>Munich, private collection; <bibl><title>JdI</title> 94 (1979) 103, fig. 36</bibl>; <bibl>Padgett 1989 (supra) 191-92, fig. 115</bibl>.</p></note> The swordsman on a neck-amphora at Stanford may be based on the statue of the tyrannicide Aristogeiton, which stood in the Agora.<note anchored="true" n="45"><p><rs key="Perseus:object:Stanford 70.2" type="vase">Stanford 70.2</rs> (formerly Arlesheim, Schweizer collection); <bibl>ARV2, 272, 8</bibl>. The pose is not so uncommon in this period that a connection with the statue can be fully supported. Cf. the young swordsman by the Cartellino Painter on <rs key="Perseus:object:Princeton 1991-22" type="vase">Princeton 1991-22</rs>; <bibl><title>Record of the Art Museum, Princeton University</title> 51, no. 1 (1992) 69</bibl>.</p></note></p>

<p>Among the rarer subjects are the capture of Silenus, already discussed (<rs key="Perseus:object:Baltimore, Hopkins AIA B13" type="vase">Baltimore, Hopkins AIA B13</rs>; <figure n="1990.06.0351" rend="float"></figure>), and a rhapsode standing on a bema, perhaps reciting Homer in the competition for rhapsodes at the Panathenaia.<note anchored="true" n="46"><p>The identification as a rhapsode is not completely certain, as the man lacks the customary staff (<foreign xml:lang="xgreek">rhabdos</foreign>). For rhapsodes and rhapsodic competitions, see <bibl>Neils 1992, 72-75 (H. A. Shapiro)</bibl>; and <bibl>J. A. Davison, <title>JHS</title> 82 (1962) 141-42</bibl>.</p></note> The scene on a column-krater from Sabucina, with satyrs assisting at the forge of Hephaistos, is unique; it may have been inspired by a satyr play, like the appealing satyr-athlete on an oinochoe found in Athens.<note anchored="true" n="47"><p>Forge of Hephaistos: <rs key="Perseus:object:Caltanissetta 20371" type="vase">Caltanissetta 20371</rs> (<bibl>Para., 354, 39 bis</bibl>); see <bibl>R. G. Gempeler, "Die Schmiede des Hephäst — Eine Satyrspielszene des Harrow-Malers," <title>AntK</title> 12 (1969) 12-21</bibl>. Satyr-athlete: <rs key="Perseus:object:New York 12.229.13" type="vase">New York 12.229.13</rs> (<bibl>ARV2, 276, 80</bibl>). For satyr plays concerned with athletics, see <bibl>E. Simon, "Satyr-plays on Vases in the Time of Aeschylus," in <title>The Eye of Greece</title> (Cambridge 1982) 129-31</bibl>.</p></note></p></div>

<div type="section" n="14"><head>Column Krater Harvard 1960.339</head>

<p>Among the grandest and most monumentally conceived of the Harrow Painter's works is the column-krater <rs key="Perseus:object:Harvard 1960.339" type="vase">Harvard 1960.339</rs> (<figure n="1990.01.1544" rend="float"></figure>), found at Ruvo and formerly in the collections of the Princess Tricase and David M. Robinson.<note anchored="true" n="48"><p><bibl>ARV2, 274, 39</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 103</bibl>; <bibl>CVA, Robinson 2, 25-27, pls. 31-33</bibl>; <bibl>H. A. Shapiro, "Theseus, Athens, and Troizen," <title>AA</title> (1982) 294, fig. 4</bibl>; <bibl>B. Gentili, "Il Ditirambo XVII Sn. di Bacchilide e il cratere Tricase da Ruvo," <title>ArchCl</title> 6 (1954) 121-25, pls. 30-31</bibl>; <bibl>J. J. Pollitt, "Pots, Politics, and Personifications in Early Classical Athens," <title>Yale University Art Gallery Bulletin</title> (Spring 1987) 11-12, fig. 4</bibl>.</p></note> A large vessel, 49.2 cm. tall, it was found unbroken in a grave. The shape is more or less standard, with a bulbous body tapering to a torus foot in two degrees, a concave neck, "columnar" handles topped by horizontal plates, and a thick, overhanging rim, concave on the sides and slightly convex on top. The ornamental bands framing the pictures — tongues above and ivy vines at the sides — are also standard, as are the rays and red stripes circling the lower body. The top of the mouth is decorated with black palmettes on the handle plates and bands of lotus buds on the rim (<figure n="1990.01.1552" rend="float"></figure>). On the reverse, the side of the rim has the usual ivy vine (<figure n="1990.01.1603" rend="float"></figure>), but the obverse rim has pairs of horizontal red-figure palmettes, arranged back-to-back and enclosed in lyre-shaped tendrils, a unique ornament for a column-krater (<figure n="1990.01.1604" rend="float"></figure>). <note anchored="true" n="49"><p>Cf. the black palmettes on the rim of <rs key="Perseus:object:Cleveland 30.104" type="vase">Cleveland 30.104</rs>, by the Cleveland Painter (<bibl>ARV2, 516, 1</bibl>). Palmettes like those on the Harvard vase enjoyed a brief vogue in this period and are found on Nolan amphorae and other shapes; e.g. <rs key="Perseus:object:Brussels 721" type="vase">Brussels 721</rs>, a Nolan by the Eucharides Painter (<bibl>ARV2, 226, 5</bibl>), and <rs key="Perseus:object:Leiden PC 83" type="vase">Leiden PC 83</rs>, a hydria by the Kleophrades Painter, (<bibl>ARV2, 188, 71</bibl>). On two other column-kraters, the Harrow Painter put palmettes of a related type — slanted, back-to-back, and linked by coiling tendrils — on the obverse neck: Munich, private collection; <bibl><title>JdI</title> 94 (1979) 103, fig. 36</bibl>; <bibl>Padgett 1989 (supra) 191-92, fig. 115, no. H.65A</bibl>; and another once in the New York art market, Sotheby's, May 20, 1982, no. 100; <bibl>Padgett 1989 (supra) 192, no. H.65B</bibl>.</p></note></p>

<milestone ed="BZ" unit="page"/>
<milestone ed="JG" unit="Card"/>

<p>The subject on the reverse of the Harvard krater is a concert, or to be more precise, a musical competition, perhaps at the Panathenaic festival. The youth leaning on his staff at the right holds the forked wand of a judge (<figure n="1990.01.1599" rend="float"></figure>), and the youth playing a cithara is wearing a musician's festal costume: a diadem and a long gown with a black border (<figure n="1990.01.1593" rend="float"></figure>). The musician has just struck the strings with the plektron in his right hand (<figure n="1990.01.1598" rend="float"></figure>). The strap that normally loops around the left wrist to support the cithara while freeing the hand is instead looped over a bulge in the sound box (<figure n="1990.01.1595" rend="float"></figure>). The musician has raised his head, but his mouth is closed. If he is about to sing, he is a citharode, but if he is only playing and not singing, he is properly termed a citharist; competitions for both were held at the Panathenaia.<note anchored="true" n="50"><p>For citharodes and citharists, see <bibl>Neils 1992, 58-60 and 65-71 (H. A. Shapiro)</bibl>.</p></note> Two other draped males stand at the left, a youth and a bearded man; they seem more interested in one another than in the music. The size of the vessel required the painter to add these extraneous characters; another, smaller column-krater by the painter has a more tightly-knit group of citharode and judge.<note anchored="true" n="51"><p>New York art market; <bibl>Padgett 1989 (supra) no. H. 65B</bibl>. The citharode, in this case a bearded man, wears the same type of gown, with a broad black border.</p></note></p></div>

<div type="section" n="15"><head>Harvard 1960.339: Theseus and Poseidon</head>

<p>The obverse of the Harvard krater represents the visit of Theseus to his divine father, Poseidon, who in some accounts slept with Theseus' mother Aithra on the same night as his mortal father, Aigeus. When Theseus went to Crete, Minos challenged him to prove his divine parentage by retrieving a ring thrown into the sea, a feat he accomplished with Amphitrite's help. In the Harrow Painter's version, Poseidon and Theseus are the focal point, shaking hands in the center. Poseidon wears a fillet, a dotted chiton with folds in dilute glaze, and a himation. In his left hand he holds a tall trident, which overlaps the frame above. Theseus wears a wreath, short chiton with a belted overfold, and a fringed shawl. The sword hanging at his waist is presumably the weapon left under a rock at Troizen by Aigeus. His hair is shorter than the god's and is tied in a short queue; thinned glaze is used for his budding sideburns. The round object in his left hand is certainly not a ring; it looks more like an apple. Standing at the left are an old man and a younger woman, identifiable as Nereus and one of his daughters, a Nereid. A slender Doric column stands between them. The Nereid holds an oinochoe in her right hand and a phiale in her left; she is pouring a libation to mark Theseus' arrival. Nereus, leaning on a tall staff, turns back to look at his daughter, whose elaborate dress has been described above. Nereus is more modestly attired in a chiton and himation. His stubbly beard and close-cropped hair are rendered in dilute glaze. At the far right, behind Theseus, stands Poseidon's queen, Amphitrite. She raises her right hand to crown the hero with a wreath of added red, now nearly invisible. She has a long fillet in her hair and is dressed in a chiton, himation, and dotted earrings. Her face and that of Theseus are drawn in a manner characteristic of the painter in his more careful work, with heavy, rounded chins, narrow eyes, hooked nostrils, and slightly parted lips. The way Theseus' pupil is attached only to the upper contour of the eye is somewhat unusual and gives him a rather sleepy look; Poseidon's eye is more characteristic. The treatment of Nereus' head is paralleled by the seated old man on another column-krater by the painter, in Basel.<note anchored="true" n="52"><p>Basel, ex Ludwig collection; <bibl>Para., 354, 64 bis</bibl>. R. Lullies and F. Brommer wonder if the old man might be Aigeus, with the figure facing him being Theseus; see <bibl>R. Lullies, in E. Berger, ed., <title>Antike Kunstwerke aus der Sammlung Ludwig</title> (Basel 1979) 121-22, no. 44</bibl>. Beazley, however, is surely correct in calling the second figure a female.</p></note></p>

<milestone ed="JG" unit="Card"/>

<p>This and other versions of this subject may be based loosely on Bacchylides' account of Theseus' visit to Poseidon's underwater palace (<foreign xml:lang="xgreek">megaron theon</foreign>), here represented by the column (<bibl n="Bacchyl. Dith. 17.97">Bacchyl. 17.97-116</bibl>).<note anchored="true" n="53"><p>See <bibl>Gentili 1954 (supra)</bibl>; <bibl>P. Jacobsthal, <title>Theseus auf dem Meeresgrunde</title> (Leipzig 1911)</bibl>; <bibl>J. Neils, <title>The Youthful Deeds of Theseus</title> (Rome 1987) 90</bibl>; and <bibl>F. Brommer, <title>Theseus: die Täten des griechischen Helden in der antiken Kunst und Literatur</title> (Darmstadt 1982) 77-83, pls. 22-23</bibl>.</p></note> In Bacchylides' account, it is Amphitrite who helps Theseus find the ring, and Poseidon is not present. This is the version drawn by Onesimos on a cup in Paris, who omits Poseidon but admits Theseus' divine sponsor, Athena (<rs key="Perseus:object:Louvre G 104" type="vase">Louvre G 104</rs>; <figure n="1992.06.0505" rend="float"></figure>).<note anchored="true" n="54"><p><bibl>ARV2, 318, 1</bibl>.</p></note> Bacchylides says Theseus received a mantle and a wreath from Amphitrite. The mantle must be the unusual, fringed garment draped over Theseus' shoulders. The red wreath held by Amphitrite is somewhat superfluous, as it pales beside the carefully drawn crown which the hero already wears. In two other contemporary versions of the subject, by the Briseis and Triptolemos Painters, Amphitrite again stands behind Theseus, proffering a wreath.<note anchored="true" n="55"><p>Briseis Painter: <rs key="Perseus:object:New York 53.11.4" type="vase">New York 53.11.4</rs> (<bibl>ARV 406, 7</bibl>); Triptolemos Painter: <rs key="Perseus:object:Copenhagen, Ny Carlsberg 2695" type="vase">Copenhagen, Ny Carlsberg 2695</rs> (<bibl>ARV2, 362, 19</bibl>).</p></note> On the Briseis Painter's cup, Theseus faces Athena; on the pelike by the Triptolemos Painter, it is Poseidon who stands before the seated youth. The one consistent motif — Amphitrite standing behind Theseus with a wreath — may be an element borrowed from a common visual source.</p>

<milestone ed="JG" unit="Card"/>

<p>One possibility is mentioned by Pausanias (<bibl n="Paus. 1.17.2">Paus. 1.17.2</bibl>), who says the subject was depicted by the artist Mikon in a painting in the sanctuary of Theseus in Athens. Mikon's painting most likely dates to Kimon's renovation of the Theseion, sometime between 478 and 470 B.C., the very period when these vases were painted. Another possibility, considering his undoubted influence on the Harrow Painter, is that the composition was copied from a lost work by the Berlin Painter. Other versions of the subject are differently composed. On a calyx-krater by the Syriskos Painter, Amphitrite stands behind Poseidon, who shakes hands with Theseus.<note anchored="true" n="56"><p><rs key="Perseus:object:Paris, Cab. Md. 418" type="vase">Paris, Cab. Méd. 418</rs> (<bibl>ARV2, 260, 2</bibl>).</p></note> Sometimes only Poseidon and Theseus are represented, as on an oinochoe at Yale (<rs key="Perseus:object:Yale 1913.143" type="vase">Yale 1913.143</rs>, the name-vase of the Painter of the Yale Oinochoe; <figure n="1990.02.0360" rend="float"></figure>).<note anchored="true" n="57"><p><bibl>ARV2, 503, 25</bibl>.</p></note> In other contexts, Theseus also shakes hands with his mortal father, Aigeus, who welcomes him to Athens.<note anchored="true" n="58"><p><rs key="Perseus:object:Louvre G 195" type="vase">Louvre G 195</rs>, by the Brygos Painter; <bibl>ARV2, 381, 174</bibl>.</p></note> A related scene on an amphora by the Oinanthe Painter is interpreted by Pollitt not as Aigeus greeting Theseus, but rather as Pittheus shaking Theseus' hand as he departs from Troizen.<note anchored="true" n="59"><p><rs key="Perseus:object:London E 264" type="vase">London E 264</rs> (<bibl>ARV2, 579, 1</bibl>); see <bibl>Pollitt 1987 (supra) 11</bibl>.</p></note></p>

<milestone ed="JG" unit="Card"/>

<p>This impressive vase, with its rare mythological subject inspired by poetry and, perhaps, by the work of a major muralist, might have been regarded by the Harrow Painter as one of his better works. It is that, but it is also somewhat ponderous and not a little dull. Nonetheless, it might have served as the mixing bowl at a symposium of aristocratic supporters of Kimon, whose connection with Theseus was cemented by his discovery of the hero's bones on Skyros. One feels that the Harrow Painter labored long over such a showpiece, but with less result than in some of his more modest works.</p></div>

<div type="section" n="16"><head>Followers of the Harrow Painter</head>

<p>For so prolific a painter, the Harrow Painter had little impact on his contemporaries. He had few followers, and those who did learn from him drew on his late work; the crude vapidity of their paintings reflects the decline in his own talent. The Painter of Ferrara T.756, whom Beazley placed near the Harrow Painter, is known only from two small column-kraters (<bibl>ARV2, 278, 1-2</bibl>), both dating to the mid-460s and executed in a broad, Early Classical style. A somewhat larger oeuvre — six column-kraters and two pelikai<note anchored="true" n="60"><p><bibl>ARV2, 278-79, 1-7, and 1641, 8</bibl>.</p></note> — is assigned to the Walters Painter, a negligible artist clearly in the Harrow Painter's orbit; he may even have copied some of the painter's late works.<note anchored="true" n="61"><p>Cf. the symposium scenes on <rs key="Perseus:object:Florence 3999" type="vase">Florence 3999</rs>, by the Harrow Painter (<bibl>ARV2, 275, 47</bibl>) and <rs key="Perseus:object:Louvre C 10756" type="vase">Louvre C 10756</rs>, by the Walters Painter (<bibl>ARV2, 278, 4</bibl>); the servant boys with jugs and strainers are virtually identical. See <bibl>Jan N. Bremmer, "Adolescents, <title>Symposia</title> and Pederasty," in O. Murray, ed., <title>Sympotica</title> (Oxford, 1990) 135-48</bibl>.</p></note> The figures on the obverse of the pelike <rs key="Perseus:object:Tampa 86.65" type="vase">Tampa 86.65</rs> (<bibl>ARV2, 1641, 8</bibl>), particularly the mantled boy and the man leaning on his staff, are familiar types from the Harrow Painter's repertoire (<figure n="1991.08.0132" rend="float"></figure>); compare the figures on <rs key="Perseus:object:Agrigento C.2033" type="vase">Agrigento C.2033</rs> (<bibl>ARV2, 275, 52</bibl>). The shape of the Tampa pelike and the frieze of silhouetted animals are alien to the Harrow Painter, but the cap-like hair, outlined ears, and banal mantled figures are clearly related. The subject of the obverse, a boy between two youths, one of whom offers him a purse, is also familiar. The young athletes on the reverse are hoplitodromoi, to judge by the shield and helmet on the ground (<figure n="1991.08.0141" rend="float"></figure>). Its ancient owner apparently valued this vase enough to have its broken handle re-attached with bronze rivets (<figure n="1991.08.0149" rend="float"></figure>). Neither the Walters Painter nor the Painter of Ferrara T.756 left a legacy as diverse and individual as that of the Harrow Painter.</p></div>

<div type="section" n="17"><head>The Geras Painter</head>

<p>One painter with whom the Harrow Painter was probably acquainted, although no definite workshop connection can be established, is the Geras Painter, another pot specialist active in the period 480-465 B.C.<note anchored="true" n="62"><p>For the Geras Painter, see <bibl>ARV2, 285-87 and 1642</bibl>; <bibl>Para., 355</bibl>; <bibl>Beazley Addenda 2, 209</bibl>; <bibl>Padgett 1989, 1-134</bibl>; <bibl>D. A. Amyx, "A New Pelike by the Geras Painter," <title>AJA</title> 49 (1945) 508-518</bibl>; and <bibl>C. Bérard, "Une nouvelle péliké du Peintre de Geras," <title>AntK</title> 9 (1966) 93-100</bibl>. To the 37 vases attributed to the painter by Beazley, Padgett and others have added another twenty.</p></note> There is a kinship between the two painters that is difficult to demonstrate in terms of specific details, but which is discernible in their general approach to representation. Like brothers, they went their own ways, but in spirit were never far apart. Only half as many vases have been attributed to the Geras Painter, and although he too decorated a variety of shapes, his pelikai outnumber his column-kraters and amphorae put together.<note anchored="true" n="63"><p>32 pelikai, 11 column-kraters, 3 neck-amphorae, 1 amphora of type A, 3 hydriai, 2 stamnoi, 2 volute-kraters, 2 unclassified pot fragments, and one oinochoe of shape 5A.</p></note> He had a greater taste for myth than the Harrow Painter and is a more intriguing personality. He seems, in fact, to have been something of an eccentric, with a taste for unusual subjects and a quirky approach to more standard themes; for example, he shows a maenad chasing a satyr, instead of the other way round.<note anchored="true" n="64"><p><rs key="Perseus:object:Naples 164331" type="vase">Naples 164331</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 287, 25</bibl>.</p></note> It is not certain that this humor was always intentional, for he is nothing if not sincere, and his work has an earnest charm that overcomes his shortcomings as an artist. Although capable of careful work, he was not a good draughtsman, and his line can be loose and imprecise. His satyrs are memorable, his gods less so, though the seated Zeus served by Ganymede is an exception (<rs key="Perseus:object:Louvre G 224" type="vase">Louvre G 224</rs>).<note anchored="true" n="65"><p><bibl>ARV2, 285, 1</bibl>.</p></note> Herakles was a favorite subject, and he delighted in representing the hero in unusual situations or activities, or performing canonical deeds in an unusual manner.</p>

<milestone ed="JG" unit="Card"/>

<p>The origins and career of the Geras Painter are less cloudy than the Harrow Painter's. He seems to have trained in the workshop of the Nikoxenos and Eucharides Painters, with whose sour-faced figures his characters have a definite kinship. Thereafter, he was for some years a member of what may be called the Syleus Workshop, after its principal artist, the Syleus Painter, and the other painters of the so-called Syleus Sequence.<note anchored="true" n="66"><p>The Painter of the Munich Amphora, the Gallatin Painter, and the Diogenes Painter. See <bibl>ARV2, 245-255</bibl>.</p></note> Also affiliated with this workshop at various times and in varying degrees were the Argos Painter, the Flying-Angel Painter, the Tyszkiewicz Painter, the Triptolemus Painter, the Pan Painter, and the Painter of Louvre G 238. Sometime in the mid-470s, the Geras Painter moved to another workshop where he and his more talented associate, the Pan Painter, produced small column-kraters and a series of small pelikai with unframed pictures.<note anchored="true" n="67"><p>For this "Class of Small Geras Painter Pelikai" (Class XX), which includes several works by the Pan Painter and his follower, the Perseus Painter, see <bibl>Becker 1977, 61-70</bibl>.</p></note></p></div>

<div type="section" n="18"><head>Pelike Harvard 1925.30.34</head>

<p>One of the most intriguing of the Geras Painter's pelikai from this period is <rs key="Perseus:object:Harvard 1925.30.34" type="vase">Harvard 1925.30.34</rs>.<note anchored="true" n="68"><p><bibl>ARV2, 285, 7</bibl>; <bibl>CVA, Hoppin-Gallatin, p. 8, pl. 12, 3-4</bibl>; <bibl>Padgett 1989 (supra) 36-38, figs. 22-23, no. G.7</bibl>; <bibl>Becker 1977 (supra) p. 61, no. 175</bibl>; <bibl>LIMC, p. 798, pl. 531, Herakles 1324 (J. Boardman)</bibl>.</p></note> Of medium size, it has the usual bag-shaped body and torus mouth and foot.<note anchored="true" n="69"><p>H. 21.2 cm.; Diam. 15.6 cm.; Diam. mouth 11.0 cm.; Diam. foot 12.2 cm.</p></note> Although unbroken, the surface is heavily weathered and pitted, and there is flaking on the figures and a certain amount of repainting, particularly of the black background.<note anchored="true" n="70"><p>On the figures, the most damage is to the right amphora, the lower body and right leg of Herakles, and the lower body and legs of the satyr.</p></note> The subsidiary ornament is relatively common on this type of pelike and in this case has a rather perfunctory look. Above the figures on either side is a band of egg-pattern. The groundlines consist of double rows of dots that are actually degenerate abbreviations of pomegranate-net pattern. Below either handle is a single palmette, pointing downward, with scrolling tendrils at the top. The rest of the vase is black except for the bottom of the foot and a narrow reserved band inside the rim. There are no inscriptions, but on the bottom of the foot is an graffito: an alpha and two straight lines.<note anchored="true" n="71"><p>See <bibl>Padgett 1989, p. 36</bibl>.</p></note></p>

<milestone ed="JG" unit="Card"/>

<p>On one side, Herakles is striding to the right with a sturdy carrying-pole balanced on his left shoulder. Lashed by the handles to either end of the pole are a pair of pointed amphorae. Herakles is dressed in a short chiton with folds drawn with dilute glaze. Over this, the skin of the Nemean Lion is pulled snugly around his body and secured with a belt; the forepaws are knotted at the throat and the head worn like a hood. The skin is edged with a stripe of thinned glaze, and the furry texture is indicated with numerous small crescents in dilute glaze. The hero rests his knotty club on his right shoulder.</p>

<milestone ed="JG" unit="Card"/>

<p>On the reverse, a balding satyr with a beard, long ears, and a tail is standing in profile to the right. He wears a cloak wrapped around his waist and legs like a long skirt, a motif employed elsewhere by the painter.<note anchored="true" n="72"><p>Cf. a satyr on <rs key="Perseus:object:Boston 64.2032" type="vase">Boston 64.2032</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 285, 2</bibl>.</p></note> He leans over and with both hands grasps the rope of a shadoof, a water-drawing device of Egyptian origin consisting of a long pole, weighted at one end and balanced on a post. The rope, drawn with added red, is secured to a vessel, the mouth of which is just appearing at the top of the well, which apparently has no well-head. The vessel is being raised, not lowered, as there is slack in the rope above the satyr's hands. From the shape of the mouth, the vessel can be identified as a <foreign xml:lang="xgreek">kados</foreign>, a type of plain-ware jar which, to judge by other representations on vases, was in common use as a well bucket.<note anchored="true" n="73"><p> On a skyphos by the Zephyros Painter in Zurich, a man raises a kados using a shadoof; <bibl>H. Bloesch, ed., <title>Greek Vases from the Hirschmann Collection</title> (Zurich 1982) 80-81, no. 39</bibl>. Cf. also the kadoi in well-scenes by the Brygos Painter (<rs key="Perseus:object:Milan 266" type="vase">Milan 266</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 379, 145</bibl>) and the Painter of Munich 2335 (<rs key="Perseus:object:Havana, Lagunillas Collection, 213" type="vase">Havana, Lagunillas Collection, 213</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 1166, 98</bibl>). On the Havana vase, the rope is attached to a pulley; see <bibl>R. Olmos Romera, <title>Vasos griegos de la Colleccion Condes de Lagunillas</title> (Kilchberg 1990) 152-53, no. 43</bibl>. For the identification of this type of vessel as a kados, see <bibl>D. A. Amyx, "The Attic Stelai, Part III. Vases and other Containers," <title>Hesperia</title> 27 (1958) 186-90</bibl>; and <bibl>H. Gericke, <title>Gefässdarstellungen auf griechischen Vasen</title> (Berlin 1970) 54-55</bibl>.</p></note></p>

<milestone ed="JG" unit="Card"/>

<p>The meaning of these scenes is obscure, but the two sides are probably connected; one thinks of another pelike by the Geras Painter, on which a satyr is preparing a dish of some kind on one side, and another satyr, on the reverse, is running up with a bucket of water.<note anchored="true" n="74"><p><rs key="Perseus:object:Berkeley 8.1583" type="vase">Berkeley 8.1583</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 286, 10</bibl>.</p></note> Herakles and the satyrs did not normally get along well, as the satyrs were always trying to steal his weapons. Satyrs are sometimes shown harassing women when they come to fetch water, and in two cases a shadoof is represented.<note anchored="true" n="75"><p>One is a red-figure bell-krater, <rs key="Perseus:object:Tbingen 1343" type="vase">Tübingen 1343</rs>; <bibl>Moon 1983, 213, fig. 14.7</bibl>. The other is a black-figure pelike, <rs key="Perseus:object:Berlin F 3228" type="vase">Berlin F 3228</rs>; <bibl>B. Sparkes, "Illustrating Aristophanes," <title>JHS</title> 95 (1975) 130, pl. 14e</bibl>.</p></note> In this case, Herakles must be bringing the amphorae to be filled at the well. The same subject, without the satyr, was depicted by the Pan Painter on a column-krater in Berlin.<note anchored="true" n="76"><p><rs key="Perseus:object:Berlin F 4027" type="vase">Berlin F 4027</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 551, 5</bibl>.</p></note> In the Pan Painter's version, Herakles carries an amphora in each hand and runs toward a fountain on the reverse, which has a spout in the shape of a donkey's head. Some scholars have suggested an allusion to Herakles' water-drawing contest with Lepreos.<note anchored="true" n="77"><p>First suggested by <bibl>G. Jatta, "La sfida di Ercole con Lepreo," <title>AdI</title> 49 (1877) 410 ff.</bibl>; he is supported by <bibl>Follmann 1968, 61</bibl>. For Lepreos, see <bibl n="Ath. 10.412">Athenaeus 10.412</bibl>; <bibl>Zenodotos, <title>FGrH</title> 19 F 1</bibl>; and <bibl>F. Brommer, <title>Herakles II. Die unkannonischen Täten des Helden</title> (Darmstadt 1984) 13</bibl>.</p></note> This seems an obscure and unlikely explanation and, as Boardman points out, Lepreos is not present on either vase.<note anchored="true" n="78"><p><bibl>LIMC, IV, 798 (J. Boardman)</bibl>.</p></note></p>

<milestone ed="JG" unit="Card"/>

<p>Furtwängler suggested that the Herakles on the Pan Painter's krater was preparing for his bath, and this is probably also what the Geras Painter's Herakles has in mind.<note anchored="true" n="79"><p>See <bibl>A. Furtwängler, in Roscher I, 2237 ff</bibl>. Brommer thinks both paintings show Herakles preparing his bath; he discounts the Lepreos interpretation and, like several other scholars, notes a connection with numerous Etruscan representations of Herakles with an amphora at a fountain or reclining on a raft of amphorae (<bibl>Brommer 1984</bibl>; see <bibl>Beazley 1974a, 10</bibl>; and <bibl>LIMC, IV, 798 (J. Boardman)</bibl>). For the Etruscan representations, see <bibl>Brommer 1984, 76-77</bibl>; <bibl>LIMC, V, 207-209, pl. 168 (S. J. Schwarz, "Herakles/Hercle")</bibl>; and <bibl>G. A. Mansuelli, "Uno specchio Etruscho inedito del Museo Civico di Bologna e il mito di Ercole alla Fonte," <title>StEtr</title> 15 (1947) 99-108</bibl>. To the examples discussed by Schwarz and Mansuelli, add two 4th-century bronze candelabrum figurines, formerly in the Swiss art market: <bibl>Ars Antiqua AG, <title>Antike Kunstwerke</title>, Auktion V (Lucerne, November 7, 1964) no. 34</bibl>; and <bibl>Münzen und Medaillen AG, <title>Kunstwerke der Antike</title>, Auktion XXII (Basel, May 13, 1961) no. 75</bibl>.</p></note> The presence of the satyr indicates a possibly comic situation, such as a satyr play. The comic possibilities are many: Herakles might force the satyrs to draw water for his bath, and they, when he is thus occupied, might attempt to make off with his clothes and weapons. The carrying-pole used by the hero may have been suggested by the painter's depiction, on a volute-krater in Munich, of Herakles carrying the Kerkopes, a story in which the pole is an essential and traditional element (<rs key="Perseus:object:Munich 2382" type="vase">Munich 2382</rs>).<note anchored="true" n="80"><p><bibl>ARV2, 287, 27</bibl>. Sometimes porters are shown carrying amphorae in the same way; e.g. <rs key="Perseus:object:Athens, Agora P 1275" type="vase">Athens, Agora P 1275</rs>; <bibl>ARV2, 105</bibl>; <bibl>S. Roberts, <title>Hesperia</title> 55 (1986) pl. 15</bibl>.</p></note></p></div>
</body></text></TEI>
